<PAPER>
	<S sid="0">SemEval-2007 Task 10: English Lexical Substitution Task</S><ABSTRACT>
		<S sid="1" ssid="1">In this paper we describe the English Lexical Substitution task for SemEval.</S>
		<S sid="2" ssid="2">In the task, annotators and systems find an alternative substitute word or phrase for a target word in context.</S>
		<S sid="3" ssid="3">The task involves both finding the synonyms and disambiguating the context.Participating systems are free to use any lexical resource.</S>
		<S sid="4" ssid="4">There is a subtask which re quires identifying cases where the word isfunctioning as part of a multiword in the sen tence and detecting what that multiword is.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number="1">
			<S sid="5" ssid="5">Word sense disambiguation (WSD) has been de scribed as a task in need of an application.</S>
			<S sid="6" ssid="6">Whilstresearchers believe that it will ultimately prove useful for applications which need some degree of se mantic interpretation, the jury is still out on this point.</S>
			<S sid="7" ssid="7">One problem is that WSD systems have been tested on fine-grained inventories, rendering the task harder than it need be for many applications (Ide and Wilks, 2006).</S>
			<S sid="8" ssid="8">Another significant problem is that there is no clear choice of inventory for any given task (other than the use of a parallel corpus for a specific language pair for a machine translation application).</S>
			<S sid="9" ssid="9">The lexical substitution task follows on fromsome previous ideas (McCarthy, 2002) to examine the capabilities of WSD systems built by re searchers on a task which has potential for NLP applications.</S>
			<S sid="10" ssid="10">Finding alternative words that canoccur in given contexts would potentially be useful to many applications such as question answer ing, summarisation, paraphrase acquisition (Daganet al, 2006), text simplification and lexical acquisi tion (McCarthy, 2002).</S>
			<S sid="11" ssid="11">Crucially this task does not specify the inventory for use beforehand to avoidbias to one predefined inventory and makes it eas ier for those using automatically acquired resources to enter the arena.</S>
			<S sid="12" ssid="12">Indeed, since the systems in SemEval did not know the candidate substitutes for a word before hand, the lexical resource is evaluatedas much as the context based disambiguation com ponent.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Task set up. " number="2">
			<S sid="13" ssid="1">The task involves a lexical sample of nouns, verbs,adjectives and adverbs.</S>
			<S sid="14" ssid="2">Both annotators and sys tems select one or more substitutes for the target word in the context of a sentence.</S>
			<S sid="15" ssid="3">The data wasselected from the English Internet Corpus of English produced by Sharoff (2006) from the Inter net (http://corpus.leeds.ac.uk/internet.html).</S>
			<S sid="16" ssid="4">This is a balanced corpus similar in flavour to the BNC, though with less bias to British English, obtained by sampling data from the web.</S>
			<S sid="17" ssid="5">Annotators are notprovided with the PoS (noun, verb, adjective or ad verb) but the systems are.</S>
			<S sid="18" ssid="6">Annotators can provide up to three substitutes but all should be equally as good.</S>
			<S sid="19" ssid="7">They are instructed that they can provide aphrase if they can?t think of a good single word sub stitute.</S>
			<S sid="20" ssid="8">They can also use a slightly more general word if that is close in meaning.</S>
			<S sid="21" ssid="9">There is a ?NAME?</S>
			<S sid="22" ssid="10">response if the target is part of a proper name and ?NIL?</S>
			<S sid="23" ssid="11">response if annotators cannot think of a good substitute.</S>
			<S sid="24" ssid="12">The subjects are also asked to identify 48 if they feel the target word is an integral part of a phrase, and what that phrase was.</S>
			<S sid="25" ssid="13">This optionwas envisaged for evaluation of multiword detection.</S>
			<S sid="26" ssid="14">Annotators did sometimes use it for paraphras ing a phrase with another phrase.</S>
			<S sid="27" ssid="15">However, for an item to be considered a constituent of a multiword, a majority of at least 2 annotators had to identify the same multiword.1 The annotators were 5 native English speakers from the UK.</S>
			<S sid="28" ssid="16">They each annotated the entire dataset.All annotations were semi-automatically lemma tised (substitutes and identified multiwords) unless the lemmatised version would change the meaning of the substitute or if it was not obvious what the canonical version of the multiword should be.</S>
			<S sid="29" ssid="17">2.1 Data Selection.</S>
			<S sid="30" ssid="18">The data set comprises 2010 sentences, 201 target words each with 10 sentences.</S>
			<S sid="31" ssid="19">We released 300 for the trial data and kept the remaining 1710 for the test release.</S>
			<S sid="32" ssid="20">298 of the trial, and 1696 of the test release remained after filtering items with less than 2 non NIL and non NAME responses and a few witherroneous PoS tags.</S>
			<S sid="33" ssid="21">The words included were se lected either manually (70 words) from examinationof a variety of lexical resources and corpora or au tomatically (131) using information in these lexical resources.</S>
			<S sid="34" ssid="22">Words were selected from those having a number of different meanings, each with at least onesynonym.</S>
			<S sid="35" ssid="23">Since typically the distribution of mean ings of a word is strongly skewed (Kilgarriff, 2004), for the test set we randomly selected 20 words ineach PoS for which we manually selected the sen tences 2 (we refer to these words as MAN) whilst forthe remaining words (RAND) the sentences were se lected randomly.</S>
			<S sid="36" ssid="24">2.2 Inter Annotator Agreement.</S>
			<S sid="37" ssid="25">Since we have sets of substitutes for each item andannotator, pairwise agreement was calculated between each pair of sets (p1, p2 ? P ) from each pos sible pairing (P ) as ? p1,p2?P p1?p2 p1?p2 |P | 1Full instructions given to the annotators are posted at http://www.informatics.susx.ac.uk/research/nlp/mccarthy/files/ instructions.pdf.2There were only 19 verbs due to an error in automatic selection of one of the verbs picked for manual selection of sen tences.</S>
			<S sid="38" ssid="26">Pairwise inter-annotator agreement was 27.75%.</S>
			<S sid="39" ssid="27">73.93% had modes, and pairwise agreement with themode was 50.67%.</S>
			<S sid="40" ssid="28">Agreement is increased if we remove one annotator who typically gave 2 or 3 sub stitutes for each item, which increased coverage butreduced agreement.</S>
			<S sid="41" ssid="29">Without this annotator, inter annotator agreement was 31.13% and 64.7% with mode.</S>
			<S sid="42" ssid="30">Multiword detection pairwise agreement was 92.30% and agreement on the identification of the exact form of the actual multiword was 44.13%.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Scoring. " number="3">
			<S sid="43" ssid="1">We have 3 separate subtasks 1) best 2) oot and 3) mw which we describe below.</S>
			<S sid="44" ssid="2">3 In the equations and results tables that follow we use P for precision, R for recall, and Mode P and Mode R where we calculate precision and recall against the substitute chosen by the majority of annotators, provided that there is a majority.</S>
			<S sid="45" ssid="3">Let H be the set of annotators, T be the set of test items with 2 or more responses (non NIL or NAME) and hi be the set of responses for an item i ? T for annotator h ? H . For each i ? T we calculate the mode (mi) i.e. the most frequent response provided that there is a response more frequent than the others.</S>
			<S sid="46" ssid="4">The set of items where there is such a mode is referred to as TM . Let A (and AM ) be the set of items from T(or TM ) where the system provides at least one sub stitute.</S>
			<S sid="47" ssid="5">Let ai : i ? A (or ai : i ? AM ) be the set of guesses from the system for item i. For each i we calculate the multiset union (Hi) for all hi for all h ? H and for each unique type (res) in Hi willhave an associated frequency (freqres) for the num ber of times it appears in Hi.</S>
			<S sid="48" ssid="6">For example: Given an item (id 9999) for happy;a supposing the annotators had supplied answers as follows: annotator responses 1 glad merry 2 glad 3 cheerful glad 4 merry 5 jovial3The scoring measures are as described in the doc ument at http://nlp.cs.swarthmore.edu/semeval/tasks/task10/ task10documentation.pdf released with our trial data.</S>
			<S sid="49" ssid="7">49 then Hi would be glad glad glad merry merry cheerful jovial.</S>
			<S sid="50" ssid="8">The res with associated frequencies would be glad 3 merry 2 cheerful 1 and jovial 1.</S>
			<S sid="51" ssid="9">best measures This requires the best file produced by the system which gives as many guesses as the system believes are fitting, but where the credit for each correct guess is divided by the number of guesses.</S>
			<S sid="52" ssid="10">The first guess in the list is taken as the best guess (bg).</S>
			<S sid="53" ssid="11">P = ? ai:i?A ? res?ai freqres |ai| |Hi| |A| (1) R = ? ai:i?T ? res?ai freqres |ai| |Hi| |T | (2) Mode P = ? bgi?AM 1 if bg = mi |AM | (3) Mode R = ? bgi?TM 1 if bg = mi |TM | (4) A system is permitted to provide more than one response, just as the annotators were.</S>
			<S sid="54" ssid="12">They cando this if they are not sure which response is bet ter, however systems will maximise the score if theyguess the most frequent response from the annotators.</S>
			<S sid="55" ssid="13">For P and R the credit is divided by the number of guesses that a system makes to prevent a system simply hedging its bets by providing many re sponses.</S>
			<S sid="56" ssid="14">The credit is also divided by the number of responses from annotators.</S>
			<S sid="57" ssid="15">This gives higher scores to items with less variation.</S>
			<S sid="58" ssid="16">We want to emphasise test items with better agreement.</S>
			<S sid="59" ssid="17">Using the example for happy;a id 9999 above, ifthe system?s responses for this item was glad; cheer ful the credit for a9999 in the numerator of P and R would be 3+1 2 7 = .286 For Mode P and Mode R we use the system?sfirst guess and compare this to the mode of the anno tators responses on items where there was a response more frequent than the others.</S>
			<S sid="60" ssid="18">oot measures This allows a system to make up to 10 guesses.</S>
			<S sid="61" ssid="19">The credit for each correct guess is not divided by the number of guesses.</S>
			<S sid="62" ssid="20">This allows for the fact that there is a lot of variation for the task and we only have 5 annotators.</S>
			<S sid="63" ssid="21">With 10 guesses there is a better chance that the systems find the responses of these 5 annotators.</S>
			<S sid="64" ssid="22">There is no ordering of the guesses and the Mode scores give credit where the mode was found in one of the system?s 10 guesses.</S>
			<S sid="65" ssid="23">P = ? ai:i?A ? res?ai freqres |Hi| |A| (5) R = ? ai:i?T ? res?ai freqres |Hi| |T | (6) Mode P = ? ai:i?AM 1 if any guess ? ai = mi |AM | (7) Mode R = ? ai:i?TM 1 if any guess ? ai = mi |TM | (8) mw measures For this measure, a system must identify items where the target is part of a multiword and what the multiword is. The annotators do not all have linguistics background, they are simply asked if the target is an integral part of a phrase, and if so what the phrase is. Sometimes this option is usedby the subjects for paraphrasing a phrase of the sentence, but typically it is used when there is a mul tiword.</S>
			<S sid="66" ssid="24">For scoring, a multiword item is one with a majority vote for the same multiword with more than 1 annotator identifying the multiword.</S>
			<S sid="67" ssid="25">Let MW be the subset of T for which there is such a multiword response from a majority of at least 2 annotators.</S>
			<S sid="68" ssid="26">Let mwi ? MW be the multiword identified by majority vote for item i. Let MWsys be the subset of T for which there is a multiword response from the system and mwsysi be a multiword specified by the system for item i. detection P = ? mwsysi?MWsys 1 if mwi exists at i |MWsys| (9) detection R = ? mwsysi?MW 1 if mwi exists at i |MW | (10) identification P = ? mwsysi?MWsys 1 if mwsysi = mwi |MWsys| (11) 50 identification R = ? mwsysi?MW 1 if mwsysi = mwi |MW | (12) 3.1 Baselines.</S>
			<S sid="69" ssid="27">We produced baselines using WordNet 2.1 (Miller et al., 1993a) and a number of distributional similarity measures.</S>
			<S sid="70" ssid="28">For the WordNet best baseline we found the best ranked synonym using the criteria 1 to 4 below in order.</S>
			<S sid="71" ssid="29">For WordNet oot we found up to 10 synonyms using criteria 1 to 4 in order until 10 were found: 1.</S>
			<S sid="72" ssid="30">Synonyms from the first synset of the target.</S>
			<S sid="73" ssid="31">word, and ranked with frequency data obtained from the BNC (Leech, 1992).</S>
			<S sid="74" ssid="32">2.</S>
			<S sid="75" ssid="33">synonyms from the hypernyms (verbs and nouns) or closely related classes (adjectives) of that first synset, ranked with the frequency data.</S>
			<S sid="76" ssid="34">3.</S>
			<S sid="77" ssid="35">Synonyms from all synsets of the target word,.</S>
			<S sid="78" ssid="36">and ranked using the BNC frequency data.</S>
			<S sid="79" ssid="37">4.</S>
			<S sid="80" ssid="38">synonyms from the hypernyms (verbs and nouns) or closely related classes (adjectives) of all synsets of the target, ranked with the BNC frequency data.</S>
			<S sid="81" ssid="39">We also produced best and oot baselines usingthe distributional similarity measures l1, jaccard, co sine, lin (Lin, 1998) and ?SD (Lee, 1999) 4.</S>
			<S sid="82" ssid="40">We tookthe word with the largest similarity (or smallest dis tance for ?SD and l1) for best and the top 10 for oot.</S>
			<S sid="83" ssid="41">For mw detection and identification we used WordNet to detect if a multiword in WordNet which includes the target word occurs within a window of 2 words before and 2 words after the target word.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Systems. " number="4">
			<S sid="84" ssid="1">9 teams registered and 8 participated, and two ofthese teams (SWAG and IRST) each entered two sys tems, we distinguish the first and second systems with a 1 and 2 suffix respectively.The systems all used 1 or more predefined inven tories.</S>
			<S sid="85" ssid="2">Most used web queries (HIT, MELB, UNT) or web data (Brants and Franz, 2006) (IRST2, KU, 4We used 0.99 as the parameter for ? for this measure.</S>
			<S sid="86" ssid="3">SWAG1, SWAG2, USYD, UNT) to obtain counts fordisambiguation, with some using algorithms to derive domain (IRST1) or co-occurrence (TOR) infor mation from the BNC.</S>
			<S sid="87" ssid="4">Most systems did not use sense tagged data for disambiguation though MELBdid use SemCor (Miller et al, 1993b) for filtering in frequent synonyms and UNT used a semi-supervised word sense disambiguation combined with a host ofother techniques, including machine translation en gines.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Results. " number="5">
			<S sid="88" ssid="1">In tables 1 to 3 we have ordered systems according to R on the best task, and in tables 4 to 6 according to R on oot.</S>
			<S sid="89" ssid="2">We show all scores as per centages i.e. we multiply the scores in section 3 by 100.</S>
			<S sid="90" ssid="3">In tables 3 and 6 we show results using the subset of items which were i) NOT identified asmultiwords (NMWT) ii) scored only on non multi word substitutes from both annotators and systems (i.e. no spaces) (NMWS).</S>
			<S sid="91" ssid="4">Unfortunately we do not have space to show the analysis for the MAN and RAND subsets here.</S>
			<S sid="92" ssid="5">Please refer to the task website for these results.</S>
			<S sid="93" ssid="6">5 We retain the same ordering for the further analysis tables when we look at subsets of the data.</S>
			<S sid="94" ssid="7">Although there are further differences in the systems which would warrant reranking on anindividual analysis, since we combined the subanal yses in one table we keep the order as for 1 and 4 respectively for ease of comparison.There is some variation in rank order of the sys tems depending on which measures are used.</S>
			<S sid="95" ssid="8">6 KUis highest ranking on R for best.</S>
			<S sid="96" ssid="9">UNT is best at find ing the mode, particularly on oot, though it is the most complicated system exploiting a great many knowledge sources and components.</S>
			<S sid="97" ssid="10">IRST2 does well at finding the mode in best.</S>
			<S sid="98" ssid="11">The IRST2 best R score is lower because it supplied many answers for each item however it achieves the best R score on the oot task.</S>
			<S sid="99" ssid="12">The baselines are outperformed by most systems.</S>
			<S sid="100" ssid="13">The WordNet baseline outperformsthose derived from distributional methods.</S>
			<S sid="101" ssid="14">The dis tributional methods, especially lin, show promising results given that these methods are automatic and 5The task website is at http://www.informatics.sussex.ac.uk/ research/nlp/mccarthy/task10index.html.</S>
			<S sid="102" ssid="15">6There is not a big difference between P and R because systems typically supplied answers for most items.</S>
			<S sid="103" ssid="16">51 Systems P R Mode P Mode R KU 12.90 12.90 20.65 20.65 UNT 12.77 12.77 20.73 20.73 MELB 12.68 12.68 20.41 20.41 HIT 11.35 11.35 18.86 18.86 USYD 11.23 10.88 18.22 17.64 IRST1 8.06 8.06 13.09 13.09 IRST2 6.95 6.94 20.33 20.33 TOR 2.98 2.98 4.72 4.72 Table 1: best results Systems P R Mode P Mode R WordNet 9.95 9.95 15.28 15.28 lin 8.84 8.53 14.69 14.23 l1 8.11 7.82 13.35 12.93 lee 6.99 6.74 11.34 10.98 jaccard 6.84 6.60 11.17 10.81 cos 5.07 4.89 7.64 7.40 Table 2: best baseline results don?t require hand-crafted inventories.</S>
			<S sid="104" ssid="17">As yet we haven?t combined the baselines with disambiguation methods.</S>
			<S sid="105" ssid="18">Only HIT attempted the mw task.</S>
			<S sid="106" ssid="19">It outperforms all baselines from WordNet.</S>
			<S sid="107" ssid="20">5.1 Post Hoc Analysis.</S>
			<S sid="108" ssid="21">Choosing a lexical substitute for a given word is not clear cut and there is inherently variation in thetask.</S>
			<S sid="109" ssid="22">Since it is quite likely that there will be syn onyms that the five annotators do not think of we conducted a post hoc analysis to see if the synonyms selected by the original annotators were better, on the whole, than those in the systems responses.</S>
			<S sid="110" ssid="23">We randomly selected 100 sentences from the subset of items which had more than 2 single word substitutes, no NAME responses, and where the target word was NMWT NMWS Systems P R P R KU 13.39 13.39 14.33 13.98 UNT 13.46 13.46 13.79 13.79 MELB 13.35 13.35 14.19 13.82 HIT 11.97 11.97 12.55 12.38 USYD 11.68 11.34 12.48 12.10 IRST1 8.44 8.44 8.98 8.92 IRST2 7.25 7.24 7.67 7.66 TOR 3.22 3.22 3.32 3.32 Table 3: Further analysis for best Systems P R Mode P Mode R IRST2 69.03 68.90 58.54 58.54 UNT 49.19 49.19 66.26 66.26 KU 46.15 46.15 61.30 61.30 IRST1 41.23 41.20 55.28 55.28 USYD 36.07 34.96 43.66 42.28 SWAG2 37.80 34.66 50.18 46.02 HIT 33.88 33.88 46.91 46.91 SWAG1 35.53 32.83 47.41 43.82 TOR 11.19 11.19 14.63 14.63 Table 4: oot results Systems P R Mode P Mode R WordNet 29.70 29.35 40.57 40.57 lin 27.70 26.72 40.47 39.19 l1 24.09 23.23 36.10 34.96 lee 20.09 19.38 29.81 28.86 jaccard 18.23 17.58 26.87 26.02 cos 14.07 13.58 20.82 20.16 Table 5: oot baseline results NMWT NMWS Systems P R P R IRST2 72.04 71.90 76.19 76.06 UNT 51.13 51.13 54.01 54.01 KU 48.43 48.43 49.72 49.72 IRST1 43.11 43.08 45.13 45.11 USYD 37.26 36.17 40.13 38.89 SWAG2 39.95 36.51 40.97 37.75 HIT 35.60 35.60 36.63 36.63 SWAG1 37.49 34.64 38.36 35.67 TOR 11.77 11.77 12.22 12.22 Table 6: Further analysis for oot HIT WordNet BL P R P R detection 45.34 56.15 43.64 36.92 identification 41.61 51.54 40.00 33.85 Table 7: MW results 52 good reasonable bad sys 9.07 19.08 71.85 origA 37.36 41.01 21.63 Table 8: post hoc resultsnot one of those identified as a multiword (i.e. a majority vote by 2 or more annotators for the same mul tiword as described in section 2).</S>
			<S sid="111" ssid="24">We then mixed the substitutes from the human annotators with those of the systems.</S>
			<S sid="112" ssid="25">Three fresh annotators7 were given the test sentence and asked to categorise the randomly ordered substitutes as good, reasonable or bad.</S>
			<S sid="113" ssid="26">We take the majority verdict for each substitute, but if there is one reasonable and one good verdict, thenwe categorise the substitute as reasonable.</S>
			<S sid="114" ssid="27">The per centage of substitutes for systems (sys) and original annotators (origA) categorised as good, reasonableand bad by the post hoc annotators are shown in ta ble 8.</S>
			<S sid="115" ssid="28">We see the substitutes from the humans have a higher proportion of good or reasonable responsesby the post hoc annotators compared to the substi tutes from the systems.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions and Future Directions. " number="6">
			<S sid="116" ssid="1">We think this task is an interesting one in which to evaluate automatic approaches of capturing lexical meaning.</S>
			<S sid="117" ssid="2">There is an inherent variation in the task because several substitutes may be possible for a given context.</S>
			<S sid="118" ssid="3">This makes the task hard and scoring is less straightforward than a task which has fixed choices.</S>
			<S sid="119" ssid="4">On the other hand, we believe the task taps into human understanding of word meaning and we hope that computers that perform well on this task will have potential in NLP applications.</S>
			<S sid="120" ssid="5">Since a pre-defined inventory is not used, the task allows usto compare lexical resources as well as disambiguation techniques without a bias to any predefined inventory.</S>
			<S sid="121" ssid="6">It is possible for those interested in disam biguation to focus on this, rather than the choice of substitutes, by using the union of responses from the annotators in future experiments.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acknowledgements. " number="7">
			<S sid="122" ssid="1">We acknowledge support from the Royal Society UK for fund ing the annotation for the project, and for a Dorothy Hodgkin 7Again, these were native English speakers from the UK.</S>
			<S sid="123" ssid="2">Fellowship to the first author.</S>
			<S sid="124" ssid="3">We also acknowledge support to the second author from INTEROP NoE (508011, 6th EU FP).</S>
			<S sid="125" ssid="4">We thank the annotators for their hard work.</S>
			<S sid="126" ssid="5">We thank Serge Sharoff for the use of his Internet corpus, Julie Weeds for the software we used for producing the distributional similarity baselines and Suzanne Stevenson for suggesting the oot task .</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
