<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">Meteor 1.3: Automatic Metric for Reliable Optimization and Evaluation of Machine Translation Systems</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">This paper describes Meteor 1.3, our submission to the 2011 EMNLP Workshop on Statistical Machine Translation automatic evaluation metric tasks.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">New metric features include improved text normalization, higher-precision paraphrase matching, and discrimination between content and function words.</S>
    <S sid="3" ssid="3">We include Ranking and Adequacy versions of the metric shown to have high correlation with human judgments of translation quality as well as a more balanced Tuning version shown to outperform BLEU in minimum error rate training for a phrase-based Urdu-English system.</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="1 Introduction" number="1">
    <S sid="4" ssid="1">The Meteor1 metric (Banerjee and Lavie, 2005; Denkowski and Lavie, 2010b) has been shown to have high correlation with human judgments in evaluations such as the 2010 ACL Workshop on Statistical Machine Translation and NIST Metrics MATR (Callison-Burch et al., 2010).</S>
    <S sid="5" ssid="2">However, previous versions of the metric are still limited by lack of punctuation handling, noise in paraphrase matching, and lack of discrimination between word types.</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="3">We introduce new resources for all WMT languages including text normalizers, filtered paraphrase tables, and function word lists.</S>
    <S sid="7" ssid="4">We show that the addition of these resources to Meteor allows tuning versions of the metric that show higher correlation with human translation rankings and adequacy scores on unseen test data.</S>
    <S sid="8" ssid="5">The evaluation resources are modular, usable with any other evaluation metric or MT software.</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="6">We also conduct a MT system tuning experiment on Urdu-English data to compare the effectiveness of using multiple versions of Meteor in minimum error rate training.</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="7">While versions tuned to various types of human judgments do not perform as well as the widely used BLEU metric (Papineni et al., 2002), a balanced Tuning version of Meteor consistently outperforms BLEU over multiple end-to-end tune-test runs on this data set.</S>
    <S sid="11" ssid="8">The versions of Meteor corresponding to the translation evaluation task submissions, (Ranking and Adequacy), are described in Sections 3 through 5 while the submission to the tunable metrics task, (Tuning), is described in Section 6.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="2 New Metric Resources" number="2">
    <S sid="12" ssid="1">Whereas previous versions of Meteor simply strip punctuation characters prior to scoring, version 1.3 includes a new text normalizer intended specifically for translation evaluation.</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="2">The normalizer first replicates the behavior of the tokenizer distributed with the Moses toolkit (Hoang et al., 2007), including handling of non-breaking prefixes.</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="3">After tokenization, we add several rules for normalization, intended to reduce meaning-equivalent punctuation styles to common forms.</S>
    <S sid="15" ssid="4">The following two rules are particularly helpful: Consider the behavior of the Moses tokenizer and Meteor normalizers given a reference translation containing the phrase &#8220;U.S.-based organization&#8221;: Of these, only the Meteor 1.3 normalization allows metrics to match all of the following stylizations: While intended for Meteor evaluation, use of this normalizer is a suitable preprocessing step for other metrics to improve accuracy when reference sentences are stylistically different from hypotheses.</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="5">The original Meteor paraphrase tables (Denkowski and Lavie, 2010b) are constructed using the phrase table &#8220;pivoting&#8221; technique described by Bannard and Callison-Burch (2005).</S>
    <S sid="17" ssid="6">Many paraphrases suffer from word accumulation, the appending of unaligned words to one or both sides of a phrase rather than finding a true rewording from elsewhere in parallel data.</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="7">To improve the precision of the paraphrase tables, we filter out all cases of word accumulation by removing paraphrases where one phrase is a substring of the other.</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="8">Table 1 lists the number of phrase pairs found in each paraphrase table before and after filtering.</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="9">In addition to improving accuracy, the reduction of phrase table sizes also reduces the load time and memory usage of the Meteor paraphrase matcher.</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="10">The tables are a modular resource suitable for other MT or NLP software.</S>
    <S sid="22" ssid="11">Commonly used metrics such as BLEU and earlier versions of Meteor make no distinction between content and function words.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="12">This can be problematic for ranking-based evaluations where two system outputs can differ by a single word, such as mistranslating either a main verb or a determiner.</S>
    <S sid="24" ssid="13">To improve Meteor&#8217;s discriminative power in such cases, we introduce a function word list for each WMT language and a new 6 parameter to adjust the relative weight given to content words (any word not on the list) versus function words (see Section 3).</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="14">Function word lists are estimated according to relative frequency in large monolingual corpora.</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="15">For each language, we pool freely available WMT 2011 data consisting of Europarl (Koehn, 2005), news (sentence-uniqued), and news commentary data.</S>
    <S sid="27" ssid="16">Any word with relative frequency of 10&#8722;3 or greater is added to the function word list.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="17">Table 2 lists corpus size and number of function words learned for each language.</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="18">In addition to common words, punctuation symbols consistently rise to the tops of function word lists.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="3 Meteor Scoring" number="3">
    <S sid="30" ssid="1">Meteor evaluates translation hypotheses by aligning them to reference translations and calculating sentence-level similarity scores.</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="2">This section describes our extended version of the metric.</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="3">For a hypothesis-reference pair, the search space of possible alignments is constructed by identifying all possible matches between the two sentences according to the following matchers: Exact: Match words if their surface forms are identical.</S>
    <S sid="33" ssid="4">Stem: Stem words using a language-appropriate Snowball Stemmer (Porter, 2001) and match if the stems are identical.</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="5">Synonym: Match words if they share membership in any synonym set according to the WordNet (Miller and Fellbaum, 2007) database.</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="6">Paraphrase: Match phrases if they are listed as paraphrases in the paraphrase tables described in Section 2.2.</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="7">All matches are generalized to phrase matches with a start position and phrase length in each sentence.</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="8">Any word occurring less than length positions after a match start is considered covered by the match.</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="9">The exact and paraphrase matchers support all five WMT languages while the stem matcher is limited to English, French, German, and Spanish and the synonym matcher is limited to English.</S>
    <S sid="39" ssid="10">Once matches are identified, the final alignment is resolved as the largest subset of all matches meeting the following criteria in order of importance: Given an alignment, the metric score is calculated as follows.</S>
    <S sid="40" ssid="11">Content and function words are identified in the hypothesis (hc, hf) and reference (rc, rf) according to the function word lists described in Section 2.3.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="12">For each of the matchers (mi), count the number of content and function words covered by matches of this type in the hypothesis (mi(hc), mi(hf)) and reference (mi(rc), mi(rf)).</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="13">Calculate weighted precision and recall using matcher weights (wi...wn) and content-function word weight (&#948;): The parameterized harmonic mean of P and R (van Rijsbergen, 1979) is then calculated: To account for gaps and differences in word order, a fragmentation penalty is calculated using the total number of matched words (m, average over hypothesis and reference) and number of chunks (ch): The parameters &#945;, &#946;, &#947;, &#948;, and wi...wn are tuned to maximize correlation with human judgments.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="4 Parameter Optimization" number="4">
    <S sid="43" ssid="1">The 2009 and 2010 WMT shared evaluation data sets are made available as development data for WMT 2011.</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="2">Data sets include MT system outputs, reference translations, and human rankings of translation quality.</S>
    <S sid="45" ssid="3">Table 3 lists the number of judgments for each evaluation and combined totals.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="4">To evaluate a metric&#8217;s performance on a data set, we count the number of pairwise translation rankings preserved when translations are re-ranked by metric score.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="5">We then compute Kendall&#8217;s &#964; correlation coefficient as follows: For each WMT language, we learn Meteor parameters that maximize T over the combined 2009 and 2010 data sets using an exhaustive parametric sweep.</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="6">The resulting parameters, listed in Table 4, are used in the default Ranking version of Meteor 1.3.</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="7">For each language, the 6 parameter is above 0.5, indicating a preference for content words over function words.</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="8">In addition, the fragmentation penalties are generally less severe across languages.</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="9">The additional features in Meteor 1.3 allow for more balanced parameters that distribute responsibility for penalizing various types of erroneous translations.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="5 Evaluation Experiments" number="5">
    <S sid="52" ssid="1">To compare Meteor 1.3 against previous versions of the metric on the task of evaluating MT system outputs, we tune a version for each language on 2009 WMT data and evaluate on 2010 data.</S>
    <S sid="53" ssid="2">This replicates the 2010 WMT shared evaluation task, allowing comparison to Meteor 1.2.</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="3">Table 5 lists correlation of each metric version with ranking judgments on tune and test data.</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="4">Meteor 1.3 shows significantly higher correlation on both tune and test data for English, French, and Spanish while Czech and German demonstrate overfitting with higher correlation on tune data but lower on test data.</S>
    <S sid="56" ssid="5">This overfitting effect is likely due to the limited number of systems providing translations into these languages and the difficulty of these target languages leading to significantly noisier translations skewing the space of metric scores.</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="6">We believe that tuning to combined 2009 and 2010 data will counter these issues for the official Ranking version.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="7">To evaluate the impact of new features on other evaluation tasks, we follow Denkowski and Lavie (2010a), tuning versions of Meteor to maximize length-weighted sentence-level Pearson&#8217;s r correlation coefficient with adequacy and H-TER (Snover et al., 2006) scores of translations.</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="8">Data sets include 2008 and 2009 NIST Open Machine Translation Evaluation adequacy data (Przybocki, 2009) and GALE P2 and P3 H-TER data (Olive, 2005).</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="9">For each type of judgment, metric versions are tuned and tested on each year and scores are compared.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="10">We compare Meteor 1.3 results with those from version 1.2 with results shown in Table 6.</S>
    <S sid="62" ssid="11">For both adequacy data sets, Meteor 1.3 significantly outperforms version 1.2 on both tune and test data.</S>
    <S sid="63" ssid="12">The version tuned on MT09 data is selected as the official Adequacy version of Meteor 1.3.</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="13">H-TER versions either show no improvement or degradation due to overfitting.</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="14">Examination of the optimal H-TER parameter sets reveals a mismatch between evaluation metric and human judgment type.</S>
    <S sid="66" ssid="15">As H-TER evaluation is ultimately limited by the TER aligner, there is no distinction between content and function words, and words sharing stems are considered nonmatches.</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="16">As such, these features do not help Meteor improve correlation, but rather act as a source of additional possibility for overfitting.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="6 MT System Tuning Experiments" number="6">
    <S sid="68" ssid="1">The 2011 WMT Tunable Metrics task consists of using Z-MERT (Zaidan, 2009) to tune a pre-built Urdu-English Joshua (Li et al., 2009) system to a new evaluation metric on a tuning set with 4 reference translations and decoding a test set using the resulting parameter set.</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="2">As this task does not provide a devtest set, we select a version of Meteor by exploring the effectiveness of using multiple versions of the metric to tune phrase-based translation systems for the same language pair.</S>
    <S sid="70" ssid="3">We use the 2009 NIST Open Machine Translation Evaluation Urdu-English parallel data (Przybocki, 2009) plus 900M words of monolingual data from the English Gigaword corpus (Parker et al., 2009) to build a standard Moses system (Hoang et al., 2007) as follows.</S>
    <S sid="71" ssid="4">Parallel data is word aligned using the MGIZA++ toolkit (Gao and Vogel, 2008) and alignments are symmetrized using the &#8220;growdiag-final-and&#8221; heuristic.</S>
    <S sid="72" ssid="5">Phrases are extracted using standard phrase-based heuristics (Koehn et al., 2003) and used to build a translation table and lexicalized reordering model.</S>
    <S sid="73" ssid="6">A standard SRI 5-gram language model (Stolke, 2002) is estimated from monolingual data.</S>
    <S sid="74" ssid="7">Using Z-MERT, we tune this system to baseline metrics as well as the versions of Meteor discussed in previous sections.</S>
    <S sid="75" ssid="8">We also tune to a balanced Tuning version of Meteor designed to minimize bias.</S>
    <S sid="76" ssid="9">This data set provides a single set of reference translations for MERT.</S>
    <S sid="77" ssid="10">To account for the variance of MERT, we run end-to-end tuning 3 times for each metric and report the average results on two unseen test sets: newswire and weblog.</S>
    <S sid="78" ssid="11">Test set translations are evaluated using BLEU, TER, and Meteor 1.2.</S>
    <S sid="79" ssid="12">The parameters for each Meteor version are listed in Table 7 while the results are listed in Table 8.</S>
    <S sid="80" ssid="13">The results are fairly consistent across both test sets: the Tuning version of Meteor outperforms BLEU across all metrics while versions of Meteor that perform well on other tasks perform poorly in tuning.</S>
    <S sid="81" ssid="14">This illustrates the differences between evaluation and tuning tasks.</S>
    <S sid="82" ssid="15">In evaluation tasks, metrics are engineered to score 1-best translations from systems most often tuned to BLEU.</S>
    <S sid="83" ssid="16">As listed in Table 7, these parameters are often skewed to emphasize the differences between system outputs.</S>
    <S sid="84" ssid="17">In the tuning scenario, MERT optimizes translation quality with respect to the tuning metric.</S>
    <S sid="85" ssid="18">If a metric is biased (for example, assigning more weight to recall than precision), it will guide the MERT search toward pathological translations that receive lower scores across other metrics.</S>
    <S sid="86" ssid="19">Balanced between precision and recall, content and function words, and word choice versus fragmentation, the Tuning version of Meteor is significantly less susceptible to gaming.</S>
    <S sid="87" ssid="20">Chosen as the official submission for WMT 2011, we believe that this Tuning version of Meteor will further generalize to other tuning scenarios.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="7 Conclusions" number="7">
    <S sid="88" ssid="1">We have presented Ranking, Adequacy, and Tuning versions of Meteor 1.3.</S>
    <S sid="89" ssid="2">The Ranking and Adequacy versions are shown to have high correlation with human judgments except in cases of overfitting due to skewed tuning data.</S>
    <S sid="90" ssid="3">We believe that these overfitting issues are lessened when tuning to combined 2009 and 2010 data due to increased variety in translation characteristics.</S>
    <S sid="91" ssid="4">The Tuning version of Meteor is shown to outperform BLEU in minimum error rate training of a phrase-based system on small Urdu-English data and we believe that it will generalize well to other tuning scenarios.</S>
    <S sid="92" ssid="5">The source code and all resources for Meteor 1.3 and the version of Z-MERT with Meteor integration will be available for download from the Meteor website.</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
