<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">PARADISE: A Framework For Evaluating Spoken Dialogue Agents</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">This paper presents PARADISE (PARAdigm for DIalogue System Evaluation), a general framework for evaluating spoken rlialogue agents.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">The framework decouples task requirements from an agent's dialogue behaviors, supports comparisons among dialogue strategies, enables the calculation of performance over subdialogues and whole dialogues, specifies the relative contribution of various factors to performance, and makes it possible to compare agents performing different tasks by normalizing for task complexity.</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="1 Introduction" number="1">
    <S sid="3" ssid="1">Recent advances in dialogue modeling, speech recognition, and natural language processing have made it possible to build spoken dialogue agents for a wide variety of applications.'</S>
    <S sid="4" ssid="2">Potential benefits of such agents include remote or hands-free access, ease of use, naturalness, and greater efficiency of interaction.</S>
    <S sid="5" ssid="3">However, a critical obstacle to progress in this area is the lack of a general framework for evaluating and comparing the performance of different dialogue agents.</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="4">One widely used approach to evaluation is based on the notion of a reference answer (Hirschman et al., 1990).</S>
    <S sid="7" ssid="5">An agent's responses to a query are compared with a predefined key of minimum and maximum reference answers; performance is the proportion of responses that match the key.</S>
    <S sid="8" ssid="6">This approach has many widely acknowledged limitations (Hirschman and Pao, 1993; Danieli et al., 1992; Bates and Ayuso, 1993), e.g., although there may be many potential dialogue strategies for carrying out a task, the key is tied to one particular dialogue strategy.</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="7">In contrast, agents using different dialogue strategies can be compared with measures such as inappropriate utterance ratio, turn correction ratio, concept accuracy, implicit recovery and transaction success (Danieli 'We use the term agent to emphasize the fact that we are evaluating a speaking entity that may have a personality.</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="8">Readers who wish to may substitute the word &amp;quot;system&amp;quot; wherever &amp;quot;agent&amp;quot; is used. and Gerbino, 1995; Hirschman and Pao, 1993; Polifroni et al., 1992; Simpson and Fraser, 1993; Shriberg, Wade, and Price, 1992).</S>
    <S sid="11" ssid="9">Consider a comparison of two train timetable information agents (Danieli and Gerbino, 1995), where Agent A in Dialogue 1 uses an explicit confirmation strategy, while Agent B in Dialogue 2 uses an implicit confirmation strategy: Danieli and Gerbino found that Agent A had a higher transaction success rate and produced less inappropriate and repair utterances than Agent B, and thus concluded that Agent A was more robust than Agent B.</S>
    <S sid="12" ssid="10">However, one limitation of both this approach and the reference answer approach is the inability to generalize results to other tasks and environments (Fraser, 1995).</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="11">Such generalization requires the identification of factors that affect performance (Cohen, 1995; Sparck-Jones and Galliers, 1996).</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="12">For example, while Danieli and Gerbino found that Agent A's dialogue strategy produced dialogues that were approximately twice as long as Agent B's, they had no way of determining whether Agent A's higher transaction success or Agent B's efficiency was more critical to performance.</S>
    <S sid="15" ssid="13">In addition to agent factors such as dialogue strategy, task factors such as database size and environmental factors such as background noise may also be relevant predictors of performance.</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="14">These approaches are also limited in that they currently do not calculate performance over subdialogues as well as whole dialogues, correlate performance with an external validation criterion, or normalize performance for task complexity.</S>
    <S sid="17" ssid="15">This paper describes PARADISE, a general framework for evaluating spoken dialogue agents that addresses these limitations.</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="16">PARADISE supports comparisons among dialogue strategies by providing a task representation that decouples what an agent needs to achieve in terms of the task requirements from how the agent carries out the task via dialogue.</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="17">PARADISE uses a decision-theoretic framework to specify the relative contribution of various factors to an agent's overall performance.</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="18">Performance is modeled as a weighted function of a task-based success measure and dialogue-based cost measures, where weights are computed by correlating user satisfaction with performance.</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="19">Also, performance can be calculated for subdialogues as well as whole dialogues.</S>
    <S sid="22" ssid="20">Since the goal of this paper is to explain and illustrate the application of the PARADISE framework, for expository purposes, the paper uses simplified domains with hypothetical data throughout.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="21">Section 2 describes PARADISE's performance model, and Section 3 discusses its generality, before concluding in Section 4.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="2 A Performance Model for Dialogue" number="2">
    <S sid="24" ssid="1">PARADISE uses methods from decision theory (Keeney and Raiffa, 1976; Doyle, 1992) to combine a disparate set of performance measures (i.e., user satisfaction, task success, and dialogue cost, all of which have been previously noted in the literature) into a single performance evaluation function.</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="2">The use of decision theory requires a specification of both the objectives of the decision problem and a set of measures (known as attributes in decision theory) for operationalizing the objectives.</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="3">The PARADISE model is based on the structure of objectives (rectangles) shown in Figure 1.</S>
    <S sid="27" ssid="4">The PARADISE model posits that performance can be correlated with a meaningful external criterion such as usability, and thus that the overall goal of a spoken dialogue agent is to maximize an objective related to usability.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="5">User satisfaction ratings (Kamm, 1995; Shriberg, Wade, and Price, 1992; Polifroni et al., 1992) have been frequently used in the literature as an external indicator of the usability of a dialogue agent.</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="6">The model further posits that two types of factors are potential relevant contributors to user satisfaction (namely task success and dialogue costs), and that two types of factors are potential relevant contributors to costs (Walker, 1996).</S>
    <S sid="30" ssid="7">In addition to the use of decision theory to create this objective structure, other novel aspects of PARADISE include the use of the Kappa coefficient (Carletta, 1996; Siegel and Castellan, 1988) to operationalize task success, and the use of linear regression to quantify the relative contribution of the success and cost factors to user satisfaction.</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="8">The remainder of this section explains the measures (ovals in Figure 1) used to operationalize the set of objectives, and the methodology for estimating a quantitative performance function that reflects the objective structure.</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="9">Section 2.1 describes PARADISE's task representation, which is needed to calculate the task-based success measure described in Section 2.2.</S>
    <S sid="33" ssid="10">Section 2.3 describes the cost measures considered in PARADISE, which reflect both the efficiency and the naturalness of an agent's dialogue behaviors.</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="11">Section 2.4 describes the use of linear regression and user satisfaction to estimate the relative contribution of the success and cost measures in a single performance function.</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="12">Finally, Section 2.5 explains how performance can be calculated for subdialogues as well as whole dialogues, while Section 2.6 summarizes the method.</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="13">A general evaluation framework requires a task representation that decouples what an agent and user accomplish from how the task is accomplished using dialogue strategies.</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="14">We propose that an attribute value matrix (AVM) can represent many dialogue tasks.</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="15">This consists of the information that must be exchanged between the agent and the user during the dialogue, represented as a set of ordered pairs of attributes and their possible values.2 As a first illustrative example, consider a simplification of the train timetable domain of Dialogues 1 and 2, where the timetable only contains information about rush-hour trains between four cities, as shown in Table 1.</S>
    <S sid="39" ssid="16">This AVM consists of four attributes (abbreviations for each attribute name are also shown).3 In Table 1, these attribute-value pairs are annotated with the direction of information flow to represent who acquires the information, although this information is not used for evaluation.</S>
    <S sid="40" ssid="17">During the dialogue the agent must acquire from the user the values of DC, AC, and DR, while the user must acquire DT.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="18">Performance evaluation for an agent requires a corpus of dialogues between users and the agent, in which users execute a set of scenarios.</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="19">Each scenario execution has a corresponding AVM instantiation indicating the task information requirements for the scenario, where each attribute is paired with the attribute value obtained via the dialogue.</S>
    <S sid="43" ssid="20">For example, assume that a scenario requires the user to find a train from Torino to Milano that leaves in the evening, as in the longer versions of Dialogues 1 and 2 in Figures 2 and 3.4 Table 2 contains an AVM corresponding to a &amp;quot;key&amp;quot; for this scenario.</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="21">All dialogues resulting from execution of this scenario in which the agent and the user correctly convey all attribute values (as in Figures 2 and 3) would have the same AVM as the scenario key in Table 2.</S>
    <S sid="45" ssid="22">The AVMs of the remaining dialogues would differ from the key by at least one value.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="23">Thus, even though the dialogue strategies in Figures 2 and 3 are radically different, the AVM task representation for these dialogues is identical and the performance of the system for the same task can thus be assessed on the basis of the AVM representation.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="24">Success at the task for a whole dialogue (or subdialogue) is measured by how well the agent and user achieve the information requirements of the task by the end of the dialogue (or subdialogue).</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="25">This section explains how PARADISE uses the Kappa coefficient (Carletta, 1996; Siegel and Castellan, 1988) to operationalize the taskbased success measure in Figure 1.</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="26">The Kappa coefficient, K, is calculated from a confusion matrix that summarizes how well an agent achieves the information requirements of a particular task for a set of dialogues instantiating a set of scenarios.5 For example, Tables 3 and 4 show two hypothetical confusion matrices that could have been generated in an evaluation of 100 complete dialogues with each of two train timetable agents A and B (perhaps using the confirmation strategies illustrated in Figures 2 and 3, respectively).6 The values in the matrix cells are based on comparisons between the dialogue and scenario key AVMs.</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="27">Whenever an attribute value in a dialogue (i.e., data) AVM matches the value in its scenario key, the number in the appropriate diagonal cell of the matrix (boldface for clarity) is incremented by 1.</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="28">The off diagonal cells represent misunderstandings that are not corrected in the dialogue.</S>
    <S sid="52" ssid="29">Note that depending on the strategy that a spoken dialogue agent uses, confusions across attributes are possible, e.g., &amp;quot;Milano&amp;quot; could be confused with &amp;quot;morning.&amp;quot; The effect of misunderstandings that are corrected during the course of the dialogue are reflected in the costs associated with the dialogue, as will be discussed below.</S>
    <S sid="53" ssid="30">The first matrix summarizes how the 100 AVMs representing each dialogue with Agent A compare with the AVMs representing the relevant scenario keys, while the second matrix summarizes the information exchange with Agent B. Labels vi to v4 in each matrix represent the possible values of depart-city shown in Table 1; v5 to v8 are for arrival-city, etc.</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="31">Columns represent the key, specifying which information values the agent and user were supposed to communicate to one another given a particular scenario.</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="32">(The equivalent column sums in both tables reflects that users of both agents were assumed to have performed the same scenarios).</S>
    <S sid="56" ssid="33">Rows represent the data collected from the dialogue corpus, reflecting what attribute values were actually communicated between the agent and the user.</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="34">Given a confusion matrix M, success at achieving the information requirements of the task is measured with the Kappa coefficient (Carletta, 1996; Siegel and Castellan, 1988): by chance.7 When there is no agreement other than that which would be expected by chance, n =0.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="35">When there is total agreement, K = 1. ic is superior to other measures of success such as transaction success (Danieli and Gerbino, 1995), concept accuracy (Simpson and Fraser, 1993), and percent agreement (Gale, Church, and Yarowsky, 1992) because n takes into account the inherent complexity of the task by correcting for chance expected agreement.</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="36">Thus rc provides a basis for comparisons across agents that are performing different tasks.</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="37">When the prior distribution of the categories is unknown, P(E), the expected chance agreement between the data and the key, can be estimated from the distribution of the values in the keys.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="38">This can be calculated from confusion matrix M, since the columns represent the values in the keys.</S>
    <S sid="62" ssid="39">In particular: P(A) is the proportion of times that the AVMs for the actual set of dialogues agree with the AVMs for the scenario keys, and P(E) is the proportion of times that the AVMs for the dialogues and the keys are expected to agree 7K has been used to measure pairwise agreement among coders making category judgments (Carletta, 1996; Krippendorf, 1980; Siegel and Castellan, 1988).</S>
    <S sid="63" ssid="40">Thus, the observed user/agent interactions are modeled as a coder, and the ideal interactions as an expert coder. where ti is the sum of the frequencies in column i of M, and T is the sum of the frequencies in M (ti + .</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="41">.</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="42">.</S>
    <S sid="66" ssid="43">+ tn).</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="44">P(A), the actual agreement between the data and the key, is always computed from the confusion matrix M: Given the confusion matrices in Tables 3 and 4, P(E) = 0.079 for both agents.8 For Agent A, P(A) = 0.795 and frc = 0.777, while for Agent B, P(A) = 0.59 and c=0.555, suggesting that Agent A is more successful than B in achieving the task goals.</S>
    <S sid="68" ssid="45">As shown in Figure 1, performance is also a function of a combination of cost measures.</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="46">Intuitively, cost measures should be calculated on the basis of any user or agent dialogue behaviors that should be minimized.</S>
    <S sid="70" ssid="47">A wide range of cost measures have been used in previous work; these include pure efficiency measures such as the number of turns or elapsed time to complete the task (Abella, Brown, and Buntschuh, 1996; Hirschman et al., 1990; Smith and Gordon, 1997; Walker, 1996), as well as measures of qualitative phenomena such as inappropriate or repair utterances (Danieli and Gerbino, 1995; Hirschman and Pao, 1993; Simpson and Fraser, 1993).</S>
    <S sid="71" ssid="48">PARADISE represents each cost measure as a function ci that can be applied to any (sub)dialogue.</S>
    <S sid="72" ssid="49">First, consider the simplest case of calculating efficiency measures over a whole dialogue.</S>
    <S sid="73" ssid="50">For example, let cl be the total number of utterances.</S>
    <S sid="74" ssid="51">For the whole dialogue D1 in Figure 2, c1(D1) is 23 utterances.</S>
    <S sid="75" ssid="52">For the whole dialogue D2 in Figure 3, ci (D2) is 10 utterances.</S>
    <S sid="76" ssid="53">To calculate costs over subdialogues and for some of the qualitative measures, it is necessary to be able to specify which information goals each utterance contributes to.</S>
    <S sid="77" ssid="54">PARADISE uses its AVM representation to link the information goals of the task to any arbitrary dialogue behavior, by tagging the dialogue with the attributes for the task.9 This makes it possible to evaluate any potential dialogue strategies for achieving the task, as well as to evaluate dialogue strategies that operate at the level of dialogue subtasks (subdialogues).</S>
    <S sid="78" ssid="55">Consider the longer versions of Dialogues 1 and 2 in Figures 2 and 3.</S>
    <S sid="79" ssid="56">Each utterance in Figures 2 and 3 has been tagged using one or more of the attribute abbreviations in Table 1, according to the subtask(s) the utterance contributes to.</S>
    <S sid="80" ssid="57">As a convention of this type of tagging, 'Using a single confusion matrix for all attributes as in Tables 3 and 4 inflates 1G when there are few cross-attribute confusions by making P(E) smaller.</S>
    <S sid="81" ssid="58">In some cases it might be desirable to calculate ic first for identification of attributes and then for values within attributes, or to average ic for each attribute to produce an overall ic for the task.</S>
    <S sid="82" ssid="59">9This tagging can be hand generated, or system generated and hand corrected.</S>
    <S sid="83" ssid="60">Preliminary studies indicate that reliability for human tagging is higher for AVM attribute tagging than for other types of discourse segment tagging (Passonneau and Litman, 1997; Hirschberg and Nakatani, 1996). utterances that contribute to the success of the whole dialogue, such as greetings, are tagged with all the attributes.</S>
    <S sid="84" ssid="61">Since the structure of a dialogue reflects the structure of the task (Carberry, 1989; Grosz and Sidner, 1986; Litman and Allen, 1990), the tagging of a dialogue by the AVM attributes can be used to generate a hierarchical discourse structure such as that shown in Figure 4 for Dialogue 1 (Figure 2).</S>
    <S sid="85" ssid="62">For example, segment (subdialogue) S2 in Figure 4 is about both depart-city (DC) and arrivalcity (AC).</S>
    <S sid="86" ssid="63">It contains segments S3 and S4 within it, and consists of utterances UI ... U6.</S>
    <S sid="87" ssid="64">Tagging by AVM attributes is required to calculate costs over subdialogues, since for any subdialogue, task attributes define the subdialogue.</S>
    <S sid="88" ssid="65">For subdialogue S4 in Figure 4, which is about the attribute arrival-city and consists of utterances A6 and U6, c(S4) is 2.</S>
    <S sid="89" ssid="66">Tagging by AVM attributes is also required to calculate the cost of some of the qualitative measures, such as number of repair utterances.</S>
    <S sid="90" ssid="67">(Note that to calculate such costs, each utterance in the corpus of dialogues must also be tagged with respect to the qualitative phenomenon in question, e.g. whether the utterance is a repair)&#176;) For example, let c2 be the number of repair utterances.</S>
    <S sid="91" ssid="68">The repair utterances in Figure 2 are A3 through U6, thus c2(D1) is 10 utterances and c2(S4) is 2 utterances.</S>
    <S sid="92" ssid="69">The repair utterance in Figure 3 is U2, but note that according to the AVM task tagging, U2 simultaneously addresses the information goals for depart-range.</S>
    <S sid="93" ssid="70">In general, if an utterance U contributes to the information goals of N different attributes, each attribute accounts for UN of any costs derivable from U.</S>
    <S sid="94" ssid="71">Thus, c2(D2) is .5.</S>
    <S sid="95" ssid="72">Given a set of ci, it is necessary to combine the difwPrevious work has shown that this can be done with high reliability (Hirschman and Pao, 1993). ferent cost measures in order to determine their relative contribution to performance.</S>
    <S sid="96" ssid="73">The next section explains how to combine is with a set of ci to yield an overall performance measure.</S>
    <S sid="97" ssid="74">Given the definition of success and costs above and the model in Figure 1, performance for any (sub)dialogue D is defined as follows:&amp;quot; Here a is a weight on is, the cost functions ci are weighted by wi, and H is a Z score normalization function (Cohen, 1995).</S>
    <S sid="98" ssid="75">The normalization function is used to overcome the problem that the values of ci are not on the same scale as K, and that the cost measures ci may also be calculated over widely varying scales (e.g. response delay could be measured using seconds while, in the example, costs were calculated in terms of number of utterances).</S>
    <S sid="99" ssid="76">This problem is easily solved by normalizing each factor x to its Z score: cr, where is the standard deviation for x.</S>
    <S sid="100" ssid="77">Agents A and B To illustrate the method for estimating.a performance function, we will use a subset of the data from Tables 3 and 4, shown in Table 5.</S>
    <S sid="101" ssid="78">Table 5 represents the results &amp;quot; We assume an additive performance (utility) function because it appears that K and the various cost factors ci are utility independent and additive independent (Keeney and Raiffa, 1976).</S>
    <S sid="102" ssid="79">It is possible however that user satisfaction data collected in future experiments (or other data such as willingness to pay or use) would indicate otherwise.</S>
    <S sid="103" ssid="80">If so, continuing use of an additive function might require a transformation of the data, a reworking of the model shown in Figure 1, or the inclusion of interaction terms in the model (Cohen, 1995). from a hypothetical experiment in which eight users were randomly assigned to communicate with Agent A and eight users were randomly assigned to communicate with Agent B.</S>
    <S sid="104" ssid="81">Table 5 shows user satisfaction (US) ratings (discussed below), is, number of utterances (#utt) and number of repair utterances (#rep) for each of these users.</S>
    <S sid="105" ssid="82">Users 5 and 11 correspond to the dialogues in Figures 2 and 3 respectively.</S>
    <S sid="106" ssid="83">To normalize ci for user 5, we determine that FT is 38.6 and cc, is 18.9.</S>
    <S sid="107" ssid="84">Thus, H(ci ) is -0.83.</S>
    <S sid="108" ssid="85">Similarly .1V(ci) for user 11 is -1.51.</S>
    <S sid="109" ssid="86">To estimate the performance function, the weights a and wi must be solved for.</S>
    <S sid="110" ssid="87">Recall that the claim implicit in Figure 1 was that the relative contribution of task success and dialogue costs to performance should be calculated by considering their contribution to user satisfaction.</S>
    <S sid="111" ssid="88">User satisfaction is typically calculated with surveys that ask users to specify the degree to which they agree with one or more statements about the behavior or the performance of the system.</S>
    <S sid="112" ssid="89">A single user satisfaction measure can be calculated from a single question, or as the mean of a set of ratings.</S>
    <S sid="113" ssid="90">The hypothetical user satisfaction ratings shown in Table 5 range from a high of 6 to a low of 1.</S>
    <S sid="114" ssid="91">Given a set of dialogues for which user satisfaction (US), is and the set of ci have been collected experimentally, the weights a and wi can be solved for using multiple linear regression.</S>
    <S sid="115" ssid="92">Multiple linear regression produces a set of coefficients (weights) describing the relative contribution of each predictor factor in accounting for the variance in a predicted factor.</S>
    <S sid="116" ssid="93">In this case, on the basis of the model in Figure 1, US is treated as the predicted factor.</S>
    <S sid="117" ssid="94">Normalization of the predictor factors (n and ci) to their Z scores guarantees that the relative magnitude of the coefficients directly indicates the relative contribution of each factor.</S>
    <S sid="118" ssid="95">Regression on the Table 5 data for both sets of users tests which factors K, kat, #rep most strongly predicts US.</S>
    <S sid="119" ssid="96">In this illustrative example, the results of the regression with all factors included shows that only K and #rep are significant (p &lt; .02).</S>
    <S sid="120" ssid="97">In order to develop a performance function estimate that includes only significant factors and eliminates redundancies, a second regression including only significant factors must then be done.</S>
    <S sid="121" ssid="98">In this case, a second regression yields the predictive equation: i.e., a is .40 and w2 is .78.</S>
    <S sid="122" ssid="99">The results also show rc is significant at p &lt; .0003, #rep significant at p &lt; .0001, and the combination of is and #rep account for 92% of the variance in US, the external validation criterion.</S>
    <S sid="123" ssid="100">The factor #utt was not a significant predictor of performance, in part because #utt and #rep are highly redundant.</S>
    <S sid="124" ssid="101">(The correlation between #utt and #rep is 0.91).</S>
    <S sid="125" ssid="102">Given these predictions about the relative contribution of different factors to performance, it is then possible to return to the problem first introduced in Section 1: given potentially conflicting performance criteria such as robustness and efficiency, how can the performance of Agent A and Agent B be compared?</S>
    <S sid="126" ssid="103">Given values for a and wi , performance can be calculated for both agents using the equation above.</S>
    <S sid="127" ssid="104">The mean performance of A is -.44 and the mean performance of B is .44, suggesting that Agent B may perform better than Agent A overall.</S>
    <S sid="128" ssid="105">The evaluator must then however test these performance differences for statistical significance.</S>
    <S sid="129" ssid="106">In this case, a t test shows that differences are only significant at the p &lt;.07 level, indicating a trend only.</S>
    <S sid="130" ssid="107">In this case, an evaluation over a larger subset of the user population would probably show significant differences.</S>
    <S sid="131" ssid="108">Since both tc and ci can be calculated over subdialogues, performance can also be calculated at the subdialogue level by using the values for a and wi as solved for above.</S>
    <S sid="132" ssid="109">This assumes that the factors that are predictive of global performance, based on US, generalize as predictors of local performance, i.e. within subdialogues defined by subtasks, as defined by the attribute tagging.I2 Consider calculating the performance of the dialogue strategies used by train timetable Agents A and B, over the subdialogues that repair the value of depart-city.</S>
    <S sid="133" ssid="110">Segment S3 (Figure 4) is an example of such a subdialogue with Agent A.</S>
    <S sid="134" ssid="111">As in the initial estimation of a performance function, our analysis requires experimental data, namely a set of values for and c, and the application of the Z score normalization function to this data.</S>
    <S sid="135" ssid="112">However, the values for rc and ci are now calculated at the subdialogue rather than the whole dialogue level.</S>
    <S sid="136" ssid="113">In addition, only data from comparable strategies can be used to calculate the mean and standard deviation for normalization.</S>
    <S sid="137" ssid="114">Informally, a comparable strategy is one which applies in the same state and has the same effects.</S>
    <S sid="138" ssid="115">For example, to calculate for Agent A over the subdialogues that repair depart-city, P(A) and P(E) are computed using only the subpart of Table 3 concerned with depart-city.</S>
    <S sid="139" ssid="116">For Agent A, P(A) = .78, P(E) = .265, and frc = .70.</S>
    <S sid="140" ssid="117">Then, this value of is is normalized using data from comparable subdialogues with both Agent A and Agent B.</S>
    <S sid="141" ssid="118">Based on the data in Tables 3 and 4, the mean is .515 and a is .261, so that H(x) for Agent A is .71.</S>
    <S sid="142" ssid="119">To calculate c2 for Agent A, assume that the average number of repair utterances for Agent A's subdialogues that repair depart-city is 6, that the mean over all comparable repair subdialogues is 4, and the standard deviation is 2.79.</S>
    <S sid="143" ssid="120">Then H(c2) is .72.</S>
    <S sid="144" ssid="121">Let Agent A's repair dialogue strategy for subdialogues repairing depart-city be RA and Agent B's repair strategy for depart-city be Rg.</S>
    <S sid="145" ssid="122">Then using the performance equation above, predicted performance for RA is: For Agent B, using the appropriate subpart of Table 4 to calculate lc, assuming that the average number of depart-city repair utterances is 1.38, and using similar I2This assumption has a sound basis in theories of dialogue structure (Carberry, 1989; Grosz and Sidner, 1986; Litman and Allen, 1990), but should be tested empirically. calculations, yields Performance(RB ) = .40* &#8212;.71 &#8212; .78 * &#8212;.94 = 0.45 Thus the results of these experiments predict that when an agent needs to choose between the repair strategy that Agent B uses and the repair strategy that Agent A uses for repairing depart-city, it should use Agent B's strategy RB, since the performance(RB) is predicted to be greater than the performance(RA ).</S>
    <S sid="146" ssid="123">Note that the ability to calculate performance over subdialogues allows us to conduct experiments that simultaneously test multiple dialogue strategies.</S>
    <S sid="147" ssid="124">For example, suppose Agents A and B had different strategies for presenting the value of depart-time (in addition to different confirmation strategies).</S>
    <S sid="148" ssid="125">Without the ability to calculate performance over subdialogues, it would be impossible to test the effect of the different presentation strategies independently of the different confirmation strategies.</S>
    <S sid="149" ssid="126">We have presented the PARADISE framework, and have used it to evaluate two hypothetical dialogue agents in a simplified train timetable task domain.</S>
    <S sid="150" ssid="127">We used PARADISE to derive a performance function for this task, by estimating the relative contribution of a set of potential predictors to user satisfaction.</S>
    <S sid="151" ssid="128">The PARADISE methodology consists of the following steps: Note that all of these steps are required to develop the performance function.</S>
    <S sid="152" ssid="129">However once the weights in the performance function have been solved for, user satisfaction ratings no longer need to be collected.</S>
    <S sid="153" ssid="130">Instead, predictions about user satisfaction can be made on the basis of the predictor variables, as illustrated in the application of PARADISE to subdialogues.</S>
    <S sid="154" ssid="131">Given the current state of knowledge, it is important to emphasize that researchers should be cautious about generalizing a derived performance function to other agents or tasks.</S>
    <S sid="155" ssid="132">Performance function estimation should be done iteratively over many different tasks and dialogue strategies to see which factors generalize.</S>
    <S sid="156" ssid="133">In this way, the field can make progress on identifying the relationship between various factors and can move towards more predictive models of spoken dialogue agent performance.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="3 Generality" number="3">
    <S sid="157" ssid="1">In the previous section we used PARADISE to evaluate two confirmation strategies, using as examples fairly simple information access dialogues in the train timetable domain.</S>
    <S sid="158" ssid="2">In this section we demonstrate that PARADISE is applicable to a range of tasks, domains, and dialogues, by presenting AVMs for two tasks involving more than information access, and showing how additional dialogue phenomena can be tagged using AVM attributes.</S>
    <S sid="159" ssid="3">First, consider an extension of the train timetable task, where an agent can handle requests to reserve a seat or purchase a ticket.</S>
    <S sid="160" ssid="4">This task could be represented using the AVM in Table 6 (an extension of Table 1), where the agent must now acquire the value of the attribute request-type, in order to know what to do with the other information it has acquired.</S>
    <S sid="161" ssid="5">Figure 5 presents a hypothetical dialogue in this extended task domain, and illustrates user utterance types and an agent dialogue strategy that are very different from those in Figures 2 and 3.</S>
    <S sid="162" ssid="6">First, Agent C in Figure 5 uses a &amp;quot;no confirmation&amp;quot; dialogue strategy, in contrast to the explicit and implicit confirmation strategies used in Figures 2 and 3.</S>
    <S sid="163" ssid="7">Second, Figure 5 illustrates new types of user utterances that do not directly further the informational goals of the task.</S>
    <S sid="164" ssid="8">In U2, the user asks the agent a wh-question about the DR attribute itself, rather than providing information about that attribute's value.</S>
    <S sid="165" ssid="9">Since U2 satisfies a knowledge precondition related to answering Cl, U2 contributes to the DR goal and is tagged as such.</S>
    <S sid="166" ssid="10">In U3, the user similarly asks a yes-no question that addresses a subgoal related to answering Cl.</S>
    <S sid="167" ssid="11">Finally, U5 illustrates a user request for an agent action, and is tagged with the RT attribute.</S>
    <S sid="168" ssid="12">The value of RT in the AVM instantiation for the dialogue would be &amp;quot;reserve?'</S>
    <S sid="169" ssid="13">Second, consider the very different domain and task of diagnosing a fault and repairing a circuit (Smith and Gordon, 1997).</S>
    <S sid="170" ssid="14">Figure 6 presents one dialogue from this domain.</S>
    <S sid="171" ssid="15">Smith and Gordon collected 144 dialogues for this task, in which agent initiative was varied by using different dialogue strategies, and tagged each dialogue according to the following subtask structure:13 Our informational analysis of this task results in the AVM shown in Table 7.</S>
    <S sid="172" ssid="16">Note that the attributes are almost identical to Smith and Gordon's list of subtasks.</S>
    <S sid="173" ssid="17">CircuitID corresponds to Introduction, Correct-Circuit-Behavior and Current-Circuit-Behavior correspond to Assessment, Fault-Type corresponds to Diagnosis, Fault-Correction corresponds to Repair, and Test corresponds to Test.</S>
    <S sid="174" ssid="18">The attribute names emphasize information exchange, while the subtask names emphasize function.</S>
    <S sid="175" ssid="19">Figure 6 is tagged with the attributes from Table 7.</S>
    <S sid="176" ssid="20">Smith and Gordon's tagging of this dialogue according to their subtask representation was as follows: turns 14 were I, turns 5-14 were A, turns 15-16 were D, turns 17-18 were R, and turns 19-35 were T. Note that there are only two differences between the dialogue structures yielded by the two tagging schemes.</S>
    <S sid="177" ssid="21">First, in our scheme (Figure 6), the greetings (turns 1 and 2) are tagged with all the attributes.</S>
    <S sid="178" ssid="22">Second, Smith and Gordon's single tag A corresponds to two attribute tags in Table 7, which in our scheme defines an extra level of structure within assessment subdialogues.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="4 Discussion" number="4">
    <S sid="179" ssid="1">This paper presented the PARADISE framework for evaluating spoken dialogue agents.</S>
    <S sid="180" ssid="2">PARADISE is a general framework for evaluating spoken dialogue agents that integrates and enhances previous work.</S>
    <S sid="181" ssid="3">PARADISE supports comparisons among dialogue strategies with a task representation that decouples what an agent needs to achieve in terms of the task requirements from how the agent carries out the task via dialogue.</S>
    <S sid="182" ssid="4">Furthermore, this task representation supports the calculation of performance over subdialogues as well as whole dialogues.</S>
    <S sid="183" ssid="5">In addition, because PARADISE's success measure normalizes for task complexity, it provides a basis for comparing agents performing different tasks.</S>
    <S sid="184" ssid="6">The PARADISE performance measure is a function of both task success (K) and dialogue costs (ci), and has a number of advantages.</S>
    <S sid="185" ssid="7">First, it allows us to evaluate performance at any level of a dialogue, since K and ci can be calculated for any dialogue subtask.</S>
    <S sid="186" ssid="8">Since performance can be measured over any subtask, and since dialogue strategies can range over subdialogues or the whole dialogue, we can associate performance with individual dialogue strategies.</S>
    <S sid="187" ssid="9">Second, because our success measure K takes into account the complexity of the task, comparisons can be made across dialogue tasks.</S>
    <S sid="188" ssid="10">Third, K allows us to measure partial success at achieving the task.</S>
    <S sid="189" ssid="11">Fourth, performance can combine both objective and subjective cost measures, and specifies how to evaluate the relative contributions of those costs factors to overall performance.</S>
    <S sid="190" ssid="12">Finally, to our knowledge, we are the first to propose using user satisfaction to determine weights on factors related to performance.</S>
    <S sid="191" ssid="13">In addition, this approach is broadly integrative, incorporating aspects of transaction success, concept accuracy, multiple cost measures, and user satisfaction.</S>
    <S sid="192" ssid="14">In our framework, transaction success is reflected in K, corresponding to dialogues with a P(A) of 1.</S>
    <S sid="193" ssid="15">Our performance measure also captures information similar to concept accuracy, where low concept accuracy scores translate into either higher costs for acquiring information from the user, or lower K scores.</S>
    <S sid="194" ssid="16">One limitation of the PARADISE approach is that the task-based success measure does not reflect that some solutions might be better than others.</S>
    <S sid="195" ssid="17">For example, in the train timetable domain, we might like our task-based success measure to give higher ratings to agents that suggest express over local trains, or that provide helpful information that was not explicitly requested, especially since the better solutions might occur in dialogues with higher costs.</S>
    <S sid="196" ssid="18">It might be possible to address this limitation by using the interval scaled data version of K (Krippendorf, 1980).</S>
    <S sid="197" ssid="19">Another possibility is to simply substitute a domain-specific task-based success measure in the performance model for K. The evaluation model presented here has many applications in apoken dialogue processing.</S>
    <S sid="198" ssid="20">We believe that the framework is also applicable to other dialogue modalities, and to human-human task-oriented dialogues.</S>
    <S sid="199" ssid="21">In addition, while there are many proposals in the literature for algorithms for dialogue strategies that are cooperative, collaborative or helpful to the user (Webber and Joshi, 1982; Pollack, Hirschberg, and Webber, 1982; Joshi, Webber, and Weischedel, 1984; Chu-Carrol and Carberry, 1995), very few of these strategies have been evaluated as to whether they improve any measurable aspect of a dialogue interaction.</S>
    <S sid="200" ssid="22">As we have demonstrated here, any dialogue strategy can be evaluated, so it should be possible to show that a cooperative response, or other cooperative strategy, actually improves task performance by reducing costs or increasing task success.</S>
    <S sid="201" ssid="23">We hope that this framework will be broadly applied in future dialogue research.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="5 Acknowledgments" number="5">
    <S sid="202" ssid="1">We would like to thank James Allen, Jennifer ChuCarroll, Morena Danieli, Wieland Eckert, Giuseppe Di Fabbrizio, Don Hindle, Julia Hirschberg, Shri Narayanan, Jay Wilpon, Steve Whittaker and three anonymous reviews for helpful discussion and comments on earlier versions of this paper.</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
