<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">This paper investigates adapting a lexicalized probabilistic context-free grammar (PCFG) to a novel domain, using maximum a posteriori (MAP) estimation.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">The MAP framework is gen­eral enough to include some previous model adaptation approaches, such as corpus mixing in Gildea (2001), for example.</S>
		<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">Other approaches falling within this framework are more effec­tive.</S>
		<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">In contrast to the results in Gildea (2001), we show F-measure parsing accuracy gains of as much as 2.5% for high accuracy lexicalized pars­ing through the use of out-of-domain treebanks, with the largest gains when the amount of in-domain data is small.</S>
		<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">MAP adaptation can also be based on either supervised or unsupervised adap­tation data.</S>
		<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">Even when no in-domain treebank is available, unsupervised techniques provide a sub­stantial accuracy gain over unadapted grammars, as much as nearly 5% F-measure improvement.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">A fundamental concern for nearly all data-driven ap­proaches to language processing is the sparsity of la­beled training data.</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">The sparsity of syntactically anno­tated corpora is widely remarked upon, and some recent papers present approaches to improving performance in the absence of large amounts of annotated training data.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">Johnson and Riezler (2000) looked at adding features to a maximum entropy model for stochastic uni.cation-based grammars (SUBG), from corpora that are not annotated with the SUBG, but rather with simpler treebank annota­tions for which there are much larger treebanks.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">Hwa (2001) demonstrated how active learning techniques can reduce the amount of annotated data required to converge on the best performance, by selecting from among the candidate strings to be annotated in ways which promote more in­formative examples for earlier annotation.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">Hwa (1999) and Gildea (2001) looked at adapting parsing models trained on large amounts of annotated data from outside of the domain of interest (out-of-domain), through the use of a relatively small amount of in-domain annotated data.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">Hwa (1999) used a variant of the inside-outside algorithm presented in Pereira and Schabes (1992) to exploit a partially labeled out-of-domain treebank, and found an advantage to adapta­tion over direct grammar induction.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">Gildea (2001) simply added the out-of-domain treebank to his in-domain training data, and derived a very small bene.t for his high accuracy, lexicalized parser, concluding that even a large amount of out-of-domain data is of little use for lexicalized parsing.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">Statistical model adaptation based on sparse in-domain data, however, is neither a new problem nor unique to pars­ing.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">It has been studied extensively by researchers work­ing on acoustic modeling for automatic speech recognition (ASR) (Legetter and Woodland, 1995; Gauvain and Lee, 1994; Gales, 1998; Lamel et al., 2002).</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">One of the meth­ods that has received much attention in the ASR literature is maximum a posteriori (MAP) estimation (Gauvain and Lee, 1994).</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">In MAP estimation, the parameters of the model are considered to be random variables themselves with a known distribution (the prior).</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">The prior distribution and the max­imum likelihood distribution based on the in-domain obser­vations then give a posterior distribution over the parame­ters, from which the mode is selected.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">If the amount of in-domain (adaptation) data is large, the mode of the posterior distribution is mostly de.ned by the adaptation sample; if the amount of adaptation data is small, the mode will nearly coincide with the mode of the prior distribution.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "20">The intu­ition behind MAP estimation is that once there are suf.cient observations, the prior model need no longer be relied upon.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "21">Bacchiani and Roark (2003) investigated MAP adapta­tion of n-gram language models, in a way that is straight­forwardly applicable to probabilistic context-free grammars (PCFGs).</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "22">Indeed, this approach can be used for any gen­erative probabilistic model, such as part-of-speech taggers.</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "23">In their language modeling approach, in-domain counts are mixed with the out-of-domain model, so that, if the num­ber of observations within the domain is small, the out-of-domain model is relied upon, whereas if the number of observations in the domain is high, the model will move toward a Maximum Likelihood (ML) estimate on the in-domain data alone.</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "24">The case of a parsing model trained via relative frequency estimation is identical: in-domain counts can be combined with the out-of-domain model in just such a way.</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "25">We will show below that weighted count merging is a special case of MAP adaptation; hence the approach of Gildea (2001) cited above is also a special case of MAPadaptation, with a particular parameterization of the prior.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "26">This parameterization is not necessarily the one that opti­mizes performance.</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "27">In the next section, MAP estimation for PCFGs is pre­sented.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "28">This is followed by a brief presentation of the PCFG model that is being learned, and the parser that is used for the empirical trials.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "29">We will present empirical results for multiple MAP adaptation schema, both starting from the Penn Wall St. Journal treebank and adapting to the Brown corpus, and vice versa.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "30">We will compare our su­pervised adaptation performance with the results presented in Gildea (2001).</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "31">In addition to supervised adaptation, i.e. with a manually annotated treebank, we will present results for unsupervised adaptation, i.e. with an automatically an-a set of rule productions P of the form: A . ., where A . V and . .</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "32">(V . T )* . A probabilistic context-free grammar (PCFG) is a CFG with a probability assigned to each rule, such that the probabilities of all rules expanding a given non-terminal sum to one; speci.cally, each right-hand side has a probability given the left-hand side of the rule1.</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "33">Let A denote the left-hand side of a production, and .i the i-th possible expansion of A. Let the probability estimate for the production A . .i according to the out-of-domain model be denoted as cP(.i | A) and let the expected adapta­tion counts be denoted as c(A . .i).</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "34">Then the parameters of the prior distribution for left-hand side A are chosen as .A i = tA c P(.i | A)+1 1 = i = K.</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "35">(4) notated treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "36">We investigate a number of unsupervised where tA is the left-hand side dependent prior weighting pa-approaches, including multiple iterations, increased sample rameter.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "37">This choice of prior parameters de.nes the MAP sizes, and self-adaptation.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="MAP estimation. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "1">estimate of the probability of expansion .i from the left-hand side A as tA c In the maximum a posteriori estimation framework de­ ˆ P(.i | A)= scribed in detail in Gauvain and Lee (1994), the model pa­ + tA P(.i | A)+ c(A . .i) 1 = i = K.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "2">(5) K k=1 c(A . .k) rameters . are assumed to be a random vector in the space Note that the MAP estimates with this parameterization re­ T. Given an observation sample x, the MAP estimate is obduce to the out-of-domain model parameters in the absence tained as the mode of the posterior distribution of . denoted as g(.</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "3">| x) of adaptation data.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "4">Each left-hand side A has its own prior distribution, pa­ rameterized with tA . This presents an over-parameterization.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "5">problem.</S>
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "6">We follow Gauvain and Lee (1994) in adopt­ .MAP = argmax g(.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "7">| x) = argmax f(x | .)g(.)</S>
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "8">(1) ..</S>
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "9">In the case of n-gram model adaptation, as discussed in Bacchiani and Roark (2003), the objective is to estimate probabilities for a discrete distribution across words, en­tirely analogous to the distribution across mixture compo­nents within a mixture density, which is a common use for MAP estimation in ASR.</S>
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "10">A practical candidate for the prior distribution of the weights .1,.2, ··· ,.K , is its conjugate prior, the Dirichlet density, K K ing a parameter tying approach.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "11">As pointed out in Bacchiani and Roark (2003), two methods of parameter ty­ing, in fact, correspond to two well known model mixing approaches, namely count merging and model interpolation.</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "12">Let cc denote the probabilities and counts from the P and cout-of-domain model, and let P and c denote the probabili­ties and counts from the adaptation model (i.e. in-domain).</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "13">2.1 Count Merging.</S>
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "14">If the left-hand side dependent prior weighting parameter is chosen as ..i-1 i (2) ag(.1,.2, ··· ,.K | .1,.2, ··· ,.K ) . tA = cc(A) (6) , ß i=1 where .i &gt; 0 are the parameters of the Dirichlet distribu­tion.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "15">With such a prior, if the expected counts for the i-th component is denoted as ci, the mode of the posterior distri­bution is obtained as (.i - 1) + ci .ˆi = K K 1 = i = K.</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "16">(3) (.k - 1) + k=1k=1 ck We can use this formulation to estimate the posterior, but we must still choose the parameters of the Dirichlet.</S>
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "17">First, let us introduce some notation.</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "18">A context-free grammar (CFG) G =(V, T, P, S†), consists of a set of non-terminal symbols V , a set of terminal symbols T , a start symbol S† . V , and the MAP adaptation reduces to count merging, scaling the out-of-domain counts with a factor a and the in-domain counts with a factor ß: cc(A) a Pc(.i | A)+ c(A . .i)ˆß P(.i | A)= c (A) a + c(A) ß acc(A . .i)+ ßc(A . .i) = (7) ac (A)+ ßc(A) 1An additional condition for well-formedness is that the PCFG is consistent or tight, i.e. there is no probability mass lost to in­.nitely large trees.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "19">Chi and Geman (1998) proved that this con­dition is met if the rule probabilities are estimated using relative frequency estimation from a corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "20">2.2 Model Interpolation.</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "21">If the left-hand side dependent prior weighting parameter is chosen as . c(A) 1-.</S>
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "22">, 0 &lt;.&lt; 1 if c(A) &gt; 0 tA =(8) 1 otherwise the MAP adaptation reduces to model interpolation using interpolation parameter .: . c c(A) P(.i | A)+ c(A . .i) 1-.</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "23">P (.i | A)= . c(A)+ c(A) 1-.</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "24">c P(.i | A)+ P(.i | A) 1-.</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "25">= . 1-.</S>
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "26">+1 = .cP(.i | A) + (1 - .)P(.i | A) (9) 2.3 Other Tying Candidates.</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "27">While we will not be presenting empirical results for other parameter tying approaches in this paper, we should point out that the MAP framework is general enough to allow for other schema, which could potentially improve perfor­mance over simple count merging and model interpolation approaches.</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "28">For example, one may choose a more com­plicated left-hand side dependent prior weighting parameter such as . c(A) , 0 &lt;.&lt; 1 if c (A) » c(A) &gt;.</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "29">t=1-.</S>
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "30">A c (A) a ß otherwise (10) for some threshold ..</S>
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "31">Such a schema may do a better job of managing how quickly the model moves away from the prior, particularly if there is a large difference in the respec­tive sizes of the in-domain and out-of domain corpora.</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "32">We leave the investigation of such approaches to future research.</S>
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "33">Before providing empirical results on the count merging and model interpolation approaches, we will introduce the parser and parsing models that were used.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Grammar and parser. " number = "3">
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "1">For the empirical trials, we used a top-down, left-to-right (incremental) statistical beam-search parser (Roark, 2001a; Roark, 2003).</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "2">We refer readers to the cited papers for de­tails on this parsing algorithm.</S>
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "3">Brie.y, the parser maintains a set of candidate analyses, each of which is extended to attempt to incorporate the next word into a fully connected partial parse.</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "4">As soon as “enough” candidate parses have been extended to the next word, all parses that have not yet attached the word are discarded, and the parser moves on to the next word.</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "5">This beam search is parameterized with a base beam parameter ., which controls how many or how few parses constitute “enough”.</S>
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "6">Candidate parses are ranked by a .gure-of-merit, which promotes better can­didates, so that they are worked on earlier.</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "7">The .gure-of­merit consists of the probability of the parse to that point times a look-ahead statistic, which is an estimate of how much probability mass it will take to connect the parse with the next word.</S>
			<S sid ="78" ssid = "8">It is a generative parser that does not require any pre-processing, such as POS tagging or chunking.</S>
			<S sid ="79" ssid = "9">It has been demonstrated in the above papers to perform compet­itively on standard statistical parsing tasks with full cover­age.</S>
			<S sid ="80" ssid = "10">Baseline results below will provide a comparison with other well known statistical parsers.</S>
			<S sid ="81" ssid = "11">The PCFG is a Markov grammar (Collins, 1997; Char­niak, 2000), i.e. the production probabilities are estimated by decomposing the joint probability of the categories on the right-hand side into a product of conditionals via the chain rule, and making a Markov assumption.</S>
			<S sid ="82" ssid = "12">Thus, for example, a .rst order Markov grammar conditions the probability of the category of the i-th child of the left-hand side on the cat­egory of the left-hand side and the category of the (i-1)-th child of the left-hand side.</S>
			<S sid ="83" ssid = "13">The bene.ts of Markov gram­mars for a top-down parser of the sort we are using is de­tailed in Roark (2003).</S>
			<S sid ="84" ssid = "14">Further, as in Roark (2001a; 2003), the production probabilities are conditioned on the label of the left-hand side of the production, as well as on features from the left-context.</S>
			<S sid ="85" ssid = "15">The model is smoothed using standard deleted interpolation, wherein a mixing parameter . is esti­mated using EM on a held out corpus, such that probability of a production A . ., conditioned on j features from the left context, Xj = X1 ...Xj, is de.ned recursively as 1 jj P(A . . | X)= P(.</S>
			<S sid ="86" ssid = "16">| A, X) (11) 11 jj1 = (1 - .)P (.</S>
			<S sid ="87" ssid = "17">| A, X)+ .P(.</S>
			<S sid ="88" ssid = "18">| A, X) 11 where P is the maximum likelihood estimate of the condi­tional probability.</S>
			<S sid ="89" ssid = "19">These conditional probabilities decom­pose via the chain rule as mentioned above, and a Markov assumption limits the number of previous children already emitted from the left-hand side that are conditioned upon.</S>
			<S sid ="90" ssid = "20">These previous children are treated exactly as other con­ditioning features from the left context.</S>
			<S sid ="91" ssid = "21">Table 1 gives the conditioning features that were used for all empirical trials in this paper.</S>
			<S sid ="92" ssid = "22">There are different conditioning features for parts-of-speech (POS) and non-POS non-terminals.</S>
			<S sid ="93" ssid = "23">Deleted interpolation leaves out one feature at a time, in the reverse order as they are presented in the table 1.</S>
			<S sid ="94" ssid = "24">The grammar that is used for these trials is a PCFG that is induced using relative frequency estimation from a trans­formed treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="95" ssid = "25">The trees are transformed with a selec­tive left-corner transformation (Johnson and Roark, 2000) that has been .attened as presented in Roark (2001b).</S>
			<S sid ="96" ssid = "26">This transform is only applied to left-recursive productions, i.e. productions of the form A . A..</S>
			<S sid ="97" ssid = "27">The transformed trees look as in .gure 1.</S>
			<S sid ="98" ssid = "28">The transform has the bene.t for a top-down incremental parser of this sort of delaying many of the parsing decisions until later in the string, without un­duly disrupting the immediate dominance relationships that provide conditioning features for the probabilistic model.</S>
			<S sid ="99" ssid = "29">(a) NP NP NP NN NNP POS dog Jim ’s PP (b) NP NNP POS NP/NP (c) NP NNP POS NP/NP NP/NP IN with . . .NP Jim ’s NN dog NP/NP PP IN NP Jim ’s NN dog PP IN with . . .</S>
			<S sid ="100" ssid = "30">NP with . . .</S>
			<S sid ="101" ssid = "31">Figure 1: Three representations of NP modi.cations: (a) the original treebank representation; (b) Selective left-corner representation; and (c) a .at structure that is unambiguously equivalent to (b) Features for non-POS left-hand sides 0 Left-hand side (LHS).</S>
			<S sid ="102" ssid = "32">1 Last child of LHS.</S>
			<S sid ="103" ssid = "33">2 2nd last child of LHS 3 3rd last child of LHS</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Parent of LHS (PAR). " number = "4">
			<S sid ="104" ssid = "1">6 Parent of PAR (GPAR).</S>
			<S sid ="105" ssid = "2">7 Last child of GPAR.</S>
			<S sid ="106" ssid = "3">8 First child of conjoined category.</S>
			<S sid ="107" ssid = "4">9 Lexical head of current constituent.</S>
			<S sid ="108" ssid = "5">Features for POS left-hand sides 0 Left-hand side (LHS).</S>
			<S sid ="109" ssid = "6">1 Parent of LHS (PAR).</S>
			<S sid ="110" ssid = "7">2 Last child of PAR.</S>
			<S sid ="111" ssid = "8">3 Parent of PAR (GPAR).</S>
			<S sid ="112" ssid = "9">4 POS of C-Commanding head.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="C-Commanding lexical head  " number = "5">
			<S sid ="113" ssid = "1">Table 1: Conditioning features for the probabilistic CFG used in the reported empirical trials The parse trees that are returned by the parser are then de­transformed to the original form of the grammar for evalua­tion2.</S>
			<S sid ="114" ssid = "2">For the trials reported in the next section, the base beam parameter is set at . = 10.</S>
			<S sid ="115" ssid = "3">In order to avoid being pruned, a parse must be within a probability range of the best scoring parse that has incorporated the next word.</S>
			<S sid ="116" ssid = "4">Let k be the num­ber of parses that have incorporated the next word, and let p˜be the best probability from among that set.</S>
			<S sid ="117" ssid = "5">Then the prob­ pk3 ability of a parse must be above ˜to avoid being pruned.</S>
			<S sid ="118" ssid = "6">10.</S>
			<S sid ="119" ssid = "7">2See Johnson (1998) for a presentation of the transform/de­transform paradigm in parsing.</S>
			<S sid ="120" ssid = "8">4 Empirical trials.</S>
			<S sid ="121" ssid = "9">The parsing models were trained and tested on treebanks from the Penn Treebank II.</S>
			<S sid ="122" ssid = "10">For the Wall St. Journal portion, we used the standard breakdown: sections 221 were kept training data; section 24 was held-out development data; and section 23 was for evaluation.</S>
			<S sid ="123" ssid = "11">For the Brown corpus por­tion, we obtained the training and evaluation sections used in Gildea (2001).</S>
			<S sid ="124" ssid = "12">In that paper, no held-out section was used for parameter tuning3, so we further partitioned the training data into kept and held-out data.</S>
			<S sid ="125" ssid = "13">The sizes of the corpora are given in table 2, as well as labels that are used to refer to the corpora in subsequent tables.</S>
			<S sid ="126" ssid = "14">4.1 Baseline performance.</S>
			<S sid ="127" ssid = "15">The .rst results are for parsing the Brown corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="128" ssid = "16">Table 3 presents our baseline performance, compared with the Gildea (2001) results.</S>
			<S sid ="129" ssid = "17">Our system is labeled as ‘MAP’.</S>
			<S sid ="130" ssid = "18">All parsing results are presented as labeled precision and recall.</S>
			<S sid ="131" ssid = "19">Whereas Gildea (2001) reported parsing results just for sen­tences of length less than or equal to 40, our results are for all sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="132" ssid = "20">The goal is not to improve upon Gildea’s parsing performance, but rather to try to get more bene.t from the out-of-domain data.</S>
			<S sid ="133" ssid = "21">While our performance is 0.5­ 1.5 percent better than Gildea’s, the same trends hold – low eighties in accuracy when using the Wall St. Journal (out-of­domain) training; mid eighties when using the Brown corpus training.</S>
			<S sid ="134" ssid = "22">Notice that using the Brown held out data with the Wall St. Journal training improved precision substantially.</S>
			<S sid ="135" ssid = "23">Tuning the parameters on in-domain data can make a big difference in parser performance.</S>
			<S sid ="136" ssid = "24">Choosing the smoothing parameters as Gildea did, based on the distribution within the corpus itself, may be effective when parsing within the same distribution, but appears less so when using the tree-bank for parsing outside of the domain.</S>
			<S sid ="137" ssid = "25">3According to the author, smoothing parameters for his parser were based on the formula from Collins (1999).</S>
			<S sid ="138" ssid = "26">Corpus;Sect WSJ;221 Used for Training Sentences 39,832 Words 950,028 WSJ;24 Held out 1,346 32,853 WSJ;23 Eval 2,416 56,684 Brown;T Training 19,740 373,152 Brown;H Held out 2,078 40,046 Brown;E Eval 2,425 45,950 Table 2: Corpus sizes System Training Heldout LR LP Gildea WSJ;221 80.3 81.0 MAP WSJ;221 WSJ;24 81.3 80.9 MAP WSJ;221 Brown;H 81.6 82.3 Gildea Brown;T,H 83.6 84.6 MAP Brown;T Brown;H 84.4 85.0 Table 3: Parser performance on Brown;E, baselines.</S>
			<S sid ="139" ssid = "27">Note that the Gildea results are for sentences = 40 words in length.</S>
			<S sid ="140" ssid = "28">Table 4 gives the baseline performance on section 23 of the WSJ Treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="141" ssid = "29">Note, again, that the Gildea results are for sentences = 40 words in length, while all others are for all sentences in the test set.</S>
			<S sid ="142" ssid = "30">Also, Gildea did not report per­formance of a Brown corpus trained parser on the WSJ.</S>
			<S sid ="143" ssid = "31">Our performance under that condition is not particularly good, but again using an in-domain held out set for parameter tun­ing provided a substantial increase in accuracy, somewhat more in terms of precision than recall.</S>
			<S sid ="144" ssid = "32">Our baseline results for a WSJ section 221 trained parser are slightly better than the Gildea parser, at more-or-less the same level of perfor­mance as Charniak (1997) and Ratnaparkhi (1999), but sev­eral points below the best reported results on this task.</S>
			<S sid ="145" ssid = "33">4.2 Supervised adaptation.</S>
			<S sid ="146" ssid = "34">Table 5 presents parsing results on the Brown;E test set for models using both in-domain and out-of-domain training data.</S>
			<S sid ="147" ssid = "35">The table gives the adaptation (in-domain) treebank that was used, and the tA that was used to combine the adap­tation counts with the model built from the out-of-domain treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="148" ssid = "36">Recall that ac (A) times the out-of-domain model yields count merging, with a the ratio of out-of-domain to in-domain counts; and ac(A) times the out-of-domain model yields model interpolation, with a the ratio of out-of­domain to in-domain probabilities.</S>
			<S sid ="149" ssid = "37">Gildea (2001) merged the two corpora, which just adds the counts from the out-of­domain treebank to the in-domain treebank, i.e. a =1.</S>
			<S sid ="150" ssid = "38">This resulted in a 0.25 improvement in the F-measure.</S>
			<S sid ="151" ssid = "39">In our case, combining the counts in this way yielded a half a point, perhaps because of the in-domain tuning of the smoothing parameters.</S>
			<S sid ="152" ssid = "40">However, when we optimize a em­pirically on the held-out corpus, we can get nearly a full point improvement.</S>
			<S sid ="153" ssid = "41">Model interpolation in this case per-Table 4: Parser performance on WSJ;23, baselines.</S>
			<S sid ="154" ssid = "42">Note that the Gildea results are for sentences = 40 words in length.</S>
			<S sid ="155" ssid = "43">All others include all sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="156" ssid = "44">System Training Heldout LR LP MAP Brown;T Brown;H 76.0 75.4 MAP Brown;T WSJ;24 76.9 77.1 Gildea WSJ;221 86.1 86.6 MAP WSJ;221 WSJ;24 86.9 87.1 Charniak (1997) WSJ;221 WSJ;24 86.7 86.6 Ratnaparkhi (1999) WSJ;221 86.3 87.5 Collins (1999) WSJ;221 88.1 88.3 Charniak (2000) WSJ;221 WSJ;24 89.6 89.5 Collins (2000) WSJ;221 89.6 89.9 forms nearly identically to count merging.</S>
			<S sid ="157" ssid = "45">Adaptation to the Brown corpus, however, does not ad­equately represent what is likely to be the most common adaptation scenario, i.e. adaptation to a consistent domain with limited in-domain training data.</S>
			<S sid ="158" ssid = "46">The Brown corpus is not really a domain; it was built as a balanced corpus, and hence is the aggregation of multiple domains.</S>
			<S sid ="159" ssid = "47">The reverse scenario – Brown corpus as out-of-domain parsing model and Wall St. Journal as novel domain – is perhaps a more natural one.</S>
			<S sid ="160" ssid = "48">In this direction, Gildea (2001) also reported very small improvements when adding in the out-of-domain treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="161" ssid = "49">This may be because of the same issue as with the Brown corpus, namely that the optimal ratio of in-domain to out-of-domain is not 1 and the smoothing parameters need to be tuned to the new domain; or it may be because the new domain has a million words of training data, and hence has less use for out-of-domain data.</S>
			<S sid ="162" ssid = "50">To tease these apart, we par­titioned the WSJ training data (sections 221) into smaller treebanks, and looked at the gain provided by adaptation as the in-domain observations grow.</S>
			<S sid ="163" ssid = "51">These smaller treebanks provide a more realistic scenario: rapid adaptation to a novel domain will likely occur with far less manual annotation of trees within the new domain than can be had in the full Penn Treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="164" ssid = "52">Table 6 gives the baseline performance on WSJ;23, with models trained on fractions of the entire 221 test set.</S>
			<S sid ="165" ssid = "53">Sec­tions 221 contain approximately 40,000 sentences, and we partitioned them by percentage of total sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="166" ssid = "54">From ta­ble 6 we can see that parser performance degrades quite dra­matically when there is less than 20,000 sentences in the training set, but that even with just 2000 sentences, the sys­tem outperforms one trained on the Brown corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="167" ssid = "55">Table 7 presents parsing accuracy when a model trained on the Brown corpus is adapted with part or all of the WSJ training corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="168" ssid = "56">From this point forward, we only present results for count merging, since model interpolation con­sistently performed 0.20.5 points below the count merging System Training Heldout Adapt tA Baseline Adapted .F LR LP F LR LP F Gildea WSJ;221 Brown;T,H c (A) 83.6 84.6 84.1 83.9 84.8 84.35 0.25 MAP WSJ;221 Brown;H Brown;T c (A) 84.4 85.0 84.7 84.9 85.6 85.25 0.55 MAP WSJ;221 Brown;H Brown;T 0.25c (A) 84.4 85.0 84.7 85.4 85.9 85.65 0.95 MAP WSJ;221 Brown;H Brown;T 0.20c(A) 84.4 85.0 84.7 85.3 85.9 85.60 0.90 Table 5: Parser performance on Brown;E, supervised adaptation System Training % Heldout LR LP MAP WSJ;221 100 WSJ;24 86.9 87.1 MAP WSJ;221 75 WSJ;24 86.6 86.8 MAP WSJ;221 50 WSJ;24 86.3 86.4 MAP WSJ;221 25 WSJ;24 84.8 85.0 MAP WSJ;221 10 WSJ;24 82.6 82.6 MAP WSJ;221 5 WSJ;24 80.4 80.6 Table 6: Parser performance on WSJ;23, baselines performing parameter from the supervised trials, namely 0.20c (A).</S>
			<S sid ="169" ssid = "57">Since we are no longer limited to manually anno­tated data, the amount of in-domain WSJ data that we can include is essentially unlimited.</S>
			<S sid ="170" ssid = "58">Hence the trials reported go beyond the 40,000 sentences in the Penn WSJ Treebank, to include up to 5 times that number of sentences from other years of the WSJ.</S>
			<S sid ="171" ssid = "59">Table 8 shows the results of unsupervised adaptation as we have described it.</S>
			<S sid ="172" ssid = "60">Note that these improvements are had without seeing any manually annotated Wall St. Journal approach4.</S>
			<S sid ="173" ssid = "61">The tA mixing parameter was empirically optitreebank data.</S>
			<S sid ="174" ssid = "62">Using the approximately 40,000 sentences mized on the held out set when the in-domain training was just 10% of the total; this optimization makes over a point difference in accuracy.</S>
			<S sid ="175" ssid = "63">Like Gildea, with large amounts of in-domain data, adaptation improved our performance by half a point or less.</S>
			<S sid ="176" ssid = "64">When the amount of in-domain data is small, however, the impact of adaptation is much greater.</S>
			<S sid ="177" ssid = "65">4.3 Unsupervised adaptation.</S>
			<S sid ="178" ssid = "66">Bacchiani and Roark (2003) presented unsupervised MAP adaptation results for n-gram models, which use the same methods outlined above, but rather than using a manually annotated corpus as input to adaptation, instead use an auto­matically annotated corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="179" ssid = "67">Their automatically annotated corpus was the output of a speech recognizer which used the out-of-domain n-gram model.</S>
			<S sid ="180" ssid = "68">In our case, we use the pars­ing model trained on out-of-domain data, and output a set of candidate parse trees for the strings in the in-domain cor­pus, with their normalized scores.</S>
			<S sid ="181" ssid = "69">These normalized scores (posterior probabilities) are then used to give weights to the features extracted from each candidate parse, in just the way that they provide expected counts for an expectation maxi­mization algorithm.</S>
			<S sid ="182" ssid = "70">For the unsupervised trials that we report, we collected up to 20 candidate parses per string5.</S>
			<S sid ="183" ssid = "71">We were interested in investigating the effects of adaptation, not in optimizing per­formance, hence we did not empirically optimize the mixing parameter tA for the new trials, so as to avoid obscuring the in f221, we derived a 3.8 percent F-measure improvement over using just the out of domain data.</S>
			<S sid ="184" ssid = "72">Going beyond the size of the Penn Treebank, we continued to gain in accuracy, reaching a total F-measure improvement of 4.2 percent with 200 thousand sentences, approximately 5 million words.</S>
			<S sid ="185" ssid = "73">A second iteration with this best model, i.e. re-parsing the 200 thousand sentences with the adapted model and retraining, yielded an additional 0.65 percent F-measure improvement, for a total F-measure improvement of 4.85 percent over the baseline model.</S>
			<S sid ="186" ssid = "74">A .nal unsupervised adaptation scenario that we inves­tigated is self-adaptation, i.e. adaptation on the test set it­self.</S>
			<S sid ="187" ssid = "75">Because this adaptation is completely unsupervised, thus does not involve looking at the manual annotations at all, it can be equally well applied using the test set as the un­supervised adaptation set.</S>
			<S sid ="188" ssid = "76">Using the same adaptation proce­dure presented above on the test set itself, i.e. producing the top 20 candidates from WSJ;23 with normalized posterior probabilities and re-estimating, we produced a self-adapted parsing model.</S>
			<S sid ="189" ssid = "77">This yielded an F-measure accuracy of 76.8, which is a 1.1 percent improvement over the baseline.</S>
			<S sid ="190" ssid = "78">5 Conclusion.</S>
			<S sid ="191" ssid = "79">What we have demonstrated in this paper is that maximum a posteriori (MAP) estimation can make out-of-domain train­ing data bene.cial for statistical parsing.</S>
			<S sid ="192" ssid = "80">In the most likely effects due to adaptation alone.</S>
			<S sid ="193" ssid = "81">Rather, we used the best scenario – porting a parser to a novel domain for which there is little or no annotated data – the improvements can be quite 4This is consistent with the results presented in large.</S>
			<S sid ="194" ssid = "82">Like active learning, model adaptation can reduce the Bacchiani and Roark (2003), which found a small but con amount of annotation required to converge to a best level of performance.</S>
			<S sid ="195" ssid = "83">In fact, MAP coupled with active learning sistent improvement in performance with count merging versus model interpolation for n-gram modeling.</S>
			<S sid ="196" ssid = "84">5Because of the left-to-right, heuristic beam-search, the parser may reduce the required amount of annotation further.</S>
			<S sid ="197" ssid = "85">does not produce a chart, rather a set of completed parses.</S>
			<S sid ="198" ssid = "86">There are a couple of interesting future directions for this System % of WSJ;221 tA Baseline Adapted .F LR LP F LR LP F Gildea 100 c (A) 86.1 86.6 86.35 86.3 86.9 86.60 0.25 MAP 100 0.20c (A) 86.9 87.1 87.00 87.2 87.5 87.35 0.35 MAP 75 0.20c (A) 86.6 86.8 86.70 87.1 87.3 87.20 0.50 MAP 50 0.20c (A) 86.3 86.4 86.35 86.7 86.9 86.80 0.45 MAP 25 0.20c (A) 84.8 85.0 84.90 85.3 85.5 85.40 0.50 MAP 10 0.20c (A) 82.6 82.6 82.60 84.3 84.4 84.35 1.75 MAP 10 c (A) 82.6 82.6 82.60 83.2 83.4 83.30 0.70 MAP 5 0.20c (A) 80.4 80.6 80.50 83.0 83.1 83.05 2.55 Table 7: Parser performance on WSJ;23, supervised adaptation.</S>
			<S sid ="199" ssid = "87">All models use Brown;T,H as the out-of-domain treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="200" ssid = "88">Baseline models are built from the fractions of WSJ;221, with no out-of-domain treebank.</S>
			<S sid ="201" ssid = "89">Adaptation Sentences Iter­ation LR LP F-measure .F 0 0 76.0 75.4 75.70 4000 1 78.6 77.9 78.25 2.55 10000 1 78.9 78.0 78.45 2.75 20000 1 79.3 78.5 78.90 3.20 30000 1 79.7 78.9 79.30 3.60 39832 1 79.9 79.1 79.50 3.80 100000 1 79.7 79.2 79.45 3.75 200000 1 80.2 79.6 79.90 4.20 200000 2 80.6 80.5 80.55 4.85 Table 8: Parser performance on WSJ;23, unsupervised adaptation.</S>
			<S sid ="202" ssid = "90">For all trials, the base training is Brown;T, the held out is Brown;H plus the parser output for WSJ;24, and the mixing parameter tA is 0.20c (A).</S>
			<S sid ="203" ssid = "91">research.</S>
			<S sid ="204" ssid = "92">First, a question that is not addressed in this paper is how to best combine both supervised and unsupervised adaptation data.</S>
			<S sid ="205" ssid = "93">Since each in-domain resource is likely to have a different optimal mixing parameter, since the super­vised data is more reliable than the unsupervised data, this becomes a more dif.cult, multidimensional parameter op­timization problem.</S>
			<S sid ="206" ssid = "94">Hence, we would like to investigate au­tomatic methods for choosing mixing parameters, such as EM.</S>
			<S sid ="207" ssid = "95">Also, an interesting question has to do with choosing which treebank to use for out-of-domain data.</S>
			<S sid ="208" ssid = "96">For a new domain, is it better to choose as prior the balanced Brown corpus, or rather the more robust Wall St. Journal treebank?</S>
			<S sid ="209" ssid = "97">Perhaps one could use several out-of-domain treebanks as priors.</S>
			<S sid ="210" ssid = "98">Most generally, one can imagine using k treebanks, some in-domain, some out-of-domain, and trying to .nd the best mixture to suit the particular task.</S>
			<S sid ="211" ssid = "99">The conclusion in Gildea (2001), that out-of-domain tree-banks are not particularly useful in novel domains, was pre­mature.</S>
			<S sid ="212" ssid = "100">Instead, we can conclude that, just as in other sta­tistical estimation problems, there are generalizations to be had from these out-of-domain trees, providing more robust estimates, especially in the face of sparse training data.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
