<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">Discriminative Training And Maximum Entropy Models For Statistical Machine Translation</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">We present a framework for statistical machine translation of natural languages based on direct maximum entropy models, which contains the widely used source-channel approach as a special case.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">All knowledge sources are treated as feature functions, which depend on the source language sentence, the target language sentence and possible hidden variables.</S>
    <S sid="3" ssid="3">This approach allows a baseline machine translation system to be extended easily by adding new feature functions.</S>
    <S sid="4" ssid="4">We show that a baseline statistical machine translation system is significantly improved using this approach.</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="1 Introduction" number="1">
    <S sid="5" ssid="1">We are given a source (&#8216;French&#8217;) sentence fJ1 = f1, ... , fj, ... , fJ, which is to be translated into a target (&#8216;English&#8217;) sentence eI1 = e1, ... , ei, ... , eI.</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="2">Among all possible target sentences, we will choose the sentence with the highest probability:1 The argmax operation denotes the search problem, i.e. the generation of the output sentence in the target language.</S>
    <S sid="7" ssid="3">According to Bayes&#8217; decision rule, we can equivalently to Eq.</S>
    <S sid="8" ssid="4">1 perform the following maximization: This approach is referred to as source-channel approach to statistical MT.</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="5">Sometimes, it is also referred to as the &#8216;fundamental equation of statistical MT&#8217; (Brown et al., 1993).</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="6">Here, Pr(eI1) is the language model of the target language, whereas Pr(fJ1 |eI1) is the translation model.</S>
    <S sid="11" ssid="7">Typically, Eq.</S>
    <S sid="12" ssid="8">2 is favored over the direct translation model of Eq.</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="9">1 with the argument that it yields a modular approach.</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="10">Instead of modeling one probability distribution, we obtain two different knowledge sources that are trained independently.</S>
    <S sid="15" ssid="11">The overall architecture of the source-channel approach is summarized in Figure 1.</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="12">In general, as shown in this figure, there may be additional transformations to make the translation task simpler for the algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="17" ssid="13">Typically, training is performed by applying a maximum likelihood approach.</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="14">If the language model Pr(eI1) = p&#947;(eI1) depends on parameters &#947; and the translation model Pr(fJ1 |eI1) = p&#952;(fJ1 |eI1) depends on parameters &#952;, then the optimal parameter values are obtained by maximizing the likelihood on a parallel training corpus fS1 , eS1 (Brown et al., 1993): We obtain the following decision rule: instead of Eq.</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="15">5 (Och et al., 1999): State-of-the-art statistical MT systems are based on this approach.</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="16">Yet, the use of this decision rule has various problems: Here, we replaced p&#710;&#65533;(fJ1 |ei) by p&#710;&#65533;(ei|fJ1 ).</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="17">From a theoretical framework of the sourcechannel approach, this approach is hard to justify.</S>
    <S sid="22" ssid="18">Yet, if both decision rules yield the same translation quality, we can use that decision rule which is better suited for efficient search.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="19">As alternative to the source-channel approach, we directly model the posterior probability Pr(ei|fJ1 ).</S>
    <S sid="24" ssid="20">An especially well-founded framework for doing this is maximum entropy (Berger et al., 1996).</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="21">In this framework, we have a set of M feature functions hm(ei, fJ1 ), m = 1, ... , M. For each feature function, there exists a model parameter am, m = 1, ... , M. The direct translation probability is given the following two feature functions: This approach has been suggested by (Papineni et al., 1997; Papineni et al., 1998) for a natural language understanding task.</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="22">We obtain the following decision rule: Hence, the time-consuming renormalization in Eq.</S>
    <S sid="27" ssid="23">8 is not needed in search.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="24">The overall architecture of the direct maximum entropy models is summarized in Figure 2.</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="25">Interestingly, this framework contains as special case the source channel approach (Eq.</S>
    <S sid="30" ssid="26">5) if we use and set A1 = A2 = 1.</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="27">Optimizing the corresponding parameters A1 and A2 of the model in Eq.</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="28">8 is equivalent to the optimization of model scaling factors, which is a standard approach in other areas such as speech recognition or pattern recognition.</S>
    <S sid="33" ssid="29">The use of an &#8216;inverted&#8217; translation model in the unconventional decision rule of Eq.</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="30">6 results if we use the feature function log Pr(eI1|fJ1 ) instead of log Pr(fJ1 |eI1).</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="31">In this framework, this feature can be as good as log Pr(fJ1 |eI1).</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="32">It has to be empirically verified, which of the two features yields better results.</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="33">We even can use both features log Pr(eI1|fJ1 ) and log Pr(fJ1 |eI1), obtaining a more symmetric translation model.</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="34">As training criterion, we use the maximum class posterior probability criterion: This corresponds to maximizing the equivocation or maximizing the likelihood of the direct translation model.</S>
    <S sid="39" ssid="35">This direct optimization of the posterior probability in Bayes decision rule is referred to as discriminative training (Ney, 1995) because we directly take into account the overlap in the probability distributions.</S>
    <S sid="40" ssid="36">The optimization problem has one global optimum and the optimization criterion is convex.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="37">Typically, the probability Pr(fJ1 |eI1) is decomposed via additional hidden variables.</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="38">In statistical alignment models Pr(fJ1 , aJ1 |eI1), the alignment aJ1 is introduced as a hidden variable:</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="2 Alignment Templates" number="2">
    <S sid="43" ssid="1">As specific MT method, we use the alignment template approach (Och et al., 1999).</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="2">The key elements of this approach are the alignment templates, which are pairs of source and target language phrases together with an alignment between the words within the phrases.</S>
    <S sid="45" ssid="3">The advantage of the alignment template approach compared to single word-based statistical translation models is that word context and local changes in word order are explicitly considered.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="4">The alignment template model refines the translation probability Pr(fJ1 |eI1) by introducing two hidden variables zK1 and aK1 for the K alignment templates and the alignment of the alignment templates: The alignment mapping is j &#8594; i = aj from source position j to target position i = aj.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="5">Search is performed using the so-called maximum approximation: Hence, the search space consists of the set of all possible target language sentences eI1 and all possible alignments aJ1 .</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="6">Generalizing this approach to direct translation models, we extend the feature functions to include the dependence on the additional hidden variable.</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="7">Using M feature functions of the form hm(eI1, fJ1 , aJ1), m = 1, ... , M, we obtain the following model: Obviously, we can perform the same step for translation models with an even richer structure of hidden variables than only the alignment aJ1 .</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="8">To simplify the notation, we shall omit in the following the dependence on the hidden variables of the model.</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="9">Hence, we obtain three different probability distributions: Pr(aK1 |eI1), Pr(zK1 |aK1 , eI1) and Pr(fJ1 |zK1 ,aK1 ,eI1).</S>
    <S sid="52" ssid="10">Here, we omit a detailed description of modeling, training and search, as this is not relevant for the subsequent exposition.</S>
    <S sid="53" ssid="11">For further details, see (Och et al., 1999).</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="12">To use these three component models in a direct maximum entropy approach, we define three different feature functions for each component of the translation model instead of one feature function for the whole translation model p(fJ1 |eI1).</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="13">The feature functions have then not only a dependence on fJ1 and eI1 but also on zK1 , aK1 .</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="3 Feature functions" number="3">
    <S sid="56" ssid="1">So far, we use the logarithm of the components of a translation model as feature functions.</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="2">This is a very convenient approach to improve the quality of a baseline system.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="3">Yet, we are not limited to train only model scaling factors, but we have many possibilities: This corresponds to a word penalty for each produced target word.</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="4">&#8226; We could use grammatical features that relate certain grammatical dependencies of source and target language.</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="5">For example, using a function k(&#183;) that counts how many verb groups exist in the source or the target sentence, we can define the following feature, which is 1 if each of the two sentences contains the same number of verb groups: In the same way, we can introduce semantic features or pragmatic features such as the dialogue act classification.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="6">We can use numerous additional features that deal with specific problems of the baseline statistical MT system.</S>
    <S sid="62" ssid="7">In this paper, we shall use the first three of these features.</S>
    <S sid="63" ssid="8">As additional language model, we use a class-based five-gram language model.</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="9">This feature and the word penalty feature allow a straightforward integration into the used dynamic programming search algorithm (Och et al., 1999).</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="10">As this is not possible for the conventional dictionary feature, we use n-best rescoring for this feature.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="4 Training" number="4">
    <S sid="66" ssid="1">To train the model parameters &#955;M1 of the direct translation model according to Eq.</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="2">11, we use the GIS (Generalized Iterative Scaling) algorithm (Darroch and Ratcliff, 1972).</S>
    <S sid="68" ssid="3">It should be noted that, as was already shown by (Darroch and Ratcliff, 1972), by applying suitable transformations, the GIS algorithm is able to handle any type of real-valued features.</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="4">To apply this algorithm, we have to solve various practical problems.</S>
    <S sid="70" ssid="5">The renormalization needed in Eq.</S>
    <S sid="71" ssid="6">8 requires a sum over a large number of possible sentences, for which we do not know an efficient algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="72" ssid="7">Hence, we approximate this sum by sampling the space of all possible sentences by a large set of highly probable sentences.</S>
    <S sid="73" ssid="8">The set of considered sentences is computed by an appropriately extended version of the used search algorithm (Och et al., 1999) computing an approximate n-best list of translations.</S>
    <S sid="74" ssid="9">Unlike automatic speech recognition, we do not have one reference sentence, but there exists a number of reference sentences.</S>
    <S sid="75" ssid="10">Yet, the criterion as it is described in Eq.</S>
    <S sid="76" ssid="11">11 allows for only one reference translation.</S>
    <S sid="77" ssid="12">Hence, we change the criterion to allow Rs reference translations es,1, ... , es,Rs for the sentence es: We use this optimization criterion instead of the optimization criterion shown in Eq.</S>
    <S sid="78" ssid="13">11.</S>
    <S sid="79" ssid="14">In addition, we might have the problem that no single of the reference translations is part of the nbest list because the search algorithm performs pruning, which in principle limits the possible translations that can be produced given a certain input sentence.</S>
    <S sid="80" ssid="15">To solve this problem, we define for maximum entropy training each sentence as reference translation that has the minimal number of word errors with respect to any of the reference translations.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="5 Results" number="5">
    <S sid="81" ssid="1">We present results on the VERBMOBIL task, which is a speech translation task in the domain of appointment scheduling, travel planning, and hotel reservation (Wahlster, 1993).</S>
    <S sid="82" ssid="2">Table 1 shows the corpus statistics of this task.</S>
    <S sid="83" ssid="3">We use a training corpus, which is used to train the alignment template model and the language models, a development corpus, which is used to estimate the model scaling factors, and a test corpus.</S>
    <S sid="84" ssid="4">So far, in machine translation research does not exist one generally accepted criterion for the evaluation of the experimental results.</S>
    <S sid="85" ssid="5">Therefore, we use a large variety of different criteria and show that the obtained results improve on most or all of these criteria.</S>
    <S sid="86" ssid="6">In all experiments, we use the following six error criteria: of the target sentence, so that the WER measure alone could be misleading.</S>
    <S sid="87" ssid="7">To overcome this problem, we introduce as additional measure the position-independent word error rate (PER).</S>
    <S sid="88" ssid="8">This measure compares the words in the two sentences ignoring the word order. more detailed analysis, subjective judgments by test persons are necessary.</S>
    <S sid="89" ssid="9">Each translated sentence was judged by a human examiner according to an error scale from 0.0 to 1.0 (NieBen et al., 2000).</S>
    <S sid="90" ssid="10">&#8226; IER (information item error rate): The test sentences are segmented into information items.</S>
    <S sid="91" ssid="11">For each of them, if the intended information is conveyed and there are no syntactic errors, the sentence is counted as correct (NieBen et al., 2000).</S>
    <S sid="92" ssid="12">In the following, we present the results of this approach.</S>
    <S sid="93" ssid="13">Table 2 shows the results if we use a direct translation model (Eq.</S>
    <S sid="94" ssid="14">6).</S>
    <S sid="95" ssid="15">As baseline features, we use a normal word trigram language model and the three component models of the alignment templates.</S>
    <S sid="96" ssid="16">The first row shows the results using only the four baseline features with &#955;1 = &#183; &#183; &#183; = &#955;4 = 1.</S>
    <S sid="97" ssid="17">The second row shows the result if we train the model scaling factors.</S>
    <S sid="98" ssid="18">We see a systematic improvement on all error rates.</S>
    <S sid="99" ssid="19">The following three rows show the results if we add the word penalty, an additional class-based five-gram GIS algorithm for maximum entropy training of alignment templates. language model and the conventional dictionary features.</S>
    <S sid="100" ssid="20">We observe improved error rates for using the word penalty and the class-based language model as additional features.</S>
    <S sid="101" ssid="21">Figure 3 show how the sentence error rate (SER) on the test corpus improves during the iterations of the GIS algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="102" ssid="22">We see that the sentence error rates converges after about 4000 iterations.</S>
    <S sid="103" ssid="23">We do not observe significant overfitting.</S>
    <S sid="104" ssid="24">Table 3 shows the resulting normalized model scaling factors.</S>
    <S sid="105" ssid="25">Multiplying each model scaling factor by a constant positive value does not affect the decision rule.</S>
    <S sid="106" ssid="26">We see that adding new features also has an effect on the other model scaling factors.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="6 Related Work" number="6">
    <S sid="107" ssid="1">The use of direct maximum entropy translation models for statistical machine translation has been suggested by (Papineni et al., 1997; Papineni et al., 1998).</S>
    <S sid="108" ssid="2">They train models for natural language understanding rather than natural language translation.</S>
    <S sid="109" ssid="3">In contrast to their approach, we include a dependence on the hidden variable of the translation model in the direct translation model.</S>
    <S sid="110" ssid="4">Therefore, we are able to use statistical alignment models, which have been shown to be a very powerful component for statistical machine translation systems.</S>
    <S sid="111" ssid="5">In speech recognition, training the parameters of the acoustic model by optimizing the (average) mutual information and conditional entropy as they are defined in information theory is a standard approach (Bahl et al., 1986; Ney, 1995).</S>
    <S sid="112" ssid="6">Combining various probabilistic models for speech and language modeling has been suggested in (Beyerlein, 1997; Peters and Klakow, 1999).</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="7 Conclusions" number="7">
    <S sid="113" ssid="1">We have presented a framework for statistical MT for natural languages, which is more general than the widely used source-channel approach.</S>
    <S sid="114" ssid="2">It allows a baseline MT system to be extended easily by adding new feature functions.</S>
    <S sid="115" ssid="3">We have shown that a baseline statistical MT system can be significantly improved using this framework.</S>
    <S sid="116" ssid="4">There are two possible interpretations for a statistical MT system structured according to the sourcechannel approach, hence including a model for Pr(ei) and a model for Pr(fi Iei).</S>
    <S sid="117" ssid="5">We can interpret it as an approximation to the Bayes decision rule in Eq.</S>
    <S sid="118" ssid="6">2 or as an instance of a direct maximum entropy model with feature functions log Pr(ei) and log Pr(fi |ei).</S>
    <S sid="119" ssid="7">As soon as we want to use model scaling factors, we can only do this in a theoretically justified way using the second interpretation.</S>
    <S sid="120" ssid="8">Yet, the main advantage comes from the large number of additional possibilities that we obtain by using the second interpretation.</S>
    <S sid="121" ssid="9">An important open problem of this approach is the handling of complex features in search.</S>
    <S sid="122" ssid="10">An interesting question is to come up with features that allow an efficient handling using conventional dynamic programming search algorithms.</S>
    <S sid="123" ssid="11">In addition, it might be promising to optimize the parameters directly with respect to the error rate of the MT system as is suggested in the field of pattern and speech recognition (Juang et al., 1995; Schl&#168;uter and Ney, 2001).</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
