<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">The viability of web-derived polarity lexicons</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">We examine the viability of building large polarity lexicons semi-automatically from the web.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">We begin by describing a graph propagation framework inspired by previous work on constructing polarity lexicons from lexical graphs (Kim and Hovy, 2004; Hu and Liu, 2004; Esuli and Sabastiani, 2009; Blair- Goldensohn et al., 2008; Rao and Ravichandran, 2009).</S>
    <S sid="3" ssid="3">We then apply this technique to build an English lexicon that is significantly larger than those previously studied.</S>
    <S sid="4" ssid="4">Crucially, this web-derived lexicon does not require WordNet, part-of-speech taggers, or other language-dependent resources typical of sentiment analysis systems.</S>
    <S sid="5" ssid="5">As a result, the lexicon is not limited to specific word classes &#8211; e.g., adjectives that occur in WordNet &#8211; and in fact contains slang, misspellings, multiword expressions, etc.</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="6">We evaluate a lexicon derived from English documents, both qualitatively and quantitatively, and show that it provides superior performance to previously studied lexicons, including one derived from</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="1 Introduction" number="1">
    <S sid="7" ssid="1">Polarity lexicons are large lists of phrases that encode the polarity of each phrase within it &#8211; either positive or negative &#8211; often with some score representing the magnitude of the polarity (Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown, 1997; Wiebe, 2000; Turney, 2002).</S>
    <S sid="8" ssid="2">Though classifiers built with machine learning algorithms have become commonplace in the sentiment analysis literature, e.g., Pang et al. (2002), the core of many academic and commercial sentiment analysis systems remains the polarity lexicon, which can be constructed manually (Das and Chen, 2007), through heuristics (Kim and Hovy, 2004; Esuli and Sabastiani, 2009) or using machine learning (Turney, 2002; Rao and Ravichandran, 2009).</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="3">Often lexicons are combined with machine learning for improved results (Wilson et al., 2005).</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="4">The pervasiveness and sustained use of lexicons can be ascribed to a number of reasons, including their interpretability in large-scale systems as well as the granularity of their analysis.</S>
    <S sid="11" ssid="5">In this work we investigate the viability of polarity lexicons that are derived solely from unlabeled web documents.</S>
    <S sid="12" ssid="6">We propose a method based on graph propagation algorithms inspired by previous work on constructing polarity lexicons from lexical graphs (Kim and Hovy, 2004; Hu and Liu, 2004; Esuli and Sabastiani, 2009; Blair-Goldensohn et al., 2008; Rao and Ravichandran, 2009).</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="7">Whereas past efforts have used linguistic resources &#8211; e.g., WordNet &#8211; to construct the lexical graph over which propagation runs, our lexicons are constructed using a graph built from co-occurrence statistics from the entire web.</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="8">Thus, the method we investigate can be seen as a combination of methods for propagating sentiment across lexical graphs and methods for building sentiment lexicons based on distributional characteristics of phrases in raw data (Turney, 2002).</S>
    <S sid="15" ssid="9">The advantage of breaking the dependence on WordNet (or related resources like thesauri (Mohammad et al., 2009)) is that it allows the lexicons to include non-standard entries, most notably spelling mistakes and variations, slang, and multiword expressions.</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="10">The primary goal of our study is to understand the characteristics and practical usefulness of such a lexicon.</S>
    <S sid="17" ssid="11">Towards this end, we provide both a qualitative and quantitative analysis for a web-derived English lexicon relative to two previously published lexicons &#8211; the lexicon used in Wilson et al. (2005) and the lexicon used in Blair-Goldensohn et al.</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="12">(2008).</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="13">Our experiments show that a web-derived lexicon is not only significantly larger, but has improved accuracy on a sentence polarity classification task, which is an important problem in many sentiment analysis applications, including sentiment aggregation and summarization (Hu and Liu, 2004; Carenini et al., 2006; Lerman et al., 2009).</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="14">These results hold true both when the lexicons are used in conjunction with string matching to classify sentences, and when they are included within a contextual classifier framework (Wilson et al., 2005).</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="15">Extracting polarity lexicons from the web has been investigated previously by Kaji and Kitsuregawa (2007), who study the problem exclusively for Japanese.</S>
    <S sid="22" ssid="16">In that work a set of positive/negative sentences are first extracted from the web using cues from a syntactic parser as well as the document structure.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="17">Adjectives phrases are then extracted from these sentences based on different statistics of their occurrence in the positive or negative set.</S>
    <S sid="24" ssid="18">Our work, on the other hand, does not rely on syntactic parsers or restrict the set of candidate lexicon entries to specific syntactic classes, i.e., adjective phrases.</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="19">As a result, the lexicon built in our study is on a different scale than that examined in Kaji and Kitsuregawa (2007).</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="20">Though this hypothesis is not tested here, it also makes our techniques more amenable to adaptation for other languages.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="2 Constructing the Lexicon" number="2">
    <S sid="27" ssid="1">In this section we describe a method to construct polarity lexicons using graph propagation over a phrase similarity graph constructed from the web.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="2">We construct our lexicon using graph propagation techniques, which have previously been investigated in the construction of polarity lexicons (Kim and Hovy, 2004; Hu and Liu, 2004; Esuli and Sabastiani, 2009; Blair-Goldensohn et al., 2008; Rao and Ravichandran, 2009).</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="3">We assume as input an undirected edge weighted graph G = (V, E), where wij E [0, 1] is the weight of edge (vi, vj) E E. The node set V is the set of candidate phrases for inclusion in a sentiment lexicon.</S>
    <S sid="30" ssid="4">In practice, G should encode semantic similarities between two nodes, e.g., for sentiment analysis one would hope that wij &gt; wik if vi=good, vj=great and vk=bad.</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="5">We also assume as input two sets of seed phrases, denoted P for the positive seed set and N for the negative seed set.</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="6">The common property among all graph propagation algorithms is that they attempt to propagate information from the seed sets to the rest of the graph through its edges.</S>
    <S sid="33" ssid="7">This can be done using machine learning, graph algorithms or more heuristic means.</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="8">The specific algorithm used in this study is given in Figure 1, which is distinct from common graph propagation algorithms, e.g., label propagation (see Section 2.3).</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="9">The output is a polarity vector pol E RIVE such that poli is the polarity score for the ith candidate phrase (or the ith node in G).</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="10">In particular, we desire pol to have the following semantics: { &gt; 0 ith phrase has positive polarity &#65533; 0 ith phrase has negative polarity = 0 ith phrase has no sentiment Intuitively, the algorithm works by computing both a positive and a negative polarity magnitude for each node in the graph, call them pol+i and pol-i.</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="11">These values are equal to the sum over the max weighted path from every seed word (either positive or negative) to node vi.</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="12">Phrases that are connected to multiple positive seed words through short yet highly weighted paths will receive high positive values.</S>
    <S sid="39" ssid="13">The final polarity of a phrase is then set to poli = pol+i &#8722; Qpol-i, where Q a constant meant to account for the difference in overall mass of positive and negative flow in the graph.</S>
    <S sid="40" ssid="14">Thus, after the algorithm is run, if a phrase has a higher positive than negative polarity score, then its final polarity will be positive, and negative otherwise.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="15">There are some implementation details worth pointing out.</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="16">First, the algorithm in Figure 1 is written in an iterative framework, where on each iteration, paths of increasing lengths are considered.</S>
    <S sid="43" ssid="17">The input variable T controls the max path length considered by the algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="18">This can be set to be a small value in practice, since the multiplicative path weights result in long paths rarely contributing to polarity scores.</S>
    <S sid="45" ssid="19">Second, the parameter -y is a threshold that defines the minimum polarity magnitude a Initialize: poli, pol+i, pol-i = 0, for all i pol+i = 1.0 for all vi E P and pol-i = 1.0 for all vi E N phrase must have to be included in the lexicon.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="20">Both T and y were tuned on held-out data.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="21">To construct the final lexicon, the remaining nodes &#8211; those with polarity scores above y &#8211; are extracted and assigned their corresponding polarity.</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="22">Graph propagation algorithms rely on the existence of graphs that encode meaningful relationships between candidate nodes.</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="23">Past studies on building polarity lexicons have used linguistic resources like WordNet to define the graph through synonym and antonym relations (Kim and Hovy, 2004; Esuli and Sabastiani, 2009; Blair-Goldensohn et al., 2008; Rao and Ravichandran, 2009).</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="24">The goal of this study is to examine the size and quality of polarity lexicons when the graph is induced automatically from documents on the web.</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="25">Constructing a graph from web-computed lexical co-occurrence statistics is a difficult challenge in and of itself and the research and implementation hurdles that arise are beyond the scope of this work (Alfonseca et al., 2009; Pantel et al., 2009).</S>
    <S sid="52" ssid="26">For this study, we used an English graph where the node set V was based on all n-grams up to length 10 extracted from 4 billion web pages.</S>
    <S sid="53" ssid="27">This list was filtered to 20 million candidate phrases using a number of heuristics including frequency and mutual information of word boundaries.</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="28">A context vector for each candidate phrase was then constructed based on a window of size six aggregated over all mentions of the phrase in the 4 billion documents.</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="29">The edge set E was constructed by first, for each potential edge (vi, vj), computing the cosine similarity value between context vectors.</S>
    <S sid="56" ssid="30">All edges (vi, vj) were then discarded if they were not one of the 25 highest weighted edges adjacent to either node vi or vj.</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="31">This serves to both reduce the size of the graph and to eliminate many spurious edges for frequently occurring phrases, while still keeping the graph relatively connected.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="32">The weight of the remaining edges was set to the corresponding cosine similarity value.</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="33">Since this graph encodes co-occurrences over a large, but local context window, it can be noisy for our purposes.</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="34">In particular, we might see a number of edges between positive and negative sentiment words as well as sentiment words and non-sentiment words, e.g., sentiment adjectives and all other adjectives that are distributionally similar.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="35">Larger windows theoretically alleviate this problem as they encode semantic as opposed to syntactic similarities.</S>
    <S sid="62" ssid="36">We note, however, that the graph propagation algorithm described above calculates the sentiment of each phrase as the aggregate of all the best paths to seed words.</S>
    <S sid="63" ssid="37">Thus, even if some local edges are erroneous in the graph, one hopes that, globally, positive phrases will be influenced more by paths from positive seed words as opposed to negative seed words.</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="38">Section 3, and indeed this paper, aims to measure whether this is true or not.</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="39">Previous studies on constructing polarity lexicons from lexical graphs, e.g., Rao and Ravichandran (2009), have used the label propagation algorithm, which takes the form in Figure 2 (Zhu and Ghahramani, 2002).</S>
    <S sid="66" ssid="40">Label propagation is an iterative algorithm where each node takes on the weighted average of its neighbour&#8217;s values from the previous iteration.</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="41">The result is that nodes with many paths to seeds get high polarities due to the influence from their neighbours.</S>
    <S sid="68" ssid="42">The label propagation algorithm is known to have many desirable properties including convergence, a well defined objective function Input: G = (V, E), wig &#8712; [0, 1], P, N Output: pol &#8712; R|V | Initialize: poli = 1.0 for all vi &#8712; P and poli = &#8722;1.0 for all vi &#8712; N and poli = 0.0 &#8704;vi &#8712;&#65533; P &#8746; N (minimize squared error between values of adjacent nodes), and an equivalence to computing random walks through graphs.</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="43">The primary difference between standard label propagation and the graph propagation algorithm given in Section 2.1, is that a node with multiple paths to a seed will be influenced by all these paths in the label propagation algorithm, whereas only the single path from a seed will influence the polarity of a node in our proposed propagation algorithm &#8211; namely the path with highest weight.</S>
    <S sid="70" ssid="44">The intuition behind label propagation seems justified.</S>
    <S sid="71" ssid="45">That is, if a node has multiple paths to a seed, it should be reflected in a higher score.</S>
    <S sid="72" ssid="46">This is certainly true when the graph is of high quality and all paths trustworthy.</S>
    <S sid="73" ssid="47">However, in a graph constructed from web cooccurrence statistics, this is rarely the case.</S>
    <S sid="74" ssid="48">Our graph consisted of many dense subgraphs, each representing some semantic entity class, such as actors, authors, tech companies, etc.</S>
    <S sid="75" ssid="49">Problems arose when polarity flowed into these dense subgraphs with the label propagation algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="76" ssid="50">Ultimately, this flow would amplify since the dense subgraph provided exponentially many paths from each node to the source of the flow, which caused a reinforcement effect.</S>
    <S sid="77" ssid="51">As a result, the lexicon would consist of large groups of actor names, companies, etc.</S>
    <S sid="78" ssid="52">This also led to convergence issues since the polarity is divided proportional to the size of the dense subgraph.</S>
    <S sid="79" ssid="53">Additionally, negative phrases in the graph appeared to be in more densely connected regions, which resulted in the final lexicons being highly skewed towards negative entries due to the influence of multiple paths to seed words.</S>
    <S sid="80" ssid="54">For best path propagation, these problems were less acute as each node in the dense subgraph would only get the polarity a single time from each seed, which is decayed by the fact that edge weights are smaller than 1.</S>
    <S sid="81" ssid="55">Furthermore, the fact that edge weights are less than 1 results in most long paths having weights near zero, which in turn results in fast convergence.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="3 Lexicon Evaluation" number="3">
    <S sid="82" ssid="1">We ran the best path graph propagation algorithm over a graph constructed from the web using manually constructed positive and negative seed sets of 187 and 192 words in size, respectively.</S>
    <S sid="83" ssid="2">These words were generated by a set of five humans and many are morphological variants of the same root, e.g., excel/excels/excelled.</S>
    <S sid="84" ssid="3">The algorithm produced a lexicon that contained 178,104 entries.</S>
    <S sid="85" ssid="4">Depending on the threshold -y (see Figure 1), this lexicon could be larger or smaller.</S>
    <S sid="86" ssid="5">As stated earlier, our selection of -y and all hyperparameters was based on manual inspection of the resulting lexicons and performance on held-out data.</S>
    <S sid="87" ssid="6">In the rest of this section we investigate the properties of this lexicon to understand both its general characteristics as well as its possible utility in sentiment applications.</S>
    <S sid="88" ssid="7">To this end we compare three different lexicons: Table 1 breaks down the lexicon by the number of positive and negative entries of each lexicon, which clearly shows that the lexicon derived from the web is more than an order of magnitude larger than previously constructed lexicons.2 This in and of itself is not much of an achievement if the additional phrases are of poor quality.</S>
    <S sid="89" ssid="8">However, in Section 3.2 we present an empirical evaluation that suggests that these terms provide both additional and useful information.</S>
    <S sid="90" ssid="9">Table 1 also shows the recall of the each lexicon relative to the other.</S>
    <S sid="91" ssid="10">Whereas the Wilson et al. (2005) and WordNet lexicon have a recall of only 3% relative to the web lexicon, the web lexicon has a recall of 48% and 70% relative to the two other lexicons, indicating that it contains a significant amount of information from the other lexicons.</S>
    <S sid="92" ssid="11">However, this overlap is still small, suggesting that a combination of all the lexicons could provide the best performance.</S>
    <S sid="93" ssid="12">In Section 3.2 we investigate this empirically through a meta classification system.</S>
    <S sid="94" ssid="13">Table 2 shows the distribution of phrases in the web-derived lexicon relative to the number of tokens in each phrase.</S>
    <S sid="95" ssid="14">Here a token is simply defined by whitespace and punctuation, with punctuation counting as a token, e.g., &#8220;half-baked&#8221; is counted as 3 tokens.</S>
    <S sid="96" ssid="15">For the most part, we see what one might expect, as the number of tokens increases, the number of corresponding phrases in the lexicon also decreases.</S>
    <S sid="97" ssid="16">Longer phrases are less frequent and thus will have both fewer and lower weighted edges to adjacent nodes in the graph.</S>
    <S sid="98" ssid="17">There is a single phrase of length 9, which is &#8220;motion to dismiss for failure to state a claim&#8221;.</S>
    <S sid="99" ssid="18">In fact, the lexicon contains quite a number of legal and medical phrases.</S>
    <S sid="100" ssid="19">This should not be surprising, since in a graph induced from the web, a phrase like &#8220;cancer&#8221; (or any disease) should be distributionally similar to phrases like &#8220;illness&#8221;, &#8220;sick&#8221;, and &#8220;death&#8221;, which themselves will be similar to standard sentiment phrases like &#8220;bad&#8221; and &#8220;terrible&#8221;.</S>
    <S sid="101" ssid="20">These terms are predominantly negative in the lexicon representing the broad notion that legal and medical events are undesirable.</S>
    <S sid="102" ssid="21">Perhaps the most interesting characteristic of the lexicon is that the most frequent phrase length is 2 and not 1.</S>
    <S sid="103" ssid="22">The primary reason for this is an abundance of adjective phrases consisting of an adverb and an adjective, such as &#8220;more brittle&#8221; and &#8220;less brittle&#8221;.</S>
    <S sid="104" ssid="23">Almost every adjective of length 1 is frequently combined in such a way on the web, so it not surprising that we see many of these phrases in the lexicon.</S>
    <S sid="105" ssid="24">Ideally we would see an order on such phrases, e.g., &#8220;more brittle&#8221; has a larger negative polarity than &#8220;brittle&#8221;, which in turn has a larger negative polarity than &#8220;less brittle&#8221;.</S>
    <S sid="106" ssid="25">However, this is rarely the case and usually the adjective has the highest polarity magnitude.</S>
    <S sid="107" ssid="26">Again, this is easily explained.</S>
    <S sid="108" ssid="27">These phrases are necessarily more common and will thus have more edges with larger weights in the graph and thus a greater chance of accumulating a high sentiment score.</S>
    <S sid="109" ssid="28">The prominence of such phrases suggests that a more principled treatment of them should be investigated in the future.</S>
    <S sid="110" ssid="29">Finally, Table 3 presents a selection of phrases from both the positive and negative lexicons categorized into revealing verticals.</S>
    <S sid="111" ssid="30">For both positive and negative phrases we present typical examples of phrases &#8211; usually adjectives &#8211; that one would expect to be in a sentiment lexicon.</S>
    <S sid="112" ssid="31">These are phrases not included in the seed sets.</S>
    <S sid="113" ssid="32">We also present multiword phrases for both positive and negative cases, which displays concretely the advantage of building lexicons from the web as opposed to using restricted linguistic resources such as WordNet.</S>
    <S sid="114" ssid="33">Finally, we show two special cases.</S>
    <S sid="115" ssid="34">The first is spelling variations (and mistakes) for positive phrases, which were far more prominent than for negative phrases.</S>
    <S sid="116" ssid="35">Many of these correspond to social media text where one expresses an increased level of sentiment by repeating characters.</S>
    <S sid="117" ssid="36">The second is vulgarity in negative phrases, which was far more prominent than for positive phrases.</S>
    <S sid="118" ssid="37">Some of these are clearly appropriplucky just what the doctor ordered cooool sucky flash in the pan shitty ravishing out of this world coooool subpar bumps in the road half assed spunky top of the line koool horrendous foaming at the mouth jackass enchanting melt in your mouth kewl miserable dime a dozen piece of shit precious snug as a bug cozy lousy pie - in - the - sky son of a bitch charming out of the box cosy abysmal sick to my stomach sonofabitch stupendous more good than bad sikk wretched pain in my ass sonuvabitch ate, e.g., &#8220;shitty&#8221;, but some are clearly insults and outbursts that are most likely included due to their co-occurrence with angry texts.</S>
    <S sid="119" ssid="38">There were also a number of derogatory terms and racial slurs in the lexicon, again most of which received negative sentiment due to their typical disparaging usage.</S>
    <S sid="120" ssid="39">To determine the practical usefulness of a polarity lexicon derived from the web, we measured the performance of the lexicon on a sentence classification/ranking task.</S>
    <S sid="121" ssid="40">The input is a set of sentences and the output is a classification of the sentences as being either positive, negative or neutral in sentiment.</S>
    <S sid="122" ssid="41">Additionally, the system outputs two rankings, the first a ranking of the sentence by positive polarity and the second a ranking of the sentence by negative polarity.</S>
    <S sid="123" ssid="42">Classifying sentences by their sentiment is a subtask of sentiment aggregation systems (Hu and Liu, 2004; Gamon et al., 2005).</S>
    <S sid="124" ssid="43">Ranking sentences by their polarity is a critical sub-task in extractive sentiment summarization (Carenini et al., 2006; Lerman et al., 2009).</S>
    <S sid="125" ssid="44">To classify sentences as being positive, negative or neutral, we used an augmented vote-flip algorithm (Choi and Cardie, 2009), which is given in Figure 3.</S>
    <S sid="126" ssid="45">This intuition behind this algorithm is simple.</S>
    <S sid="127" ssid="46">The number of matched positive and negative phrases from the lexicon are counted and whichever has the most votes wins.</S>
    <S sid="128" ssid="47">The algorithm flips the decision if the number of negations is odd.</S>
    <S sid="129" ssid="48">Though this algorithm appears crude, it benefits from not relying on threshold values for neutral classification, which is difficult due to the fact that the polarity scores in the three lexicons are not on the same scale.</S>
    <S sid="130" ssid="49">To rank sentences we defined the purity of a sentence X as the normalized sum of the sentiment scores for each phrase x in the sentence: This is a normalized score in the range [&#8722;1, 1].</S>
    <S sid="131" ssid="50">Intuitively, sentences with many terms of the same polarity will have purity scores at the extreme points of the range.</S>
    <S sid="132" ssid="51">Before calculating purity, a simple negation heuristic was implemented that reversed the sentiment scores of terms that were within the scope of negations.</S>
    <S sid="133" ssid="52">The term 6 helps to favor sentences with multiple phrase matches.</S>
    <S sid="134" ssid="53">Purity is a common metric used for ranking sentences for inclusion in sentiment summaries (Lerman et al., 2009).</S>
    <S sid="135" ssid="54">Purity and negative purity were used to rank sentences as being positive and negative sentiment, respectively.</S>
    <S sid="136" ssid="55">The data used in our initial English-only experiments were a set of 554 consumer reviews described in (McDonald et al., 2007).</S>
    <S sid="137" ssid="56">Each review was sentence split and annotated by a human as being positive, negative or neutral in sentiment.</S>
    <S sid="138" ssid="57">This resulted in 3,916 sentences, with 1,525, 1,542 and 849 positive, negative and neutral sentences, respectively.</S>
    <S sid="139" ssid="58">The first six columns of Table 4 shows: 1) the positive/negative precision-recall of each lexicon-based system where sentence classes were determined using the vote-flip algorithm, and 2) the average precision for each lexicon-based system where purity (or negative purity) was used to rank sentences.</S>
    <S sid="140" ssid="59">Both the Wilson et al. and WordNet LP lexicons perform at a similar level, with the former slightly better, especially in terms of precision.</S>
    <S sid="141" ssid="60">The web-derived lexicon, Web GP, outperforms the other two lexicons across the board, in particular when looking at average precision, where the gains are near 10% absolute.</S>
    <S sid="142" ssid="61">If we plot the precision-recall graphs using purity to classify sentences &#8211; as opposed to the voteflip algorithm, which only provides an unweighted classification &#8211; we can see that at almost all recall levels the web-derived lexicon has superior precision to the other lexicons (Figure 4).</S>
    <S sid="143" ssid="62">Thus, even though the web-derived lexicon is constructed from a lexical graph that contains noise, the graph propagation algorithms appear to be fairly robust to this noise and are capable of producing large and accurate polarity lexicons.</S>
    <S sid="144" ssid="63">The second six columns of Table 4 shows the performance of each lexicon as the core of a contextual classifier (Wilson et al., 2005).</S>
    <S sid="145" ssid="64">A contextual classifier is a machine learned classifier that predicts the polarity of a sentence using features of that sentence and its context.</S>
    <S sid="146" ssid="65">For our experiments, this was a maximum entropy classifier trained and evaluated using 10-fold cross-validation on the evaluation data.</S>
    <S sid="147" ssid="66">The features included in the classifier were the purity score, the number of positive and negative lexicon matches, and the number of negations in the sentence, as well as concatenations of these features within the sentence and with the same features derived from the sentences in a window of size 1.</S>
    <S sid="148" ssid="67">For each sentence, the contextual classifier predicted either a positive, negative or neutral classification based on the label with highest probability.</S>
    <S sid="149" ssid="68">Additionally, all sentences were placed in the positive and negative sentence rankings by the probability the classifier assigned to the positive and negative classes, respectively.</S>
    <S sid="150" ssid="69">Mirroring the results of Wilson et al. (2005), we see that contextual classifiers improve results substantially over lexical matching.</S>
    <S sid="151" ssid="70">More interestingly, we see that the a contextual classifier over the web-derived lexicons maintains the performance edge over the other lexicons, though the gap is smaller.</S>
    <S sid="152" ssid="71">Figure 5 plots the precision-recall curves for the positive and negative sentence rankings, again showing that at almost every level of recall, the web-derived lexicon has higher precision.</S>
    <S sid="153" ssid="72">For a final English experiment we built a metaclassification system that is identical to the contextual classifiers, except it is trained using features derived from all lexicons.</S>
    <S sid="154" ssid="73">Results are shown in the last row of Table 4 and precision-recall curves are shown in Figure 5.</S>
    <S sid="155" ssid="74">Not surprisingly, this system has the best performance in terms of average precision as it has access to the largest amount of information, though its performance is only slightly better than the contextual classifier for the web-derived lexicon.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="4 Conclusions" number="4">
    <S sid="156" ssid="1">In this paper we examined the viability of sentiment lexicons learned semi-automatically from the web, as opposed to those that rely on manual annotation and/or resources such as WordNet.</S>
    <S sid="157" ssid="2">Our qualitative experiments indicate that the web derived lexicon can include a wide range of phrases that have not been available to previous systems, most notably spelling variations, slang, vulgarity, and multiword expressions.</S>
    <S sid="158" ssid="3">Quantitatively, we observed that the web derived lexicon had superior performance to previously published lexicons for English classification.</S>
    <S sid="159" ssid="4">Ultimately, a meta classifier that incorporates features from all lexicons provides the best performance.</S>
    <S sid="160" ssid="5">In the future we plan to investigate the construction of web-derived lexicons for languages other than English, which is an active area of research (Mihalcea et al., 2007; Jijkoun and Hofmann, 2009; Rao and Ravichandran, 2009).</S>
    <S sid="161" ssid="6">The advantage of the web-derived lexicons studied here is that they do not rely on language specific resources besides unlabeled data and seed lists.</S>
    <S sid="162" ssid="7">A primary question is whether such lexicons improve performance over a translate-to-English strategy (Banea et al., 2008).</S>
    <S sid="163" ssid="8">Acknowledgements: The authors thank Andrew Hogue, Raj Krishnan and Deepak Ravichandran for insightful discussions about this work.</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
