<PAPER>
  <S sid="0" ssid="0">COOKING UP  REFERRING EXPRESS IONS Robert Dale Centre for Cognitive Science, University of Edinburgh 2 Buccleuch Place, Edinburgh EH8 9LW, Scotland email: rda~uk, ac.</S>
  <S sid="1" ssid="1">epJ.stemi~nss, c s. uc l .</S>
  <S sid="2" ssid="2">uk ABSTRACT This paper describes the referring expression generation mechanisms used in EPICURE, a com- puter program which produces natural language descriptions of cookery recipes.</S>
  <S sid="3" ssid="3">Major features of the system include: an underlying ontology which permits the representation f non-singular entities; a notion of diacriminatory power, to determine what properties hould be used in a description; and a PATR-like unification grammar to produce surface linguistic strings.</S>
  <S sid="4" ssid="4">INTRODUCTION EPICURE (Dale 1989a, 1989b) is a natural lan- guage generation system whose principal concern is the generation of referring expressions which pick out complex entities in connected iscourse.</S>
  <S sid="5" ssid="5">In particular, the system generates natural lan- guage descriptions of cookery recipes.</S>
  <S sid="6" ssid="6">Given a top level goal, the program first decomposes that goal recursively to produce a plan consisting of oper- ations at a level of detail commensurate with the assumed knowledge of the hearer.</S>
  <S sid="7" ssid="7">In order to de- scribe the resulting plan, EPICURE then models its execution, so that the processes which produce referring expressions always have access to a rep- resentation of the ingredients in the state they are in at the time of description.</S>
  <S sid="8" ssid="8">This paper describes that part of the system responsible for the generation of subsequent refer- ring expressions, i.e., references to entities which have already been mentioned in the discourse.</S>
  <S sid="9" ssid="9">The most notable features of the approach taken here are as follows: (a) the use of a sophisticated un- derlying ontology, to permit the representation f non-singular entities; (b) the use of two levels of se- mantic representation, i  conjunction with a model of the discourse, to produce appropriate anaphoric referring expressions; (c) the use of a notion of dis- crimiaatory power, to determine what properties should be used in describing an entity; and (d) the use of a PATR-1ike unification grammar (see, for ex- ample, Karttunen (1986); Shieber (1986)) to pro- duce surface linguistic strings from input semantic structures.</S>
  <S sid="10" ssid="10">THE REPRESENTATION OF INGREDIENTS In most natural anguage systems, it is assumed that all the entities in the domain of discourse are singular individuals.</S>
  <S sid="11" ssid="11">In more complex domains, such as recipes, this simplification is of limited value, since a large proportion of the objects we find are masses or sets, such as those described by the noun phrases two ounces of salt and three pounds of carrots respectively.</S>
  <S sid="12" ssid="12">In order to permit the representation f enti- ties such as these, EPICURE makes use of a notion of a generalized physical object or physob].</S>
  <S sid="13" ssid="13">This permits a consistent representation f entities irre- spective of whether they are viewed as individuals, masses or sets, by representing each as a knowledge base entity (KBE) with an appropriate structure at.</S>
  <S sid="14" ssid="14">The knowledge base entity corresponding to three pounds of carrots, for example, is that shown in figure 1.</S>
  <S sid="15" ssid="15">A knowledge base entity models a physobj in a particular state.</S>
  <S sid="16" ssid="16">An entity may change during the course of a recipe, as processes are applied to it: in particular, apart from gaining new properties such as being peeled, chopped, etc., an ingredients structure may change, for example, from set to mass.</S>
  <S sid="17" ssid="17">Each such change of state results in the creation of a new knowledge base entity.</S>
  <S sid="18" ssid="18">Suppose, for example, a grating event is applied to our three pounds of carrots between states so and sl: the entity shown in figure i will then become a mass of grated carrot, represented in state sl by the KBE shown in figure 2.</S>
  <S sid="19" ssid="19">BUILDING A REFERRING EXPRESS ION To construct a referring expression corresponding to a knowledge base entity, we first build a deep se- 68 KBE -~ indus = ZO state = so structure = set quantity = [ num~erUnit = pound= 3 ] speC = structure = indiv idual substance = carrot - , - -  [ ] packaging = ehape= carrot ?</S>
  <S sid="20" ssid="20">= regular 8|Ze Figure 1: The knowledge base entity corresponding to three pounds of  carrots KBE = irides = zo state ---- Sl strt~|urc = m~8o qu4ntity = [ uni t  = pound ] spec = number  = 3 substar~e = carrot grated = + Figure 2: The knowledge base entity corresponding to three pound8 of grated carrot mantic structure which specifies the semantic con- tent of the noun phrase to be generated.</S>
  <S sid="21" ssid="21">We call this the recoverable semantic content, since it con- sists of just that information the hearer should be able to derive from the corresponding utter- ance, even if that information is not stated explic- itly: in particular, elided elements and instances of oae-anaphora are represented in the deep seman- tic structure by their more semantically complete counterparts, as we will see below.</S>
  <S sid="22" ssid="22">From the deep semantic structure, a surface semantic structure is then constructed.</S>
  <S sid="23" ssid="23">Unlike the deep semantic structure, this closely matches the syntactic structure of the resulting noun phrase, and is suitable for passing directly to a PATR-like unification grammar.</S>
  <S sid="24" ssid="24">It is at the level of surface semantic structure that processes such as elision and one-anaphora take place.</S>
  <S sid="25" ssid="25">PRONOMINAL IZAT ION When an entity is to be referred to, we first check to see if pronominalisation is possible.</S>
  <S sid="26" ssid="26">Some pre- vious approaches to the pronominalization deci.</S>
  <S sid="27" ssid="27">don have taken into account a large number of contextual factors (see, for example, McDonald (1980:218-220)).</S>
  <S sid="28" ssid="28">The approach taken here is rel- atively simple.</S>
  <S sid="29" ssid="29">EPICURE makes use of a discourse model which distinguishes two principal compo- nents, corresponding to Groszs (1977) distinction between local focus and global focus.</S>
  <S sid="30" ssid="30">We call that part of the discourse model corresponding to the local focus cache memory: this contains the lex- ical, syntactic and semantic detail of the current utterance being generated, and the same detail for the previous utterance.</S>
  <S sid="31" ssid="31">Corresponding to global focus, the discourse model consists of a number of hierarchically-arranged focua spaces, mirroring the structure of the recipe being described.</S>
  <S sid="32" ssid="32">These focus spaces record the semantic content, but not the syntactic or lexlcal detail, of the remainder of the preceding discourse.</S>
  <S sid="33" ssid="33">In addition, we make use of a notion of discourse centre: this is intu- itively similar to the notion of centering suggested by (]ross, Joshi and Weinstein (1983), and corre- sponds to the focus of attention in the discourse.</S>
  <S sid="34" ssid="34">In recipes, we take the centre to be the result of 69 the previous operation described.</S>
  <S sid="35" ssid="35">Thus, after an utterance like Soak the butterbeaa.s the centre is the entity described by the noun phrase the but- terbeans.</S>
  <S sid="36" ssid="36">Subsequent references to the centre can be pronominalized, so that the next instruction in the recipe might then be Drain and dnse tltem.</S>
  <S sid="37" ssid="37">Following Grosz, Joshi and Weinstein (1983), references to other entities present in cache mem- ory may also be pronominalized, provided the cen- tre is pronominalized.</S>
  <S sid="38" ssid="38">1 If the intended referent is the current centre, then this is marked as part of the status infor- mation in the deep semantic structure being con- structed, and a null value is specified for the struc- tures descriptive content.</S>
  <S sid="39" ssid="39">In addition, the verb case frame used to construct he utterance speci- fies whether or not the linguistic realization of the entity filling each case role is obligatory: as we will see below, this allows us to model a common linguistic phenomenon in recipes (recipe contezt empty objects, after Massam and Roberge (1989)).</S>
  <S sid="40" ssid="40">For a case role whose surface realization is obliga- tory, the resulting deep semantic structure is then as follows: D$ = i nde :  : : [ N~en = + statttm : e.cntrs : t sem : oblig -~ + "Pec = [ "PC=q)  I This will be realized as either a pronoun or an elided NP, generated from a surface semantic struc- ture which is constructed in accordance with the following rules: ?</S>
  <S sid="41" ssid="41">If the status includes the features [centre, +] and [oblig, +], then there should be a cor- responding element in the surface semantic structure, with a null value specified for the descriptive content of the noun phrase to be generated; t We do not permit  pronominal reference to entit ies last ment ioned before the previous utterance: support  for this restriction comes from a study by Hobbs, who, in a sam- ple of one hundred consecutive ~.amples of pronouns from each of three very different texts, found that  98% of an- tecedents were either in the same or previous sentence (Hobbs 1978:322-323).</S>
  <S sid="42" ssid="42">However, see Dale (1988) for a sug- gestion as to how the few instances of/onc-dbt~a.e pronom- inalimtion that  do exist might be explained by means  of a theory of discourse structure like that  suggested by Gross and Sidner (1986).</S>
  <S sid="43" ssid="43">I f  the status includes the features [centre, +] and [oblig,-], then this participant should be omitted from the surface semantic struc- ture altogether.</S>
  <S sid="44" ssid="44">In the former case, this will result in a pronominal reference as in Remove them, where the surface se- mantic structure corresponding to the pronominal form is as follows: i nd~z  = z s ta tus  : [ SS = "1 g iven  = + | J centre = ~r oblig = + [ nu~ = pl agr 8p~ ~--- C CG$~ = GCC &amp;*c  = However, if the participant ismarked as non-obligatory, then reference to the entity is omitted, as in the following: Fry the onions.</S>
  <S sid="45" ssid="45">Add the garlic ~b.</S>
  <S sid="46" ssid="46">Here, the case frame for add specifies that the in- direct object is non-obllgatory; since the entity which fills this case role is also the centre, the complete prepositional phrase to the onions can be elided.</S>
  <S sid="47" ssid="47">Note, however, that the entity corre- sponding to the onions still figures in the deep semantic structure; thus, it is integrated into the discourse model, and is deemed to be part of the semantic ontent recoverable by the hearer.</S>
  <S sid="48" ssid="48">FULL  DEF IN ITE  NOUN PHRASE REFERENCE If pronominalization is ruled out, we have to build an appropriate description of the intended refer- ent.</S>
  <S sid="49" ssid="49">In EPICURE, the process of constructing a description is driven by two principles, very like Gricean conversational maxims (Grice 1975).</S>
  <S sid="50" ssid="50">The p~nciple of adequacy requires that a referring ex- pression should identify the intended referent un- ambiguously, and provide sufficient information to serve the purpose of the reference; and the princi- ple of e~ciency, pulling in the opposite direction, requires that the referring expression used must not contain more information than is necessary for the task at hand.</S>
  <S sid="51" ssid="51">2 These principles are implemented in EPICUItE 2Similar considerations are discussed by Appelt  (1985).</S>
  <S sid="52" ssid="52">DS ~--- inde= ..~ = status =.</S>
  <S sid="53" ssid="53">[ given = + unique = + ee l n  ~- opec  = agr = tvpe= I countable =+ ] J number  = pl category : olive $ize : regular props = pitted = + Figure 3: The deep semantic structure corresponding to the pitted olives #tat*t. = epee = a/yen= + ] unique = + [countable : -~ ] agr = number  = pl ] head = olive dee?</S>
  <S sid="54" ssid="54">= mad= [ head = pltted ] Figure 4: The surface semantic structure corresponding to the pitted olives by means of a notion of discriminatory power.</S>
  <S sid="55" ssid="55">Sup- pose that we have a set of entities U such that U = {z l , z2 , .</S>
  <S sid="56" ssid="56">, x ,} and that we wish to distinguish one of these en- tities, zl, from all the others.</S>
  <S sid="57" ssid="57">Suppose, also, that the domain includes a number of attributes (a I, a~, and so on), and that each attribute has a number of permissible values {v,,t, v,,2, and so on}; and that each entity is described by a set of attribute- value pairs.</S>
  <S sid="58" ssid="58">In order to distinguish z~ from the other entities in U, we need to find some set of attribute-value pairs which are together true of zl, but of no other entity in U.</S>
  <S sid="59" ssid="59">This set of attribute- value pairs constitutes a distinguishing descriptior, of xl with respect to the ,~ontext U.</S>
  <S sid="60" ssid="60">A mini- mal distinguishing description is then a set of such attribute-value pairs, where the cardinality of that set is such that there are no other sets of attribute- value pairs of lesser cardinality which are sufficient to distinguish the intended referent.</S>
  <S sid="61" ssid="61">We find a minimal distinguishing description by observing that different attribute-value pairs differ in the effectiveness with which they distin- guish an entity from a set of entities.</S>
  <S sid="62" ssid="62">Suppose U has N elements, where N &gt; I.</S>
  <S sid="63" ssid="63">Then, any attribute-value pair true of the intended referent zl will be true of n entities in this set, where n &gt;_ i.</S>
  <S sid="64" ssid="64">For any attribute-value pair &lt; a, v &gt; that is true of the intended referent, we can compute the discriminatory power (notated here as F) of that attribute-value pair with respect to U as fol- lows" ~(&lt; ~,v&gt;, U) = ~-~ l&lt;n&lt;N F thus has as its range the interval [0,1], where a value of 1 for a given attribute-value pair indi- cates that the attribute-value pair singles out the intended referent from the conte?t, and a value of 7] DS -~- i ndez  = z2 s ta tus  = SSf~t SpSC -~ [ #/uen= + ] unique = + number  = sg agr  = countab le  ---- + type  = ] categor l !</S>
  <S sid="65" ssid="65">= caps icum r I eolour = red properties L s i ze  = smal l Figure 5: The deep semantic structure corresponding to the small red capsicum SS = indez  = z2 , un ique  = + i Jpsc = _ ~ nu,n~sr= so ] agr- [ countable = + J Figure 6: The surface semantic structure corresponding to the small red one 0 indicates that the attribute-value pair is of no assistance in singling out the intended referent.</S>
  <S sid="66" ssid="66">Given an intended referent and a set of entities from which the intended referent must be distin- guished, this notion is used to determine which set of properties should be used in building a descrip- tion which is both adequate and efficient.</S>
  <S sid="67" ssid="67">3 There remains the question of how the constituency of the set U of entities is determined: in the present work, we  take the context always to consist of the working set.</S>
  <S sid="68" ssid="68">This is the set of distinguishable enti- sstrictly speaking, this mechanism is only applicable in the form described here to those properties of an entity which are realizable by what are known as abJolute (or t~- tereect/ee or pred~tiee) adjectives (see, for example, Kamp (1975), Keenan and FaRm (1978)).</S>
  <S sid="69" ssid="69">This is acceptable in the current domain, where many of the adjectives used are derived from the verbs used to describe processes applied to entities.</S>
  <S sid="70" ssid="70">ties in the domain at any given point in time: the constituency of this set changes as a recipe pro- ceeds, since entities may be created or destroyed.</S>
  <S sid="71" ssid="71">4 Suppose, for example, we  determine that we must identify a given object as being a set of olives which have been pitted (in a context, for example, where there are also olives which have not been pitted}; the corresponding deep semantic struc- ture is then as in figure 3.</S>
  <S sid="72" ssid="72">Note that this deep semantic structure can be realized in at least two ways: as either the olives which have been pitted or the pitted olives.</S>
  <S sid="73" ssid="73">4A slightly more sophisticated approach would be to restrict U to exclude those entities which are, in G rosz and Sidners (1986) terms, only present in closed focus spaces.</S>
  <S sid="74" ssid="74">However, the benefit gained from doing this (if indeed it is a valid thing to do) is minimal in the current context because of the small number of entities we are dealing with.</S>
  <S sid="75" ssid="75">72 i ndez  = z ~tat t~ = .</S>
  <S sid="76" ssid="76">[ ] number = pl agr = "ountable = + DS = ~.nuant 8pec = 8ubst  = ] t number--- 3 ]agr = countable = + tltpe -- categorlt = pound ] number = pl l agr = countable = + J type = category = carrot ] J Figure 7: The deep semantic structure corresponding to three pounds of carrots Both forms are possible, although they correspond to different surface semantic structures.</S>
  <S sid="77" ssid="77">Thus, the generation algorithm is non-deterministic in this respect (although one might imagine there are other factors which determine which of the two re- alizations is preferrable in a given context}.</S>
  <S sid="78" ssid="78">The surface semantic structure for the simpler of the two noun phrase structures is as shown in figure 4.</S>
  <S sid="79" ssid="79">ONE ANAPHORA The algorithms employed in EPICURE also permit the generation of onc-anaphora, as in Slice the large green capsicum.</S>
  <S sid="80" ssid="80">Now remove the top of the small red one.</S>
  <S sid="81" ssid="81">The deep semantic structure corresponding to the noun phrase the small red one is as shown in fig- ure 5.</S>
  <S sid="82" ssid="82">The mechanisms which construct the surface semantic structure determine whether one-anaphora is possible by comparing the deep semantic struc- ture corresponding to the previous utterance with that corresponding to the current utterance, to identify any elements they have in common.</S>
  <S sid="83" ssid="83">The two distinct levels of semantic representation play an important role here: in the deep semantic struc- ture, only the basic semantic category of the de scription has special status (this is similar to Wel&gt;- hers (1979) use of restricted quantification), whereas the embedding of the surface semantic structures dcsc feature closely matches that of the noun phrase to be generated.</S>
  <S sid="84" ssid="84">For one-anaphora to be possi- ble, the two deep semantic structures being com- pared must have the same value for the feature addressed by the path &lt;sere spec type category&gt;.</S>
  <S sid="85" ssid="85">Rules which specify the relative ordering of ad- jectives in the surface form are then used to build an appropriately nested surface semantic structure which, when unified with the grammar, will result in the required one-anaphoric noun phrase.</S>
  <S sid="86" ssid="86">In the present example, this results in the surface seman- tic structure in figure 6.</S>
  <S sid="87" ssid="87">PSEUDO-PARTIT I VE  NPS Partitive and pseudo-partitive noun phrases, ex- emplified by half  of  the carrots and three pounds of carrots respectively, are very common in recipes; EPICURE is capable of generating both.</S>
  <S sid="88" ssid="88">So, for example, the pseudo-partitive noun phrase three pounds of carrots (as represented by the knowledge base entity shown in figure 1) is generated from the deep semantic structure shown in figure 7 via the surface semantic structure shown in figure 8.</S>
  <S sid="89" ssid="89">The generation of partitive noun phrases re- quires slightly different semantic structures, de- scribed in greater detail in Dale (1989b).</S>
  <S sid="90" ssid="90">THE UNIF ICAT ION GRAMMAR Once the required surface semantic structure has been constructed, this is passed to a unification 73 $S = ind .= = z atatua= 8era epee = .</S>
  <S sid="91" ssid="91">[ g iuen  = --  ] countable = + agr  = number  = 3 epec I = &amp;so = $p?c2 = ] t countable = + age = number = 3 desc = head = pound agr= [[eountab|e=+ d?8c = head = carrot Figure 8: The surface semantic structure corresponding to three pounds of carrots grammar.</S>
  <S sid="92" ssid="92">In EPICURE, the grammar consists of phrase structure rules annotated with path equa- tions which determine the relationships between semantic units and syntactic units: the path equa- tions specify arbitrary constituents (either com- plex or atomic) of feature structures.</S>
  <S sid="93" ssid="93">There is insufficient space here to show the en- tire NP grammar, but we provide some representa- tive rules in figure 9 (although these rules are ex- pressed here in a PATR-Iike formalism, within EPI- CURE they are encoded as PROLOG definite clause grammar (DCG) rules (Clocksin and Mellish 1981)).</S>
  <S sid="94" ssid="94">Applying these rules to the surface semantic struc- tures described above results in the generation of the appropriate surface linguistic strings.</S>
  <S sid="95" ssid="95">CONCLUSION In this paper, we have described the processes used in EPICURE to produce noun phrase referring ex- pressions.</S>
  <S sid="96" ssid="96">EPICURE is implemented in C-PROLOG running under UNIX.</S>
  <S sid="97" ssid="97">The algorithms used in the system permit the generation of a wide range of pronominal forms, one-anaphoric forms and full noun phrase structures, including partitives and pseudo-partitives.</S>
  <S sid="98" ssid="98">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS The work described here has benefited greatly from discussions with Ewan Klein, Graeme Ritchie, :Ion Oberlander, and Marc Moens, and from Bonnie Webbers encouragement.</S>
  <S sid="99" ssid="99">REFERENCES Appelt, Douglas E. (1985) Planning English Refer- ring Expressions.</S>
  <S sid="100" ssid="100">Artificial Intelligence, 26, 1-33.</S>
  <S sid="101" ssid="101">Clocksin, William F. and Melllsh, Christopher S. (1981) Programming in Prolog.</S>
  <S sid="102" ssid="102">Berlin: Springer- Verlag.</S>
  <S sid="103" ssid="103">Dale, Robert (1988) The Generation ofSubsequent Referring Expressions in Structured Discourses.</S>
  <S sid="104" ssid="104">Chapter 5 in Zock, M. and Sabah, G.</S>
  <S sid="105" ssid="105">Ad- uances in Natural Language Generation: An Inter- disciplinary Perspective, Volume 2, pp58-75.</S>
  <S sid="106" ssid="106">Lon- don: Pinter Publishers Ltd. Dale, Robert (1989a) Generating Recipes: An Over- view of EPICURE.</S>
  <S sid="107" ssid="107">Extended Abstracts of the Sec- ond European Natural Language Generation Work- shop, Edinburgh, April 1989.</S>
  <S sid="108" ssid="108">Dale, Robert (1989b) Generating Referring Ex- pressions in a Domain of Objects and Processes.</S>
  <S sid="109" ssid="109">PhD Thesis, Centre for Cognitive Science, Univer- sity of Edinburgh.</S>
  <S sid="110" ssid="110">Grice, H. Paul (1975) Logic and Conversation.</S>
  <S sid="111" ssid="111">In Cole, P. and Morgan, J. L.</S>
  <S sid="112" ssid="112">Syntax and Se- mantics, Volume 3: Speech Acts, pp41-58.</S>
  <S sid="113" ssid="113">New York: Academic Press.</S>
  <S sid="114" ssid="114">Grosz, Barbara J.</S>
  <S sid="115" ssid="115">(1977} The Representation a d Use of Focus in Dialogue.</S>
  <S sid="116" ssid="116">Technical Note No.</S>
  <S sid="117" ssid="117">151, 74 NP N2 Nl l NPx NPI ---4.</S>
  <S sid="118" ssid="118">Dee N1 &lt;Dee sere&gt; &lt;NP 8yn agr&gt; &lt;N1 syn agr&gt; &lt;Dee syn agr&gt; &lt;N1 sere&gt; N &lt;N sent&gt; AP NI2 &lt;AP sere&gt; &lt;NI~ sere head&gt; &lt;NP2 sere&gt; &lt;N1 sere&gt; &lt;NI 8yn ayr&gt; &lt;NPa 8era statuJ&gt; &lt;NP2 sere status&gt; &lt;NPa 8era&gt; &lt;PP 8era&gt; = &lt;NP sere status&gt; = &lt;NP sere spec agr&gt; = &lt;NP syn agr&gt; = &lt;N1 syn agr&gt; = &lt;NP sere spec desc&gt; = &lt;N1 sent head&gt; = &lt;Nl l  sere rood&gt; -- &lt;Nlx sere head&gt; = &lt;NPx sere spec desc specx &gt; = &lt;NPx sere spec desc spe?2&gt; = &lt;NPx sere spec agr&gt; = &lt;NPz sere status&gt; = &lt;NPx sere status&gt; = &lt;NPx sere spec desc spec&gt; = &lt;NPx sere spec desc set&gt; Figure 9: A fragment of the noun phrase grammar SRI International, Menlo Park, Ca., July, 1977.</S>
  <S sid="119" ssid="119">Grosz, Barbara J., Joshi, Aravind K. and Wein- stein, Scott (1983) Providing a Unified Account of Definite Noun Phrases in Discourse.</S>
  <S sid="120" ssid="120">In Proceed- ings of the ~lst Annual Meeting o/the Associa- tion for Computational Linguistics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, Mass., 15-17 June, 1983, pp44-49.</S>
  <S sid="121" ssid="121">Grosz, Barbara J. and Sidner, Candace L. (1986) Attention, Intentions, and the Structure of Dis- course.</S>
  <S sid="122" ssid="122">Computational Linguistics, 12, 175-204.</S>
  <S sid="123" ssid="123">Hobbs, Jerry R. (1978) Resolving Pronoun Refer- ences.</S>
  <S sid="124" ssid="124">Lingua, 44, 311-338.</S>
  <S sid="125" ssid="125">Kamp, Hans (1975) Two Theories about Adjec- tives.</S>
  <S sid="126" ssid="126">In Keenan, E. L.</S>
  <S sid="127" ssid="127">Formal Semantics of Natural Language: Papers from a colloquium spon- sored by Kings College Research Centre, Cam- bridge, pp123-155.</S>
  <S sid="128" ssid="128">Cambridge: Cambridge Uni- versity Press.</S>
  <S sid="129" ssid="129">Karttunen, Lauri (1986) D-PATR: A Development Environment for Unification-Based Grammars.</S>
  <S sid="130" ssid="130">In Proceedings of the 11th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, Bonn, 25-29 Au- gust, 1986, pp74-80.</S>
  <S sid="131" ssid="131">Keenan, Edward L. and Faltz, Leonard M. (1978) Logical Types for Natural Language.</S>
  <S sid="132" ssid="132">UCLA Occa- sional Papers in Linguistics, No.</S>
  <S sid="133" ssid="133">McDonald, David D. (1980) Natural Language Gen- eration as a Process of Decision-Making under Con- straints.</S>
  <S sid="134" ssid="134">PhD Thesis, Department of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering, MIT.</S>
  <S sid="135" ssid="135">Massam, Diane and Roberge, Yves (1989) Recipe Context Null Objects in English.</S>
  <S sid="136" ssid="136">Linguistic In- quiry, 20, 134--139.</S>
  <S sid="137" ssid="137">Shieber, Stuart M. (1980) An Introduction to Unification- based Approaches to Grantmar.</S>
  <S sid="138" ssid="138">Chicago, Illinois: The University of Chicago Press.</S>
  <S sid="139" ssid="139">Webber, Bonnie Lynn (1979) A Formal Approach to Discourse Anaphora.</S>
  <S sid="140" ssid="140">London: Garland Pub- lishing.</S>
</PAPER>
