<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">A Statistical Model For Domain-Independent Text Segmentation</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">We propose a statistical method that finds the maximum-probability segmentation of a given text.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">This method does not require training data because it estimates probabilities from the given text.</S>
    <S sid="3" ssid="3">Therefore, it can be applied to any text in any domain.</S>
    <S sid="4" ssid="4">An experiment showed that the method is more accurate than or at least as accurate as a state-of-the-art text segmentation system.</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="1 Introduction" number="1">
    <S sid="5" ssid="1">Documents usually include various topics.</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="2">Identifying and isolating topics by dividing documents, which is called text segmentation, is important for many natural language processing tasks, including information retrieval (Hearst and Plaunt, 1993; Salton et al., 1996) and summarization (Kan et al., 1998; Nakao, 2000).</S>
    <S sid="7" ssid="3">In information retrieval, users are often interested in particular topics (parts) of retrieved documents, instead of the documents themselves.</S>
    <S sid="8" ssid="4">To meet such needs, documents should be segmented into coherent topics.</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="5">Summarization is often used for a long document that includes multiple topics.</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="6">A summary of such a document can be composed of summaries of the component topics.</S>
    <S sid="11" ssid="7">Identification of topics is the task of text segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="12" ssid="8">A lot of research has been done on text segmentation (Kozima, 1993; Hearst, 1994; Okumura and Honda, 1994; Salton et al., 1996; Yaari, 1997; Kan et al., 1998; Choi, 2000; Nakao, 2000).</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="9">A major characteristic of the methods used in this research is that they do not require training data to segment given texts.</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="10">Hearst (1994), for example, used only the similarity of word distributions in a given text to segment the text.</S>
    <S sid="15" ssid="11">Consequently, these methods can be applied to any text in any domain, even if training data do not exist.</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="12">This property is important when text segmentation is applied to information retrieval or summarization, because both tasks deal with domain-independent documents.</S>
    <S sid="17" ssid="13">Another application of text segmentation is the segmentation of a continuous broadcast news story into individual stories (Allan et al., 1998).</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="14">In this application, systems relying on supervised learning (Yamron et al., 1998; Beeferman et al., 1999) achieve good performance because there are plenty of training data in the domain.</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="15">These systems, however, can not be applied to domains for which no training data exist.</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="16">The text segmentation algorithm described in this paper is intended to be applied to the summarization of documents or speeches.</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="17">Therefore, it should be able to handle domain-independent texts.</S>
    <S sid="22" ssid="18">The algorithm thus does not use any training data.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="19">It requires only the given documents for segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="24" ssid="20">It can, however, incorporate training data when they are available, as discussed in Section 5.</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="21">The algorithm selects the optimum segmentation in terms of the probability defined by a statistical model.</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="22">This is a new approach for domain-independent text segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="27" ssid="23">Previous approaches usually used lexical cohesion to segment texts into topics.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="24">Kozima (1993), for examthen and hold.</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="25">This means that and correspond to each other.</S>
    <S sid="30" ssid="26">Under our assumptions, can be decomposed as follows: Next, we define as: where is the number of words in that are the same as and is the number of different words in .</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="27">For example, if , where and , then , , , ,and .</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="28">Equation (4) is known as Laplace&#8217;s law (Manning and Sch&#168;utze, 1999). can be defined as: ple, used cohesion based on the spreading activation on a semantic network.</S>
    <S sid="33" ssid="29">Hearst (1994) used the similarity of word distributions as measured by the cosine to gauge cohesion.</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="30">Reynar (1994) used word repetition as a measure of cohesion.</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="31">Choi (2000) used the rank of the cosine, rather than the cosine itself, to measure the similarity of sentences.</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="32">The statistical model for the algorithm is described in Section 2, and the algorithm for obtaining the maximum-probability segmentation is described in Section 3.</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="33">Experimental results are presented in Section 4.</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="34">Further discussion and our conclusions are given in Sections 5 and 6, respectively.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="2 Statistical Model for Text Segmentation" number="2">
    <S sid="39" ssid="1">We first define the probability of a segmentation of a given text in this section.</S>
    <S sid="40" ssid="2">In the next section, we then describe the algorithm for selecting the most likely segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="3">Let be a text consisting of words, and let be a segmentation of consisting of segments.</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="4">Then the probability of the segmentation is defined by: because is a constant for a given text .</S>
    <S sid="43" ssid="5">The definitions of and given below, in that order.</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="6">We define a topic by the distribution of words in that topic.</S>
    <S sid="45" ssid="7">We assume that different topics have different word distributions.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="8">We further assume that different topics are statistically independent of each other.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="9">We also assume that the words within the scope of a topic are statistically independent of each other given the topic.</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="10">Let be the number of words in segment , and let be the -th word in .</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="11">If we define as The definition of can vary depending on our prior information about the possibility of segmentation .</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="12">For example, we might know the average length of the segments and want to incorporate it into .</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="13">.</S>
    <S sid="52" ssid="14">Equations (5) and (6) are used in Section 3 to describe the algorithm for finding the maximumprobability segmentation. where when and are the same word and otherwise.</S>
    <S sid="53" ssid="15">For example, Our assumption, however, is that we do not have such prior information.</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="16">Thus, we have to use some uninformative prior probability.</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="17">We define as where bits.2 This description length is derived as follows: Suppose that there are two people, a sender and a receiver, both of whom know the text to be segmented.</S>
    <S sid="56" ssid="18">Only the sender knows the exact segmentation, and he/she should send a message so that the receiver can segment the text correctly.</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="19">To this end, it is sufficient for the sender to send integers, i.e., , because these integers represent the lengths of segments and thus uniquely determine the segmentation once the text is known.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="20">A segment length can be encoded using bits, because is a number between 1 and .</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="21">The total description length for all the segment lengths is thus bits.3 Generally speaking, takes a large value when the number of segments is small.</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="22">On the other hand, takes a large value when the number of segments is large.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="23">If only is used to segment the text, then the resulting segmentation will have too many segments.</S>
    <S sid="62" ssid="24">By using both and , we can get a reasonable number of segments.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="3 Algorithm for Finding the" number="3">
    <S sid="63" ssid="1">To find the maximum-probability segmentation , we first define the cost of segmentation as 2&#8216;Log&#8217; denotes the logarithm to the base 2.</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="2">3We have used as before.</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="3">But we use in this paper, because it is easily interpreted as a description length and the experimental results obtained by using are slightly better than those obtained by using .</S>
    <S sid="66" ssid="4">An anonymous reviewer suggests using a Poisson distribution whose parameter is , the average length of a segment (in words), as prior probability.</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="5">We leave it for future work to compare the suitability of various prior probabilities for text segmentation. where (12) We further rewrite Equation (12) in the form of Equation (13) below by using Equation (5) and replacing with , where is the length of words, i.e.,the number of word tokens in words.</S>
    <S sid="68" ssid="6">Equation (13) is used to describe our algorithm in Section 3.1: This section describes an algorithm for finding the minimum-cost segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="7">First, we define the terms and symbols used to describe the algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="70" ssid="8">Given a text consisting of words, we define as the position between and , so that is just before and is just after .</S>
    <S sid="71" ssid="9">Next, we define a graph , where is a set of nodes and is a set of edges. is defined as can be decomposed as follows: and we then minimize to obtain , because where the edges are ordered; the initial vertex and the terminal vertex of are and , respectively.</S>
    <S sid="72" ssid="10">An example of is shown in Figure 1.</S>
    <S sid="73" ssid="11">We say that covers (16) where is the number of different words in .</S>
    <S sid="74" ssid="12">Given these definitions, we describe the algorithm to find the minimum-cost segmentation or maximum-probability segmentation as follows: Step 2.</S>
    <S sid="75" ssid="13">Find the minimum-cost path from to .</S>
    <S sid="76" ssid="14">Algorithms for finding the minimum-cost path in a graph are well known.</S>
    <S sid="77" ssid="15">An algorithm that can provide a solution for Step 2 will be a simpler version of the algorithm used to find the maximumprobability solution in Japanese morphological analysis (Nagata, 1994).</S>
    <S sid="78" ssid="16">Therefore, a solution can be obtained by applying a dynamic programming (DP) algorithm.4 DP algorithms have also been used for text segmentation by other researchers (Ponte and Croft, 1997; Heinonen, 1998).</S>
    <S sid="79" ssid="17">The path thus obtained represents the minimum-cost segmentation in when edges correspond with segments.</S>
    <S sid="80" ssid="18">In Figure 1, for example, if is the minimum-cost path, then is the minimum-cost segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="81" ssid="19">The algorithm automatically determines the number of segments.</S>
    <S sid="82" ssid="20">But the number of segments can also be specified explicitly by specifying the number of edges in the minimum-cost path.</S>
    <S sid="83" ssid="21">The algorithm allows the text to be segmented anywhere between words; i.e., all the positions between words are candidates for segment boundaries.</S>
    <S sid="84" ssid="22">It is easy, however, to modify the algorithm so that the text can only be segmented at particular positions, such as the ends of sentences or paragraphs.</S>
    <S sid="85" ssid="23">This is done by using a subset of in Equation (15).</S>
    <S sid="86" ssid="24">We use only the edges whose initial and terminal vertices are candidate boundaries that meet particular conditions, such as being the ends of sentences or paragraphs.</S>
    <S sid="87" ssid="25">We then obtain the minimum-cost path by doing Steps 1 and 2.</S>
    <S sid="88" ssid="26">The minimum-cost segmentation thus obtained meets the boundary conditions.</S>
    <S sid="89" ssid="27">In this paper, we assume that the segment boundaries are at the ends of sentences.</S>
    <S sid="90" ssid="28">Generally speaking, the number of segments obtained by our algorithm is not sensitive to the length of a given text, which is counted in words.</S>
    <S sid="91" ssid="29">In other words, the number of segments is relatively stable with respect to variation in the text length.</S>
    <S sid="92" ssid="30">For example, the algorithm divides a newspaper editorial consisting of about 27 sentences into 4 to 6 segments, while on the other hand, it divides a long text consisting of over 1000 sentences into 10 to 20 segments.</S>
    <S sid="93" ssid="31">Thus, the number of segments is not proportional to text length.</S>
    <S sid="94" ssid="32">This is due to the term in Equation (11).</S>
    <S sid="95" ssid="33">The value of this term increases as the number of words increases.</S>
    <S sid="96" ssid="34">The term thus suppresses the division of a text when the length of the text is long.</S>
    <S sid="97" ssid="35">This stability is desirable for summarization, because summarizing a given text requires selecting a relatively small number of topics from it.</S>
    <S sid="98" ssid="36">If a text segmentation system divides a given text into a relatively small number of segments, then a summary of the original text can be composed by combining summaries of the component segments (Kan et al., 1998; Nakao, 2000).</S>
    <S sid="99" ssid="37">A finer segmentation can be obtained by applying our algorithm recursively to each segment, if necessary.5</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="4 Experiments" number="4">
    <S sid="100" ssid="1">We used publicly available data to evaluate our system.</S>
    <S sid="101" ssid="2">This data was used by Choi (2000) to compare various domain-independent text segmentation systems.6 He evaluated (Choi, 2000), TextTiling (Hearst, 1994), DotPlot (Reynar, 1998), and Segmenter (Kan et al., 1998) by using the data and reported that achieved the best performance among these systems.</S>
    <S sid="102" ssid="3">The data description is as follows: &#8220;An artificial test corpus of 700 samples is used to assess the accuracy and speed performance of segmentation algorithms.</S>
    <S sid="103" ssid="4">A sample is a concatenation of ten text segments.</S>
    <S sid="104" ssid="5">A segment is the first sentences of a randomly selected document from the Brown corpus.</S>
    <S sid="105" ssid="6">A sample is characterised by the range .&#8221; (Choi, 2000) Table 1 gives the corpus statistics. racy.</S>
    <S sid="106" ssid="7">The sample texts were preprocessed &#8211; i.e., punctuation and stop words were removed and the remaining words were stemmed &#8211; by a program using the libraries available in Choi&#8217;s package.</S>
    <S sid="107" ssid="8">The texts were then segmented by the systems listed in Tables 2 and 3.</S>
    <S sid="108" ssid="9">The segmentation boundaries were placed at the ends of sentences.</S>
    <S sid="109" ssid="10">The segmentations were evaluated by applying an evaluation program in Choi&#8217;s package.</S>
    <S sid="110" ssid="11">The results are listed in Tables 2 and 3. is the result for our system when the numbers of segments were determined by the system.</S>
    <S sid="111" ssid="12">is the result for our system when the numbers of segments were given beforehand.8 and are the corresponding results for the systems deprobabilistic error metric proposed by Beeferman, et al. (1999).7 Low indicates high accuedges in the minimum-cost path, then the resulting segmentation often contains very small segments consisting of only one or two sentences.</S>
    <S sid="112" ssid="13">We found empirically that segments obtained by recursive segmentation were better than those obtained by minimum-cost segmentation when the specified number of segments was somewhat larger than that of the minimum-cost path, whose number of segments was automatically determined by the algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="113" ssid="14">In these tables, the symbol &#8220; &#8221; indicates that the difference in between the two systems is statistically significant at the 1% level, based on &#8220;number is the probability that a randomly chosen pair of words a distance of words apart is inconsistently classified; that is, for one of the segmentations the pair lies in the same segment, while for the other the pair spans a segment boundary&#8221; (Beeferman et al., 1999), where is chosen to be half the average reference segment length (in words). ments were given beforehand. a one-sided -test of the null hypothesis of equal means.</S>
    <S sid="114" ssid="15">The probability of the null hypothesis being true is displayed in the row indicated by &#8220;prob&#8221;.</S>
    <S sid="115" ssid="16">The column labels, such as &#8220; &#8221;, indicate that the numbers in the column are the averages of over the corresponding sample texts.</S>
    <S sid="116" ssid="17">&#8220;Total&#8221; indicates the averages of over all the text samples.</S>
    <S sid="117" ssid="18">These tables show statistically that our system is more accurate than or at least as accurate as .</S>
    <S sid="118" ssid="19">This means that our system is more accurate than or at least as accurate as previous domainindependent text segmentation systems, because has been shown to be more accurate than previous domain-independent text segmentation systems.10</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="5 Discussion" number="5">
    <S sid="119" ssid="1">Evaluation of the output of text segmentation systems is difficult because the required segmentations depend on the application.</S>
    <S sid="120" ssid="2">In this paper, we have used an artificial corpus to evaluate our system.</S>
    <S sid="121" ssid="3">We regard this as appropriate for comparing relative performance among systems.</S>
    <S sid="122" ssid="4">It is important, however, to assess the performance of systems by using real texts.</S>
    <S sid="123" ssid="5">These texts should be domain independent.</S>
    <S sid="124" ssid="6">They should also be multi-lingual if we want to test the multilinguality of systems.</S>
    <S sid="125" ssid="7">For English, Klavans, et al. describe a segmentation corpus in which the texts were segmented by humans (Klavans et al., 1998).</S>
    <S sid="126" ssid="8">But, there are no such corpora for other languages.</S>
    <S sid="127" ssid="9">We are planning to build a segmentation corpus for Japanese, based on a corpus of speech transcriptions (Maekawa and Koiso, 2000).</S>
    <S sid="128" ssid="10">Our proposed algorithm finds the maximumprobability segmentation of a given text.</S>
    <S sid="129" ssid="11">This is a new approach for domain-independent text segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="130" ssid="12">A probabilistic approach, however, has already been proposed by Yamron, et al. for domain-dependent text segmentation (broadcast news story segmentation) (Yamron et al., 1998).</S>
    <S sid="131" ssid="13">They trained a hidden Markov model (HMM), whose states correspond to topics.</S>
    <S sid="132" ssid="14">Given a word sequence, their system assigns each word a topic so that the maximum-probability topic sequence is obtained.</S>
    <S sid="133" ssid="15">Their model is basically the same as that used for HMM part-of-speech (POS) taggers (Manning and Sch&#168;utze, 1999), if we regard topics as POS tags.11 Finding topic boundaries is equivalent to finding topic transitions; i.e., a continuous topic or segment is a sequence of words with the same topic.</S>
    <S sid="134" ssid="16">Their approach is indirect compared with our approach, which directly finds the maximumprobability segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="135" ssid="17">As a result, their model can not straightforwardly incorporate features pertaining to a segment itself, such as the average length of segments.</S>
    <S sid="136" ssid="18">Our model, on the other hand, can incorporate this information quite naturally.</S>
    <S sid="137" ssid="19">Suppose that the length of a segment follows a normal distribution , with a mean of and standard deviation of (Ponte and Croft, 1997).</S>
    <S sid="138" ssid="20">Then Equation (13) can be augmented to where .</S>
    <S sid="139" ssid="21">Equation (17) favors segments whose lengths are similar to the average length (in words).</S>
    <S sid="140" ssid="22">Another major difference from their algorithm is that our algorithm does not require training data to estimate probabilities, while their algorithm does.</S>
    <S sid="141" ssid="23">Therefore, our algorithm can be applied to domain-independent texts, while their algorithm is restricted to domains for which training data are available.</S>
    <S sid="142" ssid="24">It would be interesting, however, to compare our algorithm with their algorithm for the case when training data are available.</S>
    <S sid="143" ssid="25">In such a case, our model should be extended to incorporate various features such as the average segment length, clue words, named entities, and so on (Reynar, 1999; Beeferman et al., 1999).</S>
    <S sid="144" ssid="26">Our proposed algorithm naturally estimates the probabilities of words in segments.</S>
    <S sid="145" ssid="27">These probabilities, which are called word densities, have been used to detect important descriptions of words in texts (Kurohashi et al., 1997).</S>
    <S sid="146" ssid="28">This method is based on the assumption that the density of a word is high in a segment in which the word is discussed (defined and/or explained) in some depth.</S>
    <S sid="147" ssid="29">It would be interesting to apply our method to this application.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="6 Conclusion" number="6">
    <S sid="148" ssid="1">We have proposed a statistical model for domainindependent text segmentation.</S>
    <S sid="149" ssid="2">This method finds the maximum-probability segmentation of a given text.</S>
    <S sid="150" ssid="3">The method has been shown to be more accurate than or at least as accurate as previous methods.</S>
    <S sid="151" ssid="4">We are planning to build a segmentation corpus for Japanese and evaluate our method against this corpus.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="Acknowledgements" number="7">
    <S sid="152" ssid="1">We thank Freddy Y. Y. Choi for his text segmentation package.</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
