<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">Translating Collocations For Bilingual Lexicons: A Statistical Approach</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">Collocations are notoriously difficult for non-native speakers to translate, primarily because they are opaque and cannot be translated on a word-by-word basis.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">We describe a program named given a pair of parallel corpora in two different languages and a list of collocations in one of them, automatically produces their translations.</S>
    <S sid="3" ssid="3">Our goal is to provide a tool for compiling bilingual lexical information above the word level in multiple languages, for different domains.</S>
    <S sid="4" ssid="4">The algorithm we use is based on statistical methods and produces p-word translations of collocations in which not be the same.</S>
    <S sid="5" ssid="5">For example, .</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="6">.</S>
    <S sid="7" ssid="7">. decision, employment equity, market .</S>
    <S sid="8" ssid="8">.</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="9">. decision, equite matiere d'emploi, Testing three years' worth of the Hansards corpus yielded the French translations of 300 collocations for each year, evaluated at 73% accuracy on average.</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="10">In this paper, we describe the statistical measures used, the algorithm, the implementation of our results and evaluation.</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="" number="1">
    <S sid="11" ssid="1">Collocations are notoriously difficult for non-native speakers to translate, primarily because they are opaque and cannot be translated on a word-by-word basis.</S>
    <S sid="12" ssid="2">We describe a program named Champollion which, given a pair of parallel corpora in two different languages and a list of collocations in one of them, automatically produces their translations.</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="3">Our goal is to provide a tool for compiling bilingual lexical information above the word level in multiple languages, for different domains.</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="4">The algorithm we use is based on statistical methods and produces p-word translations of n-word collocations in which n and p need not be the same.</S>
    <S sid="15" ssid="5">For example, Champollion translates make .</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="6">.</S>
    <S sid="17" ssid="7">. decision, employment equity, and stock market into prendre .</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="8">.</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="9">. decision, equite en matiere d'emploi, and bourse respectively.</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="10">Testing Champollion on three years' worth of the Hansards corpus yielded the French translations of 300 collocations for each year, evaluated at 73% accuracy on average.</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="11">In this paper, we describe the statistical measures used, the algorithm, and the implementation of Champollion, presenting our results and evaluation.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="1." number="2">
    <S sid="22" ssid="1">Hieroglyphics remained undeciphered for centuries until the discovery of the Rosetta stone in the beginning of the 19th century in Rosetta, Egypt.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="2">The Rosetta stone is a tablet of black basalt containing parallel inscriptions in three different scripts: Greek and two forms of ancient Egyptian writings (demotic and hieroglyphics).</S>
    <S sid="24" ssid="3">Jean-Francois Champollion, a linguist and Egyptologist, made the assumption that these inscriptions were parallel and managed after several years of research to decipher the hieroglyphic inscriptions.</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="4">He used his work on the Rosetta stone as a basis from which to produce the first comprehensive hieroglyphics dictionary (Budge 1989).</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="5">In this paper, we describe a modern version of a similar approach: given a large corpus in two languages, our system produces translations of common word pairs and phrases that can form the basis of a bilingual lexicon.</S>
    <S sid="27" ssid="6">Our focus is on the use of statistical methods for the translation of multiword expressions, such as collocations which are often idiomatic in nature.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="7">Published translations of such collocations are not readily available, even for languages such as French and English, despite the fact that collocations have been recognized as one of the main obstacles to second language acquisition (Leed and Nakhimovsky 1979).</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="8">We have developed a program named Champollion1 , which, given a sentencealigned parallel bilingual corpus, translates collocations (or individual words) in the source language into collocations (or individual words) in the target language.</S>
    <S sid="30" ssid="9">The aligned corpus is used as a reference, or database corpus, and represents Champollion' s knowledge of both languages.</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="10">Champollion uses statistical methods to incrementally construct the collocation translation, adding one word at a time.</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="11">As a correlation measure, Champollion uses the Dice coefficient (Dice 1945; Sorensen 1948) commonly used in information retrieval (Salton and McGill 1983; Frakes and Baeza-Yates 1992).</S>
    <S sid="33" ssid="12">For a given source language collocation, Champollion identifies individual words in the target language that are highly correlated with the source collocation, thus producing a set of words in the target language.</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="13">These words are then combined in a systematic, iterative manner to produce a translation of the source language collocation.</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="14">Champollion considers all pairs of these words and identifies any that are highly correlated with the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="15">Next, triplets are produced by adding a highly correlated word to a highly correlated pair, and the triplets that are highly correlated with the source language collocation are passed to the next stage.</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="16">This process is repeated until no more highly correlated combinations of words can be found.</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="17">Champollion selects the group of words with the highest cardinality and correlation factor as the target collocation.</S>
    <S sid="39" ssid="18">Finally, it produces the correct word ordering of the target collocation by examining samples in the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="40" ssid="19">If word order is variable in the target collocation, Champollion labels it flexible (for example, to take steps to can appear as took immediate steps to, steps were taken to, etc.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="20">); otherwise, the correct word order is reported and the collocation is labeled rigid.</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="21">To evaluate Champollion, we used a collocation compiler, XTRACT (Smadja 1993), to automatically produce several lists of source (English) collocations.</S>
    <S sid="43" ssid="22">These source collocations contain both flexible word pairs, which can be separated by an arbitrary number of words, and fixed constituents, such as compound noun phrases.</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="23">Using XTRACT on three parts of the English data in the Hansards corpus, each representing one year's worth of data, we extracted three sets of collocations, each consisting of 300 randomly selected collocations occurring with medium frequency.</S>
    <S sid="45" ssid="24">We then ran Champollion on each of these sets, using three separate database corpora of varying size, also taken from the Hansards corpus.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="25">We asked several people fluent in both French and English to judge the results, and the accuracy of Champollion was found to range from 65% to 78%.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="26">In our discussion of results, we show how problems for the lower score can be alleviated by increasing the size of the database corpus.</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="27">In the following sections, we first present a review of related work in statistical natural language processing dealing with bilingual data.</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="28">Our algorithm depends on using a measure of correlation to find words that are highly correlated across languages.</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="29">We describe the measure that we use and then provide a detailed description of the algorithm, following this with a theoretical analysis of the performance of our algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="30">Next, we turn to a description of the results and evaluation.</S>
    <S sid="52" ssid="31">Finally, we show how the results can be used for a variety of applications, closing with a discussion of the limitations of our approach and of future work.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="2." number="3">
    <S sid="53" ssid="1">The recent availability of large amounts of bilingual data has attracted interest in several areas, including sentence alignment (Gale and Church 1991b; Brown, Lai, and Mercer 1991; Simard, Foster and Isabelle 1992; Gale and Church 1993; Chen 1993), word alignment (Gale and Church 1991a; Brown et al. 1993; Dagan, Church, and Gale 1993; Fung and McKeown 1994; Fung 1995b), alignment of groups of words (Smadja 1992; Kupiec 1993; van der Eijk 1993), and statistical translation (Brown et al.</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="2">1993).</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="3">Of these, aligning groups of words is most similar to the work reported here, although, as we shall show, we consider a greater variety of groups than is typical in other research.</S>
    <S sid="56" ssid="4">In this section, we describe work on sentence and word alignment and statistical translation, showing how these goals differ from our own, and then describe work on aligning groups of words.</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="5">Note that there is additional research using statistical approaches to bilingual problems, but it is less related to ours, addressing, for example, word sense disambiguation in the source language by statistically examining context (e.g., collocations) in the source language, thus allowing appropriate word selection in the target language.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="6">(Brown et al. 1991; Dagan, Itai, and Schwall 1991; Dagan and Itai 1994).</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="7">Our use of bilingual corpora assumes a prealigned corpus.</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="8">Thus, we draw on work done at AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories by Gale and Church (1991a, 1991b, 1993) and at IBM by Brown, Lai, and Mercer (1991) on bilingual sentence alignment.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="9">Sentence alignment programs take a paired bilingual corpus as input and determine which sentences in the target language translate which sentences in the source language.</S>
    <S sid="62" ssid="10">Both the AT&amp;T and the IBM groups use purely statistical techniques based on sentence length to identify sentence pairing in corpora such as the Hansards.</S>
    <S sid="63" ssid="11">The AT&amp;T group (Gale and Church 1993) defines sentence length by the number of characters in the sentences, while the IBM group (Brown, Lai, and Mercer 1991) defines sentence length by the number of words in the sentence.</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="12">Both approaches achieve similar results and have been influential in much of the research on statistical natural language processing, including ours.</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="13">It has been noted in more recent work that length-based alignment programs such as these are problematic for many cases of real world parallel data, such as OCR (Optical Character Recognition) input, in which periods may not be noticeable (Church 1993), or languages where insertions or deletions are common (Shemtov 1993; Fung and McKeown 1994).</S>
    <S sid="66" ssid="14">These algorithms were adequate for our purposes, but could be replaced by algorithms more appropriate for noisy input corpora, if necessary Sentence alignment techniques are generally used as a preprocessing stage, before the main processing component that proposes actual translations, whether of words, phrases, or full text, and they are used this way in our work as well.</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="15">Translation can be approached using statistical techniques alone.</S>
    <S sid="68" ssid="16">Brown et al. (1990, 1993) use a stochastic language model based on techniques used in speech recognition, combined with translation probabilities compiled on the aligned corpus, to do sentence translation.</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="17">Their system, Candide, uses little linguistic and no semantic information and currently produces good quality translations for short sentences containing high frequency vocabulary as measured by individual human evaluators (see Berger et al. [19941 for information on recent results).</S>
    <S sid="70" ssid="18">While they also align groups of words across languages in the process of translation, they are careful to point out that such groups may or may not occur at constituent breaks in the sentence.</S>
    <S sid="71" ssid="19">In contrast, our work aims at identifying syntactically and semantically meaningful units, which may be either constituents or flexible word pairs separated by intervening words, and provides the translation of these units for use in a variety of bilingual applications.</S>
    <S sid="72" ssid="20">Thus, the goals of our research are somewhat different.</S>
    <S sid="73" ssid="21">Kupiec (1993) describes a technique for finding noun phrase correspondences in bilingual corpora using several stages.</S>
    <S sid="74" ssid="22">First, as for Champollion, the bilingual corpus must be aligned by sentences.</S>
    <S sid="75" ssid="23">Then, each corpus is separately run through a partof-speech tagger and noun phrase recognizer.</S>
    <S sid="76" ssid="24">Finally, noun phrases are mapped to each other using an iterative re-estimation algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="77" ssid="25">Evaluation was done on the 100 highest-ranking correspondences produced by the program, yielding 90% accuracy.</S>
    <S sid="78" ssid="26">Evaluation has not been completed for the remaining correspondences-4900 distinct English noun phrases.</S>
    <S sid="79" ssid="27">The author indicates that the technique has several limitations, due in part to the compounded error rates of the taggers and noun phrase recognizers.</S>
    <S sid="80" ssid="28">Van der Eijk (1993) uses a similar approach for translating terms.</S>
    <S sid="81" ssid="29">His work is based on the assumption that terms are noun phrases and thus, like Kupiec, uses sentence alignment, tagging, and a noun phrase recognizer.</S>
    <S sid="82" ssid="30">His work differs in the correlation measure he uses: he compares local frequency of the term (i.e., frequency in sentences containing the term) to global frequency (i.e., frequency in the full corpus), decreasing the resulting score by a weight representing the distance between the actual position of the target term and its expected position in the corpus; this weight is small if the target term is exactly aligned with the source term and larger as the distance increases.</S>
    <S sid="83" ssid="31">His evaluation shows 68% precision and 64% recall.</S>
    <S sid="84" ssid="32">We suspect that the lower precision is due in part to the fact that van der Eijk evaluated all translations produced by the program while Kupiec only evaluated the top 2%.</S>
    <S sid="85" ssid="33">Note that the greatest difference between these two approaches and ours is that van der Eijk and Kupiec only handle noun phrases whereas collocations have been shown to include parts of noun phrases, categories other than noun phrases (e.g., verb phrases), as well as flexible phrases that involve words separated by an arbitrary number of other words (e.g., to take .</S>
    <S sid="86" ssid="34">.</S>
    <S sid="87" ssid="35">. steps, to demonstrate .</S>
    <S sid="88" ssid="36">.</S>
    <S sid="89" ssid="37">. support).</S>
    <S sid="90" ssid="38">In this work, as in earlier work (Smadja 1992), we address the full range of collocations including both flexible and rigid collocations for a variety of syntactic categories.</S>
    <S sid="91" ssid="39">Another approach, begun more recently than our work, is taken by Dagan and Church (1994), who use statistical methods to translate technical terminology.</S>
    <S sid="92" ssid="40">Like van der Eijk and Kupiec, they preprocess their corpora by tagging and by identifying noun phrases.</S>
    <S sid="93" ssid="41">However, they use a word alignment program as opposed to sentence alignment and they include single words as candidates for technical terms.</S>
    <S sid="94" ssid="42">One of the major differences between their work and ours is that, like van der Eijk and Kupiec, they only handle translation of uninterrupted sequences of words; they do not handle the broader class of flexible collocations.</S>
    <S sid="95" ssid="43">Their system, Termight, first extracts candidate technical terms, presenting them to a terminologist for filtering.</S>
    <S sid="96" ssid="44">Then, Termight identifies candidate translations for each occurrence of a source term by using the word alignment to find the first and last target positions aligned with any words of the source terms.</S>
    <S sid="97" ssid="45">All candidate translations for a given source term are sorted by frequency and presented to the user, along with a concordance.</S>
    <S sid="98" ssid="46">Because Termight does not use additional correlation statistics, relying instead only on the word alignment, it will find translations for infrequent terms; none of the other approaches, including Champollion, can make this claim.</S>
    <S sid="99" ssid="47">Accuracy, however, is considerably lower; the most frequent translation for a term is correct only 40% of the time (compare with Champollion's 73% accuracy).</S>
    <S sid="100" ssid="48">Since Termight is fully integrated within a translator's editor (another unique feature) and is used as an aid for human translators, it gets around the problem of accuracy by presenting the sorted list of translations to the translator for a choice.</S>
    <S sid="101" ssid="49">In all cases, the correct translation was found in this list and translators were able to speed up both the task of identifying technical terminology and translating terms.</S>
    <S sid="102" ssid="50">Other recent related work aims at using statistical techniques to produce translations of single words (Fung and McKeown 1994; Wu and Xia 1994; Fung 1995b) as opposed to collocations or phrases.</S>
    <S sid="103" ssid="51">Wu and Xia (1994) employed an estimationmaximization technique to find the optimal word alignment from previously sentencealigned clean parallel corpora2, with additional significance filtering.</S>
    <S sid="104" ssid="52">The work by Fung and McKeown (1994) and Fung (1995b) is notable for its use of techniques suitable to Asian/Romance language pairs as well as Romance language pairs.</S>
    <S sid="105" ssid="53">Given that Asian languages differ considerably in structure from Romance languages, statistical methods that were previously proposed for pairs of European languages do not work well for these pairs.</S>
    <S sid="106" ssid="54">Fung and McKeown's work also focuses on word alignment from noisy parallel corpora, where there are no clear sentence boundaries or perfect translations.</S>
    <S sid="107" ssid="55">Work on the translation of single words into multiword sequences that integrates techniques for machine-readable dictionaries with statistical corpus analysis (Klavans and Tzoukermann 1990; Klavans and Tzoukermann in press) is also relevant.</S>
    <S sid="108" ssid="56">While this work focuses on a smaller set of words for translation (movement verbs), it provides a sophisticated approach using multiple knowledge sources to address both one-to-many word translations and the problem of sense disambiguation.</S>
    <S sid="109" ssid="57">Given only one word in the source, their system, BICORD, uses the corpus to extend dictionary definitions and provide translations that are appropriate for a given sense but do not occur in the dictionary, producing a bilingual lexicon of movement verbs as output.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="3." number="4">
    <S sid="110" ssid="1">Collocations, commonly occurring word pairs and phrases, are a notorious source of difficulty for non-native speakers of a language (Leed and Nakhimovsky 1979; Benson 1985; Benson, Benson, and Ilson 1986).</S>
    <S sid="111" ssid="2">This is because they cannot be translated on a word-by-word basis.</S>
    <S sid="112" ssid="3">Instead, a speaker must be aware of the meaning of the phrase as a whole in the source language and know the common phrase typically used in the target language.</S>
    <S sid="113" ssid="4">While collocations are not predictable on the basis of syntactic or semantic rules, they can be observed in language and thus must be learned through repeated usage.</S>
    <S sid="114" ssid="5">For example, in American English one says set the table while in British English the phrase lay the table is used.</S>
    <S sid="115" ssid="6">These are expressions that have evolved over time.</S>
    <S sid="116" ssid="7">It is not the meaning of the words lay and set that determines the use of one or the other in the full phrase.</S>
    <S sid="117" ssid="8">Here, the verb functions as a support verb; it derives its meaning in good part from the object in this context and not from its own semantic features.</S>
    <S sid="118" ssid="9">In addition, such collocations are flexible.</S>
    <S sid="119" ssid="10">The constraint is between the verb and its object and any number of words may occur between these two elements (e.g., You will be setting a gorgeously decorated and lavishly appointed table designed for a king).</S>
    <S sid="120" ssid="11">Collocations also include rigid groups of words that do not change from one context to another, such as compounds, as in Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms.</S>
    <S sid="121" ssid="12">To understand the difficulties that collocations pose for translation, consider sentences (le) and (10 in Figure 1.</S>
    <S sid="122" ssid="13">Although these sentences are relatively simple, automatically translating (le) as (10 involves several problems.</S>
    <S sid="123" ssid="14">Inability to translate on a word-by-word basis is due in part to the presence of collocations.</S>
    <S sid="124" ssid="15">For example, the English collocation to demonstrate support is translated as prouver son adhesion.</S>
    <S sid="125" ssid="16">This translation uses words that do not correspond to individual words in the source; the English translation of prouver is prove and son adhe'sion translates as one's adhesion.</S>
    <S sid="126" ssid="17">As a phrase, however, prouver son adhesion carries the same meaning as the source phrase.</S>
    <S sid="127" ssid="18">Other groups of words in (1e) cause similar problems, including to take steps to, provi2 These corpora had little noise.</S>
    <S sid="128" ssid="19">Most sentences neatly corresponded to translations in the paired corpus, with few extraneous sentences.</S>
    <S sid="129" ssid="20">(1e) &amp;quot;Mr. Speaker, our Government has demonstrated its support for these important principles by taking steps to enforce the provisions of the Charter more vigorously.&amp;quot; (10 &amp;quot;Monsieur le Pr&#233;sident, notre gouvernement a prouve son adhesion ces importants principes en prenant des mesures pour appliquer plus systematiquement les preceptes de la Charte.&amp;quot; sions of the Charter, and to enforce provisions.</S>
    <S sid="130" ssid="21">These groups are identified as collocations for a variety of reasons.</S>
    <S sid="131" ssid="22">For example, to take steps is a collocation because to take is used here as a support verb for the noun steps.</S>
    <S sid="132" ssid="23">The agent our government doesn't actually physically take anything; rather, it has begun the process of enforcement through small, concrete actions.</S>
    <S sid="133" ssid="24">While the French translation en prenant des mesures does use the French for take, the object is the translation of a word that does not appear in the source, measures.</S>
    <S sid="134" ssid="25">These are flexible collocations exhibiting variations in word order.</S>
    <S sid="135" ssid="26">On the other hand, the compound provisions of the Charter is very commonly used as a whole in a much more rigid way.</S>
    <S sid="136" ssid="27">This example also illustrates that collocations are domain dependent, often forming part of a sublanguage.</S>
    <S sid="137" ssid="28">For example, Mr. Speaker is the proper way to refer to the Speaker of the House in the Canadian Parliament when speaking English.</S>
    <S sid="138" ssid="29">The French equivalent, Monsieur le Pr&#233;sident, is not the literal translation but instead uses the translation of the term President.</S>
    <S sid="139" ssid="30">While this is an appropriate translation for the Canadian Parliament, in different contexts another translation would be better.</S>
    <S sid="140" ssid="31">Note that these problems are quite similar to the difficulties in translating technical terminology, which also is usually part of a particular technical sublanguage (Dagan and Church 1994).</S>
    <S sid="141" ssid="32">The ability to automatically acquire collocation translations is thus a definite advantage for sublanguage translation.</S>
    <S sid="142" ssid="33">When moving to a new domain and sublanguage, translations that are appropriate can be acquired by running Champollion on a new corpus from that domain.</S>
    <S sid="143" ssid="34">Since in some instances parts of a sentence can be translated on a word-by-word basis, a translator must know when a full phrase or pair of words must be considered for translation and when a word-by-word technique will suffice.</S>
    <S sid="144" ssid="35">Two tasks must therefore be considered: For both tasks, general knowledge of the two languages is not sufficient.</S>
    <S sid="145" ssid="36">It is also necessary to know the expressions used in the sublanguage, since we have seen that idiomatic phrases often have different translations in a restricted sublanguage than in general usage.</S>
    <S sid="146" ssid="37">In order to produce a fluent translation of a full sentence, it is necessary to know the specific translation for each of the source collocations.</S>
    <S sid="147" ssid="38">We use XTRACT (Smadja and McKeown 1990; Smadja 1991a; Smadja 1993), a tool we developed previously, to identify collocations in the source language (task 1).</S>
    <S sid="148" ssid="39">XTRACT works in three stages.</S>
    <S sid="149" ssid="40">In the first stage, word pairs that co-occur with significant frequency are identified.</S>
    <S sid="150" ssid="41">These words can be separated by up to four intervening words and thus constitute flexible collocations.</S>
    <S sid="151" ssid="42">In the second stage, XTRACT identifies combinations of word pairs from stage one with other words and phrases, producing compounds and idiomatic templates (i.e., phrases with one or more holes to be filled by specific syntactic types).</S>
    <S sid="152" ssid="43">In the final stage, XTRACT filters any pairs that do not consistently occur in the same syntactic relation, using a parsed version of the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="153" ssid="44">This tool has been used in several projects at Columbia University and has been distributed to a number of research and commercial sites worldwide.</S>
    <S sid="154" ssid="45">XTRACT has been developed and tested on English-only input.</S>
    <S sid="155" ssid="46">For optimal performance, XTRACT itself relies on other tools, such as a part-of-speech tagger and a robust parser.</S>
    <S sid="156" ssid="47">Although such tools are becoming more widely available in many languages, they are still hard to find.</S>
    <S sid="157" ssid="48">We have thus assumed in Champollion that these tools were only available in one of the two languages; namely, English, termed the source language throughout the paper.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="4." number="5">
    <S sid="158" ssid="1">To rank the proposed translations so that the best one is selected, Champollion uses a quantitative measure of correlation between the source collocation and its complete or partial translations.</S>
    <S sid="159" ssid="2">This measure is also used to reduce the search space to a manageable size, by filtering out partial translations that are not highly correlated with the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="160" ssid="3">In this section, we discuss the properties of similarity measures that are appropriate for our application.</S>
    <S sid="161" ssid="4">We explain why the Dice coefficient meets these criteria and why this measure is more appropriate than another frequently used measure&#8212;mutual information.</S>
    <S sid="162" ssid="5">Our approach is based on the assumption that each collocation is unambiguous in the source language and has a unique translation in the target language (at least in a clear majority of the cases).</S>
    <S sid="163" ssid="6">In this way, we can ignore the context of the collocations and their translations, and base our decisions only on the patterns of co-occurrence of each collocation and its candidate translations across the entire corpus.</S>
    <S sid="164" ssid="7">This approach is quite different from those adopted for the translation of single words (Klavans and Tzoukermann 1990; Dorr 1992; Klavans and Tzoukermann 1996), since for single words polysemy cannot be ignored; indeed, the problem of sense disambiguation has been linked to the problem of translating ambiguous words (Brown et al. 1991; Dagan, Itai, and Schwa11 1991; Dagan and Itai 1994).</S>
    <S sid="165" ssid="8">The assumption of a single meaning per collocation was based on our previous experience with English collocations (Smadja 1993), is supported for less opaque collocations by the fact that their constituent words tend to have a single sense when they appear in the collocation (Yarowsky 1993), and was verified during our evaluation of Champollion (Section 7).</S>
    <S sid="166" ssid="9">We construct a mathematical model of the events we want to correlate, namely, the appearance of any word or group of words in the sentences of our corpus, as follows: To each group of words G, in either the source or the target language, we map a binary random variable XG that takes the value &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; if G appears in a particular sentence and &amp;quot;0&amp;quot; if not.</S>
    <S sid="167" ssid="10">Then, the corpus of paired sentences comprising our database represents a collection of samples for the various random variables X for the various groups of words.</S>
    <S sid="168" ssid="11">Each new sentence in the corpus provides a new independent sample for every variable XG.</S>
    <S sid="169" ssid="12">For example, if G is unemployment rate and the words unemployment rate appear only in the fifth and fifty-fifth sentences of our corpus (not necessarily in that order and perhaps with other words intervening), then in our sample collection, XG takes the value &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; for the fifth and fifty-fifth sentences and &amp;quot;0&amp;quot; for all other sentences in the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="170" ssid="13">Furthermore, for the measurement of correlation between a word group G in the source language and another word group H in the target language, we map the paired sentences in our corpus to a collection of paired samples for the random variables XG and XH.</S>
    <S sid="171" ssid="14">This modeling process allows us to use correlation metrics between paired samples of random variables (XG and Xx) to measure the correlation between word groups (G and H) across languages.</S>
    <S sid="172" ssid="15">There are several ways to measure the correlation of two such random variables.</S>
    <S sid="173" ssid="16">One measure frequently used in information retrieval is the Dice coefficient (Dice 1945; Sorensen 1948; Salton and McGill 1983; Frakes and Baeza-Yates 1992).</S>
    <S sid="174" ssid="17">It is defined as where p(X, Y), p(X), and p(Y) are the joint and marginal probability mass functions of the variables X and Y, respectively.</S>
    <S sid="175" ssid="18">Using maximum likelihood estimates for the probabilities in the above equation, we have where fx, fy, and fxy are the absolute frequencies of appearance of &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s for the variables X, Y, and both X and Y together, respectively.</S>
    <S sid="176" ssid="19">On the other hand, in computational linguistics, information-theoretic measures such as mutual information are widely used (e.g., Bahl et al. 1986; Church and Hanks 1990; Church et al.</S>
    <S sid="177" ssid="20">1991; Dagan, Marcus, and Markovitch 1993; Su, Wu, and Chang 1994).</S>
    <S sid="178" ssid="21">In information theory, the mutual information I(X, Y) between two binary random variables X and Y is defined as However, in computational linguistics, the term mutual information has been used most of the time to describe only a part of the above sum, namely the term from the X =1, Y =1 case (unweighted by the joint probability p(X = 1, Y = 1)) .</S>
    <S sid="179" ssid="22">In other words, this alternative measure of mutual information, which we will refer to as specific mutual information S/(X, Y), is The quantity /(X, Y) is the average of SI(X, Y) taken over the four combinations of values of X and Y according to the joint probability distribution p(X, Y), so sometimes the term average mutual information is used for /(X, Y).</S>
    <S sid="180" ssid="23">Average mutual information expresses the difference between the entropy (information) of one of the variables and the conditional entropy of that variable given the other variable (Cover and Thomas 1991).</S>
    <S sid="181" ssid="24">Thus, average mutual information measures the reduction in the uncertainty about the value of one variable that knowledge of the value of the other variable provides, averaged over all possible values of the two variables.</S>
    <S sid="182" ssid="25">Equivalently, average mutual information is &amp;quot;the information about X contained in Y&amp;quot; (Papoulis 1984, 518) (or the information about Y contained in X).</S>
    <S sid="183" ssid="26">Specific mutual information represents the log-likelihood ratio of the joint probability of seeing a &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; in both variables over the probability that such an event would have if the two variables were independent, and thus provides a measure of the departure from independence.</S>
    <S sid="184" ssid="27">The Dice coefficient, on the other hand, combines the conditional probabilities p(X==1 I Y=1) and p(Y=1 I X=1) with equal weights in a single number.</S>
    <S sid="185" ssid="28">This can be shown by replacing p(X=1, Y=1) on the right side of equation (1):3 As is evident from the above equation, the Dice coefficient depends only on the conditional probabilities of seeing a &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; for one of the variables after seeing a &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; for the other variable, and not on the marginal probabilities of &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s for the two variables.</S>
    <S sid="186" ssid="29">In contrast, both the average and the specific mutual information depend on both the conditional and the marginal probabilities.</S>
    <S sid="187" ssid="30">For S/(X, Y) in particular, we have To select among the three measures, we first observe that for our application, 1-1 matches (paired samples where both X and Y are 1) are significant while 0-0 matches (samples where both X and Y are 0) are not.</S>
    <S sid="188" ssid="31">These two types of matches correspond to the cases where either both word groups of interest appear in a pair of aligned sentences or neither word group does.</S>
    <S sid="189" ssid="32">Seeing the two word groups in aligned sentences (a 1-1 match) certainly contributes to their association and increases our belief that one is the translation of the other.</S>
    <S sid="190" ssid="33">Similarly, seeing only one of them (a 1-0 or 0-1 mismatch) decreases our belief in their association.</S>
    <S sid="191" ssid="34">But, given the many possible groups of words that can appear in each sentence, the fact that neither of two groups of words appears in a pair of aligned sentences does not offer any information about their similarity.</S>
    <S sid="192" ssid="35">Even when the word groups have been observed relatively few times (together or separately), seeing additional sentences containing none of the groups of words we are interested in should not affect our estimate of their similarity.</S>
    <S sid="193" ssid="36">In other words, in our case, X and Y are highly asymmetric; a &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; value (and a 1-1 match) is much more informative than a &amp;quot;0&amp;quot; value (or 0-0 match).</S>
    <S sid="194" ssid="37">Therefore, we should select a similarity measure that is based only on 1-1 matches and mismatches.</S>
    <S sid="195" ssid="38">0-0 matches should be completely ignored; otherwise, they would dominate the similarity measure, given the overall relatively low frequency of any particular word or word group in our corpus.</S>
    <S sid="196" ssid="39">The Dice coefficient satisfies the above requirement of asymmetry: adding 0-0 matches does not change any of the absolute frequencies fxY, fx, and fy, and so does not affect Dice(X,Y).</S>
    <S sid="197" ssid="40">On the other hand, average mutual information depends only on the distribution of X and Y and not on the actual values of the random variables.</S>
    <S sid="198" ssid="41">In fact, I(X, Y) is a completely symmetric measure.</S>
    <S sid="199" ssid="42">If the variables X and Y are transformed so that every &amp;quot;1&amp;quot; is replaced with a &amp;quot;0&amp;quot; and vice versa, the average mutual information between X and Y remains the same.</S>
    <S sid="200" ssid="43">This is appropriate in the context of communications for which mutual information was originally developed (Shannon 1948), where the ones and zeros encode two different states with no special preference for either of them.</S>
    <S sid="201" ssid="44">But in the context of translation, exchanging the &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s and &amp;quot;0&amp;quot;s is equivalent to considering a word or word group to be present when it was absent and vice versa, thus converting all 1-1 matches to 0-0 matches and all 0-0 matches to 1-1 matches.</S>
    <S sid="202" ssid="45">As explained above, such a change should not be considered similarity preserving, since 1-1 matches are much more significant than 0-0 ones.</S>
    <S sid="203" ssid="46">As a concrete example, consider a corpus of 100 matched sentences, where each of the word groups associated with X and Y appears five times.</S>
    <S sid="204" ssid="47">Furthermore, suppose that the two groups appear twice in a pair of aligned sentences and each word group also appears three times by itself.</S>
    <S sid="205" ssid="48">This situation is depicted in the column labeled &amp;quot;Original Variables&amp;quot; in Table 1.</S>
    <S sid="206" ssid="49">Since each word group appears two times with the other group and three times by itself, we would normally consider the source and target groups somewhat similar but not strongly related.</S>
    <S sid="207" ssid="50">And indeed, the value of the Dice coefficient (254 = 0.4) intuitively corresponds to that assessment of similarity.4 Now, suppose that the &amp;quot;0&amp;quot;s and &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s in X and Y are exchanged, so that the situation is now described by the last column of Table 1.</S>
    <S sid="208" ssid="51">The transformed variables now indicate that out of 100 sentences, the two word groups appear together 92 times, while each appears by itself three times and there are two sentences that contain none of the groups.</S>
    <S sid="209" ssid="52">We would consider such evidence to strongly indicate very high similarity between the two groups, and indeed the Dice coefficient of the transformed variables is now 4115 = 0.9684.</S>
    <S sid="210" ssid="53">However, the average mutual information of the variables would remain the same.</S>
    <S sid="211" ssid="54">Specific mutual information falls somewhere in between the Dice coefficient and average mutual information: it is not completely symmetric but neither does it ignore 0-0 matches.</S>
    <S sid="212" ssid="55">This measure is very sensitive to the marginal probabilities (relative frequencies) of the &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s in the two variables, tending to give higher values as these probabilities decrease.</S>
    <S sid="213" ssid="56">Adding 0-0 matches lowers the relative frequencies of &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s, and therefore always increases the estimate of SI(X, Y).</S>
    <S sid="214" ssid="57">Furthermore, as the marginal probabilities of the two word groups become very small, SI(X, Y) tends to infinity, independently of the distribution of matches (including 1-1 and 0-0 ones) and mismatches, as long as the joint probability of 1-1 matches is not zero.</S>
    <S sid="215" ssid="58">By taking the limit of SI(X, Y) for p(X =1) &#8212;+0 or p(Y =1) &#8212;+0 in equation (2) we can easily verify that this happens even if the conditional probabilities p(X =1 I Y=1) and p(Y = 1 I X = 1) remain constant, a fact that should indicate a constant degree of relatedness between the two variables.</S>
    <S sid="216" ssid="59">Neither of these problems occurs with the Dice coefficient, exactly because that measure combines the conditional probabilities of &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s in both directions without looking at the marginal distributions of the two variables.</S>
    <S sid="217" ssid="60">In fact, in cases such as the examples of Table 1, where p(X = 1 I Y = 1) = p(Y = 1 I X = 1), the Dice coefficient becomes equal to these conditional probabilities.</S>
    <S sid="218" ssid="61">The dependence of SI(X, Y) on the marginal probabilities of &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s shows that using it would make rare word groups look more similar than they really are.</S>
    <S sid="219" ssid="62">For our example in Table 1, the specific mutual information is SI(X, Y) = log 0.05o.o20.05 = log 8 = 3 bits for the original variables, but SI(X', Y') = log 0.95%920,95 = log 1.019391 = 0.027707 bits for the transformed variables.</S>
    <S sid="220" ssid="63">Note, however, that the change is in the opposite direction from the appropriate one; that is, the new variables are deemed far less similar than the old ones.</S>
    <S sid="221" ssid="64">This can be attributed to the fact that the number of &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s in the original variables is far smaller.</S>
    <S sid="222" ssid="65">SI(X,Y) also suffers disproportionately from estimation errors when the observed counts of &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;s are very small.</S>
    <S sid="223" ssid="66">While all similarity measures will be inaccurate when the data is sparse, the results produced by specific mutual information can be more misleading than the results of other measures, because SI is not bounded.</S>
    <S sid="224" ssid="67">This is not a problem for our application, as Champollion applies absolute frequency thresholds to avoid considering very rare words and word groups; but it indicates another potential problem with the use of SI to measure similarity.</S>
    <S sid="225" ssid="68">Finally, another criterion for selecting a similarity measure is its suitability for testing for a particular outcome, where outcome is determined by the application.</S>
    <S sid="226" ssid="69">In our case, we need a clear-cut test to decide when two events are correlated.</S>
    <S sid="227" ssid="70">Both for mutual information and the Dice coefficient, this involves comparison with an experimentally determined threshold.</S>
    <S sid="228" ssid="71">Although the two measures are similar in that they compare the joint probability p(X=1,Y =1) with the marginal probabilities, they have different asymptotic behaviors.</S>
    <S sid="229" ssid="72">This was demonstrated in the previous paragraphs for the cases of small and decreasing relative frequencies.</S>
    <S sid="230" ssid="73">Here we examine two more cases associated with specific tests.</S>
    <S sid="231" ssid="74">We consider the two extreme cases, where In the first case, both average and specific mutual information are equal to 0 since log p51c-x)xptyYy)) = log 1 = 0 for all x and y, and are thus easily testable, whereas the Dice coefficient is equal to 2xp(r)(cx-1)1&#177;))V-.01)) and is thus a function of the individual frequencies of the two word groups.</S>
    <S sid="232" ssid="75">In this case, the test is easier to decide using mutual information.</S>
    <S sid="233" ssid="76">In the second case, the results are reversed; specific mutual information is equal to log pP((xtil))2 = log(p(X = 1)), and it can be shown that the average mutual information becomes equal to the entropy H(X) of X (or Y).</S>
    <S sid="234" ssid="77">Both of these measures depend on the individual probabilities (or relative frequencies) of the word groups, whereas the Dice coefficient is equal to px p) 1.</S>
    <S sid="235" ssid="78">In this case, the test is easier to decide using the Dice coefficient.</S>
    <S sid="236" ssid="79">Since we are looking for a way to identify positively correlated events we must be able to easily test the second case, while testing the first case is not relevant.</S>
    <S sid="237" ssid="80">Specific mutual information is a good measure of independence (which it was designed to measure), but good measures of independence are not necessarily good measures of similarity.</S>
    <S sid="238" ssid="81">The above arguments all support the use of the Dice coefficient over either average or specific mutual information.</S>
    <S sid="239" ssid="82">We have confirmed the theoretically expected behavior of the similarity measures through testing.</S>
    <S sid="240" ssid="83">In our early work on Champollion (Smadja 1992), we used specific mutual information (SI) as a correlation metric.</S>
    <S sid="241" ssid="84">After carefully studying the errors produced, we suspected that the Dice measure would produce better results for our task, according to the arguments given above.</S>
    <S sid="242" ssid="85">Consider the example given in Table 2.</S>
    <S sid="243" ssid="86">In the table, the second column represents candidate French word pairs for translating the single word today.</S>
    <S sid="244" ssid="87">The third column gives the frequency of the word today in a subset of the Hansards containing 182,584 sentences.</S>
    <S sid="245" ssid="88">The fourth column gives the frequency of each French word pair in the French counterpart of the same corpus, and the fifth column gives the frequency of appearance of today and each French word pair in matched sentences.</S>
    <S sid="246" ssid="89">Finally, the sixth and seventh columns give the similarity scores for today and each French word pair computed according to the Dice measure or specific mutual information (in bits) respectively.</S>
    <S sid="247" ssid="90">Of the four candidates, aujourd hui (shown in bold) is the only correct translation.'</S>
    <S sid="248" ssid="91">We see from the table that the specific mutual information scores fail to identify aujourd hui as the best candidate&#8212;it is only ranked fourth.</S>
    <S sid="249" ssid="92">Furthermore, the four SI scores are very similar, thus not clearly differentiating the results.</S>
    <S sid="250" ssid="93">In contrast, the Dice coefficient clearly identifies aujourd hui as the group of words most similar to today, which is what we want.</S>
    <S sid="251" ssid="94">After implementing Champollion, we attempted to generalize these results and confirm our theoretical argumentation by performing an experiment to compare SI and the Dice coefficient in the context of Champollion.</S>
    <S sid="252" ssid="95">We selected a set of 45 collocations with mid-range frequency identified by XTRACT and we ran Champollion on them using sample training corpora (databases).</S>
    <S sid="253" ssid="96">For each run of Champollion, and for each input collocation, we took the final set of candidate translations of different lengths produced by Champollion (with the intermediate stages driven by the Dice coefficient) and compared the results obtained using both the Dice coefficient and SI at the last stage for selecting the proposed translation.</S>
    <S sid="254" ssid="97">The 45 collocations were randomly selected from a larger set of 300 collocations so that the Dice coefficient's performance on them is representative (i.e., approximately 70% of them are translated correctly by Champollion when the Dice measure is used), and the correct translation is always included in the final set of candidate translations.</S>
    <S sid="255" ssid="98">In this way, the number of erroneous decisions made when SI is used at the final pass is a lower bound on the number of errors that would have been made if SI had also been used in the intermediate stages.</S>
    <S sid="256" ssid="99">We compared the results and found that out of the 45 source collocations, Table 3 summarizes these results and shows the breakdown across categories.</S>
    <S sid="257" ssid="100">In the table, the numbers of collocations correctly and incorrectly translated when the Dice coefficient is used are shown in the second and third rows respectively.</S>
    <S sid="258" ssid="101">For both cases, the second column indicates the number of collocations that were correctly translated with SI and the third column indicates the number of these collocations that were incorrectly translated with SI.</S>
    <S sid="259" ssid="102">The last column and the last row show the total number of collocations correctly and incorrectly translated when the Dice coefficient or SI is used respectively.</S>
    <S sid="260" ssid="103">From the table we see that every time SI produced good results, the Dice coefficient also produced good results; there were no cases for which SI produced a correct result while the Dice coefficient produced an incorrect one.</S>
    <S sid="261" ssid="104">In addition, we see that out of the 17 incorrect results produced by SI, the Dice coefficient corrected 10.</S>
    <S sid="262" ssid="105">Although based on only a few cases, this experiment confirms that the Dice coefficient outperforms SI in the context of Champollion.</S>
    <S sid="263" ssid="106">Table 4 gives concrete examples from this experiment in which the Dice coefficient outperforms specific mutual information.</S>
    <S sid="264" ssid="107">The table has a format similar to that of Table 2.</S>
    <S sid="265" ssid="108">X represents an English collocation (credit card or affirmative action), and Y represents candidate translations in French (for the credit cards example: cartes, cartes credit, cartes credit taux, and cartes credit taux paient).</S>
    <S sid="266" ssid="109">The correct translations are again shown in bold.</S>
    <S sid="267" ssid="110">The third and fourth columns give the independent frequencies of each word group, while the fifth column gives the number of times that both groups appear in matched sentences.</S>
    <S sid="268" ssid="111">The two subsequent columns give the similarity values computed according to the Dice coefficient and specific mutual information (in bits).</S>
    <S sid="269" ssid="112">The corpus used for these examples contained 54,944 sentences in each language.</S>
    <S sid="270" ssid="113">We see from Table 4 that, as for the today example in Table 2, the SI scores are very close to each other and fail to select the correct candidate whereas the Dice scores cover a wider range and clearly peak for the correct translation.</S>
    <S sid="271" ssid="114">In conclusion, both theoretical arguments and experimental results support the choice of the Dice coefficient over average or specific mutual information for our Champollion translates single words or collocations in one language into collocations (including single word translations) in a second language using the aligned corpus as a reference database.</S>
    <S sid="272" ssid="115">Before running Champollion there are two steps that must be carried out: source and target language sentences of the database corpus must be aligned and a list of collocations to be translated must be provided in the source language.</S>
    <S sid="273" ssid="116">For our experiments, we used corpora that had been aligned by Gale and Church's sentence alignment program (Gale and Church 1991b) as our input data.8 Since our intent in this paper is to evaluate Champollion, we tried not to introduce errors into the training data; for this purpose, we kept only the 1-1 alignments.</S>
    <S sid="274" ssid="117">Indeed, more complex sentence alignments tend to have a much higher alignment error rate (Gale and Church 1991b).</S>
    <S sid="275" ssid="118">By doing so, we lost an estimated 10% of the text (Brown, Lai, and Mercer 1991), which was not problematic since we had enough data.</S>
    <S sid="276" ssid="119">In the future, we plan to design more flexible techniques that would work from a loosely aligned corpus (see Section 9).</S>
    <S sid="277" ssid="120">To compile collocations, we used XTRACT on the English version of the Hansards.</S>
    <S sid="278" ssid="121">Some of the collocations retrieved are shown in Table 5.</S>
    <S sid="279" ssid="122">Collocations labeled &amp;quot;fixed,&amp;quot; such as International Human Rights Covenants, are rigid compounds.</S>
    <S sid="280" ssid="123">Collocations labeled &amp;quot;flexible&amp;quot; are pairs of words that can be separated by intervening words or occur in reverse order, possibly with different inflected forms.</S>
    <S sid="281" ssid="124">Given a source English collocation, Champollion first identifies in the database corpus all the sentences containing the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="282" ssid="125">It then attempts to find all words that can be part of the translation of the collocation, producing all words that are highly correlated with the source collocation as a whole.</S>
    <S sid="283" ssid="126">Once this set of words is identified, Champollion iteratively combines these words in groups, so that each group is in turn highly correlated with the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="284" ssid="127">Finally, Champollion produces as the translation the largest group of words having a high correlation with the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="285" ssid="128">More precisely, for a given source collocation, Champollion initially identifies a set S of k words that are highly correlated with the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="286" ssid="129">This operation is described in detail in Section 5.1 below.</S>
    <S sid="287" ssid="130">Champollion assumes that the target collocation is a combination of some subset of these words.</S>
    <S sid="288" ssid="131">Its search space at this point thus consists of the powerset P(S) of S containing 2k elements.</S>
    <S sid="289" ssid="132">Instead of computing a correlation factor for each of the 2&amp;quot; elements with the source collocation, Champollion searches a part of this space in an iterative manner.</S>
    <S sid="290" ssid="133">Champollion first forms all pairs of words in S, evaluates the correlation between each pair and the source collocation using the Dice coefficient, and keeps only those pairs that score above some threshold.</S>
    <S sid="291" ssid="134">Subsequently, it constructs the three-word elements of P (S) containing one of 7 The choice of the Dice coefficient is not crucial; for example, using the Jaccard coefficient or any other similarity measure that is monotonically related to the Dice coefficient would be equivalent.</S>
    <S sid="292" ssid="135">What is important is that the selected measure satisfy the conditions of asymmetry insensitivity to marginal word probabilities, and convenience in testing for correlation.</S>
    <S sid="293" ssid="136">There are many other possible measures of association, and the general points made in this section may apply to them insofar as they also exhibit the properties we discussed.</S>
    <S sid="294" ssid="137">For example, the normalized chi-square measure (02) used in Gale and Church (1991a) shares some of the important properties of average mutual information (for example, it is completely symmetric with respect to 1-1 and 0-0 matches).</S>
    <S sid="295" ssid="138">8 We are thankful to Ken Church and the AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories for providing us with a prealigned Hansards corpus. these highly correlated pairs plus a member of S. measures their correlation with the source collocation, and keeps the triplets that score above the threshold.</S>
    <S sid="296" ssid="139">This process is repeated until, for some value n &lt; k, no n-word element of 2(S) scores above the threshold.</S>
    <S sid="297" ssid="140">Then Champollion selects the best translation among the top candidates in each group of i words, 1 &lt;i &lt; n &#8212; 1, and determines whether the selected translation is a single word, a flexible collocation, or a rigid collocation.</S>
    <S sid="298" ssid="141">For rigid collocations, Champollion also reports the (fixed) order in which the words in the translation appear in the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="299" ssid="142">Champollion operates in four consecutive stages.</S>
    <S sid="300" ssid="143">Each of these stages corresponds to one step of the algorithm, with the exception of the main iteration stage, which covers steps 2 to 4 of the algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="301" ssid="144">An additional preprocessing stage where indexing structures are created for fast access to the corpus is required when the corpus database is changed.</S>
    <S sid="302" ssid="145">We describe the algorithm below, alternating each step with a description of what is produced at that step, using the example given in Figure 2.</S>
    <S sid="303" ssid="146">This figure shows information exactly as Champollion produces it.</S>
    <S sid="304" ssid="147">We have added italicized comments explaining the various components of the output.</S>
    <S sid="305" ssid="148">The output includes the various potential candidate translations, of incrementally larger lengths, and the final selected translation having the best score.</S>
    <S sid="306" ssid="149">Note that Champollion correctly determines the word order in the French translation, which is the opposite of the word order in the English collocation.</S>
    <S sid="307" ssid="150">Stage 1&#8212;Step 1: Initialization of the work space.</S>
    <S sid="308" ssid="151">Starting with a source language word group (possibly a single word) W, Champollion identifies all words in the target IanLe depute n' ignore pas que le gouvernement compte presenter, avant la fin de l' armee, un projet de revision de la Loi sur les langues officielles.</S>
    <S sid="309" ssid="152">Finally, additional information concerning word order is computed and presented.</S>
    <S sid="310" ssid="153">For a rigid collocation such as this one, Champollion will print for all words in the selected translation except the first one their distance from the first word.</S>
    <S sid="311" ssid="154">In our example, the second word (langues) appears in most cases one word before officielles, to form the compound langues officielles.</S>
    <S sid="312" ssid="155">Note that this information is added during postprocessing after the translation has been selected, and takes very little time to compute because of the indexing.</S>
    <S sid="313" ssid="156">In this case, it took a few seconds to compute this information. guage that satisfy the following two conditions: Words that pass these tests are collected in a set S. from which the final translation will eventually be produced.</S>
    <S sid="314" ssid="157">When given official languages as input (see Figure 2), this step produces a set S with the following eleven words: suivantes, doug, deposer, suprematie, lewis, petitions, honneur, programme, mixte, officielles, and langues.</S>
    <S sid="315" ssid="158">The Dice threshold Td (currently set at 0.10) is the major criterion that Champollion uses to decide which words or partial collocations should be kept as candidates for the final translation of the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="316" ssid="159">In Section 6 we explain why this incremental filtering process is necessary and we show that it does not significantly degrade the quality of Champ&#176;llion's output.</S>
    <S sid="317" ssid="160">To our surprise, we found that the filtering process may even increase the quality of the proposed translation.</S>
    <S sid="318" ssid="161">The absolute frequency threshold Tf (currently set at 5) also helps limit the size of S, by rejecting words that appear too few times opposite the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="319" ssid="162">Its most important function, however, is to remove from consideration words that appear too few times for our statistical methods to be meaningful.</S>
    <S sid="320" ssid="163">Applying the Dice measure (or any other statistical similarity measure) to very sparse data can produce misleading results, so we use Tf as a guide for the applicability of our method to low frequency words.</S>
    <S sid="321" ssid="164">It is possible to modify the thresholds Td and Tf according to properties of the database corpus and the collocations that are translated.</S>
    <S sid="322" ssid="165">Such an approach would use lower values of the thresholds, especially of Tf, for smaller corpora or less frequent collocations.</S>
    <S sid="323" ssid="166">In that case, a separate estimation phase is needed to automatically determine the values of the thresholds.</S>
    <S sid="324" ssid="167">The alternative we currently support is to allow the user to replace the default thresholds during the execution of Champollion with values that are more appropriate for the corpus at hand.</S>
    <S sid="325" ssid="168">After all words have been collected in S, the initial set of possible translations P is set equal to S, and Champollion proceeds with the next stage.</S>
    <S sid="326" ssid="169">Stage 2&#8212;Step 2: Scoring of possible translations.</S>
    <S sid="327" ssid="170">In this step, Champollion examines all members of the set P of possible translations.</S>
    <S sid="328" ssid="171">For each member x of P, Champollion computes the Dice coefficient between the source language collocation W and x.</S>
    <S sid="329" ssid="172">If the Dice coefficient is below the threshold Td, X is discarded from further consideration; otherwise, x is saved in a set P'.</S>
    <S sid="330" ssid="173">When given official languages as input, the first iteration of Step 2 simply sets P' to P, the second iteration selects 35 word pairs out of the possible 110 candidates, the third iteration selects 61 word triplets, and so on until the final (ninth) iteration when none of the three elements of P passes the threshold Td and thus P' has no elements.</S>
    <S sid="331" ssid="174">Stage 2&#8212;Step 3: Identifying the locally best translation.</S>
    <S sid="332" ssid="175">Once the set of surviving translations P' has been computed, Champollion checks if it is empty.</S>
    <S sid="333" ssid="176">If it is, there cannot be any more translations to be considered, so Champollion proceeds to Step 5.</S>
    <S sid="334" ssid="177">If P' is not empty, Champollion locates the translation that looks locally the best; that is, among all members of P' analyzed at this iteration, the translation that has the highest Dice coefficient value with the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="335" ssid="178">This translation is saved in a table C of candidate final translations, along with its length in words and its similarity score.</S>
    <S sid="336" ssid="179">Champollion then continues with the next step.</S>
    <S sid="337" ssid="180">The first iteration of Step 3 on our example collocation would select the word officielles (among the 11 words in S) as the first candidate translation, with a score of 0.94.</S>
    <S sid="338" ssid="181">On the second iteration, the word pair (officielles, langues) is selected (out of 35 pairs that pass the threshold) with a score of 0.95.</S>
    <S sid="339" ssid="182">On the third run, the word triplet (honneur, officielles, langues), is selected (out of 61 triplets) with a score of 0.45.</S>
    <S sid="340" ssid="183">On the eighth iteration of Step 3, P' has only one element, the 8-tuple (suivantes, doug, deposer, lewis, petitions, honneur, officielles, langues) with a score of 0.20.</S>
    <S sid="341" ssid="184">Finally, on the ninth iteration of Step 3, P' is empty and Champollion goes to Step 5.</S>
    <S sid="342" ssid="185">Stage 2&#8212;Step 4: Updating the set of possible translations.</S>
    <S sid="343" ssid="186">Champollion updates the set of possible translations by setting P equal to the Cartesian product of the surviving translations P' and the collection of words S (i.e., those related to the source collocation).9 Control then returns to the start of Step 2.</S>
    <S sid="344" ssid="187">In our example, during the first run of Step 4, a set of word pairs would be produced, including, for example, (suivantes, doug), (deposer, lewis), (petitions, honneur), and (officielles, langues).</S>
    <S sid="345" ssid="188">Some of the word triplets formed during the second iteration of Step 4 on our example starting from the word pair (officielles, longues) are (officielles, langues, suivantes), (officielles, langues, doug), (officielles, langues, lewis), and (officielles, langues, honneur).</S>
    <S sid="346" ssid="189">Similarly, on the third run of Step 4 quadruplets are formed such as (officielles, langues, suivantes, lewis).</S>
    <S sid="347" ssid="190">Finally, on the eighth iteration of this step, three 9-tuples are formed, including, for example, (suivantes, doug, deposer, lewis, petitions, honneur, officielles, langues, mixte), and are passed on to Step 2; note that none of them will pass the Dice threshold at the next iteration of Step 2.</S>
    <S sid="348" ssid="191">Stage 3&#8212;Step 5: Identifying the globally best translation.</S>
    <S sid="349" ssid="192">If the list of candidate final translations C is empty, Champollion has failed to locate a target language translation of the source collocation and stops, reporting this.</S>
    <S sid="350" ssid="193">Otherwise, the entry with the highest Dice coefficient with the source collocation is selected as the translation.</S>
    <S sid="351" ssid="194">In the case of ties, the longer of the tied collocations is selected.</S>
    <S sid="352" ssid="195">Note that because of the way table C is maintained, the word group selected in this way is guaranteed to correspond to a global maximum (among all word groups considered) of the similarity measure.</S>
    <S sid="353" ssid="196">We are planning to experiment with a more sophisticated technique for selecting the globally best translation, giving more weight to the collocation length so that longer word groups are considered better choices.</S>
    <S sid="354" ssid="197">If the final translation contains just one word, Champollion reports the result and halts.</S>
    <S sid="355" ssid="198">Otherwise, the following step is executed.</S>
    <S sid="356" ssid="199">Step 5 in our example selects the pair (officielles, langues) with a score of 0.951070 as the best candidate and continues with the following step.</S>
    <S sid="357" ssid="200">Stage 4&#8212;Step 6: Determination of word ordering.</S>
    <S sid="358" ssid="201">Once a multiword translation has been selected, Champollion examines all the sentences containing the selected translation to determine whether the collocation is flexible (i.e., word order is not fixed) or rigid.</S>
    <S sid="359" ssid="202">Champollion looks at all the sentences containing the target language collocation and determines if the words involved are used consistently (i.e., in at least 60% of the cases) in the same order and at the same distance from one another.</S>
    <S sid="360" ssid="203">If the collocation is found to be rigid, the word order and the interword distances are also reported.</S>
    <S sid="361" ssid="204">Note that although this is a postprocessing stage, it does not require any sentence of the corpus to be reread, since the necessary information has already been precomputed.</S>
    <S sid="362" ssid="205">For the official languages example, Champollion determines that langues appears before officielles with no intervening words and produces the rigid collocation langues officielles.</S>
    <S sid="363" ssid="206">See Figure 2 on page 17 for more details.</S>
    <S sid="364" ssid="207">Considering the size of the corpora that must be handled by Champollion, special care has been taken to minimize the number of disk accesses made during processing.</S>
    <S sid="365" ssid="208">We have experimented on up to two full years of the Hansards corpus, amounting to some 640,000 sentences in each language or about 220 megabytes of uncompressed text.</S>
    <S sid="366" ssid="209">With corpora of this magnitude, Champollion takes between one and two minutes to translate a collocation, thus enabling its practical use as a bilingual lexicography tool.</S>
    <S sid="367" ssid="210">To achieve efficient processing of the corpus database, Champollion is implemented in two phases: the preparation phase and the actual translation phase.</S>
    <S sid="368" ssid="211">The preparation phase reads in the database corpus and indexes it for fast future access using a commercial B-tree package (Informix 1990).</S>
    <S sid="369" ssid="212">Each word in the original corpus is associated with a set of pointers to all the sentences containing it and to the positions of the word in each of these sentences.</S>
    <S sid="370" ssid="213">The frequency of each word (in sentences) is also computed at this stage.</S>
    <S sid="371" ssid="214">Thus, all the necessary information is collected from the corpus database at this preprocessing phase with only one pass over the corpus file.</S>
    <S sid="372" ssid="215">At the translation phase, only the indices are accessed.</S>
    <S sid="373" ssid="216">For the translation phase, we developed an algorithm that avoids computing the Dice coefficient for French words when the result must necessarily fall below the threshold.</S>
    <S sid="374" ssid="217">Using the index file on the English part of the corpus, we collect all French sentences that match the source collocation, and produce a list of all words that appear in these sentences, together with their frequency (in sentences) in this subset of the French corpus.</S>
    <S sid="375" ssid="218">This operation takes only a few seconds to perform, and yields a list of a few thousand French words.</S>
    <S sid="376" ssid="219">The list also contains the local frequency of these words (i.e., frequency within this subset of the French corpus), and is sorted by this frequency in decreasing order.</S>
    <S sid="377" ssid="220">We start from the top of this list and work our way downwards until we find a word that fails either of the following tests: Once a word fails one of the above tests, we are guaranteed that all subsequent words in the list (with lower local frequencies) will also fail the same test.</S>
    <S sid="378" ssid="221">By applying these two tests and removing all closed-class words from the list, we greatly reduce the number of words that must be considered.</S>
    <S sid="379" ssid="222">In practice, about 90-98% of the words in the list fail to meet the two tests above, so we dramatically reduce our search space without having to perform any relatively expensive operations.</S>
    <S sid="380" ssid="223">For the remaining words in the list, we need to compute their Dice coefficient value so as to select the best-ranking one-word translation of the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="381" ssid="224">The first of the above tests is rather obviously valid and easy to apply.</S>
    <S sid="382" ssid="225">For the second test, we compute an upper bound for the Dice coefficient between the word under consideration and the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="383" ssid="226">Let X and Y stand for the source collocation and the French word under consideration, respectively, at some step of the loop through the word list.</S>
    <S sid="384" ssid="227">At this point, we know the global frequency of the source collocation (fx) and the local frequency of the candidate translation word (fxy), but not the global frequency of the candidate word (fy).</S>
    <S sid="385" ssid="228">We need all these three quantities to compute the Dice coefficient, but while fx is computed once for all Y, and it is very efficient to compute fx y at the same time as the set of sentences matching X is identified, it is more costly to find fy even if a special access structure is maintained.</S>
    <S sid="386" ssid="229">So, we first check whether there is any possibility that this word correlates with the source collocation highly enough to pass the Dice threshold by assuming temporarily that the word does not appear at all outside the sentences matching the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="387" ssid="230">By setting fy=fxy, we can efficiently compute the Dice coefficient between X and Y under this assumption: Of course, this assumption most likely won't be true.</S>
    <S sid="388" ssid="231">But since we know that fxY &lt; fy, it follows that Dicea(X,Y) is never less than the true value of the Dice coefficient between X and Y.1&#176; Comparing Dicea(X,Y) with the Dice threshold Td will only filter out words that are guaranteed not to have a high enough Dice coefficient value independently of their overall frequency fy; thus, this is the most efficient process for this task that also guarantees correctness.'</S>
    <S sid="389" ssid="232">Another possible implementation involves representing the words as integers using hashing.</S>
    <S sid="390" ssid="233">Then it would be possible to compute fy and the Dice coefficient in linear time.</S>
    <S sid="391" ssid="234">Our method, in comparison, takes 0(n log n) time to sort n candidates by their local frequency fxy, but it retrieves the frequency fy and computes the Dice coefficient for a much smaller percentage of them.</S>
    <S sid="392" ssid="235">In this section, we analyze the generative capacity of our algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="393" ssid="236">In particular, we compare it to the obvious method of exhaustively generating and testing all possible groups of k words, with k varying from 1 to some maximum length of the translation in.</S>
    <S sid="394" ssid="237">Our concern is whether our algorithm will actually generate all valid translations&#8212; those with final Dice coefficient above the threshold&#8212;while it is clear that the exhaustive algorithm would.'</S>
    <S sid="395" ssid="238">Does the filtering process we use sometimes cause our algorithm to omit a valid translation?</S>
    <S sid="396" ssid="239">In other words, is there a possibility that a group of words has high similarity with the source collocation (above the threshold) and at the same time one or more of its subgroups have similarity below the threshold?</S>
    <S sid="397" ssid="240">In the worst case, as we show below, the answer to this question is affirmative.</S>
    <S sid="398" ssid="241">However, if only very few translations are missed in practice, the algorithm is indeed a good choice.</S>
    <S sid="399" ssid="242">In this section, we first show why the filtering we use is necessary and how it can miss valid translations, and then present the results of Monte Carlo simulation experiments (Rubenstein 1981) showing that with appropriate selection of the threshold, the algorithm misses very few translations, that this rate of failure can be reduced even more by using different thresholds at each level, and that the missed translations are in general the less interesting ones, so that the rejection of some of the valid (according to the Dice coefficient) translations most likely leads to an increase of Champollion's performance.</S>
    <S sid="400" ssid="243">The exhaustive algorithm described above suffers from two disadvantages: First, the only guaranteed correct value of m is the number of words Q in the target language that have been selected in Stage 1 as viable candidate translations and pass the Dice coefficient test as single words (see Section 5.1).</S>
    <S sid="401" ssid="244">This set of words typically contains 100-120 words, so enumerating all its subsets is impractical.</S>
    <S sid="402" ssid="245">But even if we artificially impose some lower ceiling for m&#8212;say three times the length of the source language collocation&#8212;we run into the second, and more severe, problem of the exhaustive approach.</S>
    <S sid="403" ssid="246">We need to consider candidate translations.</S>
    <S sid="404" ssid="247">With typical values of Q = 110 and m = 10, which we observed in our corpus, the above formula evaluates to 5.2.</S>
    <S sid="405" ssid="248">1013, or more than 50 trillion candidate translations.</S>
    <S sid="406" ssid="249">Clearly, we need to reduce this number to a more practical value.</S>
    <S sid="407" ssid="250">Our algorithm achieves this reduction by filtering out groups of words not having a high similarity with the source collocation, assuming that such groups will not be part of the translation.</S>
    <S sid="408" ssid="251">Let ri (i &gt; 2) be the fraction of proposed translations with i words which pass the threshold Td.</S>
    <S sid="409" ssid="252">Let 131 be the number of translations with i words that are examined by Champollion, and Si the number of these translations that actually survive the thresholds and will be used to generate the candidate translations with i +1 words.</S>
    <S sid="410" ssid="253">Clearly, Si =-- P1 Q, P2 = (?</S>
    <S sid="411" ssid="254">), and Si = ri &#8226; P, for i &gt; 2.</S>
    <S sid="412" ssid="255">During the generation of the candidate translations of length i + 1 (i &gt; 2), each of the Si translations of length i can combine with Q - i single words that are sufficiently correlated with the source language collocation, generating Q - i possible translations of length i +1, since Champollion does not consider translations that include repeated words.</S>
    <S sid="413" ssid="256">However, there are up to i + 1 different ways that the same set of i +1 words can be generated in this manner; for example, (ABC) can be generated by adding C to (AB), adding B to (AC), or adding A to (BC).</S>
    <S sid="414" ssid="257">When the set of translations of length i has been filtered, it is possible that not all of the i + 1 ways to generate a given translation of length i + 1 are available.</S>
    <S sid="415" ssid="258">In general, we have and with a similar derivation, for the upper bound (i &gt; 3), .Pi &lt; Hi) 2(Q 01 The sums of the bounds on the values Pi for i = 3 to m, plus the value P1 + P2 = Q + (?</S>
    <S sid="416" ssid="259">), give upper and lower bounds on the total number of candidate translations generated and examined by Champollion.</S>
    <S sid="417" ssid="260">When the r,'s are high, the actual number of candidate translations will be close to the lower bound.</S>
    <S sid="418" ssid="261">On the other hand, low values for the ri's (i.e., a low threshold Td) will result in the actual number of candidate translations being close to the upper bound.</S>
    <S sid="419" ssid="262">To estimate the average number of candidate translations examined, we make the simplifying assumption that the decisions to reject each candidate translation with i words are made independently with constant probability ri.</S>
    <S sid="420" ssid="263">Under these assumptions, the probability of generating a particular candidate translation with i words is the same for all translations with length i; the same applies to the probability Ai that a translation with i words is included in the set of translations of length i that will generate the candidate translations of length i + 1.</S>
    <S sid="421" ssid="264">Clearly, A1 =- yi = = 1 and Ai = rai for i &gt; 2.</S>
    <S sid="422" ssid="265">For a particular translation with i &gt; 3 words to be generated, at least one of its i subsets with i &#8212; 1 words must have survived the threshold.</S>
    <S sid="423" ssid="266">With our assumptions, we have From this recurrence equation and the boundary conditions given above we can compute the values of and A, for all i.</S>
    <S sid="424" ssid="267">Then the expected (average) number of candidate translations with i &gt; 3 words examined by Champollion will be and the sum of these terms for i = 3 to m, plus the terms Q and (?</S>
    <S sid="425" ssid="268">), gives the total complexity of our algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="426" ssid="269">In Table 6 we show the number of candidate translations examined by the exhaustive algorithm and the corresponding best-, worst-, and average-case behavior of Champollion for several values of Q and m, using empirical estimates of the ri's.</S>
    <S sid="427" ssid="270">We showed above that filtering is necessary to bring the number of proposed translations down to manageable levels.</S>
    <S sid="428" ssid="271">For any corpus of reasonable size, we can find cases where a valid translation is missed because a part of it does not pass the threshold.</S>
    <S sid="429" ssid="272">Let N be the size of the corpus in terms of matched sentences.</S>
    <S sid="430" ssid="273">Separate the N sentences into eight categories, depending on whether each of the source collocation (X) and the partial translations (i.e., A and B) appear in it.</S>
    <S sid="431" ssid="274">Let the counts of these sentences be 11ABx, nAB)--c, &#8226;, nag, where a bar indicates that the corresponding term is absent.</S>
    <S sid="432" ssid="275">We can then find values of the n. 's that cause the algorithm to miss a valid translation as long as the corpus contains a modest number of sentences.</S>
    <S sid="433" ssid="276">This happens when one or more of the parts of the final translation appear frequently in the corpus but not together with the other parts or the source collocation.</S>
    <S sid="434" ssid="277">This phenomenon occurs even if we are allowed to vary the Dice thresholds at each stage of the algorithm.</S>
    <S sid="435" ssid="278">With our current constant Dice threshold Td = 0.1, we may miss a valid translation as long as the corpus contains at least 20 sentences.</S>
    <S sid="436" ssid="279">While our algorithm will necessarily miss some valid translations, this is a worst case scenario.</S>
    <S sid="437" ssid="280">To study the average-case behavior of our algorithm, we simulated its performance with randomly selected points with integer non-negative coordinates where No is the number of &amp;quot;interesting&amp;quot; sentences in the corpus for the translation under consideration, that is, the number of sentences that contain at least one of X, A, or B.13 Sampling from this six-dimensional polytope in seven-dimensional space is not easy.</S>
    <S sid="438" ssid="281">We accomplish it by constructing a mapping from the uniform distribution to each allowed value for the n...'s, using combinatorial methods.</S>
    <S sid="439" ssid="282">For example, for No = 50, there are 3,478,761 different points with 11ABx = 0 but only one with nABX = 50.</S>
    <S sid="440" ssid="283">Using the above method, we sampled 20,000 points for each of several values for No (N0 = 50, 100, 500, and 1000).</S>
    <S sid="441" ssid="284">The results of the simulation were very similar for the different values of No, with no apparent pattern emerging as No increased.</S>
    <S sid="442" ssid="285">Therefore, in the following we give averages over the values of No tried.</S>
    <S sid="443" ssid="286">We first measured the percentage of missed valid translations when either A or B, or both, do not pass the threshold but AB should, for different values of the threshold parameter (solid line in Figure 3).</S>
    <S sid="444" ssid="287">We observed that for low values of the threshold, less than 1% of the valid translations are missed; for example, for the threshold value of 0.10 we currently use, the error rate is 0.74%.</S>
    <S sid="445" ssid="288">However, as the threshold increases, the rate of failure can become unacceptable.</S>
    <S sid="446" ssid="289">A higher value for the threshold has two advantages: First, it offers higher selectivity, allowing fewer false positives (proposed translations that are not considered 13 Note that the number of sentences that do not contain any of X, A, or B does not enter any of the Dice coefficients computed by Champollion and consequently does not affect the algorithm's decisions.</S>
    <S sid="447" ssid="290">As discussed in Section 4, this gives a definite advantage to the Dice method over other measures of similarity.</S>
    <S sid="448" ssid="291">Failure rate of the translation algorithm with constant and increasing thresholds.</S>
    <S sid="449" ssid="292">The case a = 1 (solid line) represents the basic algorithm with no threshold changes. accurate by the human judges).</S>
    <S sid="450" ssid="293">Second, it speeds up the execution of the algorithm, as all fractions r!</S>
    <S sid="451" ssid="294">'s decrease and the overall number of candidate translations is reduced.</S>
    <S sid="452" ssid="295">However, as Figure 3 shows, high values of the threshold parameter cause the algorithm to miss a significant percentage of valid translations.</S>
    <S sid="453" ssid="296">Intuitively, we expect this problem to be alleviated if a higher threshold value is used for the final admittance of a translation, but a lower threshold is used internally when the subparts of the translation are considered.</S>
    <S sid="454" ssid="297">Our second simulation experiment tested this expectation for various values of the final threshold using a lower initial threshold equal to a constant a &lt; 1 times the final threshold.</S>
    <S sid="455" ssid="298">The results are represented by the remaining curves of Figure 3.</S>
    <S sid="456" ssid="299">Surprisingly, we found that with moderate values of a (close to 1) this method gives a very low failure rate even for high final threshold values, and is preferable to using a constant but lower threshold just to reduce the failure rate.</S>
    <S sid="457" ssid="300">For example, running the algorithm at an initial threshold of 0.3 and a final threshold of 0.6 gives a failure rate of 0.45%, much less than the failure rate of 6.59% which corresponds to a constant threshold of 0.3 for both stages.'</S>
    <S sid="458" ssid="301">The above analyses show that the algorithm fails quite rarely when the threshold is low, and its performance can be improved with a sequence of increasing thresholds.</S>
    <S sid="459" ssid="302">We also studied cases where the algorithm does fail.</S>
    <S sid="460" ssid="303">For this purpose, we stratified 14 The curves in Figure 3 become noticeably less smooth for values of the final threshold that are greater than 0.8.</S>
    <S sid="461" ssid="304">This happens for all settings of a in Figure 3.</S>
    <S sid="462" ssid="305">This apparently different behavior for high threshold values can be traced to sampling issues.</S>
    <S sid="463" ssid="306">Since few of the 20,000 points in each sample meet the criterion of having Dice(AB, X) greater or equal to the threshold for high final threshold values, the estimate of the percentage of failures is more susceptible to random variation in such cases.</S>
    <S sid="464" ssid="307">Furthermore, since the same sample (for a given No) is used for all values of a, any such random variation due to small sample size will be replicated in all curves of Figure 3. our samples into five groups, based on the Dice coefficient between the two parts A and B (which does not directly enter the computations of the algorithm).</S>
    <S sid="465" ssid="308">Figure 4 shows the failure rate for the groups of low (0 to 0.2), middle (0.4 to 0.6), and high (0.8 to 1) Dice(A,B) values, using the same threshold at both levels.</S>
    <S sid="466" ssid="309">We observe that the algorithm tends to fail much less frequently when the two parts of the final translation are strongly related.</S>
    <S sid="467" ssid="310">But this is desirable behavior, since a strong correlation between the two subparts of the word group indicates that it is indeed a collocation in the target language.</S>
    <S sid="468" ssid="311">Therefore, failures of the algorithm act, to some extent, as an (unintentional) filter, rejecting uninteresting translations that would otherwise have been accepted by the exhaustive method.</S>
    <S sid="469" ssid="312">Table 7 shows sample results from the simulation experiments, summarizing Figures 3 and 4 for several representative cases.</S>
    <S sid="470" ssid="313">The first column gives the threshold used at the second level, while the second through fourth columns show failure rates for various values of a.</S>
    <S sid="471" ssid="314">For example, the second column shows failure rates when the same threshold is used for both levels.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="7." number="6">
    <S sid="472" ssid="1">We evaluated Champollion in several separate trials, varying the collocations provided as input and the database corpora used as reference.</S>
    <S sid="473" ssid="2">We used three different sets of collocations as input, each taken from a different year of the English half of the Hansards corpus!'</S>
    <S sid="474" ssid="3">We tested these collocations on database corpora of varying size 15 We limited the evaluation of Champollion to three types of collocations, Noun-Noun (Chamber of Commerce), Verb-Noun (express hope), and Adjective-Noun (annual deficit) obtained using the first two stages of XTRACT. and year, taken from the aligned Hansards.</S>
    <S sid="475" ssid="4">Table 8 illustrates the range of translations which Champollion produces.</S>
    <S sid="476" ssid="5">Flexible collocations are shown with ellipsis points (... ) indicating where additional, variable words could appear.</S>
    <S sid="477" ssid="6">These examples show cases where a two word collocation is translated as one word (e.g., health insurance), a two word collocation is translated as three words (e.g., employment equity), and how words can be inverted in the translation (e.g., additional costs).</S>
    <S sid="478" ssid="7">In this section, we discuss the design of the separate tests and our evaluation methodology, and present the results of our evaluation.</S>
    <S sid="479" ssid="8">We carried out three tests with Champollion using two database corpora and three sets of source collocations.</S>
    <S sid="480" ssid="9">The first database corpus (DB1) consists of 8 months of Hansards aligned data taken from 1986 (16 megabytes, 3.5 million words) and the second database corpus (DB2) consists of all of the 1986 and 1987 transcripts of the Canadian Parliament (a total of approximately 45 megabytes and 8.5 million words).</S>
    <S sid="481" ssid="10">For the first corpus (DB1), we ran XTRACT and obtained a set of approximately 3,000 collocations from which we randomly selected a subset of 300 for manual evaluation purposes.</S>
    <S sid="482" ssid="11">The 300 collocations were selected from among the collocations of mid-range frequency&#8212;collocations appearing more than 10 times in the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="483" ssid="12">We call this first set of source collocations Cl.</S>
    <S sid="484" ssid="13">The second set (C2) is a set of 300 collocations similarly selected from the set of approximately 5,000 collocations identified by XTRACT on all data from 1987.</S>
    <S sid="485" ssid="14">The third set of collocations (C3) consists of 300 collocations selected from the set of approximately 5,000 collocations identified by XTRACT on all data from 1988.</S>
    <S sid="486" ssid="15">We used DB1 with both Cl (experiment 1) and C2 (experiment 2) and we used DB2 with C3 (experiment 3).</S>
    <S sid="487" ssid="16">We asked three fluent bilingual speakers to evaluate the results for the different experiments.</S>
    <S sid="488" ssid="17">The evaluators first examined the source collocation, validating that it indeed was a word group exhibiting semantic coherence.</S>
    <S sid="489" ssid="18">Source collocations that seemed incorrect (i.e., mistakenly identified as collocations by XTRACT) were removed from further consideration.</S>
    <S sid="490" ssid="19">The evaluators then classified the translations of the remaining collocations as either correct or incorrect.</S>
    <S sid="491" ssid="20">In this way, we decoupled the evaluation of Champollion from the errors made by XTRACT.</S>
    <S sid="492" ssid="21">It is clear that our classification scheme is not perfect because some cases are difficult to judge.</S>
    <S sid="493" ssid="22">The judges were not especially familiar with the institutionalized differences between Canadian French and continental French (which is the form of French they speak).</S>
    <S sid="494" ssid="23">For example, without knowledge of Canadian French, it is difficult to judge if the translation of affirmative action is action positive since this term is not used in other forms of French.</S>
    <S sid="495" ssid="24">One of the biggest problems for the evaluators was scoring translations of collocations with prepositions and articles.</S>
    <S sid="496" ssid="25">Champollion does not translate closed-class words such as prepositions and articles.</S>
    <S sid="497" ssid="26">Their frequency is so high in comparison to openclass words that including them in the candidate translations causes problems with the correlation metric.</S>
    <S sid="498" ssid="27">Evaluators generally counted a translation as incorrect if it did not contain a preposition or article when it should have.</S>
    <S sid="499" ssid="28">There is one exception to this general rule: When the translation should have included one closed-class word, it was obvious what that word should be, it occurred in one empty slot in the phrase, and Champollion produced a rigid collocation with an empty slot at that position; and with the correct open-class words, they judged the translation correct.</S>
    <S sid="500" ssid="29">It is exactly in these cases that the closed-class word could easily be filled in when examining samples in the corpus to determine word ordering.</S>
    <S sid="501" ssid="30">Since the collocation is rigid, the same preposition or article occurs in most cases, so it could be extracted from the samples along with word ordering.</S>
    <S sid="502" ssid="31">For example, when judging the translation of assistance program into programme X aide the judges knew that the missing word (X) was d' even without looking at the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="503" ssid="32">In Section 9, we describe a later version of Champollion in which we added the capability to identify these types of closed-class words during the last stage.</S>
    <S sid="504" ssid="33">The results of the evaluation experiments are given in Table 9.</S>
    <S sid="505" ssid="34">The first column describes the experiment, the second column gives the percentage of XTRACT errors, and the next two columns give the percentages of incorrect and correct translations of source collocations in comparison to the total number of collocations.</S>
    <S sid="506" ssid="35">Since our previous work shows that XTRACT has a rate of accuracy of 80% (Smadja 1991b), it is reasonable to expect a certain number of errors in the input to Champollion, but these should not contribute to the evaluation of Champollion.</S>
    <S sid="507" ssid="36">Consequently, we have included in the last column of the table the percentage of correct translations produced by Champollion in comparison to the total number of valid collocations supplied to it; namely, the percentage of Champ&#176;llion's correct translations if XTRACT'S errors are filtered from the input.</S>
    <S sid="508" ssid="37">This quantity is equal to the ratio of the fourth column over the sum of the third and fourth columns.'</S>
    <S sid="509" ssid="38">The accuracy figures shown in Table 9 are computed by averaging the scores of the three individual judges.</S>
    <S sid="510" ssid="39">However, we noted that the scores of the individual evaluators never varied by more than 2%, thus showing high agreement between the judges.'</S>
    <S sid="511" ssid="40">Such results indicate that, in general, there is a single correct answer in each case, verifying the hypothesis of a unique translation per collocation independently of context, which we postulated in Section 4.</S>
    <S sid="512" ssid="41">They also indicate that it is generally easy for the evaluators to identify this unique correct answer.</S>
    <S sid="513" ssid="42">When there is not a single correct answer, or when it is not easy for the evaluators to identify the correct answer, it is prudent to guard against the introduction of (usually pro-system) bias by asking the evaluators to produce their answers independently of the system's output, as we have argued elsewhere (Hatzivassiloglou and McKeown 1993; Hatzivassiloglou in press).</S>
    <S sid="514" ssid="43">However, for the problem at hand, the uniqueness and accessibility of the correct answer greatly alleviates' the danger of introducing bias by letting the evaluators grade the translations produced by Champollion.</S>
    <S sid="515" ssid="44">Since the latter method makes more efficient use of the judges, we decided to adopt it for our evaluation.</S>
    <S sid="516" ssid="45">Among the three experiments described above, our best results are obtained when the database corpus is also used as the corpus from which XTRACT identifies the source language collocations (experiment Cl /DB1).</S>
    <S sid="517" ssid="46">In this case, not counting XTRACT errors, accuracy is rated at 78%.</S>
    <S sid="518" ssid="47">It should be noted that the thresholds used by Champollion were determined by experimenting on a separate data set.</S>
    <S sid="519" ssid="48">Since determining the thresholds is the only training required for our statistical method, using the same corpus as both the database and the source of input collocations is not a case of testing on the training data.</S>
    <S sid="520" ssid="49">The second experiment yielded the lowest results because many input collocations simply did not appear often enough in the database corpus.</S>
    <S sid="521" ssid="50">However, we suspected that this could be corrected by using a larger database corpus!'</S>
    <S sid="522" ssid="51">Thus, for our third experiment, we used DB2, which contained two years of the Hansards (1986 and 1987), and drew our input collocations from yet a different year (1988).</S>
    <S sid="523" ssid="52">Evaluation on this third experiment raised the accuracy to nearly as high as the first experiment, yielding 74%.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="8." number="7">
    <S sid="524" ssid="1">A bilingual lexicon of collocations has a variety of potential uses.</S>
    <S sid="525" ssid="2">The most obvious are machine translation and machine-assisted human translation, but other multilingual applications, including information retrieval, summarization, and computational lexicography, also require access to bilingual lexicons.</S>
    <S sid="526" ssid="3">While some researchers are attempting machine translation through purely statistical techniques, the more common approach is to use some hybrid of interlingual and transfer techniques.</S>
    <S sid="527" ssid="4">These symbolic machine translation systems must have access to a bilingual lexicon and the ability to construct one semi-automatically would ease the development of such systems.</S>
    <S sid="528" ssid="5">Champollion is particularly promising for this purpose for two reasons.</S>
    <S sid="529" ssid="6">First, it constructs translations for multiword collocations.</S>
    <S sid="530" ssid="7">Collocations are known to be opaque; that is, their meaning often derives from the combination of the words and not from the meaning of the individual words themselves.</S>
    <S sid="531" ssid="8">As a result, translation of collocations cannot be done on a word-by-word basis, and some representation of collocations in both languages is needed if the system is to translate fluently.</S>
    <S sid="532" ssid="9">Second, collocations are domain dependent.</S>
    <S sid="533" ssid="10">Particularly in technical domains, the collocations differ from those in general use.</S>
    <S sid="534" ssid="11">Accordingly, the ability to automatically discover collocations for a given domain by using a new corpus as input to Champollion would ease the work required to transfer an MT system to a new domain.</S>
    <S sid="535" ssid="12">Multilingual systems are now being developed in addition to pure machine translation systems.</S>
    <S sid="536" ssid="13">These systems also need access to bilingual phrases.</S>
    <S sid="537" ssid="14">We are currently developing a multilingual summarization system, in which we will use the results from Champollion.</S>
    <S sid="538" ssid="15">An early version of this system (McKeown and Radev 1995) produces short summaries of multiple news articles covering the same event using as input the templates produced by information extraction systems developed under the ARPA message understanding program.</S>
    <S sid="539" ssid="16">Since some information extraction systems, such as General Electric's NLToolset (Jacobs and Rau 1990), already produce similar representations for Japanese and English news articles, the addition of an English summary generator will automatically allow for English summarization of Japanese.</S>
    <S sid="540" ssid="17">In addition, we are planning to add a second language for the summaries.</S>
    <S sid="541" ssid="18">While the output is not a direct translation of input articles, collocations that appear frequently in the news articles will also appear in summaries.</S>
    <S sid="542" ssid="19">Thus, a list of bilingual collocations would be useful for the summarization process.</S>
    <S sid="543" ssid="20">Information retrieval is another prospective application.</S>
    <S sid="544" ssid="21">As shown in Maarek and Smadja (1989) and more recently in Broglio et al. (1995), the precision of information retrieval systems can be improved through the use of collocations in addition to the more traditional single word indexing units.</S>
    <S sid="545" ssid="22">A collocation gives the context in which a given word was used, which will help retrieve documents using the word with the same sense and thus improve precision.</S>
    <S sid="546" ssid="23">The well-known New Mexico example in information retrieval describes an oft-encountered problem when single word searches are employed: searching for new and Mexico independently will retrieve a multitude of documents that do not relate to New Mexico.</S>
    <S sid="547" ssid="24">Automatically identifying and explicitly using collocations such as New Mexico at search or indexing time can help solve this problem.</S>
    <S sid="548" ssid="25">We have licensed XTRACT to several sites that are using it to improve the accuracy of their retrieval or text categorization systems.</S>
    <S sid="549" ssid="26">A bilingual list of collocations could be used for the development of a multilingual information retrieval system.</S>
    <S sid="550" ssid="27">In cases where the database of texts includes documents written in multiple languages, the search query need only be expressed in one language.</S>
    <S sid="551" ssid="28">The bilingual collocations could be used to translate the query (particularly given that it may consist of collocations in addition to single words) from the input language to other languages in the database.</S>
    <S sid="552" ssid="29">Another potential application, as demonstrated by Dagan and Church (1994), is machine-aided human translation.</S>
    <S sid="553" ssid="30">For this scenario, when a translator begins work on a collocation inside a translation editor, the translation produced by Champollion could be provided as a prompt giving the translator the opportunity to approve it.</S>
    <S sid="554" ssid="31">In such cases, it may be useful to provide the top several translations produced by Champollion allowing the translator to choose the best, as Dagan and Church do.</S>
    <S sid="555" ssid="32">Finally, Champollion could also be used for computer-assisted lexicography.</S>
    <S sid="556" ssid="33">Since its output includes the translation of 1 to n word phrases, Champollion could be used to automatically translate lexicons.</S>
    <S sid="557" ssid="34">While it could not translate sentences that are often used in dictionaries as examples, it could be used for translation of both individual words and phrases.</S>
    <S sid="558" ssid="35">In this way, a list of translated words could be produced automatically from a monolingual dictionary and filtered by a lexicographer.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="9." number="8">
    <S sid="559" ssid="1">Champollion is one of the first attempts at translating lexical constructions using statistical techniques and our work has several limitations, which will be addressed in future work.</S>
    <S sid="560" ssid="2">In this section we describe some of them and we give possible directions for future research.</S>
    <S sid="561" ssid="3">Translating closed class words.</S>
    <S sid="562" ssid="4">In the experiments described in this paper, Champollion produced only partial collocations in the target language, because we eliminated closed-class words from our indices.</S>
    <S sid="563" ssid="5">There are two reasons for eliminating such words.</S>
    <S sid="564" ssid="6">First, they are very frequent and appear in almost any context, so that using them would blur our statistics.</S>
    <S sid="565" ssid="7">The second reason is one of time and space efficiency: since these words appear in many sentences in the corpus database, it is economical to remove them from the indices.</S>
    <S sid="566" ssid="8">However, this causes Champollion to produce only partial collocations, for example, to cause havoc gets translated as semer[0], desarrois[2].</S>
    <S sid="567" ssid="9">The position numbers indicate that a word is missing between the two French words.</S>
    <S sid="568" ssid="10">This word is the article le, and the full collocation is semer le desarrois.</S>
    <S sid="569" ssid="11">We implemented an extension that checks the positions around the words of a rigid collocation.&amp;quot; Note that for flexible collocations the words can occur in any order, separated by any number of words, and therefore it is difficult to check whether the same close class word is consistently used.</S>
    <S sid="570" ssid="12">Our extension checks one word to the left and to the right of the collocation, plus any gaps between words.</S>
    <S sid="571" ssid="13">If the same preposition or article is found to occur in the same position in 90% of the sentences in which the rigid collocation occurs, it is added to the output.</S>
    <S sid="572" ssid="14">Note that if Champollion were to be used as part of machine-assisted human translation, another option would be to produce a ranked list of several prepositions or articles that are used in the corpus and let the translator choose the best option.</S>
    <S sid="573" ssid="15">This extension improves the fluency of the translations tremendously.</S>
    <S sid="574" ssid="16">For example, employment equity is translated as equite en matiere d' emploi with prepositions in place of the empty slots shown in Table 8 on page 27.</S>
    <S sid="575" ssid="17">Table 10 shows a variety of translations produced by this extension.</S>
    <S sid="576" ssid="18">While we have not yet completed a full evaluation of these results, preliminary work using the evaluation of only one judge suggests that our results improve substantially.</S>
    <S sid="577" ssid="19">Tools for the target language.</S>
    <S sid="578" ssid="20">Tools in French, such as a morphological analyzer, a tagger, a list of acronyms, a robust parser, and various lists of tagged words, would be most helpful and would allow us to improve our results.</S>
    <S sid="579" ssid="21">For example, a tagger for French would allow us to run XTRACT on the French part of the corpus, and thus to translate from either French or English as input.</S>
    <S sid="580" ssid="22">In addition, running XTRACT on the French part of the corpus would allow for independent confirmation of the proposed translations, which should be French collocations.</S>
    <S sid="581" ssid="23">Similarly, a morphological analyzer would allow us to produce richer results, since several forms of the same word would be conflated, increasing both the expected and the actual frequencies of the co-occurrence events; this has been found empirically to have a positive effect in overall performance in other problems (Hatzivassiloglou in press).</S>
    <S sid="582" ssid="24">Note that ignoring inflectional distinctions can sometimes have a detrimental effect if only particular forms of a word participate in a given collocation.</S>
    <S sid="583" ssid="25">Consequently, it might be beneficial to take into account both the distribution of the base form and the differences between the distributions of the various inflected forms.</S>
    <S sid="584" ssid="26">In the current implementation of Champollion, we were restricted to using tools for only one of the two languages, since at the time of implementation tools for French were not readily available.</S>
    <S sid="585" ssid="27">However, from the above discussion it is clear that certain tools would improve the system's performance.</S>
    <S sid="586" ssid="28">Separating corpus-dependent translations from general ones.</S>
    <S sid="587" ssid="29">Champollion identifies translations for the source collocations using the aligned corpora database as its entire knowledge of the two languages.</S>
    <S sid="588" ssid="30">Consequently, sometimes the results are specific to the domain and seem peculiar when viewed in a more general context.</S>
    <S sid="589" ssid="31">For example, we have already mentioned that Mr. Speaker was translated as Monsieur le Pr&#233;sident, which is obviously only valid for this domain.</S>
    <S sid="590" ssid="32">Canadian family is another example; it is often translated as famille (the Canadian qualifier is dropped in the French version).</S>
    <S sid="591" ssid="33">This is an important feature of the system, since in this way the sublanguage of the domain is employed for the translation.</S>
    <S sid="592" ssid="34">However, many of the collocations that Champollion identifies are general, domain-independent ones.</S>
    <S sid="593" ssid="35">Champollion cannot make any distinction between domain-specific and general collocations.</S>
    <S sid="594" ssid="36">What is clearly needed is a way to determine the generality of each produced translation, as many translations found by Champollion are of general use and could be directly applied to other domains.</S>
    <S sid="595" ssid="37">This may be possible by intersecting the output of Champollion on corpora from many different domains.</S>
    <S sid="596" ssid="38">Handling low frequency collocations.</S>
    <S sid="597" ssid="39">The statistics we used do not produce good results when the frequencies are low.</S>
    <S sid="598" ssid="40">This shows up clearly when our evaluation results on the first two experiments are compared.</S>
    <S sid="599" ssid="41">Running the collocation set C2 over the database DB1 produced our worst results, and this can be attributed to the low frequency in DBI of many collocations in C2.</S>
    <S sid="600" ssid="42">Recall that C2 was extracted from a different (and larger) corpus from DBI.</S>
    <S sid="601" ssid="43">This problem is due not only to the frequencies of the source collocations or of the words involved but also to the frequencies of their &amp;quot;official&amp;quot; translations.</S>
    <S sid="602" ssid="44">Indeed, while most collocations exhibit unique senses in a given domain, sometimes a source collocation appearing multiple times in the corpus is not consistently translated into the same target collocation in the database.</S>
    <S sid="603" ssid="45">This sampling problem, which generally affects all statistical approaches, was not addressed in the paper.</S>
    <S sid="604" ssid="46">We reduced the effects of low frequencies by purposefully limiting ourselves to source collocations of frequencies higher than 10, containing individual words with frequencies higher than 15.</S>
    <S sid="605" ssid="47">Analysis of the effects of our thresholds.</S>
    <S sid="606" ssid="48">Various thresholds are used in Champollion's algorithm to reduce the search space.</S>
    <S sid="607" ssid="49">A threshold too low would significantly slow down the search as, according to Zipf's law (Zipf 1949), the number of terms occurring n times in a general English corpus is a decreasing function of n2.</S>
    <S sid="608" ssid="50">Unfortunately, sometimes this filtering step causes Champollion to miss a valid translation.</S>
    <S sid="609" ssid="51">For example, one of the incorrect translations made by Champollion is that important factor was translated into facteur (factor) alone instead of the proper translation facteur important.</S>
    <S sid="610" ssid="52">The error is due to the fact that the French word important did not pass the first step of the algorithm as its Dice coefficient with important factor was too low.</S>
    <S sid="611" ssid="53">Important occurs a total of 858 times in the French part of the corpus and only 8 times in the right context, whereas a minimum of 10 appearances is required to pass this step.</S>
    <S sid="612" ssid="54">Although the theoretical analysis and simulation experiments of Section 6.2 show that such cases of missing the correct translation are rare, more work needs to be done in quantifying this phenomenon.</S>
    <S sid="613" ssid="55">In particular, experiments with actual corpus data should supplement the theoretical results (based on uniform distributions).</S>
    <S sid="614" ssid="56">Furthermore, more experimentation with the values of the thresholds needs to be done, to locate the optimum trade-off point between efficiency and accuracy.</S>
    <S sid="615" ssid="57">An additional direction for future experiments is to vary the thresholds (and especially the frequency threshold Tf) according to the size of the database corpus and the frequency of the collocation being translated.</S>
    <S sid="616" ssid="58">Incorporating the length of the translation into the score.</S>
    <S sid="617" ssid="59">Currently our scoring method only uses the lengths of candidate translations to break a tie in the similarity measure.</S>
    <S sid="618" ssid="60">It seems, however, that longer translations should get a &amp;quot;bonus.&amp;quot; For example, using our scoring technique the correlation of the collocation official languages with the French word officielles is equal to 0.94 and the correlation with the French collocation langues officielles is 0.95.</S>
    <S sid="619" ssid="61">Our scoring only uses the relative frequencies of the events without taking into account that some of these events are composed of multiple single events.</S>
    <S sid="620" ssid="62">We plan to refine our scoring method so that the length (number of words involved) of the events is taken into account.</S>
    <S sid="621" ssid="63">Using nonparallel corpora.</S>
    <S sid="622" ssid="64">Champollion requires an aligned bilingual corpus as input.</S>
    <S sid="623" ssid="65">However, finding bilingual corpora can be problematic in some domains.</S>
    <S sid="624" ssid="66">Although organizations such as the United Nations, the European Community, and governments of countries with several official languages are big producers, such corpora are still difficult to obtain for research purposes.</S>
    <S sid="625" ssid="67">While aligned bilingual corpora will become more available in the future, it would be helpful if we could relax the constraint for aligned data.</S>
    <S sid="626" ssid="68">Bilingual corpora in the same domain, which are not necessarily translations of each other, are more easily available.</S>
    <S sid="627" ssid="69">For example, news agencies such as the Associated Press and Reuters publish in several languages.</S>
    <S sid="628" ssid="70">News stories often relate similar facts but they are not direct translations of one another.</S>
    <S sid="629" ssid="71">Even though the stories probably use equivalent terminology, totally different techniques would be necessary to be able to use such &amp;quot;nonalignable&amp;quot; corpora as databases.</S>
    <S sid="630" ssid="72">Ultimately, such techniques would be more useful than those currently used, because they would be able to extract knowledge from noisy data.</S>
    <S sid="631" ssid="73">While this is definitely a large research problem, our research team at Columbia University has begun work in this area (Fung and McKeown 1994) that shows promise for noisy parallel corpora (in which the target corpus may contain either additional or deleted paragraphs and where the languages themselves do not involve neat sentence-by-sentence translations).</S>
    <S sid="632" ssid="74">Bilingual word correspondences extracted from nonparallel corpora with techniques such as those proposed by Fung (1995a) also look promising.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="10." number="9">
    <S sid="633" ssid="1">We have presented a method for translating collocations, implemented in Champollion.</S>
    <S sid="634" ssid="2">The ability to provide translations for collocations is important for three main reasons.</S>
    <S sid="635" ssid="3">First, because they are opaque constructions, they cannot be translated on a word-byword basis.</S>
    <S sid="636" ssid="4">Instead, translations must be provided for the phrase as a whole.</S>
    <S sid="637" ssid="5">Second, collocations are domain dependent.</S>
    <S sid="638" ssid="6">Each domain includes a variety of phrases that have specific meanings and translations that apply only in the given domain.</S>
    <S sid="639" ssid="7">Finally, a quick look at a bilingual dictionary, even for two widely studied languages such as English and French, shows that correspondences between collocations in two languages are largely unexplored.</S>
    <S sid="640" ssid="8">Thus, the ability to compile a set of translations for a new domain automatically will ultimately increase the portability of machine translation systems.</S>
    <S sid="641" ssid="9">By applying Champollion to a corpus in a new domain, translations for the domain-specific collocations can be automatically compiled and inaccurate results filtered by a native speaker of the target language.</S>
    <S sid="642" ssid="10">The output of our system is a bilingual list of collocations that can be used in a variety of multilingual applications.</S>
    <S sid="643" ssid="11">It is directly applicable to machine translation systems that use a transfer approach, since such systems rely on correspondences between words and phrases of the source and target languages.</S>
    <S sid="644" ssid="12">For interlingua systems, identification of collocations and their translations provide a means of augmenting the interlingua.</S>
    <S sid="645" ssid="13">Since such phrases cannot be translated compositionally, they indicate where concepts representing such phrases must be added to the interlingua.</S>
    <S sid="646" ssid="14">Such bilingual phrases are also useful for other multilingual tasks, including information retrieval of multilingual documents given a phrase in one language, summarization in one language of texts in another, and multilingual generation.</S>
    <S sid="647" ssid="15">Finally, we have carried out three evaluations of the system on three separate years of the Hansards corpus.</S>
    <S sid="648" ssid="16">These evaluations indicate that Champollion has a high rate of accuracy: in the best case, 78% of the French translations of valid English collocations were judged to be good.</S>
    <S sid="649" ssid="17">This is a good score in comparison with evaluations carried out on full machine translation systems.</S>
    <S sid="650" ssid="18">We conjecture that by using statistical techniques to translate a particular type of construction, known to be easily observable in language, we can achieve better results than by applying the same technique to all constructions uniformly.</S>
    <S sid="651" ssid="19">Our work is part of a paradigm of research that focuses on the development of tools using statistical analysis of text corpora.</S>
    <S sid="652" ssid="20">This line of research aims at producing tools that satisfactorily handle relatively simple tasks.</S>
    <S sid="653" ssid="21">These tools can then be used by other systems to address more complex tasks.</S>
    <S sid="654" ssid="22">For example, previous work has addressed low-level tasks such as tagging a free-style corpus with part-of-speech information (Church 1988), aligning a bilingual corpus (Gale and Church 1991b; Brown, Lai, and Mercer 1991), and producing a list of collocations (Smadja 1993).</S>
    <S sid="655" ssid="23">While each of these tools is based on simple statistics and tackles elementary tasks, we have demonstrated with our work on Champollion that by combining them, one can reach new levels of complexity in the automatic treatment of natural languages.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="Acknowledgments" number="10">
    <S sid="656" ssid="1">This work was supported jointly by the Advanced Research Projects Agency and the Office of Naval Research under grant N00014-89&#8212;J-1782, by the Office of Naval Research under grant N00014-95-1-0745, by the National Science Foundation under grant GER-90-24069, and by the New York State Science and Technology Foundation under grants NYSSTF&#8212;CAT(91)-053 and NYSSTF&#8212;CAT(94)-013.</S>
    <S sid="657" ssid="2">We wish to thank Pascale Fung and Dragomir Radev for serving as evaluators, Thanasis Tsantilas for discussions relating to the average-case complexity of Champollion, and the anonymous reviewers for providing useful comments on an earlier version of the paper.</S>
    <S sid="658" ssid="3">We also thank Ofer Wainberg for his excellent work on improving the efficiency of Champollion and for adding the preposition extension, and Ken Church and AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories for providing us with a prealigned Hansards corpus.</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
