<PAPER>
	<S sid="0">Joint Extraction Of Entities And Relations For Opinion Recognition</S><ABSTRACT>
		<S sid="1" ssid="1">We present an approach for the joint extraction of entities and relations in the con text of opinion recognition and analysis.</S>
		<S sid="2" ssid="2">We identify two types of opinion-related entities ? expressions of opinions andsources of opinions ? along with the linking relation that exists between them.</S>
		<S sid="3" ssid="3">In spired by Roth and Yih (2004), we employ an integer linear programming approach to solve the joint opinion recognition task,and show that global, constraint-based inference can significantly boost the perfor mance of both relation extraction and theextraction of opinion-related entities.</S>
		<S sid="4" ssid="4">Performance further improves when a seman tic role labeling system is incorporated.</S>
		<S sid="5" ssid="5">The resulting system achieves F-measuresof 79 and 69 for entity and relation extrac tion, respectively, improving substantially over prior results in the area.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number="1">
			<S sid="6" ssid="6">Information extraction tasks such as recognizing entities and relations have long been considered critical to many domain-specific NLP tasks (e.g. Mooney and Bunescu (2005), Prager et al (2000), White et al (2001)).</S>
			<S sid="7" ssid="7">Researchers have furthershown that opinion-oriented information extrac tion can provide analogous benefits to a variety of practical applications including product reputation tracking (Morinaga et al, 2002), opinion-oriented question answering (Stoyanov et al, 2005), and opinion-oriented summarization (e.g. Cardie et al.</S>
			<S sid="8" ssid="8">(2004), Liu et al (2005)).</S>
			<S sid="9" ssid="9">Moreover, muchprogress has been made in the area of opinion extraction: it is possible to identify sources of opin ions (i.e. the opinion holders) (e.g. Choi et al (2005) and Kim and Hovy (2005b)), to determine the polarity and strength of opinion expressions(e.g. Wilson et al (2005)), and to recognize propo sitional opinions and their sources (e.g. Bethard et al (2004)) with reasonable accuracy.</S>
			<S sid="10" ssid="10">To date,however, there has been no effort to simultane ously identify arbitrary opinion expressions, their sources, and the relations between them.</S>
			<S sid="11" ssid="11">Withoutprogress on the joint extraction of opinion entities and their relations, the capabilities of opinion based applications will remain limited.</S>
			<S sid="12" ssid="12">Fortunately, research in machine learning has produced methods for global inference and jointclassification that can help to address this defi ciency (e.g. Bunescu and Mooney (2004), Roth and Yih (2004)).</S>
			<S sid="13" ssid="13">Moreover, it has been shown thatexploiting dependencies among entities and/or re lations via global inference not only solves the joint extraction task, but often boosts performanceon the individual tasks when compared to clas sifiers that handle the tasks independently ? for semantic role labeling (e.g. Punyakanok et al (2004)), information extraction (e.g. Roth and Yih (2004)), and sequence tagging (e.g. Sutton et al (2004)).In this paper, we present a global inference ap proach (Roth and Yih, 2004) to the extractionof opinion-related entities and relations.</S>
			<S sid="14" ssid="14">In par ticular, we aim to identify two types of entities(i.e. spans of text): entities that express opin ions and entities that denote sources of opinions.More specifically, we use the term opinion expression to denote all direct expressions of subjectivity including opinions, emotions, beliefs, senti ment, etc., as well as all speech expressions that introduce subjective propositions; and use the termsource to denote the person or entity (e.g. a re 431 port) that holds the opinion.1 In addition, weaim to identify the relations between opinion ex pression entities and source entities.</S>
			<S sid="15" ssid="15">That is, for a given opinion expression Oi and source entity Sj , we determine whether the relation Li,j def= (Sj expresses Oi) obtains, i.e. whether Sj is the source of opinion expression Oi.</S>
			<S sid="16" ssid="16">We refer to this particular relation as the link relation in the rest of the paper.</S>
			<S sid="17" ssid="17">Consider, for example, the following sentences: S1.</S>
			<S sid="18" ssid="18">[Bush](1) intends(1) to curb the increase in harmful gas emissions and is counting on(1) the good will(2) of [US industrialists](2) . S2.</S>
			<S sid="19" ssid="19">By questioning(3) [the Imam](4)?s edict(4) [the Islamic Republic of Iran](3) made [the people of the world](5) understand(5)...The underlined phrases above are opinion expres sions and phrases marked with square brackets aresource entities.</S>
			<S sid="20" ssid="20">The numeric superscripts on en tities indicate link relations: a source entity andan opinion expression with the same number satisfy the link relation.</S>
			<S sid="21" ssid="21">For instance, the source en tity ?Bush?</S>
			<S sid="22" ssid="22">and the opinion expression ?intends?</S>
			<S sid="23" ssid="23">satisfy the link relation, and so do ?Bush?</S>
			<S sid="24" ssid="24">and?counting on.?</S>
			<S sid="25" ssid="25">Notice that a sentence may con tain more than one link relation, and link relations are not one-to-one mappings between sources andopinions.</S>
			<S sid="26" ssid="26">Also, the pair of entities in a link rela tion may not be the closest entities to each other, asis the case in the second sentence, between ?ques tioning?</S>
			<S sid="27" ssid="27">and ?the Islamic Republic of Iran.?</S>
			<S sid="28" ssid="28">We expect the extraction of opinion relations tobe critical for many opinion-oriented NLP applications.</S>
			<S sid="29" ssid="29">For instance, consider the following ques tion that might be given to a question-answering system: ? What is the Imam?s opinion toward the Islamic Republic of Iran?Without in-depth opinion analysis, the question answering system might mistake example S2 as relevant to the query, even though S2 exhibits the opinion of the Islamic Republic of Iran toward Imam, not the other way around.</S>
			<S sid="30" ssid="30">Inspired by Roth and Yih (2004), we model our task as global, constraint-based inference over separately trained entity and relation classifiers.</S>
			<S sid="31" ssid="31">In particular, we develop three base classifiers: two sequence-tagging classifiers for the extraction 1See Wiebe et al (2005) for additional details.</S>
			<S sid="32" ssid="32">of opinion expressions and sources, and a binary classifier to identify the link relation.</S>
			<S sid="33" ssid="33">The global inference procedure is implemented via integer linear programming (ILP) to produce an optimal and coherent extraction of entities and relations.</S>
			<S sid="34" ssid="34">Because many (60%) opinion-source relations appear as predicate-argument relations, where thepredicate is a verb, we also hypothesize that se mantic role labeling (SRL) will be very useful for our task.</S>
			<S sid="35" ssid="35">We present two baseline methods for the joint opinion-source recognition task that use a state-of-the-art SRL system (Punyakanok et al,2005), and describe two additional methods for in corporating SRL into our ILP-based system.</S>
			<S sid="36" ssid="36">Our experiments show that the global inference approach not only improves relation extractionover the base classifier, but does the same for in dividual entity extractions.</S>
			<S sid="37" ssid="37">For source extraction in particular, our system achieves an F-measure of 78.1, significantly outperforming previous results in this area (Choi et al, 2005), which obtained an F-measure of 69.4 on the same corpus.</S>
			<S sid="38" ssid="38">In addition, we achieve an F-measure of 68.9 for link relationidentification and 82.0 for opinion expression ex traction; for the latter task, our system achieves human-level performance.2</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="High-Level Approach and Related. " number="2">
			<S sid="39" ssid="1">Work Our system operates in three phases.</S>
			<S sid="40" ssid="2">Opinion and Source Entity Extraction We begin by developing two separate token-levelsequence-tagging classifiers for opinion expression extraction and source extraction, using linearchain Conditional Random Fields (CRFs) (Lafferty et al, 2001).</S>
			<S sid="41" ssid="3">The sequence-tagging classifiers are trained using only local syntactic and lexical information to extract each type of entity without knowledge of any nearby or neighboring enti ties or relations.</S>
			<S sid="42" ssid="4">We collect n-best sequences from each sequence tagger in order to boost the recall of the final system.</S>
			<S sid="43" ssid="5">Link Relation Classification We also develop a relation classifier that is trained and tested on all pairs of opinion and source entities extractedfrom the aforementioned n-best opinion expres sion and source sequences.</S>
			<S sid="44" ssid="6">The relation classifier is modeled using Markov order-0 CRFs(Lafferty 2Wiebe et al (2005) reports human annotation agreement for opinion expression as 82.0 by F1 measure.</S>
			<S sid="45" ssid="7">432et al, 2001), which are equivalent to maximum entropy models.</S>
			<S sid="46" ssid="8">It is trained using only local syntac tic information potentially useful for connecting a pair of entities, but has no knowledge of nearby or neighboring extracted entities and link relations.Integer Linear Programming Finally, we for mulate an integer linear programming problem for each sentence using the results from the previous two phases.</S>
			<S sid="47" ssid="9">In particular, we specify a number of soft and hard constraints among relations andentities that take into account the confidence val ues provided by the supporting entity and relation classifiers, and that encode a number of heuristics to ensure coherent output.</S>
			<S sid="48" ssid="10">Given these constraints,global inference via ILP finds the optimal, coherent set of opinion-source pairs by exploiting mu tual dependencies among the entities and relations.</S>
			<S sid="49" ssid="11">While good performance in entity or relation extraction can contribute to better performance ofthe final system, this is not always the case.</S>
			<S sid="50" ssid="12">Pun yakanok et al (2004) notes that, in general, it isbetter to have high recall from the classifiers in cluded in the ILP formulation.</S>
			<S sid="51" ssid="13">For this reason, it is not our goal to directly optimize the performance of our opinion and source entity extraction models or our relation classifier.</S>
			<S sid="52" ssid="14">The rest of the paper is organized as follows.Related work is outlined below.</S>
			<S sid="53" ssid="15">Section 3 de scribes the components of the first phase of oursystem, the opinion and source extraction classi fiers.</S>
			<S sid="54" ssid="16">Section 4 describes the construction of the link relation classifier for phase two.</S>
			<S sid="55" ssid="17">Section 5 describes the ILP formulation to perform global inference over the results from the previous two phases.</S>
			<S sid="56" ssid="18">Experimental results that compare our ILP approach to a number of baselines are presented inSection 6.</S>
			<S sid="57" ssid="19">Section 7 describes how SRL can be incorporated into our global inference system to fur ther improve the performance.</S>
			<S sid="58" ssid="20">Final experimental results and discussion comprise Section 8.Related Work The definition of our source expresses-opinion task is similar to that of Bethardet al (2004); however, our definition of opin ion and source entities are much more extensive, going beyond single sentences and propositional opinion expressions.</S>
			<S sid="59" ssid="21">In particular, we evaluate our approach with respect to (1) a wide variety of opinion expressions, (2) explicit and implicit3 sources, (3) multiple opinion-source link relations3Implicit sources are those that are not explicitly men tioned.</S>
			<S sid="60" ssid="22">See Section 8 for more details.</S>
			<S sid="61" ssid="23">per sentence, and (4) link relations that span morethan one sentence.</S>
			<S sid="62" ssid="24">In addition, the link relation model explicitly exploits mutual dependen cies among entities and relations, while Bethard et al (2004) does not directly capture the potential influence among entities.</S>
			<S sid="63" ssid="25">Kim and Hovy (2005b) and Choi et al (2005) focus only on the extraction of sources of opinions, without extracting opinion expressions.Specifically, Kim and Hovy (2005b) assume a priori existence of the opinion expressions and ex tract a single source for each, while Choi et al(2005) do not explicitly extract opinion expres sions nor link an opinion expression to a sourceeven though their model implicitly learns approxi mations of opinion expressions in order to identify opinion sources.</S>
			<S sid="64" ssid="26">Other previous research focuses only on the extraction of opinion expressions (e.g. Kim and Hovy (2005a), Munson et al (2005) andWilson et al (2005)), omitting source identifica tion altogether.There have also been previous efforts to simultaneously extract entities and relations by ex ploiting their mutual dependencies.</S>
			<S sid="65" ssid="27">Roth and Yih (2002) formulated global inference using aBayesian network, where they captured the influ ence between a relation and a pair of entities via the conditional probability of a relation, given a pair of entities.</S>
			<S sid="66" ssid="28">This approach however, could not exploit dependencies between relations.</S>
			<S sid="67" ssid="29">Roth and Yih (2004) later formulated global inference using integer linear programming, which is the approach that we apply here.</S>
			<S sid="68" ssid="30">In contrast to our work, Roth and Yih (2004) operated in the domain of factualinformation extraction rather than opinion extraction, and assumed that the exact boundaries of en tities from the gold standard are known a priori, which may not be available in practice.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Extraction of Opinion and Source. " number="3">
			<S sid="69" ssid="1">EntitiesWe develop two separate sequence tagging classi fiers for opinion extraction and source extraction, using linear-chain Conditional Random Fields(CRFs) (Lafferty et al, 2001).</S>
			<S sid="70" ssid="2">The sequence tag ging is encoded as the typical ?BIO?</S>
			<S sid="71" ssid="3">scheme.4Each training or test instance represents a sen tence, encoded as a linear chain of tokens and their 4?B? is for the token that begins an entity, ?I? is for to kens that are inside an entity, and ?O? is for tokens outside an entity.</S>
			<S sid="72" ssid="4">433 associated features.</S>
			<S sid="73" ssid="5">Our feature set is based on that of Choi et al (2005) for source extraction5,but we include additional lexical and WordNet based features.</S>
			<S sid="74" ssid="6">For simplicity, we use the same features for opinion entity extraction and sourceextraction, and let the CRFs learn appropriate fea ture weights for each task.</S>
			<S sid="75" ssid="7">3.1 Entity extraction features.</S>
			<S sid="76" ssid="8">For each token xi, we include the following fea tures.</S>
			<S sid="77" ssid="9">For details, see Choi et al (2005).</S>
			<S sid="78" ssid="10">word: words in a [-4, +4] window centered on xi.</S>
			<S sid="79" ssid="11">part-of-speech: POS tags in a [-2, +2] window.6grammatical role: grammatical role (subject, ob ject, prepositional phrase types) of xi derived from a dependency parse.7dictionary: whether xi is in the opinion expres sion dictionary culled from the training data and augmented by approximately 500 opinion words from the MPQA Final Report8.</S>
			<S sid="80" ssid="12">Also computed for tokens in a [-1, +1] window and for xi?s parent ?chunk?</S>
			<S sid="81" ssid="13">in the dependency parse.</S>
			<S sid="82" ssid="14">semantic class: xi?s semantic class.9 WordNet: the WordNet hypernym of xi.10</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Relation Classification. " number="4">
			<S sid="83" ssid="1">We also develop a maximum entropy binary classifier for opinion-source link relation classification.</S>
			<S sid="84" ssid="2">Given an opinion-source pair, Oi-Sj , the re lation classifier decides whether the pair exhibits a valid link relation, Li,j . The relation classifier focuses only on the syntactic structure and lexical properties between the two entities of a given pair, without knowing whether the proposed entities are correct.</S>
			<S sid="85" ssid="3">Opinion and source entities are taken fromthe n-best sequences of the entity extraction mod els; therefore, some are invariably incorrect.</S>
			<S sid="86" ssid="4">From each sentence, we create training and test instances for all possible opinion-source pairings that do not overlap: we create an instance for Li,j only if the span of Oi and Sj do not overlap.</S>
			<S sid="87" ssid="5">For training, we also filter out instances forwhich neither the proposed opinion nor source en 5We omit only the extraction pattern features.</S>
			<S sid="88" ssid="6">6Using GATE: http://gate.ac.uk/ 7Provided by Rebecca Hwa, based on the Collins parser: ftp://ftp.cis.upenn.edu/pub/mcollins/PARSER.tar.gz 8https://rrc.mitre.org/pubs/mpqaFinalReport.pdf 9Using SUNDANCE: (http://www.cs.utah.edu/r?iloff/ publications.html#sundance) 10http://wordnet.princeton.edu/tity overlaps with a correct opinion or source en tity per the gold standard.</S>
			<S sid="89" ssid="7">This training instancefiltering helps to avoid confusion between exam ples like the following (where entities marked in bold are the gold standard entities, and entitiesin square brackets represent the n-best output se quences from the entity extraction classifiers): (1) [The president] s1 walked away from [themeeting] o1, [ [revealing] o2 his disap pointment] o3 with the deal.</S>
			<S sid="90" ssid="8">(2) [The monster] s2 walked away, [revealing] o4 a little box hidden underneath.For these sentences, we construct training in stances for L1,1, L1,2, and L1,3, but not L2,4, which in fact has very similar sentential structureas L1,2, and hence could confuse the learning al gorithm.</S>
			<S sid="91" ssid="9">4.1 Relation extraction features.</S>
			<S sid="92" ssid="10">The training and test instances for each (potential) link Li,j (with opinion candidate entity Oi and source candidate entity Sj) include the following features.</S>
			<S sid="93" ssid="11">opinion entity word: the words contained in Oi.phrase type: the syntactic category of the con stituent in which the entity is embedded, e.g. NP or VP.</S>
			<S sid="94" ssid="12">We encode separate features for Oi and Sj . grammatical role: the grammatical role of the constituent in which the entity is embedded.</S>
			<S sid="95" ssid="13">Grammatical roles are derived from dependencyparse trees, as done for the entity extraction classi fiers.</S>
			<S sid="96" ssid="14">We encode separate features for Oi and Sj . position: a boolean value indicating whether Sj precedes Oi.distance: the distance between Oi and Sj in numbers of tokens.</S>
			<S sid="97" ssid="15">We use four coarse categories: ad jacent, very near, near, far.dependency path: the path through the depen dency tree from the head of Sj to the head of Oi.</S>
			<S sid="98" ssid="16">For instance, ?subj?verb?</S>
			<S sid="99" ssid="17">or ?subj?verb?obj?.</S>
			<S sid="100" ssid="18">voice: whether the voice of Oi is passive or active.syntactic frame: key intra-sentential relations be tween Oi and Sj . The syntactic frames that we use are: ? [E1:role] [distance] [E2:role], where distance ? {adjacent, very near, near, far}, and Ei:role is the grammatical role of Ei.</S>
			<S sid="101" ssid="19">Either E1 is an opinion entity and E2 is a source, or vice versa.</S>
			<S sid="102" ssid="20">[E1:phrase] [distance] [E2:phrase], where Ei:phrase is the phrasal type of entity Ei.</S>
			<S sid="103" ssid="21">434 ? [E1:phrase] [E2:headword], where E2 must bethe opinion entity, and E1 must be the source en tity (i.e. no lexicalized frames for sources).</S>
			<S sid="104" ssid="22">E1 and E2 can be contiguous.</S>
			<S sid="105" ssid="23">[E1:role] [E2:headword], where E2 must be the opinion entity, and E1 must be the source entity.</S>
			<S sid="106" ssid="24">[E1:phrase] NP [E2:phrase] indicates the presence of specific syntactic patterns, e.g. ?VP NP VP?</S>
			<S sid="107" ssid="25">depending on the possible phrase types of opinion and source entities.</S>
			<S sid="108" ssid="26">The three phrases do not need to be contiguous.</S>
			<S sid="109" ssid="27">[E1:phrase] VP [E2:phrase] (See above.)</S>
			<S sid="110" ssid="28">[E1:phrase] [wh-word] [E2:phrase] (See above.)</S>
			<S sid="111" ssid="29">Src [distance] [x] [distance] Op, where x ? {by, of, from, for, between, among, and, have, be, will, not, ], ?, . . .</S>
			<S sid="112" ssid="30">}.When a syntactic frame is matched to a sen tence, the bracketed items should be instantiatedwith particular values corresponding to the sen tence.</S>
			<S sid="113" ssid="31">Pattern elements without square brackets are constants.</S>
			<S sid="114" ssid="32">For instance, the syntactic frame ?[E1:phrase] NP [E2:phrase]?</S>
			<S sid="115" ssid="33">may be instantiated as ?VP NP VP?.</S>
			<S sid="116" ssid="34">Some frames are lexicalized with respect to the head of an opinion entity to reflectthe fact that different verbs expect source enti ties in different argument positions (e.g. SOURCE blamed TARGET vs. TARGET angered SOURCE).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Integer Linear Programming. " number="5">
			<S sid="117" ssid="1">Approach As noted in the introduction, we model our taskas global, constraint-based inference over the sep arately trained entity and relation classifiers, andimplement the inference procedure as binary in teger linear programming (ILP) ((Roth and Yih, 2004), (Punyakanok et al, 2004)).</S>
			<S sid="118" ssid="2">ILP consists of an objective function which is a dot product between a vector of variables and a vector ofweights, and a set of equality and inequality constraints among variables.</S>
			<S sid="119" ssid="3">Given an objective function and a set of constraints, LP finds the opti mal assignment of values to variables, i.e. one that minimizes the objective function.</S>
			<S sid="120" ssid="4">In binary ILP, the assignments to variables must be either 0 or 1.The variables and constraints defined for the opin ion recognition task are summarized in Table 1 and explained below.</S>
			<S sid="121" ssid="5">Entity variables and weights For each opinion entity, we add two variables, Oi and O?i, where Oi = 1 means to extract the opinion entity, and Objective function f = ? i(woiOi) + ? i(w?oiO?i) + ? j(wsjSj) + ? j(w?sj S?j) + ? i,j(wli,jLi,j) + ? i(w?li,j L?i,j) ?i, Oi + O?i = 1 ?j, Sj + S?j = 1 ?i, j, Li,j + L?i,j = 1 ?i, Oi = ? j Li,j ?j, Sj + Aj = ? i Li,j ?j, Aj ? Sj ? 0 ?i, j, i &lt; j, Xi + Xj = 1,X ? {S,O} Table 1: Binary ILP formulation O?i = 1 means to discard the opinion entity.</S>
			<S sid="122" ssid="6">Toensure coherent assignments, we add equality con straints ?i, Oi + O?i = 1.</S>
			<S sid="123" ssid="7">The weights woi and w?oi for Oi and O?i respectively, are computed as a negative conditional probability of the span of an entity to be extracted (or suppressed) given the labelings of the adjacent variables of the CRFs: woi def= ?P (xk, xk+1, ..., xl|xk?1, xl+1) where xk = ?B? &amp; xm = ?I? for m ? [k + 1, l] w?oi def= ?P (xk, xk+1, ..., xl|xk?1, xl+1) where xm = ?O? for m ? [k, l]where xi is the value assigned to the random vari able of the CRF corresponding to an entity Oi.Likewise, for each source entity, we add two vari ables Sj and S?j and a constraint Sj + S?j = 1.</S>
			<S sid="124" ssid="8">The weights for source variables are computed in the same way as opinion entities.</S>
			<S sid="125" ssid="9">Relation variables and weights For each link relation, we add two variables Li,j and L?i,j , and a constraint Li,j + L?i,j = 1.</S>
			<S sid="126" ssid="10">By the definition of a link, if Li,j = 1, then it is implied that Oi = 1 and Sj = 1.</S>
			<S sid="127" ssid="11">That is, if a link is extracted, then the pair of entities for the link must be also extracted.</S>
			<S sid="128" ssid="12">Constraints to ensure this coherency are explained in the following subsection.</S>
			<S sid="129" ssid="13">The weights for linkvariables are based on probabilities from the bi nary link classifier.</S>
			<S sid="130" ssid="14">Constraints for link coherency In our corpus, asource entity can be linked to more than one opin ion entity, but an opinion entity is linked to only 435one source.</S>
			<S sid="131" ssid="15">Nonetheless, the majority of opinion source pairs involve one-to-one mappings, which we encode as hard and soft constraints as follows:For each opinion entity, we add an equality con straint Oi = ? j Li,j to enforce that only one link can emanate from an opinion entity.</S>
			<S sid="132" ssid="16">For each source entity, we add an equality constraint and an inequality constraint that together allow a source to link to at most two opinions: Sj +Aj = ? i Li,jand Aj ? Sj ? 0, where Aj is an auxiliary vari able, such that its weight is some positive constant value that suppresses Aj from being assigned to 1.</S>
			<S sid="133" ssid="17">And Aj can be assigned to 1 only if Sj is already assigned to 1.</S>
			<S sid="134" ssid="18">It is possible to add more auxiliary variables to allow more than two opinions to link to a source, but for our experiments two seemed to be a reasonable limit.</S>
			<S sid="135" ssid="19">Constraints for entity coherency When we use n-best sequences where n &gt; 1, proposed entities can overlap.</S>
			<S sid="136" ssid="20">Because this should not be the case in the final result, we add an equality constraint Xi + Xj = 1, X ? {S,O} for all pairs of entities with overlapping spans.Adjustments to weights To balance the precision and recall, and to take into account the performance of different base classifiers, we apply ad justments to weights as follows.</S>
			<S sid="137" ssid="21">1) We define six coefficients cx and c?x, where x ? {O,S,L} to modify a group of weights as follows.</S>
			<S sid="138" ssid="22">?i, x, wxi := wxi ? cx; ?i, x, w?xi := w?xi ? c?x; In general, increasing cx will promote recall, while increasing c?x will promote precision.Also, setting co &gt; cs will put higher confi dence on the opinion extraction classifier than the source extraction classifier.</S>
			<S sid="139" ssid="23">2) We also define one constant cA to set the weights for auxiliary variable Ai.</S>
			<S sid="140" ssid="24">That is, ?i, wAi := cA.</S>
			<S sid="141" ssid="25">3) Finally, we adjust the confidence of the linkvariable based on n-th-best sequences of the en tity extraction classifiers as follows.</S>
			<S sid="142" ssid="26">?i, wLi,j := wLi,j ? d where d def= 4/(3 + min(m,n)), when Oi is from an m-th sequence and Sj is from a n-th sequence.11 11This will smoothly degrade the confidence of a link based on the entities from higher n-th sequences.</S>
			<S sid="143" ssid="27">Values of d decrease as 4/4, 4/5, 4/6, 4/7....</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Experiments?I. " number="6">
			<S sid="144" ssid="1">We evaluate our system using the NRRC Multi Perspective Question Answering (MPQA) corpusthat contains 535 newswire articles that are man ually annotated for opinion-related information.</S>
			<S sid="145" ssid="2">In particular, our gold standard opinion entitiescorrespond to direct subjective expression anno tations and subjective speech event annotations (i.e. speech events that introduce opinions) in theMPQA corpus (Wiebe et al, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="146" ssid="3">Gold standard source entities and link relations can be ex tracted from the agent attribute associated with each opinion entity.</S>
			<S sid="147" ssid="4">We use 135 documents as adevelopment set and report 10-fold cross valida tion results on the remaining 400 documents in all experiments below.</S>
			<S sid="148" ssid="5">We evaluate entity and link extraction usingboth an overlap and exact matching scheme.12 Because the exact start and endpoints of the manual annotations are somewhat arbitrary, the over lap scheme is more reasonable for our task (Wiebe et al, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="149" ssid="6">We report results according to bothmatching schemes, but focus our discussion on re sults obtained using overlap matching.13 We use the Mallet14 implementation of CRFs.</S>
			<S sid="150" ssid="7">For brevity, we will refer to the opinion extractionclassifier as CRF-OP, the source extraction classi fier as CRF-SRC, and the link relation classifier asCRF-LINK.</S>
			<S sid="151" ssid="8">For ILP, we use Matlab, which pro duced the optimal assignment in a matter of few seconds for each sentence.</S>
			<S sid="152" ssid="9">The weight adjustmentconstants defined for ILP are based on the devel opment data.15 The link-nearest baselines For baselines, we first consider a link-nearest heuristic: for eachopinion entity extracted by CRF-OP, the link nearest heuristic creates a link relation with theclosest source entity extracted by CRF-SRC.</S>
			<S sid="153" ssid="10">Re call that CRF-SRC and CRF-OP extract entities from n-best sequences.</S>
			<S sid="154" ssid="11">We test the link-nearest heuristic with n = {1, 2, 10} where larger n will boost recall at the cost of precision.</S>
			<S sid="155" ssid="12">Results for the 12Given two links L1,1 = (O1, S1) and L2,2 = (O2, S2), exact matching requires the spans of O1 and O2, and the spans of S1 and S2, to match exactly, while overlap matching requires the spans to overlap.</S>
			<S sid="156" ssid="13">13Wiebe et al (2005) also reports the human annotation agreement study via the overlap scheme.</S>
			<S sid="157" ssid="14">14Available at http://mallet.cs.umass.edu 15co = 2.5, c?o = 1.0, cs = 1.5, c?s = 1.0, cL = 2.5, c?L = 2.5, cA = 0.2.</S>
			<S sid="158" ssid="15">Values are picked so as to boost recall while reasonably suppressing incorrect links.</S>
			<S sid="159" ssid="16">436 Overlap Match Exact Match r(%) p(%) f(%) r(%) p(%) f(%) NEAREST-1 51.6 71.4 59.9 26.2 36.9 30.7 NEAREST-2 60.7 45.8 52.2 29.7 19.0 23.1 NEAREST-10 66.3 20.9 31.7 28.2 00.0 00.0 SRL 59.7 36.3 45.2 32.6 19.3 24.2 SRL+CRF-OP 45.6 83.2 58.9 27.6 49.7 35.5 ILP-1 51.6 80.8 63.0 26.4 42.0 32.4 ILP-10 64.0 72.4 68.0 31.0 34.8 32.8 Table 2: Relation extraction performance NEAREST-n : link-nearest heuristic w/ n-best SRL : all V-A0 frames from SRL SRL+CRF-OP : all V-A0 filtered by CRF-OP ILP-n : ILP applied to n-best sequenceslink-nearest heuristic on the full source-expresses opinion relation extraction task are shown in the first three rows of table 2.</S>
			<S sid="160" ssid="17">NEAREST-1 performs the best in overlap-match F-measure, reaching 59.9.</S>
			<S sid="161" ssid="18">NEAREST-10 has higher recall (66.3%), but the precision is really low (20.9%).</S>
			<S sid="162" ssid="19">Performance of the opinion and source entity classifiers will be discussed in Section 8.SRL baselines Next, we consider two baselines that use a state-of-the-art SRL system (Pun yakanok et al, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="163" ssid="20">In many link relations, the opinion expression entity is a verb phrase andthe source entity is in an agent argument posi tion.</S>
			<S sid="164" ssid="21">Hence our second baseline, SRL, extracts all verb(V)-agent(A0) frames from the output of the SRL system and provides an upper bound onrecall (59.7%) for systems that use SRL in isola tion for our task.</S>
			<S sid="165" ssid="22">A more sophisticated baseline, SRL+CRF-OP, extracts only those V-A0 frames whose verb overlaps with entities extracted by the opinion expression extractor, CRF-OP.</S>
			<S sid="166" ssid="23">As shownin table 2, filtering out V-A0 frames that are incompatible with the opinion extractor boosts pre cision to 83.2%, but the F-measure (58.9) is lower than that of NEAREST-1.ILP results The ILP-n system in table 2 de notes the results of the ILP approach applied to the n-best sequences.</S>
			<S sid="167" ssid="24">ILP-10 reaches an F-measureof 68.0, a significant improvement over the high est performing baseline16 , and also a substantialimprovement over ILP-1.</S>
			<S sid="168" ssid="25">Note that the perfor mance of NEAREST-10 was much worse than that 16Statistically significant by paired-t test, where p &lt; 0.001.</S>
			<S sid="169" ssid="26">Overlap Match Exact Match r(%) p(%) f(%) r(%) p(%) f(%) ILP-1 51.6 80.8 63.0 26.4 42.0 32.4 ILP-10 64.0 72.4 68.0 31.0 34.8 32.8 ILP+SRL-f -1 51.7 81.5 63.3 26.6 42.5 32.7 ILP+SRL-f -10 65.7 72.4 68.9 31.5 34.3 32.9 ILP+SRL-fc-10 64.0 73.5 68.4 28.4 31.3 29.8 Table 3: Relation extraction with ILP and SRL ILP-n : ILP applied to n-best sequences ILP+SRL-f -n : ILP w/ SRL features, n-best ILP+SRL-fc-n : ILP w/ SRL features, and SRL constraints, n-bestof NEAREST-1, because the 10-best sequences include many incorrect entities whereas the corresponding ILP formulation can discard the bad en tities by considering dependencies among entities and relations.17</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Additional SRL Incorporation. " number="7">
			<S sid="170" ssid="1">We next explore two approaches for more directly incorporating SRL into our system.</S>
			<S sid="171" ssid="2">Extra SRL Features for the Link classifier We incorporate SRL into the link classifier by addingextra features based on SRL.</S>
			<S sid="172" ssid="3">We add boolean features to check whether the span of an SRL argu ment and an entity matches exactly.</S>
			<S sid="173" ssid="4">In addition, we include syntactic frame features as follows:?</S>
			<S sid="174" ssid="5">[E1:srl-arg] [E2:srl-arg], where Ei:srl-arg indi cates the SRL argument type of entity Ei.</S>
			<S sid="175" ssid="6">[E1.srl-arg] [E1:headword] [E2:srl-arg], where E1 must be an opinion entity, and E2 must be a source entity.</S>
			<S sid="176" ssid="7">Extra SRL Constraints for the ILP phase We also incorporate SRL into the ILP phase of our system by adding extra constraints based on SRL.</S>
			<S sid="177" ssid="8">In particular, we assign very high weights for linksthat match V-A0 frames generated by SRL, in or der to force the extraction of V-A0 frames.</S>
			<S sid="178" ssid="9">17A potential issue with overlap precision and recall is thatthe measures may drastically overestimate the system?s performance as follows: a system predicting a single link rela tion whose source and opinion expression both overlap withevery token of a document would achieve 100% overlap precision and recall.</S>
			<S sid="179" ssid="10">We can ensure this does not happen by mea suring the average number of (source, opinion) pairs to which each correct or predicted pair is aligned (excluding pairs not aligned at all).</S>
			<S sid="180" ssid="11">In our data, this does not exceed 1.08, (except for baselines), so we can conclude these evaluation measures are behaving reasonably.</S>
			<S sid="181" ssid="12">437 Opinion Source Link r(%) p(%) f(%) r(%) p(%) f(%) r(%) p(%) f(%) Before ILP CRF-OP/SRC/LINK with 1 best 76.4 88.4 81.9 67.3 81.9 73.9 60.5 50.5 55.0 merged 10 best 95.7 31.2 47.0 95.3 24.5 38.9 N/A After ILP ILP-SRL-f -10 75.1 82.9 78.8 80.6 75.7 78.1 65.7 72.4 68.9 ILP-SRL-f -10 ? CRF-OP/SRC with 1 best 82.3 81.7 82.0 81.5 73.4 77.3 N/A Table 4: Entity extraction performance (by overlap-matching)</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Experiments?II. " number="8">
			<S sid="182" ssid="1">Results using SRL are shown in Table 3 (on the previous page).</S>
			<S sid="183" ssid="2">In the table, ILP+SRL-f denotes the ILP approach using the link classifier withthe extra SRL ?f ?eatures, and ILP+SRL-fc de notes the ILP approach using both the extra SRL?f ?eatures and the SRL ?c?onstraints.</S>
			<S sid="184" ssid="3">For compar ison, the ILP-1 and ILP-10 results from Table 2 are shown in rows 1 and 2.</S>
			<S sid="185" ssid="4">The F-measure score of ILP+SRL-f -10 is 68.9, about a 1 point increase from that of ILP-10, which shows that extra SRL features for the link classifier further improve the performance over our previous best results.18 ILP+SRL-fc-10 alsoperforms better than ILP-10 in F-measure, al though it is slightly worse than ILP+SRL-f -10.</S>
			<S sid="186" ssid="5">This indicates that the link classifier with extra SRL features already makes good use of the V-A0 frames from the SRL system, so that forcing the extraction of such frames via extra ILP constraintsonly hurts performance by not allowing the extrac tion of non-V-A0 pairs in the neighborhood that could have been better choices.</S>
			<S sid="187" ssid="6">Contribution of the ILP phase In order to highlight the contribution of the ILP phase for our task, we present ?before?</S>
			<S sid="188" ssid="7">and ?after?</S>
			<S sid="189" ssid="8">performance in Table 4.</S>
			<S sid="190" ssid="9">The first row shows the performanceof the individual CRF-OP, CRF-SRC, and CRF LINK classifiers before the ILP phase.</S>
			<S sid="191" ssid="10">Without the ILP phase, the 1-best sequence generates the best scores.</S>
			<S sid="192" ssid="11">However, we also present the performance with merged 10-best entity sequences19 in orderto demonstrate that using 10-best sequences with out ILP will only hurt performance.</S>
			<S sid="193" ssid="12">The precision of the merged 10-best sequences system is very low, however the recall level is above 95% for both 18Statistically significant by paired-t test, where p &lt; 0.001.19If an entity Ei extracted by the ith-best sequence over laps with an entity Ej extracted by the jth-best sequence,where i &lt; j, then we discard Ej . If Ei and Ej do not over lap, then we extract both entities.</S>
			<S sid="194" ssid="13">CRF-OP and CRF-SRC, giving an upper bound for recall for our approach.</S>
			<S sid="195" ssid="14">The third row presentsresults after the ILP phase is applied for the 10 best sequences, and we see that, in addition to the improved link extraction described in Section 7,the performance on source extraction is substan tially improved, from F-measure of 73.9 to 78.1.Performance on opinion expression extraction decreases from F-measure of 81.9 to 78.8.</S>
			<S sid="196" ssid="15">This de crease is largely due to implicit links, which we will explain below.</S>
			<S sid="197" ssid="16">The fourth row takes the union of the entities from ILP-SRL-f -10 and the entitiesfrom the best sequences from CRF-OP and CRFSRC.</S>
			<S sid="198" ssid="17">This process brings the F-measure of CRF OP up to 82.0, with a different precision-recallbreak down from those of 1-best sequences with out ILP phase.</S>
			<S sid="199" ssid="18">In particular, the recall on opinionexpressions now reaches 82.3%, while maintain ing a high precision of 81.7%.</S>
			<S sid="200" ssid="19">Overlap Match Exact Match r(%) p(%) f(%) r(%) p(%) f(%) DEV.CONF 65.7 72.4 68.9 31.5 34.3 32.9 NO.CONF 63.7 76.2 69.4 30.9 36.7 33.5Table 5: Relation extraction with ILP weight ad justment.</S>
			<S sid="201" ssid="20">(All cases using ILP+SRL-f -10) Effects of ILP weight adjustment Finally, we show the effect of weight adjustment in the ILP formulation in Table 5.</S>
			<S sid="202" ssid="21">The DEV.CONF row shows relation extraction performance using a weight configuration based from the development data.</S>
			<S sid="203" ssid="22">In order to see the effect of weight adjustment,we ran an experiment, NO.CONF, using fixed default weights.20 Not surprisingly, our weight ad justment tuned from the development set is not theoptimal choice for cross-validation set.</S>
			<S sid="204" ssid="23">Neverthe less, the weight adjustment helps to balance the precision and recall, i.e. it improves recall at the 20To be precise, cx = 1.0, c?x = 1.0 for x ? {O, S, L}, but cA = 0.2 is the same as before.</S>
			<S sid="205" ssid="24">438 cost of precision.</S>
			<S sid="206" ssid="25">The weight adjustment is moreeffective when the gap between precision and re call is large, as was the case with the development data.</S>
			<S sid="207" ssid="26">Implicit links A good portion of errors stem from the implicit link relation, which our system did not model directly.</S>
			<S sid="208" ssid="27">An implicit link relation holds for an opinion entity without an associated source entity.</S>
			<S sid="209" ssid="28">In this case, the opinion entity islinked to an implicit source.</S>
			<S sid="210" ssid="29">Consider the follow ing example.</S>
			<S sid="211" ssid="30">Anti-Soviet hysteria was firmly oppressed.Notice that opinion expressions such as ?Anti Soviet hysteria?</S>
			<S sid="212" ssid="31">and ?firmly oppressed?</S>
			<S sid="213" ssid="32">do not have associated source entities, because sources ofthese opinion expressions are not explicitly men tioned in the text.</S>
			<S sid="214" ssid="33">Because our system forces each opinion to be linked with an explicit sourceentity, opinion expressions that do not have ex plicit source entities will be dropped during the global inference phase of our system.</S>
			<S sid="215" ssid="34">Implicit links amount to 7% of the link relations in our corpus, so the upper bound for recall for our ILP system is 93%.</S>
			<S sid="216" ssid="35">In the future we will extend our system to handle implicit links as well.</S>
			<S sid="217" ssid="36">Note thatwe report results against a gold standard that in cludes implicit links.</S>
			<S sid="218" ssid="37">Excluding them from thegold standard, the performance of our final sys tem ILP+SRL-f -10 is 72.6% in recall, 72.4% in precision, and 72.5 in F-measure.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusion. " number="9">
			<S sid="219" ssid="1">This paper presented a global inference approachto jointly extract entities and relations in the con text of opinion oriented information extraction.</S>
			<S sid="220" ssid="2">The final system achieves performance levels that are potentially good enough for many practical NLP applications.</S>
			<S sid="221" ssid="3">Acknowledgments We thank the reviewers for their many helpful comments and Vasin Punyakanok for runningour data through his SRL system.</S>
			<S sid="222" ssid="4">This work was sup ported by the Advanced Research and Development Activity (ARDA), by NSF Grants IIS-0535099 and IIS-0208028, and by gifts from Google and the Xerox Foundation.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
