<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">In this paper, we propose a practical method to detect Japanese homophone errors in Japanese texts.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">It is very important to detect homophone errors in Japanese revision systems because Japanese texts suffer from homophone errors frequently.</S>
		<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">In order to detect ho­ mophone errors, we have only to solve the homophone problem.</S>
		<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">We can use the decision list to do it because the homo­ phone problem is equivalent to the word sense disambiguation problem.</S>
		<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">However, the homophone problem is different from the word sense disambiguation problem because the former can use the written word but the latter cannot.</S>
		<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">In this pa­ per, we incorporate the written word into the original decision list by obtaining the identifying strength of the written word.</S>
		<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">The improved decision list can raise the F-measure of error detection.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">In this paper, we propose a method of detect­ ing Japanese homophone errors in Japanese texts.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">Our method is based on a decision list proposed by Yarowsky (Yarowsky, 1994; Yarowsky, 1995).</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">We improve the original decision list by using writ­ ten words in the default evidence.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">The imprqved decision list can raise the F-measure of error de­ tection.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">Most Japanese texts are written using Japanese word processors.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">To input a word composed of kanji characters, we first input the phonetic hira­ gana sequence for the word, and then convert it to the desired kanji sequence.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">However, multiple converted kanji sequences are generally produced, and we must then choose the correct kanji se­ quence.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">Therefore, Japanese texts suffer from ho mophone errors caused by incorrect choices.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">Care­ lessness of choice alone is not the cause of homo­ phone errors; Ignorance of the difference among homophone words is serious.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">For example, many Japanese are not aware of the difference between &apos;i&apos;:&apos; and &apos;i&apos;:.\ V, or between &apos;fil.&apos; and &apos;fil.l!l&apos; 1 In this paper, we define the term homophone set as a set of words consisting of kanji charac­ ters that have the same phone 2 • Then, we define the term homophone word as a word in a ho­ mophone set.</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">For example, the set {$ (proba­ bility), JL (establishment)} is a homophone set because words in the set are composed of kanji characters that have the same phone &apos;kaku-ritu&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">Thus,&apos; $&apos; and &apos; JL&apos; are homophone words.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "20">In this paper, we name the problem of choosing the correct word from the homophone set the homo­ phone problem.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "21">In order to detect homophone errors, we make a list of homophone sets in ad­ vance, find a homophone word in the text, and then solve the homophone problem for the homo­ phone word.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "22">Many methods of solving the homophone prob­ lem have been proposed (Tochinai et al., 1986; lbuki et al., 1997; Oku and Matsuoka, 1997; Oku, 1994; Wakita and Kaneko, 1996).</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "23">However, they are restricted to the homophone problem, that is, they are heuristic methods.</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "24">On the other hand, the homophone problem is equivalent to the word sense disambiguation problem if the phone of the homophone word is regarded as the word, and the homophone word as the sense.</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "25">Therefore, we can solve the homophone problem by using various 1•;if.;t:;&apos; and · .</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "26">,&apos; have a same phone &apos;i-shi&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "27">The meaning of &apos;:if..&apos;i!,!,&apos; is a general will, and the meaning of •;if.;E=:&apos; is a strong positive will.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "28">&apos;@:&apos; and &apos;@:lil&apos; have a same phone &apos;chokkan&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "29">The meaning of&apos;@:&apos; is an intuition through a feeling, and the meaning of &apos;@:lil&apos; is an intuition through a latent knowledge.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "30">2 We ignore the difference of accents, stresses and parts of speech.</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "31">That is, the homophone set is the set of words having the same expression in hiragana characters.</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "32">statistical methods proposed for the word sense disambiguation problem(Fujii, 1998).</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "33">Take the case of context-sensitive spelling error detection 3, which is equivalent to the homophone problem.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "34">For that problem, some statistical methods have been applied and succeeded(Golding, 1995; Gold­ ing and Schabes, 1996).</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "35">Hence, statistical meth­ ods are certainly valid for the homophone prob­ lem.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "36">In particular, the decision list is valid for the homophone problem(Shinnou, 1998).</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "37">The de­ cision list arranges evidences to identify the word sense in the order of strength of identifying the sense.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "38">The word sense is judged by the evidence, with the highest identifying strength, in the con­ text.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "39">Although the homophone problem is equivalent to the word sense disambiguation problem, the former has a distinct difference from the latter.</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "40">In the homophone problem, almost all of the an­ swers are given correctly, because almost all of the expressions written in the given text are correct.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "41">It is difficult to decide which is the meaning of &apos;crane&apos;, &apos;crane of animal&apos; or &apos;crane of tool&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "42">How­ ever, it is almost right that the correct expression of &apos;.Jii.lL&apos; in a text is not &apos;lit$&apos; but &apos;.Jii3t&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "43">In the homophone problem, the choice of the writ­ ten word results in high precision.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "44">We should use this information.</S>
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "45">However, the method to always choose the written word is useless for error detec­ tion because it doesn&apos;t detect errors at all.</S>
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "46">The method used for the homophone problem should be evaluated from the precision and the recall of the error detection.</S>
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "47">In this paper, we evaluate it by the F-measure to combine the precision and the recall, and use the written word to raise the F-measure of the original decision list.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "48">We use the written word as an evidence of the decision list.</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "49">The problem is how much strength to give to that evidence.</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "50">If the strength is high, the precision rises but the recall drops.</S>
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "51">On the other hand, if the strength is low, the decision list is not improved.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "52">In this paper, we calculate the strength that gives the maximum F-measure in a training corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "53">As a result, our decision list can raise the F-measure of error detection.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Homophone disambiguation by  a. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "1">decision list In this section, we describe how to construct the decision list and to apply it to the homophone problem.</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "2">3For example, confusion between &apos;peace&apos; and &apos;piece&apos;, or between &apos;quiet&apos; and &apos;quite&apos; is the context­ sensitive spelling error.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "3">2.1 Construction of the decision list.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "4">The decision list is constructed by the following steps.</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "5">step 1 Prepare homophone sets.</S>
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "6">In this paper, we use the 12 homophone sets shown in Table 1, which consist of homophone words that tend to be mis-chosen.</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "7">Table 1: Homophone sets Phone I Homophone set step 2 Set context information, i.e. evidences, to identify the homophone word.</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "8">We use the following three kinds of evidence.• word ( w) in front of H: Expressed as w • word (w) behind H: Expressed as w+ • jiritu words 4 surrounding H: We pick up the nearest three jiritu words in front of and behind H respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "9">We express them as w±3.</S>
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "10">step 3 Derive the frequency f rq( Wi,e;) of the collocation between the homophone word Wi in the homophone set {w1, w2, ···, wn} and the evidence e;, by using a training corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "11">For example, let us consider the homophone set {:JIM: (running (of a ship, etc.)), jifr (running (of a train, etc.))} and the following two Japanese sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "12">Sentence 1 I &quot;® 0)!$.\.i.l&apos;::::.</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "13">J. - r Jv &quot;t&apos;&apos; 11Hr m€0) :ii Mitx: !Ct :&gt;j: &apos;/,)&gt;-?</S>
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "14">t::.</S>
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "15">o J (A west wind of 3 m/s did not prevent the plane from flying.)</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "16">4 The jiritu.</S>
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "17">word is defined as an independent word which can form one bun-setu by itself.</S>
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "18">Nouns, verbs and adjectives are examples.</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "19">Table 2: Answers and identifying strength for evidences Evid.</S>
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "20">Freq.</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "21">of Freq.</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "22">of Ans.</S>
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "23">Identifying &apos;iiM.it&apos; &apos;iifr&apos; Strength 1:+ (to+) 77 53 iiM.it 0.538 (J)- (of-) 252 282 iih 0.162 1R:h ±3 (plane±3) 4 0 iiM.it 5.358 ...</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "24">... a;Jra, + (hour+) 14 11 iiRit 0.345 i±3 (midnight±3) 0 48 iih 8.910 m*fB ±3 (shorten±3) 0 4 iih 5.358 ...</S>
			<S sid ="78" ssid = "25">... default 1468 1422 iiRit 0.046 Sentence 2 f !f.W:Ii(J))Iqfp;J rdj !N*fsnt.: o J (Running hours in the early morning and dur­ ing the night were shortened.)</S>
			<S sid ="79" ssid = "26">From sentence I, we can extract the following evidences for the word &apos;iiRit&apos;: &quot;1:+&quot;&apos; &quot;(f) -&quot;&apos; &quot;1R;qit t ±3&quot;&apos; &quot;=±3&quot;&apos; &quot;Jll..</S>
			<S sid ="80" ssid = "27">±3&quot;&apos; &quot;::t ±3&quot;&apos; &quot; &quot;\ ±3&quot;&apos; and from sentence 2, we can extract the following evidences for the word •)Iqf•: &quot;H ra, +&quot;, &quot;(J) -&quot;, &quot; ±3&quot;, &quot;!f.Wl ±3&quot;, &quot;IJ;Jra, ±3&quot;, &quot;N*fs ±3&quot;, &quot;To ±3&quot;.</S>
			<S sid ="81" ssid = "28">step 4 Define the strength est( Wi, e;) of estimat­ ing that the homophone word Wi is correct {est( w1, e; ), est( w2, e;), ···,est( w,., e;)}, and set the word w1c as the answer for the evidence e;.</S>
			<S sid ="82" ssid = "29">In this case, the identifying strength is est( w1c, e;).</S>
			<S sid ="83" ssid = "30">For example, by steps 4 and 5 we can construct the list shown in Table 2.</S>
			<S sid ="84" ssid = "31">step 6 Fix the answer w1c; for each e; and sort identifying strengths est( w1c;, e;) in order of dimension, but remove the evidence whose identifying strength is less than the identi­ fying strength est(w1c;, default) for the evi­ dence default from the list.</S>
			<S sid ="85" ssid = "32">This is the deci­ sion list.</S>
			<S sid ="86" ssid = "33">After step 6, we obtain the decision list for the homophone set { ii-M:, jlqf }as shown in Table 3.</S>
			<S sid ="87" ssid = "34">Table 3: Example of decision list I Rank I Evid I Ans.</S>
			<S sid ="88" ssid = "35">I Strength I where P( wi ie;) is approximately calculated by: P( ·I·)- frq(wi,e;)+a L..Jic frq w1c, e; +a a in the above expression is included to avoid the unsatisfactory case of frq(wi,e;) = 0.</S>
			<S sid ="89" ssid = "36">In this paper, we set a = 0.15 . We also use the special evidence default.</S>
			<S sid ="90" ssid = "37">frq(wi,default) is defined as the frequency of Wi.</S>
			<S sid ="91" ssid = "38">step 5 Pick the highest strength est( w1c, e;) among 5 As in this paper, the addition of a small value is an easy and effective way to avoid the unsatisfactory case, as shown in (Yarowsky, 1994).</S>
			<S sid ="92" ssid = "39">1 9Ul:j[ ±3 (train±3) iih 9.453 2 f} ±3 (ship±3) iiM.it 9.106 3 i ±3 jiqf 8.910 (midnight±3) ...</S>
			<S sid ="93" ssid = "40">701 a;Jra,- (hour-) jiqf 0.358 ...</S>
			<S sid ="94" ssid = "41">746 (J)+ (of+) iih 0.162 ...</S>
			<S sid ="95" ssid = "42">760 default iiM.it 0.046 2.2 Solving by a decision.</S>
			<S sid ="96" ssid = "43">list In order to solve the homophone problem by the decision list, we first find the homophone word w in the given text, and then extract evidences E for the word w from the text: Next, picking up the evidence from the deci­ sion list for the homophone set for the homophone word win order of rank, we check whether the ev­ idence is in the set E. If the evidence ei is in the set E, the answer Wlc; for ei is judged to be the correct expression for the homophone word w. If w1ci is equal to w, w is judged to be correct, and if it is not equal, then it is shown that w may be the error for Wier</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Use  of the  written word. " number = "3">
			<S sid ="97" ssid = "1">In this section, we describe the use of the writ­ ten word in the homophone problem and how to incorporate it into the decision list.</S>
			<S sid ="98" ssid = "2">3.1 Evaluation of error detection systems.</S>
			<S sid ="99" ssid = "3">As described in the Introduction, the written word cannot be used in the word sense disambiguation problem, but it is useful for solving homophone problems.</S>
			<S sid ="100" ssid = "4">The method used for the homophone problem is trivial if the method is evaluated by the precision of distinction using the following for­ mula: number of correct discriminations number of all discriminations this paper, we regard the written word as a .kind of evidence on context, and give it an identifying strength.</S>
			<S sid ="101" ssid = "5">Consequently we can use the written word in the decision list.</S>
			<S sid ="102" ssid = "6">3.3 Calculation of the.</S>
			<S sid ="103" ssid = "7">identifying strength of the written word First, let z be the identifying strength of the writ­ ten word.</S>
			<S sid ="104" ssid = "8">We name the set of evidences with higher identifying strength than z the set a, and the set of evidences with lower identifying strength than z the set {3, Let T be the number of homophone problems for a homophone set.</S>
			<S sid ="105" ssid = "9">We solve them by the orig­ inal decision list D LO . Let G (or H) be the ratio of the number of homophone problems by judged by a (or {3) toT.</S>
			<S sid ="106" ssid = "10">Let g (or h) be the precision of a (or {3), and p be the occurrence probability of the homophone error.</S>
			<S sid ="107" ssid = "11">The number of problems correctly solved by a is as follows: GT(1- p), (2) and the number of problems incorrectly solved by a is as follows: That is, if the expression is &apos;liM!:&apos; (or •j qf&apos;), then we should clearly choose the word &apos;liM!:&apos; (or the word •j qf&apos;) from the homophone set { JIM:, JJ;qf }.</S>
			<S sid ="108" ssid = "12">This distinction method probably has better precision than any other methods for the word sense disambiguation problem.</S>
			<S sid ="109" ssid = "13">However, this method is useless because it does not detect errors at all.</S>
			<S sid ="110" ssid = "14">The method for the homophone problem should be evaluated from the standpoint of not error dis­ crimination but error detection.</S>
			<S sid ="111" ssid = "15">In this paper, we use the F-measure (Eq.1) to combine the precision P and the recall R defined as follows: P = number of real errors in detected errors number of detected errors R = number of real errors in detected errors number of errors m the te:r:t GTp.</S>
			<S sid ="112" ssid = "16">(3) The number of problems detected as errors in Eq.2 and Eq.3 are GT(1- p)(1- g) and GTpg respec­ tively.</S>
			<S sid ="113" ssid = "17">Thus, the number of problems detected as errors by a is as follows: GT((1- p)(1- g)+ pg).</S>
			<S sid ="114" ssid = "18">(4) In the same way, the number of problems detected as errors by {3 is as follows: HT((1- p)(1- h)+ ph).</S>
			<S sid ="115" ssid = "19">(5) Consequently the total number of problems de­ tected as errors is as follows: T(G((1-p)(1-g) +pg) +H((1- p)(1- h) +ph)).</S>
			<S sid ="116" ssid = "20">(6) The number of correct detections in Eq.6 is Tp(Gg + Hh).</S>
			<S sid ="117" ssid = "21">Therefore the precision Po is as F= 2PR P+R (1) follows: Po p(Gg + Hh)/{G((1- p)(1- g)+ pg) 3.2 Use of the identifying strength of the.</S>
			<S sid ="118" ssid = "22">written word The distinction method to choose the written word is useless, but it has a very high precision of error discrimination.</S>
			<S sid ="119" ssid = "23">Thus, it is valid to use this method where it is difficult to use context to solve the homophone problem.</S>
			<S sid ="120" ssid = "24">The question is when to stop using the deci­ sion from context and use the written word.</S>
			<S sid ="121" ssid = "25">In + H((1- p)(1- h)+ ph)} Because the number of real errors in T is Tp, the recall Ro is Gg+Hh.</S>
			<S sid ="122" ssid = "26">By using Po and Ro, we can get the F-measure Fo of DLO by Eq.l. Next, we construct the decision list incorporat­ ing the written word into DLO.</S>
			<S sid ="123" ssid = "27">We name this deci­ sion list DL1.</S>
			<S sid ="124" ssid = "28">In DL1, we use the written word to solve problems which we cannot judge by a. That DLO DL1 Figure 1: Construction of DL1 is, DL1 is the decision list to attach the written word as the default evidence to a: (see Fig.1).</S>
			<S sid ="125" ssid = "29">Next, we calculate the precision and the recall of DLl.</S>
			<S sid ="126" ssid = "30">Because a: of DL1 is the same as that of DLO, the number of problems detected as errors by a: is given by Eq.4.</S>
			<S sid ="127" ssid = "31">In the case of DL1, problems judged by f3 of DLO are judged by the written word.</S>
			<S sid ="128" ssid = "32">Therefore, we detect no error from these problems.</S>
			<S sid ="129" ssid = "33">As a result, the number of problems detected as errors by DL1 is given by Eq.4, and the number of real errors in these detections is TGpg.</S>
			<S sid ="130" ssid = "34">Therefore, the precision P1 of DL1 is as follows: Pt = pg (1-p)(1-g)+pg Because the number of whole errors is Tp, the recall R 1 of DL1 is Gg.</S>
			<S sid ="131" ssid = "35">By using P1 and Rt.</S>
			<S sid ="132" ssid = "36">we can get the F-measure F1 of DL1 by Eq.l. Finally, we try to define the identifying strength x. xis the value that yields the maximum F1 un­ der the condition F1 &gt; Fo.</S>
			<S sid ="133" ssid = "37">However, theoretical calculation alone cannot give x, because p is un­ known, and functions of G,H,g, and hare also unknown.</S>
			<S sid ="134" ssid = "38">In this paper, we set p = 0.05, and get values of G, H, g, and h by using the training corpus which is the resource used to construct the original deci­ sion list DLO.</S>
			<S sid ="135" ssid = "39">Take the case of the homophone set {&apos;JIJIDi:&apos;, &apos;JI{f&apos;}.</S>
			<S sid ="136" ssid = "40">For this homophone set, we try to get values ofG,H,g, and h. The training corpus has 2,890 sentences which include the word &apos;JIJIDi:&apos; or the word &apos;JI{f&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="137" ssid = "41">These 2,890 sentences are ho­ mophone problems for that homophone set.</S>
			<S sid ="138" ssid = "42">The identifying strength of DLO for this homophone set covers from 0.046 to 9.453 as shown in Table 3.</S>
			<S sid ="139" ssid = "43">Next we give x a value.</S>
			<S sid ="140" ssid = "44">For example, we set x = 2.5.</S>
			<S sid ="141" ssid = "45">In this case, the number of problems judged.</S>
			<S sid ="142" ssid = "46">by a: is 1,631, and the number of correct judgments in them is 1,593.</S>
			<S sid ="143" ssid = "47">Thus, G = 1631/2890 = 0.564 and g = 1593/1631 = 0.977.</S>
			<S sid ="144" ssid = "48">In the same way, under this assumption x 2.5, the num­ ber of problems judged by f3 is 1,259, and the number of correct judgments in them is 854.</S>
			<S sid ="145" ssid = "49">Thus, H = 1259/2890 = 0.436 and h = 854/1259 = 0.678.</S>
			<S sid ="146" ssid = "50">As a result, if x = 2.5, then Po = 0.225, Ro = 0.847, Fo = 0.356, Pt = 0.688, R1 = 0.551 and Ft = 0.612.</S>
			<S sid ="147" ssid = "51">In Fig.2, Fig.3 and Fig.4, we show the experiment result when x varies from 0.0 to 10.0 in units of 0.1.</S>
			<S sid ="148" ssid = "52">By choosing the maximum value of F1 in Fig.4, we can get the desired x. In this homophone set, we obtain x = 3.0.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Experiments. " number = "4">
			<S sid ="149" ssid = "1">First, we obtain each identifying strength of the written word for the 12 homophone sets shown in Table 1, by the above method.</S>
			<S sid ="150" ssid = "2">We show this result in Table 4.</S>
			<S sid ="151" ssid = "3">LRO in this table means the lowest rank of DLO.</S>
			<S sid ="152" ssid = "4">That is, LRO is the rank of the default evidence.</S>
			<S sid ="153" ssid = "5">LR1 means the lowest rank ofDLl.</S>
			<S sid ="154" ssid = "6">That is, LR1 is the rank of the evidence of the written word.</S>
			<S sid ="155" ssid = "7">Moreover, LRO and LR1 mean the sizes of each decision list DLO and DLl.</S>
			<S sid ="156" ssid = "8">Second, we extract sentences which include a word in the 12 homophone sets from a corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="157" ssid = "9">We note that this corpus is different from the training corpus; the corpus is one year&apos;s worth of Mainichi newspaper articles, and the training corpus is one year&apos;s worth of Nikkei newspaper articles.</S>
			<S sid ="158" ssid = "10">The extracted sentences are the test sentences of the experiment.</S>
			<S sid ="159" ssid = "11">We assume that these sentences have no homophone errors.</S>
			<S sid ="160" ssid = "12">Last, we randomly select 5% of the test sen­ tences, and forcibly put homophone errors into these selected sentences by changing the written 0.9 0.8 0.7 0 0 &apos;OL1&apos; o &apos;OL-o&apos; + Table 4: Identifying strength of the expression 0.6 0.5 .0..</S>
			<S sid ="161" ssid = "13">0.</S>
			<S sid ="162" ssid = "14">. 0.</S>
			<S sid ="163" ssid = "15">0 0.4 0.3 _....0 0.2 E::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::::: j 0 • Figure 2: Precisions Po and Pt 0.9 .---...--.----r--.-----,-.---.---,----,---,-.---, 0.4 0.3 Figure 3: Recalls Ro and Rt 0.7 .---...--.----r--.-----,-.--,---,----,.-----,-.---, &apos;DL1&apos; &lt;&gt; &apos;DL0&apos; • homophone word· to another homophone word.</S>
			<S sid ="164" ssid = "16">As a result, the test sentences include 5% errors.</S>
			<S sid ="165" ssid = "17">From these test sentences, we detect homophone errors by DLO and DL1 respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="166" ssid = "18">We conducted this experiment ten times, and got the mean of the precision, the recall and the F-measure.</S>
			<S sid ="167" ssid = "19">The result is shown in Table 5.</S>
			<S sid ="168" ssid = "20">For all homophone sets, the F-measure of our proposed DL1 is higher than the F-measure of the original decision list DLO.</S>
			<S sid ="169" ssid = "21">Therefore, it is con­ cluded that our proposed method is effective.</S>
			<S sid ="170" ssid = "22">5 Remarks The recall of DL1 is no more than the recall of DLO.</S>
			<S sid ="171" ssid = "23">Our method aims to raise the F measure by raising the precision instead of sacrificing the recall.</S>
			<S sid ="172" ssid = "24">We confirmed the validity of the method by experiments in sections 3 and 4.</S>
			<S sid ="173" ssid = "25">Thus our method has only a little effect if.</S>
			<S sid ="174" ssid = "26">the recall is evaluated with importance.</S>
			<S sid ="175" ssid = "27">However, we should note that 0.6 05 00..0 ,.,.0 t h e F m e a s u r e o f D L 1 i s a l w a y s n o t w o r s e t h a n t h e F m e a s u r e o f D L O . . .</S>
			<S sid ="176" ssid = "28">0 0 0.4 ,#cOO 00..</S>
			<S sid ="177" ssid = "29">We set the occurrence probability of the homo­ phone error at p = 0.05.</S>
			<S sid ="178" ssid = "30">However, each homo­ 0.3 00 0 ..</S>
			<S sid ="179" ssid = "31">ph on e set ha s its ow n p. W e ne ed de cid e p ex act ly be ca us e the ide nti fyi ng str en gt h of the wr itt en 0.2 00000 wo rd de pe nd s on p. Ho we ver , D L1 wil l pr od uc e better results than DLO if p is smaller than 0.05, 01 Figure 4: F-measures F0 and F1 because the precision of judgment by the written word improves without lowering the recall.</S>
			<S sid ="180" ssid = "32">The recall does not fall due to smaller p because Ro and R1 are independent of p. Moreover, from the definitions of Po and P1, we can confirm that the precision of judgments by the written word im­ proves with smaller p. Table 5: Result of experiments mean II 1,824 II 0.46o I o.9o6 I o.581 II o.56o I o.794 1 o.648 I The number of elements of all homophone sets used in this paper was two, but the number of elements of real homophone sets may be more.</S>
			<S sid ="181" ssid = "33">However, the bigger this number is, the better the result produced by our method, because the precision of judgments by the default evidence of DLO drops in this case, but that of DL1 does not.</S>
			<S sid ="182" ssid = "34">Therefore, our method is better than the original one even if the number of elements of the homo­ phone set increases.</S>
			<S sid ="183" ssid = "35">Our method has an advantage that the size of DL1 is smaller.</S>
			<S sid ="184" ssid = "36">The size of the decision list has no relation to the precision and the recall, but a small decision list has advantages of efficiency of calculation and maintenance.</S>
			<S sid ="185" ssid = "37">On the other hand, our method has a problem in that it does not use the written word in the judg­ ment from a:; Even the identifying strength of the evidence in a: must depend on the written word.</S>
			<S sid ="186" ssid = "38">We intend to study the use of the written word in the judgment from a:.</S>
			<S sid ="187" ssid = "39">Moreover, homophone errors in our experiments are artificial.</S>
			<S sid ="188" ssid = "40">We must confirm the effectiveness of the proposed method for actual homophone errors.</S>
			<S sid ="189" ssid = "41">6 Conclusions.</S>
			<S sid ="190" ssid = "42">In this paper, we used the decision list to solve the homophone problem.</S>
			<S sid ="191" ssid = "43">This strategy was based on the fact that the homophone problem is equivalent to the word sense disambiguation problem.</S>
			<S sid ="192" ssid = "44">How­ ever, the homophone problem is different from the word sense disambiguation problem because the former can use the written word but the latter cannot.</S>
			<S sid ="193" ssid = "45">In this paper, we incorporated the writ­ ten word into the original decision list by obtain ing the identifying strength of the written word.</S>
			<S sid ="194" ssid = "46">We used 12 homophone sets in experiments.</S>
			<S sid ="195" ssid = "47">In these experiments, our proposed decision list had a higher F-measure than the original one.</S>
			<S sid ="196" ssid = "48">A fu­ ture task is to further integrate context and the written word in the decision list.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acknowledgments">
			<S sid ="197" ssid = "49">We used Nikkei Shibun CDROM &apos;90 and Mainichi Shibun CDROM &apos;94 as the corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="198" ssid = "50">The Nihon Keizai Shinbun company and the Mainichi Shinbun company gave us permission of their col­ lections.</S>
			<S sid ="199" ssid = "51">We appreciate the assistance granted by both companies.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
