<PAPER>
	<S sid="0">Scalable Inference And Training Of Context-Rich Syntactic Translation Models</S><ABSTRACT>
		<S sid="1" ssid="1">Statistical MT has made great progress in the last few years, but current translation models are weakon re-ordering and target language fluency.</S>
		<S sid="2" ssid="2">Syn tactic approaches seek to remedy these problems.In this paper, we take the framework for acquiring multi-level syntactic translation rules of (Gal ley et al, 2004) from aligned tree-string pairs, and present two main extensions of their approach: first, instead of merely computing a single derivation that minimally explains a sentence pair, we constructa large number of derivations that include contextually richer rules, and account for multiple interpretations of unaligned words.</S>
		<S sid="3" ssid="3">Second, we pro pose probability estimates and a training procedure for weighting these rules.</S>
		<S sid="4" ssid="4">We contrast differentapproaches on real examples, show that our esti mates based on multiple derivations favor phrasal re-orderings that are linguistically better motivated, and establish that our larger rules provide a 3.63 BLEU point increase over minimal rules.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number="1">
			<S sid="5" ssid="5">While syntactic approaches seek to remedy word ordering problems common to statistical machine translation (SMT) systems, many of the earlier models?particularly child re-ordering models?</S>
			<S sid="6" ssid="6">fail to account for human translation behavior.Galley et al (2004) alleviate this modeling prob lem and present a method for acquiring millions of syntactic transfer rules from bilingual corpora,which we review below.</S>
			<S sid="7" ssid="7">Here, we make the fol lowing new contributions: (1) we show how to acquire larger rules that crucially condition onmore syntactic context, and show how to compute multiple derivations for each training exam ple, capturing both large and small rules, as well as multiple interpretations for unaligned words;(2) we develop probability models for these multi level transfer rules, and give estimation methods for assigning probabilities to very large rule sets.</S>
			<S sid="8" ssid="8">We contrast our work with (Galley et al, 2004), highlight some severe limitations of probability estimates computed from single derivations, and demonstrate that it is critical to account for many derivations for each sentence pair.</S>
			<S sid="9" ssid="9">We also usereal examples to show that our probability mod els estimated from a large number of derivations favor phrasal re-orderings that are linguistically well motivated.</S>
			<S sid="10" ssid="10">An empirical evaluation against a state-of-the-art SMT system similar to (Och and Ney, 2004) indicates positive prospects.</S>
			<S sid="11" ssid="11">Finally, we show that our contextually richer rules provide a 3.63 BLEU point increase over those of (Galley et al, 2004).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Inferring syntactic transformations. " number="2">
			<S sid="12" ssid="1">We assume we are given a source-language (e.g.,French) sentence f , a target-language (e.g., En glish) parse tree pi, whose yield e is a translation of f , and a word alignment a between f and e.Our aim is to gain insight into the process of transforming pi into f and to discover grammatically grounded translation rules.</S>
			<S sid="13" ssid="2">For this, we need a formalism that is expressive enough to deal with cases of syntactic divergence between source and target languages (Fox, 2002): for any given (pi, f ,a) triple, it is useful to produce a derivationthat minimally explains the transformation be tween pi and f , while remaining consistent with a. Galley et al (2004) present one such formalism (henceforth ?GHKM?).</S>
			<S sid="14" ssid="3">2.1 Tree-to-string alignments.</S>
			<S sid="15" ssid="4">It is appealing to model the transformation of pi into f using tree-to-string (xRs) transducers, sincetheir theory has been worked out in an exten sive literature and is well understood (see, e.g.,(Graehl and Knight, 2004)).</S>
			<S sid="16" ssid="5">Formally, transfor mational rules ri presented in (Galley et al, 2004) are equivalent to 1-state xRs transducers mapping a given pattern (subtree to match in pi) to a right hand side string.</S>
			<S sid="17" ssid="6">We will refer to them as lhs(ri) and rhs(ri), respectively.</S>
			<S sid="18" ssid="7">For example, some xRs 961 rules may describe the transformation of does not into ne ... pas in French.</S>
			<S sid="19" ssid="8">A particular instance may look like this: VP(AUX(does), RB(not), x0:VB) ? ne, x0, pas lhs(ri) can be any arbitrary syntax tree fragment.Its leaves are either lexicalized (e.g. does) or variables (x0, x1, etc).</S>
			<S sid="20" ssid="9">rhs(ri) is represented as a se quence of target-language words and variables.</S>
			<S sid="21" ssid="10">Now we give a brief overview of how such transformational rules are acquired automaticallyin GHKM.1 In Figure 1, the (pi, f ,a) triple is represented as a directed graph G (edges going down ward), with no distinction between edges of pi and alignments.</S>
			<S sid="22" ssid="11">Each node of the graph is labeled with its span and complement span (the latter in italic in the figure).</S>
			<S sid="23" ssid="12">The span of a node n is defined by the indices of the first and last word in f that are reachable from n. The complement span of n is the union of the spans of all nodes n?</S>
			<S sid="24" ssid="13">in G that are neither descendants nor ancestors of n. Nodesof G whose spans and complement spans are non overlapping form the frontier set F ? G.What is particularly interesting about the fron tier set?</S>
			<S sid="25" ssid="14">For any frontier of graph G containinga given node n ? F , spans on that frontier de fine an ordering between n and each other frontier node n?.</S>
			<S sid="26" ssid="15">For example, the span of VP[4-5] either precedes or follows, but never overlaps the span of any node n?</S>
			<S sid="27" ssid="16">on any graph frontier.</S>
			<S sid="28" ssid="17">This property does not hold for nodes outside of F . For instance, PP[4-5] and VBG[4] are two nodes of the same graph frontier, but they cannot be ordered because of their overlapping spans.</S>
			<S sid="29" ssid="18">The purpose of xRs rules in this framework is to order constituents along sensible frontiers in G, and all frontiers containing undefined orderings,as between PP[4-5] and VBG[4], must be disre garded during rule extraction.</S>
			<S sid="30" ssid="19">To ensure that xRs rules are prevented from attempting to re-orderany such pair of constituents, these rules are de signed in such a way that variables in their lhs can only match nodes of the frontier set.</S>
			<S sid="31" ssid="20">Rules that satisfy this property are said to be induced by G.2For example, rule (d) in Table 1 is valid accord ing to GHKM, since the spans corresponding to 1Note that we use a slightly different terminology.</S>
			<S sid="32" ssid="21">2Specifically, an xRs rule ri is extracted fromG by taking a subtree ? ?</S>
			<S sid="33" ssid="22">pi as lhs(ri), appending a variable to each leaf node of ? that is internal to pi, adding those variables to rhs(ri), ordering them in accordance to a, and if necessary inserting any word of f to ensure that rhs(ri) is a sequence of contiguous spans (e.g., [4-5][6][7-8] for rule (f) in Table 1).</S>
			<S sid="34" ssid="23">DT CD VBP NNS IN NNP NP NNS VBG 3 2 2 1 7-8 4 4 5 9 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="1-2,4" number="3">
			<S sid="35" ssid="1">-9 2 1-9 2 1-9 1 2-9 7-8 1-5,9</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="1-9" number="4">
			<S sid="36" ssid="1">4 1-9</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="1-4,7" number="5">
			<S sid="37" ssid="1">-9 9 1-8 1-2 3-9 NP 7-8 1-5,9 NP 5 1-4, 7 -9 PP 4-5 1-4,7 -9 VP 4-5 1-3,7 -9 NP 4-8 1-3,9 VP 3-8 1-2,9 S 1-9 ? 7!</S>
			<S sid="38" ssid="2">"# $ %&amp; '( ) *+ , . Thes e peop le inclu de astro naut s com ing from Fran ce ..</S>
			<S sid="39" ssid="3">7 Figure 1: Spans and complement-spans determine what rules are extracted.</S>
			<S sid="40" ssid="4">Constituents in gray are members of the frontier set; a minimal rule is extracted from each of them.</S>
			<S sid="41" ssid="5">(a) S(x0:NP, x1:VP, x2:.)</S>
			<S sid="42" ssid="6">x0, x1, x2 (b) NP(x0:DT, CD(7), NNS(people)) ? x0, 7?</S>
			<S sid="43" ssid="7">(c) DT(these) ??</S>
			<S sid="44" ssid="8">(d) VP(x0:VBP, x1:NP) ? x0, x1 (e) VBP(include) ?-?</S>
			<S sid="45" ssid="9">(f) NP(x0:NP, x1:VP) ? x1,?, x0 (g) NP(x0:NNS) ? x0 (h) NNS(astronauts) ??*,X (i) VP(VBG(coming), PP(IN(from), x0:NP)) ?e?, x0 (j) NP(x0:NNP) ? x0 (k) NNP(France) ???</S>
			<S sid="46" ssid="10">(l) .(.)</S>
			<S sid="47" ssid="11">Table 1: A minimal derivation corresponding to Figure 1.</S>
			<S sid="48" ssid="12">its rhs constituents (VBP[3] and NP[4-8]) do not overlap.</S>
			<S sid="49" ssid="13">Conversely, NP(x0:DT, x1:CD:, x2:NNS) is not the lhs of any rule extractible from G, since its frontier constituents CD[2] and NNS[2] haveoverlapping spans.3 Finally, the GHKM proce dure produces a single derivation from G, which is shown in Table 1.</S>
			<S sid="50" ssid="14">The concern in GHKM was to extract minimalrules, whereas ours is to extract rules of any arbi trary size.</S>
			<S sid="51" ssid="15">Minimal rules defined over G are thosethat cannot be decomposed into simpler rules induced by the same graph G, e.g., all rules in Table 1.</S>
			<S sid="52" ssid="16">We call minimal a derivation that only con tains minimal rules.</S>
			<S sid="53" ssid="17">Conversely, a composed ruleresults from the composition of two or more min imal rules, e.g., rule (b) and (c) compose into: NP(DT(these), CD(7), NNS(people)) ??, 7?</S>
			<S sid="54" ssid="18">3It is generally reasonable to also require that the root n of lhs(ri) be part of F , because no rule induced by G can compose with ri at n, due to the restrictions imposed on the extraction procedure, and ri wouldn?t be part of any valid derivation.</S>
			<S sid="55" ssid="19">962 OR NP (x0 :NP , x1 :V P) ! x1 ,!</S>
			<S sid="56" ssid="20">, x0 VP (x0 :VB P, x1: NP ) ! x0 , x 1 S(x 0:N P, x1: VP , x 2:.</S>
			<S sid="57" ssid="21">) ! x0 , x 1, x 2 NP (x0 :DT CD (7) , N NS (pe opl e)) ! x0 , 7 .(.)</S>
			<S sid="58" ssid="22">DT (th ese ) ! # VB P(i ncl ude ) ! $%  NP (x0 :NP , x1 :V P) ! x1 , x0 NP (x0 :NP , x1 :V P) ! x1 , x0 VP (V BG (co mi ng) , PP (IN (fro m), x0 :N P)) ! ( , x0 , ! VP (V BG (co mi ng) , PP (IN (fro m), x0 :N P)) ! ( , x0 NP (x0 :NN S) ! x0 NP (x0 :NN S) ! !, x0 NP (x0 :NN P) ! x0 , ! NN P(F ran ce) ! )* NN S(a stro nau ts) ! +,, OR OR N NS (as tro nau ts) !!</S>
			<S sid="59" ssid="23">,+ ,, OR NP (x0 :NN P) ! x0 NP (x0 :NN P) ! x0 NN P(F ran ce) ! )* , ! NP (x0 :NN S) ! x0 VP (V BG (co mi ng) , PP (IN (fro m), x0 :N P)) ! ( , x0 co min g fro m NN S IN NN P NP VP NP VB G PP NP 7-8 5 7-8 5 7-8 4 4 5 4 5 6 7 8 4 4 4-5 4-5 4-8 NN P(F ran ce) !) *, ! NP (x0 :NN P) ! x0 , ! VP (V BG (co mi ng) , PP (IN (fro m) , x0: NP )) ! ( , x0 , ! NN S(a stro nau ts) ! !</S>
			<S sid="60" ssid="24">, + ,, NP (x0 :NN S) ! !</S>
			<S sid="61" ssid="25">, x0 NP (x0 :NP , x1 :V P) ! x1 , ! , x0 (a) (b) ( )* ! +, as tro na uts Fra nce Figure 2: (a) Multiple ways of aligning?</S>
			<S sid="62" ssid="26">to constituents in the tree.</S>
			<S sid="63" ssid="27">(b) Derivation corresponding to the parse tree in Figure 1, which takes into account all alignments of?</S>
			<S sid="64" ssid="28">pictured in (a).</S>
			<S sid="65" ssid="29">Note that these properties are dependent on G, and the above rule would be considered a minimal rulein a graph G?</S>
			<S sid="66" ssid="30">similar to G, but additionally con taining a word alignment between 7 and ?.</S>
			<S sid="67" ssid="31">We will see in Sections 3 and 5 why extracting only minimal rules can be highly problematic.</S>
			<S sid="68" ssid="32">2.2 Unaligned words.</S>
			<S sid="69" ssid="33">While the general theory presented in GHKM ac counts for any kind of derivation consistent with G, it does not particularly discuss the case where some words of the source-language string f are not aligned to any word of e, thus disconnectedfrom the rest of the graph.</S>
			<S sid="70" ssid="34">This case is highly frequent: 24.1% of Chinese words in our 179 mil lion word English-Chinese bilingual corpus areunaligned, and 84.8% of Chinese sentences con tain at least one unaligned word.</S>
			<S sid="71" ssid="35">The question is what to do with such lexical items, e.g., ? inFigure 2(a).</S>
			<S sid="72" ssid="36">The approach of building one mini mal derivation for G as in the algorithm described in GHKM assumes that we commit ourselves to a particular heuristic to attach the unaligned itemto a certain constituent of pi, e.g., highest attach ment (in the example, ? is attached to NP[4-8]and the heuristic generates rule (f)).</S>
			<S sid="73" ssid="37">A more reasonable approach is to invoke the principle of insufficient reason and make no a priori assump tion about what is a ?correct?</S>
			<S sid="74" ssid="38">way of assigning the item to a constituent, and return all derivations that are consistent with G. In Section 4, we will see how to use corpus evidence to give preference to unaligned-word attachments that are the most consistent across the data.</S>
			<S sid="75" ssid="39">Figure 2(a) shows the six possible ways of attaching ? to constituents of pi: besides the highest attachment (rule (f)),?</S>
			<S sid="76" ssid="40">can move along the ancestors of France, since it is to the right of the translation of that word, and be considered to be part of an NNP, NP, or VP rule.</S>
			<S sid="77" ssid="41">We make the same reasoning to the left: ? can either start the NNS of astronauts, or start an NP.</S>
			<S sid="78" ssid="42">Our account of all possible ways of consistentlyattaching ? to constituents means we must extract more than one derivation to explain transfor mations in G, even if we still restrict ourselves to minimal derivations (a minimal derivation for G is unique if and only if no source-language word in G is unaligned).</S>
			<S sid="79" ssid="43">While we could enumerateall derivations separately, it is much more effi cient both in time and space to represent them as aderivation forest, as in Figure 2(b).</S>
			<S sid="80" ssid="44">Here, the for est covers all minimal derivations that correspondto G. It is necessary to ensure that for each deriva tion, each unaligned item (here ?) appears only once in the rules of that derivation, as shown inFigure 2 (which satisfies the property).</S>
			<S sid="81" ssid="45">That requirement will prove to be critical when we ad dress the problem of estimating probabilities forour rules: if we allowed in our example to spuri ously generate?s in multiple successive steps of the same derivation, we would not only represent the transformation incorrectly, but also ?-rules would be disproportionately represented, leading to strongly biased estimates.</S>
			<S sid="82" ssid="46">We will now see howto ensure this constraint is satisfied in our rule ex traction and derivation building algorithm.</S>
			<S sid="83" ssid="47">963 2.3 Algorithm.</S>
			<S sid="84" ssid="48">The linear-time algorithm presented in GHKM is only a particular case of the more general one we describe here, which is used to extract all rules, minimal and composed, induced by G. Similarlyto the GHKM algorithm, ours performs a top down traversal of G, but differs in the operations it performs at each node n ? F : we must explore all subtrees rooted at n, find all consistent ways of attaching unaligned words of f, and build valid derivations in accordance to these attachments.We use a table or-dforest[x, y, c] to store OR nodes, in which each OR-node can be uniquely defined by a syntactic category c and a span [x, y](which may cover unaligned words of f).</S>
			<S sid="85" ssid="49">This ta ble is used to prevent the same partial derivation to be followed multiple times (the in-degrees of OR-nodes generally become large with composedrules).</S>
			<S sid="86" ssid="50">Furthermore, to avoid over-generating un aligned words, the root and variables in each rule are represented with their spans.</S>
			<S sid="87" ssid="51">For example, inFigure 2(b), the second and third child of the top most OR-node respectively span across [4-5][6-8] and [4-6][7-8] (after constituent reordering).</S>
			<S sid="88" ssid="52">In the former case, ? will eventually be realized in an NP, and in the latter case, in a VP.</S>
			<S sid="89" ssid="53">The preprocessing step consists of assigning spans and complement spans to nodes of G, in the first case by a bottom-up exploration of the graph, and in the latter by a top-down traversal.To assign complement spans, we assign the com plement span of any node n to each of its children, and for each of them, add the span of the child to the complement span of all other children.</S>
			<S sid="90" ssid="54">In another traversal of G, we determine the minimal rule extractible from each node in F . We explore all tree fragments rooted at n by maintaining an open and a closed queue of rules extracted from n (qo and qc).</S>
			<S sid="91" ssid="55">At each step, we pick the smallest rule in qo, and for each of itsvariable nodes, try to discover new rules (?succes sor rules?)</S>
			<S sid="92" ssid="56">by means of composition with minimalrules, until a given threshold on rule size or maxi mum number of rules in qc is reached.</S>
			<S sid="93" ssid="57">There may be more that one successor per rule, since we must account for all possible spans than can be assigned to non-lexical leaves of a rule.</S>
			<S sid="94" ssid="58">Once a threshold is reached, or if the open queue is empty, we connecta new OR-node to all rules that have just been ex tracted from n, and add it to or-dforest.</S>
			<S sid="95" ssid="59">Finally, we proceed recursively, and extract new rules from each node at the frontier of the minimal rule rooted at n. Once all nodes of F have been processed, theor-dforest table contains a representation encod ing only valid derivations.</S>
			<S sid="96" ssid="60">3 Probability models.</S>
			<S sid="97" ssid="61">The overall goal of our translation system is to transform a given source-language sentence f into an appropriate translation e in the set E of all possible target-language sentences.</S>
			<S sid="98" ssid="62">In a noisy-channel approach to SMT, we uses Bayes?</S>
			<S sid="99" ssid="63">theorem and choose the English sentence e?</S>
			<S sid="100" ssid="64">E that maximizes:4 e?</S>
			<S sid="101" ssid="65">= argmax e?E { Pr(e) ? Pr(f |e) } (1) Pr(e) is our language model, and Pr(f |e) our translation model.</S>
			<S sid="102" ssid="66">In a grammatical approach to MT, we hypothesize that syntactic information can help produce good translation, and thus introduce dependencies on target-language syntax trees.</S>
			<S sid="103" ssid="67">The function to optimize becomes: e?</S>
			<S sid="104" ssid="68">= argmax e?E { Pr(e) ? ?</S>
			<S sid="105" ssid="69">pi??(e) Pr(f |pi) ?Pr(pi|e) } (2) ?(e) is the set of all English trees that yield thegiven sentence e. Estimating Pr(pi|e) is a prob lem equivalent to syntactic parsing and thus is not discussed here.</S>
			<S sid="106" ssid="70">Estimating Pr(f |pi) is the task of syntax-based translation models (SBTM).</S>
			<S sid="107" ssid="71">Given a rule set R, our SBTM makes the common assumption that left-most compositions of xRs rules ?i = r1 ? ...</S>
			<S sid="108" ssid="72">rn are independent from one another in a given derivation ?i ? ?, where ? is the set of all derivations constructible from G = (pi, f ,a) using rules of R. Assuming that ? is the set of all subtree decompositions of pi corresponding to derivations in ?, we define the estimate: Pr(f |pi) = 1 |?| ? ?i??</S>
			<S sid="109" ssid="73">rj??i p(rhs(rj)|lhs(rj)) (3) under the assumption: ? rj?R:lhs(rj)=lhs(ri) p(rhs(rj)|lhs(rj)) = 1 (4) It is important to notice that the probability distribution defined in Equation 3 requires a normalization factor (|?|) in order to be tight, i.e., sum to 1 over all strings fi ? F that can be derived 4We denote general probability distributions with Pr(?)</S>
			<S sid="110" ssid="74">and use p(?)</S>
			<S sid="111" ssid="75">for probabilities assigned by our models.</S>
			<S sid="112" ssid="76">964 Xa Y b a?</S>
			<S sid="113" ssid="77">b? c?c (!,f 1 ,a 1): X a Y b b?</S>
			<S sid="114" ssid="78">a? c?c (!,f 2 ,a 2): Figure 3: Example corpus.</S>
			<S sid="115" ssid="79">from pi.</S>
			<S sid="116" ssid="80">A simple example suffices to demonstrate it is not tight without normalization.</S>
			<S sid="117" ssid="81">Figure 3 contains a sample corpus from which four rules can be extracted: r1: X(a, Y(b, c)) ? a?, b?, c?</S>
			<S sid="118" ssid="82">r2: X(a, Y(b, c)) ? b?, a?, c?</S>
			<S sid="119" ssid="83">r3: X(a, x0:Y) ? a?, x0 r4: Y(b, c) ? b?, c?</S>
			<S sid="120" ssid="84">From Equation 4, the probabilities of r3 and r4 must be 1, and those of r1 and r2 must sum to 1.</S>
			<S sid="121" ssid="85">Thus, the total probability mass, which is dis-.</S>
			<S sid="122" ssid="86">tributed across two possible output strings a?b?c? and b?a?c?, is: p(a?b?c?|pi) + p(b?a?c?|pi) = p1 + p3 ? p4 + p2 = 2, where pi = p(rhs(ri)|lhs(ri)).It is relatively easy to prove that the probabil ities of all derivations that correspond to a givendecomposition ?i ? ?</S>
			<S sid="123" ssid="87">sum to 1 (the proof is omitted due to constraints on space).</S>
			<S sid="124" ssid="88">From this prop erty we can immediately conclude that the model described by Equation 3 is tight.5 We examine two estimates p(rhs(r)|lhs(r)).</S>
			<S sid="125" ssid="89">The first one is the relative frequency estimator conditioning on left hand sides: p(rhs(r)|lhs(r)) = f(r) ? r?:lhs(r?)=lhs(r) f(r ?)</S>
			<S sid="126" ssid="90">(5)f(r) represents the number of times rule r oc curred in the derivations of the training corpus.</S>
			<S sid="127" ssid="91">One of the major negative consequences of extracting only minimal rules from a corpus is that an estimator such as Equation 5 can become extremely biased.</S>
			<S sid="128" ssid="92">This again can be observed from Figure 3.</S>
			<S sid="129" ssid="93">In the minimal-rule extraction ofGHKM, only three rules are extracted from the example corpus, i.e. rules r2, r3, and r4.</S>
			<S sid="130" ssid="94">Let?s as sume now that the triple (pi, f1,a1) is represented 99 times, and (pi, f2,a2) only once.</S>
			<S sid="131" ssid="95">Given a tree pi, the model trained on that corpus can generate the two strings a?b?c? and b?a?c? only through two derivations, r3 ? r4 and r2, respectively.</S>
			<S sid="132" ssid="96">Since all rules in that example have probability 1, and 5If each tree fragment in pi is the lhs of some rule in R, then we have |?| = 2n, where n is the number of nodes of the frontier set F ? G (each node is a binary choice point).</S>
			<S sid="133" ssid="97">given that the normalization factor |?| is 2, both probabilities p(a?b?c?|pi) and p(b?a?c?|pi) are 0.5.</S>
			<S sid="134" ssid="98">On the other hand, if all rules are extracted andincorporated into our relative-frequency probabil ity model, r1 seriously counterbalances r2 and the probability of a?b?c? becomes: 12 ?( 99 100+1) = .995(since it differs from .99, the estimator remains bi ased, but to a much lesser extent).</S>
			<S sid="135" ssid="99">An alternative to the conditional model of Equation 3 is to use a joint model conditioning on the root node instead of the entire left hand side: p(r|root(r)) = f(r) ? r?:root(r?)=root(r) f(r ?)</S>
			<S sid="136" ssid="100">(6) This can be particularly useful if no parser or syntax-based language model is available, and we need to rely on the translation model to penalize ill-formed parse trees.</S>
			<S sid="137" ssid="101">Section 6 will describe an empirical evaluation based on this estimate.</S>
			<S sid="138" ssid="102">4 EM training.</S>
			<S sid="139" ssid="103">In our previous discussion of parameter estima tion, we did not explore the possibility that onederivation in a forest may be much more plausible than the others.</S>
			<S sid="140" ssid="104">If we knew which deriva tion in each forest was the ?true?</S>
			<S sid="141" ssid="105">derivation, then we could straightforwardly collect rule counts off those derivations.</S>
			<S sid="142" ssid="106">On the other hand, if we had good rule probabilities, we could compute the most likely (Viterbi) derivations for each trainingexample.</S>
			<S sid="143" ssid="107">This is a situation in which we can employ EM training, starting with uniform rule prob abilities.</S>
			<S sid="144" ssid="108">For each training example, we would like to: (1) score each derivation ?i as a product of the probabilities of the rules it contains, (2) compute a conditional probability pi for each derivation ?i(conditioned on the observed training pair) by nor malizing those scores to add to 1, and (3) collect weighted counts for each rule in each ?i, where the weight is pi.</S>
			<S sid="145" ssid="109">We can then normalize the counts to get refined probabilities, and iterate; the corpuslikelihood is guaranteed to improve with each it eration.</S>
			<S sid="146" ssid="110">While it is infeasible to enumerate the millions of derivations in each forest, Graehl and Knight (2004) demonstrate an efficient algorithm.They also analyze how to train arbitrary tree trans ducers into two steps.</S>
			<S sid="147" ssid="111">The first step is to build a derivation forest for each training example, where the forest contains those derivations licensed bythe (already supplied) transducer?s rules.</S>
			<S sid="148" ssid="112">The sec ond step employs EM on those derivation forests, running in time proportional to the size of the 965 Best minimal-rule derivation (Cm) p(r) (a) S(x0:NP-C x1:VP x2:.)</S>
			<S sid="149" ssid="113">x0 x1 x2 .845 (b) NP-C(x0:NPB) ? x0 .82 (c) NPB(DT(the) x0:NNS) ? x0 .507 (d) NNS(gunmen) ??K .559 (e) VP(VBD(were) x0:VP-C) ? x0 .434 (f) VP-C(x0:VBN x1:PP) ? x1 x0 .374 (g) PP(x0:IN x1:NP-C) ? x0 x1 .64 (h) IN(by) ??</S>
			<S sid="150" ssid="114">.0067 (i) NP-C(x0:NPB) ? x0 .82 (j) NPB(DT(the) x0:NN) ? x0 .586 (k) NN(police) ?f? .0429 (l) VBN(killed) ???</S>
			<S sid="151" ssid="115">.0072 (m) .(.)</S>
			<S sid="152" ssid="116">.981 . The gunm enw ere killed by the polic e. DT VBD VBN DT NN NP PP VP-C VPS NNS IN NP . ! #$ %  Best composed-rule derivation (C4) p(r) (o) S(NP-C(NPB(DT(the) NNS(gunmen))) x0:VP .(.)) ??K x0 . 1 (p) VP(VBD(were) VP-C(x0:VBN PP(IN(by) x1:NP-C))) ??</S>
			<S sid="153" ssid="117">x1 x0 0.00724 (q) NP-C(NPB(DT(the) NN(police))) ?f? 0.173 (r) VBN(killed) ???</S>
			<S sid="154" ssid="118">0.00719 Figure 4: Two most probable derivations for the graph on the right: the top table restricted to minimal rules; the bottom one, much more probable, using a large set of composed rules.</S>
			<S sid="155" ssid="119">Note: the derivations are constrained on the (pi, f ,a) triple, and thus include some non-literal translations with relatively low probabilities (e.g. killed, which is more commonly translated as{?).rule nb.</S>
			<S sid="156" ssid="120">of nb.</S>
			<S sid="157" ssid="121">of deriv- EM set rules nodes time time Cm 4M 192M 2 h. 4 h. C3 142M 1255M 52 h. 34 h. C4 254M 2274M 134 h. 60 h. Table 2: Rules and derivation nodes for a 54M-word, 1.95M sentence pair English-Chinese corpus, and time to build derivations (on 10 cluster nodes) and run 50 EM iterations.</S>
			<S sid="158" ssid="122">forests.</S>
			<S sid="159" ssid="123">We only need to borrow the second step for our present purposes, as we construct our own derivation forests when we acquire our rule set.A major challenge is to scale up this EM train ing to large data sets.</S>
			<S sid="160" ssid="124">We have been able to runEM for 50 iterations on our Chinese-English 54 million word corpus.</S>
			<S sid="161" ssid="125">The derivation forests for this corpus contain 2.2 billion nodes; the largest forest contains 1.1 million nodes.</S>
			<S sid="162" ssid="126">The outcome is to assign probabilities to over 254 million rules.Our EM runs with either lhs normalization or lhs root normalization.</S>
			<S sid="163" ssid="127">In the former case, each lhs has an average of three corresponding rhs?s that compete with each other for probability mass. 5 Model coverage.</S>
			<S sid="164" ssid="128">We now present some examples illustrating the benefit of composed rules.</S>
			<S sid="165" ssid="129">We trained three p(rhs(ri)|lhs(ri)) models on a 54 million-word English-Chinese parallel corpus (Table 2): the first one (Cm) with only minimal rules, and the twoothers (C3 and C4) additionally considering com posed rules with no more than three, respectively four, internal nodes in lhs(ri).</S>
			<S sid="166" ssid="130">We evaluated these models on a section of the NIST 2002 evaluation corpus, for which we built derivation forests and lhs: S(x0:NP-C VP(x1:VBD x2:NP-C) x3:.)</S>
			<S sid="167" ssid="131">corpus rhsi p(rhsi|lhs) Chinese x1 x0 x2 x3 .3681 (minimal) x0 x1 , x3 x2 .0357 x2 , x0 x1 x3 .0287 x0 x1 , x3 x2 . .0267 Chinese x0 x1 x2 x3 .9047 (composed) x0 x1 , x2 x3 .016 x0 , x1 x2 x3 .0083 x0 x1 ? x2 x3 .0072 Arabic x1 x0 x2 x3 .5874 (composed) x0 x1 x2 x3 .4027 x1 x2 x0 x3 .0077 x1 x0 x2  x3 .0001 Table 3: Our model transforms English subject-verb-object (SVO) structures into Chinese SVO and into Arabic VSO.</S>
			<S sid="168" ssid="132">With only minimal rules, Chinese VSO is wrongly preferred.</S>
			<S sid="169" ssid="133">extracted the most probable one (Viterbi) for each sentence pair (based on an automatic alignment produced by GIZA).</S>
			<S sid="170" ssid="134">We noticed in general thatViterbi derivations according to C4 make exten sive usage of composed rules, as it is the case inthe example in Figure 4.</S>
			<S sid="171" ssid="135">It shows the best deriva tion according to Cm and C4 on the unseen (pi,f,a)triple displayed on the right.</S>
			<S sid="172" ssid="136">The second deriva tion (log p = ?11.6) is much more probable than the minimal one (log p = ?17.7).</S>
			<S sid="173" ssid="137">In the case of Cm, we can see that many small rules must be applied to explain the transformation, and at eachstep, the decision regarding the re-ordering of con stituents is made with little syntactic context.</S>
			<S sid="174" ssid="138">For example, from the perspective of a decoder, theword by is immediately transformed into a prepo sition (IN), but it is in general useful to know which particular function word is present in thesentence to motivate good re-orderings in the up 966 lhs1: NP-C(x0:NPB PP(IN(of) x1:NP-C)) (NP-of-NP) lhs2: PP(IN(of) NP-C(x0:NPB PP(IN(of) NP-C(x1:NPB x2:VP)))) (of-NP-of-NP-VP) lhs3: VP(VBD(said) SBAR-C(IN(that) x0:S-C)) (said-that-S) lhs4: SBAR(WHADVP(WRB(when)) S-C(x0:NP-C VP(VBP(are) x1:VP-C))) (when-NP-are-VP) rhs1i p(rhs1i|lhs1) rhs2i p(rhs2i|lhs2) rhs3i p(rhs3i|lhs3) rhs4i p(rhs4i|lhs4) x1 x0 .54 x2 ? x1 ? x0 .6754 ? , x0 .6062 ( x1 x0 ? .6618 x0 x1 .2351 ( x2 ? x1 ? x0 .035 ? x0 .1073 S x1 x0 ? .0724 x1 ? x0 .0334 x2 ? x1 ? x0 , .0263 h: , x0 .0591 ( x1 x0 ? , .0579 x1 x0 ? .026 x2 ? x1 ? x0 .0116 ? ?</S>
			<S sid="175" ssid="139">, x0 .0234 , ( x1 x0 ? .0289 Table 4: Translation probabilities promote linguistically motivated constituent re-orderings (for lhs1 and lhs2), and enable non-constituent (lhs3) and non-contiguous (lhs4) phrasal translations.per levels of the tree.</S>
			<S sid="176" ssid="140">A rule like (e) is particu larly unfortunate, since it allows the word were to be added without any other evidence that the VP should be in passive voice.</S>
			<S sid="177" ssid="141">On the other hand, the composed-rule derivation of C4 incorporates more linguistic evidence in its rules, and re-orderings are motivated by more syntactic context.</S>
			<S sid="178" ssid="142">Rule (p) is particularly appropriate to create a passive VP construct, since it expects a Chinese passive marker (?), an NP-C, and a verb in its rhs, and creates the were ... by construction at once in the left hand side.</S>
			<S sid="179" ssid="143">5.1 Syntactic translation tables.</S>
			<S sid="180" ssid="144">We evaluate the promise of our SBTM by analyz ing instances of translation tables (t-table).</S>
			<S sid="181" ssid="145">Table 3shows how a particular form of SVO construc tion is transformed into Chinese, which is also anSVO language.</S>
			<S sid="182" ssid="146">While the t-table for Chinese com posed rules clearly gives good estimates for the?correct?</S>
			<S sid="183" ssid="147">x0 x1 ordering (p = .9), i.e. subject before verb, the t-table for minimal rules unreason ably gives preference to verb-subject ordering (x1x0, p = .37), because the most probable transfor mation (x0 x1) does not correspond to a minimal rule.</S>
			<S sid="184" ssid="148">We obtain different results with Arabic, an VSO language, and our model effectively learns to move the subject after the verb (p = .59).</S>
			<S sid="185" ssid="149">lhs1 in Table 4 shows that our model is able to learn large-scale constituent re-orderings, such as re-ordering NPs in a NP-of-NP construction, and put the modifier first as it is more commonlythe case in Chinese (p = .54).</S>
			<S sid="186" ssid="150">If more syntac tic context is available as in lhs2, our modelprovides much sharper estimates, and appropri ately reverses the order of three constituents with high probability (p = .68), inserting modifiers first (possessive markers?</S>
			<S sid="187" ssid="151">are needed here for better syntactic disambiguation).</S>
			<S sid="188" ssid="152">A limitation of earlier syntax-based systems is their poor handling of non-constituent phrases.</S>
			<S sid="189" ssid="153">Table 4 shows that our model can learn rules for such phrases, e.g., said that (lhs3).</S>
			<S sid="190" ssid="154">While the that has no direct translation, our model effectively learns to separate?</S>
			<S sid="191" ssid="155">(said) from the relative clause with a comma, which is common in Chinese.</S>
			<S sid="192" ssid="156">Another promising prospect of our model seems to lie in its ability to handle non-contiguous phrases, a feature that state of the art systemssuch as (Och and Ney, 2004) do not incorpo rate.</S>
			<S sid="193" ssid="157">The when-NP-are-VP construction of lhs4 presents such a case.</S>
			<S sid="194" ssid="158">Our model identifies that are needs to be deleted, that when translates into the phrase( ...?, and that the NP needs to be moved after the VP in Chinese (p = .66).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Empirical evaluation. " number="6">
			<S sid="195" ssid="1">The task of our decoder is to find the most likely English tree pi that maximizes all models involved in Equation 2.</S>
			<S sid="196" ssid="2">Since xRs rules can be converted to context-free productions by increasing the number of non-terminals, we implemented our decoder as a standard CKY parser with beam search.</S>
			<S sid="197" ssid="3">Its rule binarization is described in (Zhang et al, 2006).</S>
			<S sid="198" ssid="4">We compare our syntax-based system against an implementation of the alignment template (AlTemp) approach to MT (Och and Ney, 2004), which is widely considered to represent the state of the art in the field.</S>
			<S sid="199" ssid="5">We registered both systems in the NIST 2005 evaluation; results are presented in Table 5.</S>
			<S sid="200" ssid="6">With a difference of 6.4 BLEU points for both language pairs, we consider the resultsof our syntax-based system particularly promis ing, since these are the highest scores to date thatwe know of using linguistic syntactic transformations.</S>
			<S sid="201" ssid="7">Also, on the one hand, our AlTemp system represents quite mature technology, and in corporates highly tuned model parameters.</S>
			<S sid="202" ssid="8">On the other hand, our syntax decoder is still work in progress: only one model was used during search, i.e., the EM-trained root-normalized SBTM, and as yet no language model is incorporated in thesearch (whereas the search in the AlTemp sys tem uses two phrase-based translation models and 967 Syntactic AlTemp Arabic-to-English 40.2 46.6 Chinese-to-English 24.3 30.7 Table 5: BLEU-4 scores for the 2005 NIST test set.</S>
			<S sid="203" ssid="9">Cm C3 C4 Chinese-to-English 24.47 27.42 28.1 Table 6: BLEU-4 scores for the 2002 NIST test set, with rules of increasing sizes.12 other feature functions).</S>
			<S sid="204" ssid="10">Furthermore, our decoder doesn?t incorporate any syntax-based language model, and admittedly our ability to penal ize ill-formed parse trees is still limited.Finally, we evaluated our system on the NIST 02 test set with the three different rule sets (see Table 6).</S>
			<S sid="205" ssid="11">The performance with our largest rule set represents a 3.63 BLEU point increase (14.8% relative) compared to using only minimal rules, which indicates positive prospects for using even larger rules.</S>
			<S sid="206" ssid="12">While our rule inference algorithm scales to higher thresholds, one important area offuture work will be the improvement of our de coder, conjointly with analyses of the impact in terms of BLEU of contextually richer rules.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Related work. " number="7">
			<S sid="207" ssid="1">Similarly to (Poutsma, 2000; Wu, 1997; Yamadaand Knight, 2001; Chiang, 2005), the rules dis cussed in this paper are equivalent to productions of synchronous tree substitution grammars.</S>
			<S sid="208" ssid="2">We believe that our tree-to-string model has several advantages over tree-to-tree transformations such as the ones acquired by Poutsma (2000).</S>
			<S sid="209" ssid="3">While tree-to-tree grammars are richer formalisms thatprovide the potential benefit of rules that are lin guistically better motivated, modeling the syntax of both languages comes as an extra cost, and itis admittedly more helpful to focus our syntac tic modeling effort on the target language (e.g., English) in cases where it has syntactic resources (parsers and treebanks) that are considerably moreavailable than for the source language.</S>
			<S sid="210" ssid="4">Further more, we think there is, overall, less benefit in modeling the syntax of the source language, since the input sentence is fixed during decoding and is generally already grammatical.</S>
			<S sid="211" ssid="5">With the notable exception of Poutsma, most related works rely on models that are restricted to synchronous context-free grammars (SCFG).While the state-of-the-art hierarchical SMT system (Chiang, 2005) performs well despite stringent constraints imposed on its context-free gram mar, we believe its main advantage lies in its ability to extract hierarchical rules across phrasal boundaries.</S>
			<S sid="212" ssid="6">Context-free grammars (such as PennTreebank and Chiang?s grammars) make independence assumptions that are arguably often unrea sonable, but as our work suggests, relaxations of these assumptions by using contextually richer rules results in translations of increasing quality.</S>
			<S sid="213" ssid="7">We believe it will be beneficial to account for this finding in future work in syntax-based SMT and in efforts to improve upon (Chiang, 2005).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions. " number="8">
			<S sid="214" ssid="1">In this paper, we developed probability models for the multi-level transfer rules presented in (Galley et al, 2004), showed how to acquire larger rules that crucially condition on more syntactic context, and how to pack multiple derivations, including interpretations of unaligned words, into derivation forests.</S>
			<S sid="215" ssid="2">We presented some theoretical argumentsfor not limiting extraction to minimal rules, val idated them on concrete examples, and presented experiments showing that contextually richer rulesprovide a 3.63 BLEU point increase over the min imal rules of (Galley et al, 2004).</S>
			<S sid="216" ssid="3">AcknowledgmentsWe would like to thank anonymous review ers for their helpful comments and suggestions.</S>
			<S sid="217" ssid="4">This work was partially supported under theGALE program of the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, Contract No.</S>
			<S sid="218" ssid="5">HR0011 06-C-0022.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
