<COMMUNITY>
 <S sid ="2" ssid = "2">The model has the advantage that a pre-tagged training corpus is not required.</S> 
 <S sid ="27" ssid = "27">The work described here also makes use of a hidden Markov model.</S>
 <S sid ="29" ssid = "29">In this regard, word equivalence classes were used (Kupiec, 1989).</S><S sid ="30" ssid = "30">There it is assumed that the distribution of the use of a word depends on the set of categories it can assume, and words are partitioned accordingly.</S>
 <S sid ="87" ssid = "87">An alternative to uniformly increasing the order of the conditioning is to extend it selectively.</S><S sid ="88" ssid = "88">Mixed higher- order context can be modeled by introducing explicit state sequences.</S>
 <S sid ="29" ssid = "29">In this regard, word equivalence classes were used (Kupiec, 1989).</S><S sid ="30" ssid = "30">There it is assumed that the distribution of the use of a word depends on the set of categories it can assume, and words are partitioned accordingly.</S>
 <S sid ="69" ssid = "69">In a ranked list of words in the corpus the most frequent 100 words account for approximately 50% of the total tokens in the corpus, and thus data is available to estimate them reliably.</S><S sid ="70" ssid = "70">The most frequent 100 words of the corpus were assigned individually in the model, thereby enabling them to have different distributions over their categories.</S>
 <S sid ="88" ssid = "88">Mixed higher- order context can be modeled by introducing explicit state sequences.</S>
 <S sid ="89" ssid = "89">In the arrangement the basic first-order network remains, permitting all possible category sequences, and modeling first-order dependency.</S>
 <S sid ="90" ssid = "90">The basic network is then augmented with the extra state sequences which model certain category sequences in more detail.</S>
 <S sid ="124" ssid = "124">A model containing all of the refinements described, was tested using a magazine article containing 146 sentences (3,822 words).</S>
 <S sid ="125" ssid = "125">A 30,000 word dictionary was used, supplemented by inflectional analysis for words not found directly in the dictionary.</S>
 <S sid ="145" ssid = "145">A stochastic method for assigning part-of-speech categories to unrestricted English text has been described.</S>
 </COMMUNITY>