<PAPER>
  <S sid="0" ssid="0">A Maximum Entropy Model for Prepositional Phrase Attachment Adwait Ratnaparkhi, Jeff  Reynar,* and Salim Roukos IBM Research  D iv is ion Thomas  J. Watson  Research  Center York town Heights ,  NY  10598 1.</S>
  <S sid="1" ssid="1">Introduction A parser for natural language must often choose between two or more equally grammatical parses for the same sentence.</S>
  <S sid="2" ssid="2">Often the correct parse can be determined from the lexical properties of certain key words or from the context in which the sentence occurs.</S>
  <S sid="3" ssid="3">For example in the sentence, In July, the Environmental Protection Agency imposed agrad- ual ban on virtually all uses of asbestos.</S>
  <S sid="4" ssid="4">the prepositional phrase on virtually all uses of asbestos can attach to either the noun phrase a gradual ban, yielding [vP imposed [JvP a gradual ban [pp on virtually all uses of asbestos ]] ], or the verb phrase imposed, yielding [vP imposed [uP a gradual ban ][iop on virtually all uses off asbestos ]].</S>
  <S sid="5" ssid="5">For this example, a human annotators attachment decision, which for our purposes is the "correct" attachment, is to the noun phrase.</S>
  <S sid="6" ssid="6">We present in this paper methods for con- structing statistical models for computing the probability of attachment decisions.</S>
  <S sid="7" ssid="7">These models could be then integrated into scoring the probability of an overall parse.</S>
  <S sid="8" ssid="8">We present our methods in the context of prepositional phrase (PP) at- tachment.</S>
  <S sid="9" ssid="9">Earlier work [11 ] on PP-attachment for verb phrases (whether the PP attaches to the preceding noun phrase or to the verb phrase) used statistics on co-occurences of two bigrams: the main verb (V) and preposition (P) bigram and the main noun in the object noun phrase (N1) and preposition bigram.</S>
  <S sid="10" ssid="10">In this paper, we explore the use of more features to help in modeling the distribution of the binary PP-attachment deci- sion.</S>
  <S sid="11" ssid="11">We also describe a search procedure for selecting a "good" subset of features from a much larger pool of features for PP-attachment.</S>
  <S sid="12" ssid="12">Obviously, the feature search cannot be * Jeff Reynar, f rom University of  Pennsylvania, worked on this project as a summer  student at I .B.M.</S>
  <S sid="13" ssid="13">guaranteed tobe optimal but appears experimentally to yield a good subset of features as judged by the accuracy rate in making the PP-attachment decisons.</S>
  <S sid="14" ssid="14">These search strategies can be applied to other attachment decisions.</S>
  <S sid="15" ssid="15">We use data from two treebanks: the IBM-Lancaster Treebank of Computer Manuals and the University of Pennsylvania WSJ treebank.</S>
  <S sid="16" ssid="16">We extract he verb phrases which include PP phrases either attached to the verb or to an object noun phrase.</S>
  <S sid="17" ssid="17">Then our model assigns a probability to either of the possible attachments.</S>
  <S sid="18" ssid="18">We consider models of the exponential family that are derived using the Maximum Entropy Principle [1].</S>
  <S sid="19" ssid="19">We begin by an overview of ME models, then we describe our feature selection method and a method for constructing a larger pool of features from an exisiting set, and then give some of our results and conclusions.</S>
  <S sid="20" ssid="20">Maximum Entropy Modeling The Maximum Entropy model [1] produces aprobability dis- tribution for the PP-attachment decision using only informa- tion from the verb phrase in which the attachment occurs.</S>
  <S sid="21" ssid="21">We denote the partially parsed verb phrase, i.e., the verb phrase without the attachment decision, as a history h, and the conditional probability of an attachment asp(dlh), where d 6 .</S>
  <S sid="22" ssid="22">[0, 1} and corresponds to a noun or verb attachment (respectively).</S>
  <S sid="23" ssid="23">The probability model depends on certain features of the whole event (h, d) denoted by fi(h, d).</S>
  <S sid="24" ssid="24">An example of a binary-valued feature function is the indicator function that a particular (V, P)  bigram occured along with the attachment decision being V, i.e.</S>
  <S sid="25" ssid="25">fprint,on(h, d) is one if and only if the main verb of h is "print", the preposition is "on", and d is "V".</S>
  <S sid="26" ssid="26">As discussed in [6], the ME principle leads to a model for p(dlh ) which maximizes the training data log-likelihood, a) log p(dlh), h,d where ~(h, w) is the empirical distribution of the training set, and where p(dlh ) itself is an exponential model: 250 p(dlh) = k 11 eXY(hd) i=0 1 k YI e~f(h"0 d=0 i=0 4.</S>
  <S sid="27" ssid="27">Head Noun of the Object of the Preposition (N2) For example, questions on the history "imposed a gradual ban on virtually all uses of asbestos", can only ask about he following four words: At the maximum of the training data log-likelihood, the model has the property that its k parameters, namely the Ats, satisfy k constraints on the expected values of feature functions, where the ith constraint is, EmA = #.f~ imposed ban  on uses The notion of a "head" word here corresponds loosely to the notion of a lexical head.</S>
  <S sid="28" ssid="28">We use a small set of rules, called a Tree Head Table, to obtain the head word of a constituent [12].</S>
  <S sid="29" ssid="29">We allow two types of binary-valued questions: The model expected value is, Emf~ = ~(h)p(d lh ) f i (h ,  d) h,d 1.</S>
  <S sid="30" ssid="30">Questions about the presence of any n-gram (n _&lt; 4) of the four head words, e.g., a bigram maybe {V == i s    ,  P ==   o f    }.</S>
  <S sid="31" ssid="31">Features comprised solely of questions on words are denoted as "word" features.</S>
  <S sid="32" ssid="32">and the training data expected value, also called the desired value, is $f ,  = d)f,(h, d) h,d The values of these k parameters can be obtained by one of many iterative algorithms.</S>
  <S sid="33" ssid="33">For example, one can use the Gen- eralized Iterative Scaling algorithm of Darroch and Ratcliff [3].</S>
  <S sid="34" ssid="34">As one increases the number of features, the achievable maximum of the training data likelihood increases.</S>
  <S sid="35" ssid="35">We de- scribe in Section 3 a method for determining a reliable set of features.</S>
  <S sid="36" ssid="36">Features Feature functions allow us to use informative characteristics of the training set in estimating p(dlh).</S>
  <S sid="37" ssid="37">A feature is defined as follows: -.~(h,d) d~_f ~1, i f fd=OandVq6 Q~,q(h)= 1 O, otherwise.</S>
  <S sid="38" ssid="38">I. where Q~ is a set of binary-valued questions about h. We restrict he questions in any Q~ ask only about he following four head words: I.</S>
  <S sid="39" ssid="39">Head Verb (V) 2.</S>
  <S sid="40" ssid="40">Head Noun (N1) 3.</S>
  <S sid="41" ssid="41">Head Preposition (P) .</S>
  <S sid="42" ssid="42">Questions that involve the class membership of a head word.</S>
  <S sid="43" ssid="43">we use a binary hierarchy of classes derived by mutual information clustering which we describe below.</S>
  <S sid="44" ssid="44">Given a binary class hierarchy, we can associate a bit string with every word in the vocabulary.</S>
  <S sid="45" ssid="45">Then, by querying the value of certain bit positions we can con- stmct binary questions.</S>
  <S sid="46" ssid="46">For example, we can ask whether about a bit position for any of the four head words, e.g., Bi t  5 of P repos i t ion  == i.</S>
  <S sid="47" ssid="47">We discuss be- low a richer set of these questions.</S>
  <S sid="48" ssid="48">Features comprised solely of questions about class bits are denoted as "class" features, and features containing questions about both class bits and words are denoted as "mixed" features 1.</S>
  <S sid="49" ssid="49">Before discussing, feature selection and construction, we give a brief overview of the mutual information clustering of words.</S>
  <S sid="50" ssid="50">Mutual Information Bits Mutual information clustering, as described in [10], creates a a class "tree" for a given vocab- ulary.</S>
  <S sid="51" ssid="51">Initially, we take the C most frequent words (usually 1000) and assign each one to its own class.</S>
  <S sid="52" ssid="52">We then take the (C + 1)st word, assign it to its own class, and merge the pair of classes that minimize the loss of average mutual informa- tion.</S>
  <S sid="53" ssid="53">This repeats until all the words in the vocabulary have been exhausted.</S>
  <S sid="54" ssid="54">We then take our C classes, and use the same algorithm to merge classes that minimize the loss of mutual information, until one class remains.</S>
  <S sid="55" ssid="55">If we trace the order in which words and classes are merged, we can form a binary tree whose leaves consists of words and whose root is the class which spans the entire vocabulary.</S>
  <S sid="56" ssid="56">Consequently, we uniquely identify each word by its path from the root, which 1 See Table 7 for examples of  features 251 can be represented by a string of binary digits.</S>
  <S sid="57" ssid="57">If a path lengt of a word is less than the maximum depth, we pad the bottor of the path with Os (dummy left branches), so that all word are represented by an equally long bitstring.</S>
  <S sid="58" ssid="58">"Class" feature query the value of bits, and hence examine the path of th word in the mutual information tree.</S>
  <S sid="59" ssid="59">Special Features In addition to the types of features de scribed above, we employ two special features in the MI model, the: Complement and the Null feature.</S>
  <S sid="60" ssid="60">The Comple ment, defined as fcomr,(h,d) dJ {1,0, otherwise.ifffi(hd)=0Vfi 6.,%4 will fire on a pair (h, d) when no other fi in the model applie,, The Initial feature is simply clef I1, i f fd=O fn~zz(h, d) = ~, 0, otherwise and causes the ME model to match the a pr  i o r  i probability of seeing an N-attachment.</S>
  <S sid="61" ssid="61">Feature  Search The search problem here is to find an optimal set of features A4 for use in the ME model.</S>
  <S sid="62" ssid="62">We begin with a search space 79 of putative features, and use a feature ranking criterion which incrementally selects the features in .A4, and also incremen- tally expands the search space 79.</S>
  <S sid="63" ssid="63">Initially 79 consists of all 1, 2, 3 and 4-gram word features of the four headwords that occur in the training histories 2, and 4 all possible unigram class features 3.</S>
  <S sid="64" ssid="64">We obtain E (~) = 15 k=l word features from each training history, and, assuming each word is assigned m bits, a total of 2m * 4 unigram class features, e.g., there are 2m features per word: B i t  1 o f Verb  == O, B i t  1 o f  Verb  == 1 .</S>
  <S sid="65" ssid="65">B i t  m o f  Verb  == 0, B i t  m o f  Verb  ==I The feature search then proceeds as follows: 1.</S>
  <S sid="66" ssid="66">Initialize 79 as described above, initialize A,4 to contain complement and null feature 2.</S>
  <S sid="67" ssid="67">Select the best feature from 79 using Delta-Likelihood rank 3.</S>
  <S sid="68" ssid="68">Add it to .A4 2With a certain f requency cut-off, usual ly 3 to 5 3 Also with a certain f requency cut-off 0.85 0.8 0.75 0.7 0.65 0.6 0.55 0.5 PERFORMANCE: Wall St. Journal io io .</S>
  <S sid="69" ssid="69">20 1 O0 120 140 160 180 200 Figure 1" Performance of Maximum Entropy Model on Wall St. Journal Data 4.</S>
  <S sid="70" ssid="70">Train Maximum Entropy Model, using features in .A4 5.</S>
  <S sid="71" ssid="71">Grow 79 based on last feature selected 6. repeat from (2) If we measure the training entropy and test entropy after the addition of each feature, the training entropy will monotoni- cally decrease while the test entropy will eventually reach a minimum (due to overtraining).</S>
  <S sid="72" ssid="72">Test set performance usually peaks at the test entropy minimum ( see Fig.</S>
  <S sid="73" ssid="73">Delta-Likelihood At step (2) in the search, we rank all fea- tures in 7 9 by estimating their potential contribution to the log-likelihood of the training set.</S>
  <S sid="74" ssid="74">Let q be the conditional probability distribution of the model with the features cur- rently in A,4.</S>
  <S sid="75" ssid="75">Then for each f~ 6 79, we compute, by estimat- ing only ~,  the probability distribution p that results when fi is added to the ME model: p(dlh) = q(dlh)e~J,(h, d) 1 E q(wlh) e~J(h?)</S>
  <S sid="76" ssid="76">=0 We then compute the increase in (log) likelihood with the new model: 6L, = ~IS(h,  w)lnp(wlh ) - ~e~(h, w)lnq(wlh ) h,w h,w and choose the feature with the highest 6L.</S>
  <S sid="77" ssid="77">Features redun- dmlt or correlated to those features already in .A.4 will produce 252 1 0.9 0.~ 0.7 0.6 0.5 ENTROPY: Wall St. Journal Training 0.4 20 A dO dO .</S>
  <S sid="78" ssid="78">100 120 140 160 180 200 Figure 2: Entropy of Maximum Entropy Model on Wall St. Journal Data a zero or negligible 6L, and will therefore be outranked by genuinely informative features.</S>
  <S sid="79" ssid="79">The chosen feature is added to M and used in the ME Model.</S>
  <S sid="80" ssid="80">Growth of Putative Feature Set At step (5) in the search we expand the space 7 ~ of putative features based on the feature last selected from 72 for addition to M.  Given an n-gram feature f~ (i.e., of type "word", "class" or"mixed") that was last added to M,  we create 2m.4 new n + 1-gram features which ask questions about class bits in addition to the questions asked in fi.</S>
  <S sid="81" ssid="81">E.g., let fi(h, d) constrain d = 0 and constrain h with the questions v == imposed    , P ==   on    Then, given fi(h,d), the 2m new features generated for just the Head Noun are the following: V ==   imposed   ,  P == ~on   , B i t  1 fo r  Noun == 0 V ==   imposed   ,  P ==  on   , B i t  1 fo r  Noun == 1 V ==   imposed   ,  P == B i t  m fo r  Noun == 0 on V ==   imposed   ,  P ==  on   , B i t  m fo r  Noun == 1 We construct he remaining 6m features imilarly from the remaining 3head words.</S>
  <S sid="82" ssid="82">We skip the construction of features Computer Manuals Wall St. Journal Training Events 8264 20801 Test Events 943 3097 Table 1: Size of Data containing questions that are inconsistent or redundant with those word or class questions in fi.</S>
  <S sid="83" ssid="83">The newly created features are then added to P,  and compete for selection in the next Delta-Likelihood ranking process.</S>
  <S sid="84" ssid="84">This method allows the introduction of complex features on word classes while keeping the search space manageable; "P grows linearly with .M.</S>
  <S sid="85" ssid="85">Resu l ts We applied the Maximum Entropy model to sentences from two corpora, the I.B.M.</S>
  <S sid="86" ssid="86">Computer Manuals Data, annotated by Univ.</S>
  <S sid="87" ssid="87">of Lancaster, and the Wall St. Journal Data, annotated by Univ.</S>
  <S sid="88" ssid="88">The size of the training sets, test sets, and the results are shown in Tables 1 &amp; 2.</S>
  <S sid="89" ssid="89">The experiments in Table 2 differ in the following manner: "Words Only" The search space P begins with all possible n-gram word features with n being 1, 2, 3,or 4; this feature set does not grow during the feature search.</S>
  <S sid="90" ssid="90">"Classes Only" The search space P begins with only un- igram class features, and grows by dynamically contructing class n-gram questions as described earlier.</S>
  <S sid="91" ssid="91">"Word and Classes" The search space P begins with all possible n-gram word features and unigram class features, and grows by adding class questions (as described earlier).</S>
  <S sid="92" ssid="92">The results in Table 2 are achieved in the neighborhood of about 200 features.</S>
  <S sid="93" ssid="93">As can be seen in Figure 1, performance improves quickly as features are added and improves rather very slowly after the 60-th feature.</S>
  <S sid="94" ssid="94">The performance is fairly close for the various feature sets when a sufficient number of features are added.</S>
  <S sid="95" ssid="95">We also compared these results to a deci- sion tree grown on the same 4 head-word events.</S>
  <S sid="96" ssid="96">The same Experiment Computer Manuals Wall St. Journal Words Only 82.2% 77.7% Classes Only 84.5% 79.1% Words and Classes 84.1% 81.6% Table 2: Performance of ME Model on Test Events 253 Domain Performance Computer Manuals 79.5% Wall St. Journal 77.7% Table 3: Decision Tree Performance mutual intbrmation bits were used for growing the decision trees.</S>
  <S sid="97" ssid="97">Table 3 gives the results on the same training and test data.</S>
  <S sid="98" ssid="98">The ]VIE models are slightly better than the decision tree models.</S>
  <S sid="99" ssid="99">For comparison, we obtained the PP-attachment performances of 3 treebanking experts on a set of 300 randomly selected test events from the WSJ corpus.</S>
  <S sid="100" ssid="100">In the first trial, they were given only the four head words to make the attachment decision, and in the next, they were given the headwords along with the sentence in which they occurred.</S>
  <S sid="101" ssid="101">Figure 3 shows an example of the head words test a.</S>
  <S sid="102" ssid="102">The results of the treebankers and the performance of the ME model on that same set are shown in Table 5.</S>
  <S sid="103" ssid="103">We also identified the set of 274 events on which treebankers, given the sentence, unanimously agreed.</S>
  <S sid="104" ssid="104">We defined this to be the truth set.</S>
  <S sid="105" ssid="105">We show in Table 6 the agreement on PP-attachment of the original WSJ treebank parses with this consensus set, the average performance of the 3 human experts with head words only, and the ME model.</S>
  <S sid="106" ssid="106">The WSJ treebank indicates the accuracy rate of our training data, the human performance indicates how much information is in the headwords, and the ME model is still a good 12 4 the key is N,V,N,N,V, N,N,N,N,V,V,N,V,N,N,N,V,N,V percentage points behind.</S>
  <S sid="107" ssid="107">Selection Order Feature (1) Preposition == "of" (2) Bit 2 of Head Noun == 0 (3) Preposition is "to" (4) Bit 12 of Head Noun == 1 (9) Head Noun == "million", Preposition == "in" (30) Preposition == "to", Bit 8 of Object == 1 (47) Preposition == "in", Object == "months" Table 4: Examples of Features Chosen for Wall St. Journal Data Average Human(head words only) ~ 88.2% Average Human(with whole sentence) 93.2% ME Model 78.0% Table 5: Average Performance of Human &amp; ME Model on 300 Events of WSJ Data # Events % WSJ TB Human ME Model in Consensus Performance Performance Performance 274 95.7% 92.5% 80.7% Table 6: Human and ME model performance on consensus set for WSJ report mi l l l ion  in charges report mi l l l ion  for quarter ref lect ing sett lement of contracts carr ied all but one were in jur ies among workers had damage to bui ld ing be damage to some uses var ia t ion  of design c i ted example of d istr ict leads Pepsi in share trai ls Pepsi in sales r isk conf l ict  w i th  U.S. r isk conf l ict  over p lan oppose seat ing as delegate save some of plants introduced vers ions of cars lowered bids in ant ic ipat ion oversees trading on Nasdaq gained 1 to 19 Figure 3: Sample of 4 head words for PP-attachment We also obtained the performances of 3 non-experts on a set of 200 randomly selected test events from the Computer Manuals corpus.</S>
  <S sid="108" ssid="108">In this trial, the participants made attachment decisions given only the four head words.</S>
  <S sid="109" ssid="109">The results are shown in Table 7.</S>
  <S sid="110" ssid="110">Conclusion The Maximum Entropy model predicts prepositional phrase attachment 10 percentage points less accurately than a tree- banker, but it performs comparably toa non-expert, assuming that only only the head words of the history are available in both cases.</S>
  <S sid="111" ssid="111">The biggest improvements to the ME model will come from better utilization of classes, and a larger history.</S>
  <S sid="112" ssid="112">Currently, the use of the mutual information class bits gives us a few percentage points in performance, but the ME model should gain more from other word classing schemes which are better tuned to the PP-attachment problem.</S>
  <S sid="113" ssid="113">A scheme in which the word classes are built from the observed attach- ment preferences of words ought to outperform the mutual information clustering method, which uses only word bigram distributions[10].</S>
  <S sid="114" ssid="114">254 I Average Human I 77-3% ] ME Model 83.5% Table 7: Average Performance of Human &amp; ME Model on 200 Events of Computer Manuals Data Secondly, the ME model does not use information contained in the rest of the sentence, although it is apparently useful in predicting the attachment, as evidenced by a 5% average gain in the treebankers accuracy.</S>
  <S sid="115" ssid="115">Any implementation f this model using the rest of the sentence would require features on other words, and perhaps features on the sentences parse tree structure, coupled with an efficient incremental search.</S>
  <S sid="116" ssid="116">Such improvements should boost the performance of the model to that of treebankers.</S>
  <S sid="117" ssid="117">Already, the ME model out- performs a decision tree confronted with the same task.</S>
  <S sid="118" ssid="118">We hope to use Maximum Entropy to predict other linguistic phe- nomena that hinder the performance of most natural anguage parsers.</S>
  <S sid="119" ssid="119">Jaynes, E. T., "Information Theory and Statistical Mechanics."</S>
  <S sid="120" ssid="120">Kullback, S., Information Theory in Statistics.</S>
  <S sid="121" ssid="121">Wiley, New York, 1959.</S>
  <S sid="122" ssid="122">and Ratcliff, D., "Generalized Iterative Scaling for Log-Linear Models", The Annals of Mathematical Statis- tics, Vol.</S>
  <S sid="123" ssid="123">43, pp 1470-1480, 1972.</S>
  <S sid="124" ssid="124">Delia Pietra,S., Della Pietra, V., Mercer, R. L., Roukos, S., "Adaptive Language Modeling Using Minimum Discriminant Estimation," Proceedings oflCASSP-92, pp.</S>
  <S sid="125" ssid="125">1-633-636, San Francisco, March 1992.</S>
  <S sid="126" ssid="126">Brown, P., Delia Pietra, S., Della Pietra, V., Mercer, R., Nadas, A., and Roukos, S., "Maximum Entropy Methods and Their Applications to Maximum Likelihood Parameter Estimation of Conditional Exponential Models," A forthcoming IBM techni- cal report.</S>
  <S sid="127" ssid="127">Berger, A., Della Pietra, S.A., and Della Pietra, V.J.. Maxi- mum Entropy Methods in Machine Translation.</S>
  <S sid="128" ssid="128">manuscript in preparation.</S>
  <S sid="129" ssid="129">Black, E., Garside, R., and Leech, G., 1993.</S>
  <S sid="130" ssid="130">Statistically- driven Computer Grammars of English: The IBM/Lancaster Approach.</S>
  <S sid="131" ssid="131">Atlanta, Georgia.</S>
  <S sid="132" ssid="132">Black, E., Jelinek, F., Lafferty, J., Magerman, D. M., Mercer, R., and Roukos, S., 1993.</S>
  <S sid="133" ssid="133">Towards History-based Grammars: Using Richer Models for Probabilistic Parsing.</S>
  <S sid="134" ssid="134">In Proceed- ings of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 1993.</S>
  <S sid="135" ssid="135">Columbus, Ohio.</S>
  <S sid="136" ssid="136">Breiman, L., Friedman, J. H., Olshen, R. A., and Stone, C. J., 1984.</S>
  <S sid="137" ssid="137">Classification and Regression Trees.</S>
  <S sid="138" ssid="138">Wadsworth and Brooks.</S>
  <S sid="139" ssid="139">Pacific Grove, California.</S>
  <S sid="140" ssid="140">Brown, P. F., Della Pietra, V. J., deSouza, P. V., Lai, J. C., and Mercer, R. L. Class-based n-gram Models of Natural Language.</S>
  <S sid="141" ssid="141">In Proceedings of the IBM Natural Language 1TL, March, 1990.</S>
  <S sid="142" ssid="142">Hindle, D. and Rooth, M. 1990.</S>
  <S sid="143" ssid="143">Structural Ambiguity and Lex- ical Relations.</S>
  <S sid="144" ssid="144">In Proceedings ofthe June 1990 DARPA Speech and Natural Language Workshop.</S>
  <S sid="145" ssid="145">Hidden Valley, Pennsylva- nia.</S>
  <S sid="146" ssid="146">Magerman, D., 1994.</S>
  <S sid="147" ssid="147">Natural Language Parsing as Statistical Pattern Recognition.</S>
  <S sid="148" ssid="148">Ph.D. dissertation, Stanford University, California.</S>
</PAPER>
