<COMMUNITY>
<S sid="0">Strategic Lazy Incremental Copy Graph Unification</S><S sid ="3" ssid = "3">The other, called ti~e strategic incremental copy graph unification method, uses an early failure finding strategy which first tries to unify :;ubstructures tending to fail in unification; this method is; based on stochastic data on tim likelihood of failure and ,&apos;educes unnecessary computation.</S><S sid ="11" ssid = "11">For example, a spoken Present.</S><S sid ="14" ssid = "14">Japanese analysis system based on llPSG[Kogure 891 uses 90% - 98% of the elapsed time in FS unification.</S><S sid ="21" ssid = "21">itowever, the problem with his method is that a unitication result graph consists only of newly created structures.</S><S sid ="22" ssid = "22">This is unnecessary because there are often input snbgraphs that can be used as part of the result graph without any modification, or as sharable parts between one of the input graphs and the result graph.</S><S sid ="23" ssid = "23">Copying sharable parts is called redundant copying.</S><S sid ="24" ssid = "24">A better method would nfinimize the copying of sharable varts.</S><S sid ="24" ssid = "24">A better method would nfinimize the copying of sharable varts.</S><S sid ="39" ssid = "39">This paper proposes an FS unification method that allows structure sharing with constant m&apos;der node access time.</S><S sid ="40" ssid = "40">This method achieves structure sharing by introducing lazy copying to Wroblewski&apos;s incremental copy graph unification method.</S><S sid ="78" ssid = "22">Then, the unification of tl anti t2 is defined as their greatest lower bound or the meet.</S><S sid ="141" ssid = "2">5 disables structure sharing, ttowever, this whole copying is not necessary if a lazy evaluation method is used.</S><S sid ="142" ssid = "3">With such a method, it is possible to delay copying a node until either its own contents need to change (e.g., node G3/Ka c !7&gt;) or until it is found to have an arc (sequence) to a node t, hat needs to be copied (e.g., node X G3/&lt;a c&gt; in Fig.</S><S sid ="186" ssid = "8">in this method, theretbre, the failure tendency information is acquired by a learning process.</S><S sid ="187" ssid = "9">That is, the SING unification method applied in an analysis system uses the failure tendency information acquired by a learning analysis process.</S><S sid ="188" ssid = "10">in the learning process, when FS unification is applied, feature treatment orders are randomized for the sake of random extraction.</S><S sid ="203" ssid = "2">The LING unification method achieves structure sharing without the O(log d) data access overhead of Pereira&apos;s method.</S><S sid ="205" ssid = "4">Furthermore, structure sharing increases the portion of token identical substructures of FSs which makes it efficient to keep unification results of substructures of FSs and reuse them.</S><S sid ="206" ssid = "5">This reduces repeated calculation of substructures.</S> 
</COMMUNITY>