<PAPER>
	<S sid="0">SemEval-2007 Task-17: English Lexical Sample SRL and All Words</S><ABSTRACT>
		<S sid="1" ssid="1">This paper describes our experience in preparing the data and evaluating the results for three subtasks of SemEval-2007 Task-17 ? Lexical Sample, Semantic Role Labeling(SRL) and All-Words respectively.</S>
		<S sid="2" ssid="2">We tab ulate and analyze the results of participating systems.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number="1">
			<S sid="3" ssid="3">Correctly disambiguating words (WSD), and correctly identifying the semantic relationships be tween those words (SRL), is an important step forbuilding successful natural language processing applications, such as text summarization, question an swering, and machine translation.</S>
			<S sid="4" ssid="4">SemEval-2007Task-17 (English Lexical Sample, SRL and All Words) focuses on both of these challenges, WSD and SRL, using annotated English text taken from the Wall Street Journal and the Brown Corpus.It includes three subtasks: i) the traditional AllWords task comprising fine-grained word sense dis ambiguation using a 3,500 word section of the Wall Street Journal, annotated with WordNet 2.1 sense tags, ii) a Lexical Sample task for coarse-grainedword sense disambiguation on a selected set of lex emes, and iii) Semantic Role Labeling, using two different types of arguments, on the same subset of lexemes.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Word Sense Disambiguation. " number="2">
			<S sid="5" ssid="1">2.1 English fine-grained All-Words.</S>
			<S sid="6" ssid="2">In this task we measure the ability of systems to identify the correct fine-grained WordNet 2.1 wordsense for all the verbs and head words of their argu ments.</S>
			<S sid="7" ssid="3">2.1.1 Data Preparation We began by selecting three articles wsj 0105.mrg (on homelessness), wsj 0186.mrg (about a book on corruption), and wsj 0239.mrg (about hot-air ballooning) from a section of the WSJ corpus that has been Treebanked and PropBanked.</S>
			<S sid="8" ssid="4">All instances of verbs were identified using theTreebank part-of-speech tags, and also the head words of their noun arguments (using the PropBank and standard headword rules).</S>
			<S sid="9" ssid="5">The locations of the sentences containing them as well as the locations of the verbs and the nouns within these sentences were recorded for subsequent sense-annotation.</S>
			<S sid="10" ssid="6">A total of 465 lemmas were selected from about 3500 words of text.We use a tool called STAMP written by Benjamin Snyder for sense-annotation of these instances.</S>
			<S sid="11" ssid="7">STAMP accepts a list of pointers to the in stances that need to be annotated.</S>
			<S sid="12" ssid="8">These pointers consist of the name of the file where the instance is located, the sentence number of the instance, and finally, the word number of the ambiguous word within that sentence.</S>
			<S sid="13" ssid="9">These pointers were obtained as described in the previous paragraph.</S>
			<S sid="14" ssid="10">STAMP also requires a sense inventory, which must be stored in XML format.</S>
			<S sid="15" ssid="11">This sense inventory was obtained by querying WordNet 2.1 and storing the output as a 87set of XML files (one for each word to be anno tated) prior to tagging.</S>
			<S sid="16" ssid="12">STAMP works by displayingto the user the sentence to be annotated with the tar get word highlighted along with the previous and the following sentences and the senses from the sense inventory.</S>
			<S sid="17" ssid="13">The user can select one of the senses and move on to the next instance.</S>
			<S sid="18" ssid="14">Two linguistics students annotated the words with WordNet 2.1 senses.</S>
			<S sid="19" ssid="15">Our annotators examined each instance upon which they disagreed and resolvedtheir disagreements.</S>
			<S sid="20" ssid="16">Finally, we converted the re sulting data to the Senseval format.</S>
			<S sid="21" ssid="17">For this dataset, we got an inter-annotator agreement (ITA) of 72% on verbs and 86% for nouns.</S>
			<S sid="22" ssid="18">2.1.2 Results A total of 14 systems were evaluated on the All Words task.</S>
			<S sid="23" ssid="19">These results are shown in Table 1.</S>
			<S sid="24" ssid="20">We used the standard Senseval scorer ? scorer21 to score the systems.</S>
			<S sid="25" ssid="21">All the F-scores2 in this table as well as other tables in this paper are accompanied by a 95% confidence interval calculated using the bootstrap resampling procedure.</S>
			<S sid="26" ssid="22">2.2 OntoNotes English Lexical Sample WSD.</S>
			<S sid="27" ssid="23">It is quite well accepted at this point that it is dif ficult to achieve high inter-annotator agreement onthe fine-grained WordNet style senses, and without a corpus with high annotator agreement, auto matic learning methods cannot perform at a levelthat would be acceptable for a downstream applica tion.</S>
			<S sid="28" ssid="24">OntoNotes (Hovy et al, 2006) is a project that has annotated several layers of semantic information ? including word senses, at a high inter-annotator agreement of over 90%.</S>
			<S sid="29" ssid="25">Therefore we decided to use this data for the lexical sample task.</S>
			<S sid="30" ssid="26">2.2.1 Data All the data for this task comes from the 1M wordWSJ Treebank.</S>
			<S sid="31" ssid="27">For the convenience of the partici pants who wanted to use syntactic parse information as features using an off-the-shelf syntactic parser, we decided to compose the training data of Sections 02-21.</S>
			<S sid="32" ssid="28">For the test sets, we use data from Sections 1http://www.cse.unt.edu/?rada/senseval/senseval3/scoring/ 2scorer2 reports Precision and Recall scores for each system.</S>
			<S sid="33" ssid="29">For a sys tem that attempts all the words, both Precision and Recall are the same.</S>
			<S sid="34" ssid="30">Since a few systems had missing answers, they got different Precision and Recall scores.</S>
			<S sid="35" ssid="31">Therefore, for ranking purposes, we consolidated them into an F-score.</S>
			<S sid="36" ssid="32">Train Test Total Verb 8988 2292 11280 Noun 13293 2559 15852 Total 22281 4851 Table 2: The number of instances for Verbs andNouns in the Train and Test sets for the Lexical Sam ple WSD task.</S>
			<S sid="37" ssid="33">01, 22, 23 and 24.</S>
			<S sid="38" ssid="34">Fortunately, the distribution ofwords was amenable to an acceptable number of in stances for each lemma in the test set.</S>
			<S sid="39" ssid="35">We selecteda total of 100 lemmas (65 verbs and 35 nouns) con sidering the degree of polysemy and total instances that were annotated.</S>
			<S sid="40" ssid="36">The average ITA for these is over 90%.</S>
			<S sid="41" ssid="37">The training and test set composition is described in Table 2.</S>
			<S sid="42" ssid="38">The distribution across all the verbs and nouns is displayed in Table 4 2.2.2 ResultsA total of 13 systems were evaluated on the Lexi cal Sample task.</S>
			<S sid="43" ssid="39">Table 3 shows the Precision/Recall for all these systems.</S>
			<S sid="44" ssid="40">The same scoring software was used to score this task as well.</S>
			<S sid="45" ssid="41">2.2.3 Discussion For the all words task, the baseline performanceusing the most frequent WordNet sense for the lemmas is 51.4.</S>
			<S sid="46" ssid="42">The top-performing system was a supervised system that used a Maximum Entropy clas sifier, and got a Precision/Recall of 59.1% ? about 8 points higher than the baseline.</S>
			<S sid="47" ssid="43">Since the coarse and fine-grained disambiguation tasks have been part ofthe two previous Senseval competitions, and we happen to have access to that data, we can take this op portunity to look at the disambiguation performancetrend.</S>
			<S sid="48" ssid="44">Although different test sets were used for ev ery evaluation, we can get a rough indication of the trend.</S>
			<S sid="49" ssid="45">For the fine-grained All Words sense tagging task, which has always used WordNet, the systemperformance has ranged from our 59% to 65.2 (Sen seval3, (Decadt et al, 2004)) to 69% (Seneval2, (Chklovski and Mihalcea, 2002)).</S>
			<S sid="50" ssid="46">Because of time constraints on the data preparation, this year?s task has proportionally more verbs and fewer nouns thanprevious All-Words English tasks, which may ac count for the lower scores.</S>
			<S sid="51" ssid="47">As expected, the Lexical Sample task using coarse 88 Rank Participant System ID Classifier F 1 Stephen Tratz &lt;stephen.tratz@pnl.gov&gt; PNNL MaxEnt 59.1?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="52" ssid="48">2 Hwee Tou Ng &lt;nght@comp.nus.edu.sg&gt; NUS-PT SVM 58.7?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="53" ssid="49">3 Rada Mihalcea &lt;rada@cs.unt.edu&gt; UNT-Yahoo Memory-based 58.3?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="54" ssid="50">4 Cai Junfu &lt;caijunfu@gmail.com&gt; NUS-ML naive Bayes 57.6?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="55" ssid="51">5 Oier Lopez de Lacalle &lt;jibloleo@si.ehu.es&gt; UBC-ALM kNN 54.4?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="56" ssid="52">6 David Martinez &lt;davidm@csse.unimelb.edu.au&gt; UBC-UMB-2 kNN 54.0?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="57" ssid="53">7 Jonathan Chang &lt;jcone@princeton.edu&gt; PU-BCD Exponential Model 53.9?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="58" ssid="54">8 Radu ION &lt;radu@racai.ro&gt; RACAI Unsupervised 52.7?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="59" ssid="55">9 Most Frequent WordNet Sense Baseline N/A 51.4?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="60" ssid="56">10 Davide Buscaldi &lt;dbuscaldi@dsic.upv.es&gt; UPV-WSD Unsupervised 46.9?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="61" ssid="57">11 Sudip Kumar Naskar &lt;sudip.naskar@gmail.com&gt; JU-SKNSB Unsupervised 40.2?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="62" ssid="58">12 David Martinez &lt;davidm@csse.unimelb.edu.au&gt; UBC-UMB-1 Unsupervised 39.9?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="63" ssid="59">14 Rafael Berlanga &lt;berlanga@uji.es&gt; tkb-uo Unsupervised 32.5?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="64" ssid="60">15 Jordan Boyd-Graber &lt;jbg@princeton.edu&gt; PUTOP Unsupervised 13.2?4.5.</S>
			<S sid="65" ssid="61">Table 1: System Performance for the All-Words task.</S>
			<S sid="66" ssid="62">Rank Participant System Classifier F 1 Cai Junfu &lt;caijunfu@gmail.com&gt; NUS-ML SVM 88.7?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="67" ssid="63">2 Oier Lopez de Lacalle &lt;jibloleo@si.ehu.es&gt; UBC-ALM SVD+kNN 86.9?1.2.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Zheng-Yu Niu &lt;niu zy@hotmail.com&gt; I2R Supervised 86.4?1.2. " number="3">
			<S sid="68" ssid="1">5 Lucia Specia &lt;lspecia@gmail.com&gt; USP-IBM-1 ILP 85.1?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="69" ssid="2">5 Deniz Yuret &lt;dyuret@ku.edu.tr&gt; KU Semi-supervised 85.1?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="70" ssid="3">6 Saarikoski &lt;harri.saarikoski@helsinki.fi&gt; OE naive Bayes, SVM 83.8?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="71" ssid="4">7 University of Technology Brno VUTBR naive Bayes 80.3?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="72" ssid="5">8 Ana Zelaia &lt;ana.zelaia@ehu.es&gt; UBC-ZAS SVD+kNN 79.9?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="73" ssid="6">9 Carlo Strapparava &lt;strappa@itc.it&gt; ITC-irst SVM 79.6?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="74" ssid="7">10 Most frequent sense in training Baseline N/A 78.0?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="75" ssid="8">11 Toby Hawker &lt;toby@it.usyd.edu.au&gt; USYD SVM 74.3?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="76" ssid="9">12 Siddharth Patwardhan &lt;sidd@cs.utah.edu&gt; UMND1 Unsupervised 53.8?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="77" ssid="10">13 Saif Mohammad &lt;smm@cs.toronto.edu&gt; Tor Unsupervised 52.1?1.2.</S>
			<S sid="78" ssid="11">- Toby Hawker &lt;toby@it.usyd.edu.au&gt; USYD?</S>
			<S sid="79" ssid="12">SVM 89.1?1.2 - Carlo Strapparava &lt;strappa@itc.it&gt; ITC?</S>
			<S sid="80" ssid="13">SVM 89.1?1.2 Table 3: System Performance for the OntoNotes Lexical Sample task.</S>
			<S sid="81" ssid="14">Systems marked with an * were post-competition bug-fix submissions.grained senses provides consistently higher per formance than previous more fine-grained LexicalSample Tasks.</S>
			<S sid="82" ssid="15">The high scores here were foreshad owed in an evaluation involving a subset of the data last summer (Chen et al, 2006).</S>
			<S sid="83" ssid="16">Note that the best system performance is now closely approaching the ITA for this data of over 90%.</S>
			<S sid="84" ssid="17">Table 4 shows theperformance of the top 8 systems on all the indi vidual verbs and nouns in the test set.</S>
			<S sid="85" ssid="18">Owing to space constraints we have removed some lemmas that have perfect or almost perfect accuracies.</S>
			<S sid="86" ssid="19">At theright are mentioned the average, minimum and max imum performances of the teams per lemma, and atthe bottom are the average scores per lemma (with out considering the lemma frequencies) and broken down by verbs and nouns.</S>
			<S sid="87" ssid="20">A gap of about 10 points between the verb and noun performance seems to indicate that in general the verbs were more difficult than the nouns.</S>
			<S sid="88" ssid="21">However, this might just be owing to this particular test sample having more verbs with higher perplexities, and maybe even ones that are indeed difficult to disambiguate ? in spite of highhuman agreement.</S>
			<S sid="89" ssid="22">The hope is that better knowledge sources can overcome the gap still existing between the system performance and human agree ment.</S>
			<S sid="90" ssid="23">Overall, however, this data indicates that theapproach suggested by (Palmer, 2000) and that is be ing adopted in the ongoing OntoNotes project (Hovyet al, 2006) does result in higher system perfor mance.</S>
			<S sid="91" ssid="24">Whether or not the more coarse-grained senses are effective in improving natural language processing applications remains to be seen.</S>
			<S sid="92" ssid="25">89 Lemma S s T t 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 Average Min Max turn.v 13 8 340 62 58 61 40 55 52 53 27 44 49 27 61 go.v 12 6 244 61 64 69 38 66 43 46 31 39 49 31 69 come.v 10 9 186 43 49 46 56 60 37 23 23 49 43 23 60 set.v 9 5 174 42 62 50 52 57 50 57 36 50 52 36 62 hold.v 8 7 129 24 58 46 50 54 54 38 50 67 52 38 67 raise.v 7 6 147 34 50 44 29 26 44 26 24 12 32 12 50 work.v 7 5 230 43 74 65 65 65 72 67 46 65 65 46 74 keep.v 7 6 260 80 56 54 52 64 56 52 48 51 54 48 64 start.v 6 4 214 38 53 50 47 55 45 42 37 45 47 37 55 lead.v 6 6 165 39 69 69 85 69 51 69 36 46 62 36 85 see.v 6 5 158 54 56 54 46 54 57 52 48 48 52 46 57 ask.v 6 3 348 58 84 72 72 78 76 52 67 66 71 52 84 find.v 5 3 174 28 93 93 86 89 82 82 75 86 86 75 93 fix.v 5 3 32 2 50 50 50 50 50 0 0 50 38 0 50 buy.v 5 3 164 46 83 80 80 83 78 76 70 76 78 70 83 begin.v 4 2 114 48 83 65 75 69 79 56 50 56 67 50 83 kill.v 4 1 111 16 88 88 88 88 88 88 88 81 87 81 88 join.v 4 4 68 18 44 50 50 39 56 57 39 44 47 39 57 end.v 4 3 135 21 90 86 86 90 62 87 86 67 82 62 90 do.v 4 2 207 61 92 90 90 93 93 90 85 84 90 84 93 examine.v 3 2 26 3 100 100 67 100 100 67 100 33 83 33 100 report.v 3 2 128 35 89 91 91 91 91 91 91 86 90 86 91 regard.v 3 3 40 14 93 93 86 86 64 86 57 93 82 57 93 recall.v 3 1 49 15 100 100 87 87 93 87 87 87 91 87 100 prove.v 3 2 49 22 90 88 82 80 90 86 70 74 82 70 90 claim.v 3 2 54 15 67 73 80 80 80 80 80 87 78 67 87 build.v 3 3 119 46 74 67 74 61 54 74 61 72 67 54 74 feel.v 3 3 347 51 71 69 69 74 76 69 61 71 70 61 76 care.v 3 3 69 7 43 43 43 43 100 29 57 57 52 29 100 contribute.v 2 2 35 18 67 72 72 67 50 61 50 67 63 50 72 maintain.v 2 2 61 10 80 80 70 100 80 90 90 80 84 70 100 complain.v 2 1 32 14 93 86 86 86 86 86 86 79 86 79 93 propose.v 2 2 34 14 100 86 100 86 100 93 79 79 90 79 100 promise.v 2 2 50 8 88 88 75 88 75 75 62 88 80 62 88 produce.v 2 2 115 44 82 82 77 73 75 75 77 80 78 73 82 prepare.v 2 2 54 18 94 83 89 89 83 86 83 83 86 83 94 explain.v 2 2 85 18 94 89 94 89 94 89 89 94 92 89 94 believe.v 2 2 202 55 87 78 78 86 84 78 74 80 81 74 87 occur.v 2 2 47 22 86 73 91 96 86 96 86 82 87 73 96 grant.v 2 2 19 5 100 80 80 80 40 80 60 80 75 40 100 enjoy.v 2 2 56 14 50 57 57 50 64 57 50 57 55 50 64 need.v 2 2 195 56 89 82 86 89 86 78 70 70 81 70 89 disclose.v 1 1 55 14 93 93 93 93 93 93 93 93 93 93 93 point.n 9 6 469 150 91 91 89 91 92 87 84 79 88 79 92 position.n 7 6 268 45 78 78 78 53 56 65 58 64 66 53 78 defense.n 7 7 120 21 57 48 52 43 48 29 48 48 46 29 57 carrier.n 7 3 111 21 71 71 71 71 67 71 71 62 70 62 71 order.n 7 4 346 57 93 95 93 91 93 92 90 91 92 90 95 exchange.n 5 3 363 61 92 90 92 85 90 88 82 79 87 79 92 system.n 5 3 450 70 79 73 66 67 59 63 63 61 66 59 79 source.n 5 5 152 35 86 80 80 63 83 68 60 29 69 29 86 space.n 5 2 67 14 93 100 93 93 93 86 86 71 89 71 100 base.n 5 4 92 20 75 80 75 50 65 40 50 75 64 40 80 authority.n 4 3 90 21 86 86 81 62 71 33 71 81 71 33 86 people.n 4 4 754 115 96 96 95 96 95 90 91 91 94 90 96 chance.n 4 3 91 15 60 67 60 60 67 73 20 73 60 20 73 part.n 4 3 481 71 90 90 92 97 90 74 66 66 83 66 97 hour.n 4 2 187 48 83 85 92 83 77 90 58 92 83 58 92 development.n 3 3 180 29 100 79 86 79 76 62 79 62 78 62 100 president.n 3 3 879 177 98 97 98 97 93 96 97 85 95 85 98 network.n 3 3 152 55 91 87 98 89 84 88 87 82 88 82 98 future.n 3 3 350 146 97 96 94 97 83 98 89 85 92 83 98 effect.n 3 2 178 30 97 93 80 93 80 90 77 83 87 77 97 state.n 3 3 617 72 85 86 86 83 82 79 83 82 83 79 86 power.n 3 3 251 47 92 87 87 81 77 77 77 74 81 74 92 bill.n 3 3 404 102 98 99 98 96 90 96 96 22 87 22 99 area.n 3 3 326 37 89 73 65 68 84 70 68 65 73 65 89 job.n 3 3 188 39 85 80 77 90 80 82 69 82 80 69 90 management.n 2 2 284 45 89 78 87 73 98 76 67 64 79 64 98 condition.n 2 2 132 34 91 82 82 56 76 78 74 76 77 56 91 policy.n 2 2 331 39 95 97 97 87 95 97 90 64 90 64 97 rate.n 2 2 1009 145 90 88 92 81 92 89 88 91 89 81 92 drug.n 2 2 205 46 94 94 96 78 94 94 87 78 89 78 96 Average Overall 86 83 83 82 82 79 76 77 Verbs 78 75 73 76 73 70 65 70 Nouns 89 87 86 81 83 80 77 76 Table 4: All Supervised system performance per predicate.</S>
			<S sid="93" ssid="26">(Column legend ? S=number of senses in training; s=number senses appearing more than 3 times; T=instances in training; t=instances in test.; The numbers indicate system ranks.)</S>
			<S sid="94" ssid="27">90 3 Semantic Role Labeling.</S>
			<S sid="95" ssid="28">Subtask 2 evaluates Semantic Role Labeling (SRL) systems, where the goal is to locate the constituents which are arguments of a given verb, and to assign them appropriate semantic roles that describe howthey relate to the verb.</S>
			<S sid="96" ssid="29">SRL systems are an important building block for many larger semantic systems.</S>
			<S sid="97" ssid="30">For example, in order to determine that ques tion (1a) is answered by sentence (1b), but not by sentence (1c), we must determine the relationships between the relevant verbs (eat and feed) and their arguments.</S>
			<S sid="98" ssid="31">(1) a. What do lobsters like to eat?b. Recent studies have shown that lobsters pri marily feed on live fish, dig for clams, sea urchins, and feed on algae and eel-grass.</S>
			<S sid="99" ssid="32">c. In the early 20th century, Mainers would only eat lobsters because the fish they caught was too valuable to eat themselves.</S>
			<S sid="100" ssid="33">Traditionally, SRL systems have been trained on either the PropBank corpus (Palmer et al, 2005) ? for two years, the CoNLL workshop (Carreras and Ma`rquez, 2004; Carreras and Ma`rquez, 2005) has made this their shared task, or the FrameNet corpus ? Senseval-3 used this for their shared task(Litkowski, 2004).</S>
			<S sid="101" ssid="34">However, there is still little con sensus in the linguistics and NLP communities about what set of role labels are most appropriate.</S>
			<S sid="102" ssid="35">ThePropBank corpus avoids this issue by using theory agnostic labels (ARG0, ARG1, . . .</S>
			<S sid="103" ssid="36">, ARG5), and by defining those labels to have only verb-specific meanings.</S>
			<S sid="104" ssid="37">Under this scheme, PropBank can avoidmaking any claims about how any one verb?s ar guments relate to other verbs?</S>
			<S sid="105" ssid="38">arguments, or aboutgeneral distinctions between verb arguments and ad juncts.However, there are several limitations to this ap proach.</S>
			<S sid="106" ssid="39">The first is that it can be difficult to make inferences and generalizations based on role labels that are only meaningful with respect to a single verb.</S>
			<S sid="107" ssid="40">Since each role label is verb-specific, we can not confidently determine when two different verbs?</S>
			<S sid="108" ssid="41">arguments have the same role; and since no encoded meaning is associated with each tag, we can notmake generalizations across verb classes.</S>
			<S sid="109" ssid="42">In con trast, the use of a shared set of role labels, such System Type Precision Recall F UBC-UPC Open 84.51 82.24 83.36?0.5 UBC-UPC Closed 85.04 82.07 83.52?0.5 RTV Closed 81.82 70.37 75.66?0.6 Without ?say?</S>
			<S sid="110" ssid="43">UBC-UPC Open 78.57 74.70 76.60?0.8 UBC-UPC Closed 78.67 73.94 76.23?0.8 RTV Closed 74.15 57.85 65.00?0.9Table 5: System performance on PropBank argu ments.</S>
			<S sid="111" ssid="44">as VerbNet roles, would facilitate both inferencingand generalization.</S>
			<S sid="112" ssid="45">VerbNet has more traditional la bels such as Agent, Patient, Theme, Beneficiary, etc.</S>
			<S sid="113" ssid="46">(Kipper et al, 2006).Therefore, we chose to annotate the corpus us ing two different role label sets: the PropBank role set and the VerbNet role set.</S>
			<S sid="114" ssid="47">VerbNet roles were generated using the SemLink mapping (Loper et al,2007), which provides a mapping between Prop Bank and VerbNet role labels.</S>
			<S sid="115" ssid="48">In a small number of cases, no VerbNet role was available (e.g., because VerbNet did not contain the appropriate sense of the verb).</S>
			<S sid="116" ssid="49">In those cases, the PropBank role label was used instead.</S>
			<S sid="117" ssid="50">We proposed two levels of participation in thistask: i) Closed ? the systems could use only the an notated data provided and nothing else.</S>
			<S sid="118" ssid="51">ii) Open ?where systems could use PropBank data from Sec tions 02-21, as well as any other resource for training their labelers.</S>
			<S sid="119" ssid="52">3.1 Data.</S>
			<S sid="120" ssid="53">We selected 50 verbs from the 65 in the lexical sam ple task for the SRL task.</S>
			<S sid="121" ssid="54">The partitioning into train and test set was done in the same fashion as for the lexical sample task.</S>
			<S sid="122" ssid="55">Since PropBank does not tag any noun predicates, none of the 35 nouns from the lexical sample task were part of this data.</S>
			<S sid="123" ssid="56">3.2 Results.</S>
			<S sid="124" ssid="57">For each system, we calculated the precision, re call, and F-measure for both role label sets.</S>
			<S sid="125" ssid="58">Scores were calculated using the srl-eval.pl script from the CoNLL-2005 scoring package (Carreras and Ma`rquez, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="126" ssid="59">Only two teams chose to perform the SRL subtask.</S>
			<S sid="127" ssid="60">The performance of these two teams is shown in Table 5 and Table 6.</S>
			<S sid="128" ssid="61">91 System Type Precision Recall F UBC-UPC Open 85.31 82.08 83.66?0.5 UBC-UPC Closed 85.31 82.08 83.66?0.5 RTV Closed 81.58 70.16 75.44?0.6 Without ?say?</S>
			<S sid="129" ssid="62">UBC-UPC Open 79.23 73.88 76.46?0.8 UBC-UPC Closed 79.23 73.88 76.46?0.8 RTV Closed 73.63 57.44 64.53?0.9 Table 6: System performance on VerbNet roles.</S>
			<S sid="130" ssid="63">3.3 Discussion.</S>
			<S sid="131" ssid="64">Given that only two systems participated in the task, it is difficult to form any strong conclusions.</S>
			<S sid="132" ssid="65">It should be noted that since there was no additional VerbNet role data to be used by the Open system, the performance of that on PropBank arguments as well as VerbNet roles is exactly identical.</S>
			<S sid="133" ssid="66">It can be seenthat there is almost no difference between the perfor mance of the Open and Closed systems for tagging PropBank arguments.</S>
			<S sid="134" ssid="67">The reason for this is the factthat all the instances of the lemma under consider ation was selected from the Propbank corpus, and probably the number of training instances for each lemma as well as the fact that the predicate is such an important feature combine to make the difference negligible.</S>
			<S sid="135" ssid="68">We also realized that more than half of the test instances were contributed by the predicate ?say?</S>
			<S sid="136" ssid="69">the performance over whose arguments is in the high 90s.</S>
			<S sid="137" ssid="70">To remove the effect of ?say?</S>
			<S sid="138" ssid="71">we alsocomputed the performances after excluding exam ples of ?say?</S>
			<S sid="139" ssid="72">from the test set.</S>
			<S sid="140" ssid="73">These numbers are shown in the bottom half of the two tables.</S>
			<S sid="141" ssid="74">Theseresults are not directly comparable to the CoNLL 2005 shared task since: i) this test set comprisesSections 01, 22, 23 and 24 as opposed to just Sec tion 23, and ii) this test set comprises data for only 50 predicates as opposed to all the verb predicates in the CoNLL-2005 shared task.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions. " number="4">
			<S sid="142" ssid="1">The results in the previous discussion seem to confirm the hypothesis that there is a predictable correlation between human annotator agreement and sys tem performance.</S>
			<S sid="143" ssid="2">Given high enough ITA rates we can can hope to build sense disambiguation systemsthat perform at a level that might be of use to a con suming natural language processing application.</S>
			<S sid="144" ssid="3">Itis also encouraging that the more informative Verb Net roles which have better/direct applicability indownstream systems, can also be predicted with al most the same degree of accuracy as the PropBank arguments from which they are mapped.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acknowledgments. " number="5">
			<S sid="145" ssid="1">We gratefully acknowledge the support of the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA/IPTO) under the GALE program, DARPA/CMO Contract No.</S>
			<S sid="146" ssid="2">HR0011-06-C-0022; National Science Foundation Grant NSF-0415923, Word Sense Disambiguation; the DTO-AQUAINT NBCHC040036 grant under the University of Illinois subcontract to University of Pennsylvania 2003-07911-01; and NSF-ITR-0325646: Domain-Independent Semantic Interpretation.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
