<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction and related work. " number = "1">
			<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">Sentence compression is a paraphrasing task where the goal is to generate sentences shorter than given while preserving the essential content.</S>
			<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">A robust compression system would be useful for mobile devices as well as a module in an extractive sum- marization system (Mani, 2001).</S>
			<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">Although a compression may differ lexically and structurally from the source sentence, to date most systems are ex- tractive and proceed by deleting words from the input (Knight &amp; Marcu, 2000; Dorr et al., 2003; Turner &amp; Charniak, 2005; Clarke &amp; Lapata, 2008; Berg-Kirkpatrick et al., 2011, inter alia).</S>
			<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">To decide which words, dependencies or phrases can be dropped, (i) rule-based approaches (Grefenstette, 1998; Jing &amp; McKeown, 2000; Dorr et al., 2003; Zajic et al., 2007), (ii) supervised models trained on parallel data (Knight &amp; Marcu, 2000; Turner &amp; Charniak, 2005; McDonald, 2006; Gillick &amp; Favre, 2009; Galanis &amp; Androutsopoulos, 2010, inter alia) and (iii) unsupervised methods which make use of statistics collected from non-parallel data (Hori &amp; Furui, 2004; Zajic et al., 2007; Clarke &amp; Lapata, 2008; Filippova &amp; Strube, 2008) have been investigated.</S>
			<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">Since it is infeasible to manually devise a set of accurate deletion rules with high coverage, recent research has been devoted to developing statistical methods and possibly augmenting them with a few linguistic rules to improve output readability (Clarke &amp; Lapata, 2008; Nomoto, 2009).</S>
			<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">Supervised models.</S>
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">A major problem for supervised deletion-based systems is very limited amount of parallel data.</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">Many approaches make use of a small portion of the ZiffDavis corpus which has about 1K sentence-compression pairs1.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">Other main sources of training data are the two manually crafted compression corpora from the University of Edinburgh (“written” and “spoken”, each approx.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">1.4K pairs).</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">Galanis &amp; Androutsopoulos (2011) attempt at getting more parallel data by applying a deletion- based compressor together with an automatic para 1 The method of Galley &amp; McKeown (2007) could benefit from a larger number of sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">phraser and generating multiple alternative compressions.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">To our knowledge, this extended data set has not yet been used for successful training of compression systems.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">Scarce parallel data makes it hard to go beyond a small set of features and explore lexicalization.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">For example, Knight &amp; Marcu (2000) only induce non- lexicalized CFG rules, many of which occurred only once in the training data.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">The features of McDonald (2006) are formulated exclusively in terms of syntactic categories.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">Berg-Kirkpatrick et al.</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">(2011) have as few as 13 features to decide whether a constituent can be dropped.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">Galanis &amp; Androutsopoulos (2010) use many features when deciding which branches of the input dependency tree can be pruned but require a reranker to select most fluent compressions from a pool of candidates generated in the pruning phase, many of which are ungrammatical.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "20">Even further data limitations exist for the algorithms which operate on syntactic trees and reformulate the compression task as a tree pruning one (Nomoto, 2008; Filippova &amp; Strube, 2008; Cohn &amp; Lapata, 2009; Galanis &amp; Androutsopoulos, 2010, inter alia).</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "21">These methods are sensitive to alignment errors, their performance degrades if the syntactic structure of the compression is very different from that of the input.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "22">For example, see Nomoto’s 2009 analysis of the poor performance of the T3 system of Cohn &amp; Lapata (2009) when retrained on a corpus of loosely similar RSS feeds and news.</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "23">Unsupervised models.</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "24">Few approaches require no training data at all.</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "25">The model of Hori &amp; Furui (2004) combines scores estimated from monolingual corpora to generate compressions of transcribed speech.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "26">Adopting an integer linear programming (ILP) framework, Clarke &amp; Lapata (2008) use handcrafted syntactic constraints and an ngram language model, trained on uncompressed sentences, to find best compressions.</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "27">The model of Filippova &amp; Strube (2008) also uses ILP but the problem is formulated over dependencies and not ngrams.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "28">Conditional probabilities and word counts collected from a large treebank are combined in an ad hoc manner to assess grammatical importance and informativeness of dependencies.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "29">Similarly, Woodsend &amp; Lapata (2010) formulate an ILP problem to generate news story highlights using precomputed scores.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "30">Again, an ad hoc combination of the scores learned independently of the task is used in the objective function.</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "31">Contributions of this paper.</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "32">Our work is motivated by the obvious need for a large parallel corpus of sentences and compressions on which extractive systems can be trained.</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "33">Furthermore, we want the compressions in the corpus to be structurally very close to the input.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "34">Ideally, in every pair, the compression should correspond to a subtree of the input.</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "35">To this end, our contributions are threefold: • We describe an automatic procedure of constructing a parallel corpus of 250,000 sentence- compression pairs such that the dependency tree of the compression is a subtree of the source tree.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "36">An evaluation with human raters demonstrates high quality of the parallel data in terms of readability and informativeness.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "37">• We successfully apply the acquired data to train a novel supervised compression system which produces readable and informative compressions without employing a separate reranker.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "38">In particular, we start with the unsupervised method of Filippova &amp; Strube (2008) and replace the ad hoc edge weighting with a linear function over a rich feature representation.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "39">The parameter vector is learned from our corpus specifically for the compression task using structured prediction (Collins, 2002).</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "40">The new system significantly outperforms the baseline and hence provides further evidence for the utility of the parallel data.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "41">• We demonstrate that sparse lexical features are very useful for sentence compression, and that a large parallel corpus is a requirement for applying them successfully.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "42">The compression framework we adopt and the unsupervised baseline are introduced in Section 2, the training algorithm for learning edge weights from parallel data is described in Section 3.</S>
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "43">In Section 4 we explain how to obtain the data and present an evaluation of its quality.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "44">In Section 5 we compare the baseline with our system and report the results of an experiment with humans as well as the results of an automatic evaluation.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Framework  and baseline. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "1">We adopt the unsupervised compression framework of Filippova &amp; Strube (2008) as our baseline and extend it to a supervised structured prediction problem.</S>
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "2">In the experiments reported by Filippova &amp; Strube (2008), the system was evaluated on the Edinburgh corpora.</S>
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "3">It achieved an F-score (Riezler et al., 2003) higher than reported by other systems on the same data under an aggressive compression rate and thus presents a competitive baseline.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "4">Tree pruning as optimization.</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "5">In this framework, compressions are obtained by deleting edges of the source dependency structure so that (1) the retained edges form a valid syntactic tree, and (2) their total edge weight is maximized.</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "6">The objective function is defined over set X = {xe, e ∈ E} of bi nary variables, corresponding to the set E of the source edges, subject to the structural and length constraints, f (X ) = xe × w(e) (1) e∈E Here, w(e) denotes the weight of edge e. This constrained optimization problem is solved under the tree structure and length constraints using ILP.</S>
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "7">If xe is resolved to 1, the respective edge is retained, otherwise it is deleted.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "8">The tree structure constraints enforce at most one parent for every node and structure connectivity (i.e., no disconnected subtrees).</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "9">Given that length(node(e)) denotes the length of the node to which edge e points and α is the maximum permitted length for the compression, the length constraint is simply xe × length(node(e)) ≤ α (2) e∈E Word limit is used in the original paper, whereas we use character length which is more appropriate for system comparisons (Napoles et al., 2011).</S>
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "10">If uniform weights are used in Eq.</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "11">(1), the optimal solution would correspond to a subtree covering as many edges as possible while keeping the compression length under given limit.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "12">The solution to the surface realization problem (Belz et al., 2011) is standard: the words in the compression subtree are put in the same order they are found in the source.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "13">Due to space limitations, we refer the reader to (Filippova &amp; Strube, 2008) for a detailed description on the method.</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "14">Essential for the present discussion is that source dependency trees are transformed to dependency graphs in that (1) auxiliary, determiner, preposition, negation and possessive nodes are collapsed with their heads; (2) prepositions replace labels on the edges to their arguments; (3) the dummy root node is connected with every inflected verb.</S>
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "15">Figures 1(a)-1(b) illustrate most of the transformations.</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "16">The transformations are deterministic and reversible, they can be implemented in a single top-down tree traversal2.</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "17">The set E of edges in Eq.</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "18">(1) is thus the set of edges of the transformed dependency graph, like in Fig.</S>
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "19">1(b).</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "20">A benefit of the transformations is that function words and negation appear in the compression if and only if their head words are present.</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "21">Hence no separate constraints are required to ensure that negation or a determiner is preserved.</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "22">The dummy root node makes constraint formulation easier and also allows for the generation of compressions from any finite clause of the source.</S>
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "23">The described pruning optimization framework is used both for the unsupervised baseline and for our supervised system.</S>
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "24">The difference between the baseline and our system is in how edge weights, w(e)’s in Eq.</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "25">(1), are instantiated.</S>
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "26">Baseline edge weights.</S>
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "27">The precomputed edge weights reflect syntactic importance as well as informativeness of the nodes they point to.</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "28">Given edge e from head node h to node n, the edge weight is the product of the syntactic and the informativeness weights, w(e) = wsynt(e) × winfo(e) (3) The syntactic weight is defined as wsynt(e) = P (label(e)|lemma(h)) (4) For example, verb kill may have multiple arguments realized with dependency labels subj, dobj, in, etc. However, these argument labels are not equally likely, e.g., P (subj|kill) &gt; P (in|kill).</S>
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "29">When forced to prune an edge, the system would prefer to keep 2 Some of the transformations are comparable to what is implemented in the Stanford parser (de Marneffe et al., 2006).</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "30">root ccomp pobj poss nsubj detnsubj det pobj ps p r e p pob j a m o d a u x p a s s pre p a m o d pre p a m o d Britain ’s Ministry of Defense says a British soldier was killed in a roadside blast in southern Afghanistan (a) Source dependency tree root of subj root ccomp amod subj in amod in amod root Britain’s Ministry of Defense says British a soldier was killed roadside in a blast southern in Afghanistan (b) Transformed graph root amod subj in in root British a soldier was killed in a blast in Afghanistan (c) Tree of extracted headline A British soldier was killed in a blast in Afghanistan det subj root pobj amod auxpass prep det prep pobj A British soldier was killed in a blast in Afghanistan (d) Tree of extracted headline with transformations undone Figure 1: Source, transformed and extracted trees given headline British soldier killed in Afghanistan the subject edge over the preposition-in edge since it contributes more weight to the objective function.</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "31">The informativeness score is inspired by Wood- send &amp; Lapata (2012) and is defined as Pheadline(lemma(n)) sumably all play a role in determining the overall edge importance.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Learning  edge weights. " number = "3">
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "1">Our supervised system differs from the unsupervised winfo(e) = Particle (5) (lemma(n)) baseline in that instead of relying on precomputed scores, we define edge weight w(e) in Eq.</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "2">(1) with a This weight tells us how likely it is that a word from an article appears in the headline.</S>
			<S sid ="78" ssid = "3">For example, given two edges one of which points to verb say and another one to verb kill, the latter would be preferred over the former because kill is more “head- liny” than say.</S>
			<S sid ="79" ssid = "4">When collecting counts for the syntactic and informativeness scores, we used 9M news articles crawled from the Internet, much more than Filippova &amp; Strube (2008).</S>
			<S sid ="80" ssid = "5">As a result our estimates are probably more accurate than theirs.</S>
			<S sid ="81" ssid = "6">Although both wsynt and winfo have a meaningful interpretation, there is no guarantee that product is the best way to combine the two when assigning edge weights.</S>
			<S sid ="82" ssid = "7">Also, it is unclear how to integrate other signals, such as distance to the root, node length or information about the siblings, which pre linear function over a feature representation, w(e) = w · f (e) (6) Here f (e) is a vector of binary variables for everyfeature from the set of all possible but very infre quent features in the training set.</S>
			<S sid ="83" ssid = "8">f (e) has 1 for every feature extracted for edge e and zero otherwise.</S>
			<S sid ="84" ssid = "9">Table 1 gives an overview of the feature types we use (edge e points from head h to node n).</S>
			<S sid ="85" ssid = "10">Note that syntactic, structural and semantic features are closed-class.</S>
			<S sid ="86" ssid = "11">For all the structural features but char length, seven is used as maximum possible value; all possible character lengths are bucketed into six classes.</S>
			<S sid ="87" ssid = "12">All the features are local – for a given edge, contextual information is included about syntactic label(e); for e* to h, label(e*); pos(h); pos(n) structural depth(n); #children(n); #children(h); char length(n); #words in(n) semantic NE tag(h); NE tag(n); is negated(n) lexical lemma(n); lemma(h)-label(e); for e* to n’s siblings, lemma(h)-label(e*) Table 1: Types of features extracted for edge e from h to n the head and the target nodes, and the siblings as well as the children of the latter.</S>
			<S sid ="88" ssid = "13">The negation feature is only applicable to verb nodes which contain a negative particle, like not, after the tree transformations.</S>
			<S sid ="89" ssid = "14">Lexical features which combine lemmas and syntactic labels are inspired by the unsupervised baseline and are very sparse.</S>
			<S sid ="90" ssid = "15">In what follows, our assumption is that we have a compression corpus at our disposal where for every input sentence there is a correct “oracle” compression such that its transformed parse tree matches a subtree of the transformed input graph.</S>
			<S sid ="91" ssid = "16">Given such a corpus, we can apply structured prediction methods to learn the parameter vector w. In our study we employ an averaged variant of online structured perceptron (Collins, 2002).</S>
			<S sid ="92" ssid = "17">In the context of sentence fusion, a similar dependency structure pruning framework and a similar learning approach was adopted by Elsner &amp; Santhanam (2011).</S>
			<S sid ="93" ssid = "18">At every iteration, for every input graph, we find the optimal solution with ILP under the current parameter vector w. The maximum permitted compression length is set to be the same as the length of the oracle compression.</S>
			<S sid ="94" ssid = "19">Since the oracle compression is a subtree of the input graph, it represents a feasible solution for ILP.</S>
			<S sid ="95" ssid = "20">The parameter vector is updated if there is a mismatch between the predicted and the oracle sets of edges for all the features with a nonzero net count.</S>
			<S sid ="96" ssid = "21">More formally, given an input graph with the set of edges E, oracle compressionC ⊂ E and compression Ct ⊆ E predicted at itera tion t , the parameter update vector at t + 1 is given by Of course, training a model with a large number of features, such as a lexicalized model, is only possible if there is a large compression corpus where the dependency tree of the compression is a subtree of the source sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="97" ssid = "22">In the next section we introduce our method of getting a sufficient amount of such data.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acquiring parallel data automatically. " number = "4">
			<S sid ="98" ssid = "1">In this section we explain how we obtained a parallel corpus of sentences and compressions.</S>
			<S sid ="99" ssid = "2">The underlying idea is to harvest news articles from the Internet where the headline appears to be similar to the first sentence and use it to find an extractive compression of the sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="100" ssid = "3">Collecting headline-sentence pairs.</S>
			<S sid ="101" ssid = "4">Using a news crawler, we collected a corpus of news articles in English from the Internet.</S>
			<S sid ="102" ssid = "5">Similarly to previous work (Dolan et al., 2004; Wubben et al., 2009; Bejan &amp; Harabagiu, 2010, inter alia), the Google News service3 was used to identify news.</S>
			<S sid ="103" ssid = "6">From every article, the headline and the first sentence, which are known to be semantically similar (Dorr et al., 2003), were extracted.</S>
			<S sid ="104" ssid = "7">Predictably, very few headlines are extractive compressions of the first sentence, therefore simply looking for pairs where the headline is a subsequence of the words from the first sentence would not solve the problem of getting a large amount of parallel data.</S>
			<S sid ="105" ssid = "8">Importantly, headlines are syntactically quite different from “normal” sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="106" ssid = "9">For example, they may have no main verb, omit determiners and appear incomplete, making it hard for a supervised deletion-based system to learn useful rules.</S>
			<S sid ="107" ssid = "10">Moreover, we observed poor parsing wt+1 = wt + e∈C \Ct f (e) − e∈Ct \C f (e) (7) accuracy for headlines which would make syntactic annotations for headlines hardly useful.</S>
			<S sid ="108" ssid = "11">Thus, instead of taking the headline as it is, we use w is averaged over all the wt’s so that featuresit to find a proper extractive compression of the sen whose weight fluctuated a lot during training are penalized (Freund &amp; Shapire, 1999).</S>
			<S sid ="109" ssid = "12">3 http://news.google.com, JanDec 2012.</S>
			<S sid ="110" ssid = "13">tence by matching lemmas of content words (nouns, verbs, adjectives, adverbs) and coreference IDs of entities from the headline with those of the sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="111" ssid = "14">The exact procedure is as follows (H, S and T stand for headline, sentence and transformed graph of the sentence): PREPROCESSING H and S are preprocessed in a standard way: tokenized, lemmatized, PoS and NE tagged.</S>
			<S sid ="112" ssid = "15">Additionally, S is parsed with a dependency parser (Nivre, 2006) and transformed as described in Section 2 to obtain T. Finally, pronominal anaphora is resolved in S. Recall that S is the first sentence, so the antecedent must be located in a preceding, higher-level clause.</S>
			<S sid ="113" ssid = "16">FILTERING To restrict the corpus to grammatical and informative headlines, we implemented a cascade of filters.</S>
			<S sid ="114" ssid = "17">Pair (H, S) is discarded if any of the questions in Table 2 is answered positively.</S>
			<S sid ="115" ssid = "18">Is H a question?</S>
			<S sid ="116" ssid = "19">Is H or S too short?</S>
			<S sid ="117" ssid = "20">(less than four word tokens) Is H about as long as S?</S>
			<S sid ="118" ssid = "21">(min ratio: 1.5) Does H lack a verb?</S>
			<S sid ="119" ssid = "22">Does H begin with a verb?</S>
			<S sid ="120" ssid = "23">Is there a noun, verb, adj, adv lemma from H not found in S?</S>
			<S sid ="121" ssid = "24">Are the noun, verb, adj, adv lemmas from H found in S in a different order?</S>
			<S sid ="122" ssid = "25">Table 2: Filters applied to candidate pair (H, S) MATCHING Given the content words of H, a subset of nodes in T is selected based on lemma or coreference identity of the main (head) word in the nodes.</S>
			<S sid ="123" ssid = "26">For example, the main word of a collapsed node in T, which covers two words was killed, is killed; was is its child attached with label aux in the untransformed parse tree.</S>
			<S sid ="124" ssid = "27">This node is marked if H contains word killed or killing because of the lemma identity.</S>
			<S sid ="125" ssid = "28">In some cases there are multiple possible matches.</S>
			<S sid ="126" ssid = "29">For example, given S Barack Obama said he will attend G20 and H mentioning Obama, both Barack Obama and he nodes are marked in T. Once all the nodes in T which match content words and entities from H are identified, a minimum subtree covering these nodes is found such that every word or entity from H occurs as many times in T as in H. So if H mentions Obama only once, then either Barack Obama or he must be covered by the subtree but not both.</S>
			<S sid ="127" ssid = "30">This minimum subtree corresponds to an extractive headline, H*, which we generate by ordering the surface forms of all the words in the subtree nodes by their offsets in S. Finally, the character length of H* is compared with the length of H. If H* is much longer than H, the pair (H, S) is discarded (max ratio 1.5).</S>
			<S sid ="128" ssid = "31">As an illustration to the procedure, consider the example from Figure 1 with the extracted headline and its tree presented in Figure 1(c).</S>
			<S sid ="129" ssid = "32">Given the headline British soldier killed in Afghanistan, the extracted headline would be A British soldier was killed in a blast in Afghanistan.</S>
			<S sid ="130" ssid = "33">The lemmas british, soldier, kill, afghanistan from the headline match the nodes British, a soldier, was killed, in Afghanistan in the transformed graph.</S>
			<S sid ="131" ssid = "34">The node in a blast is added because it is on the path from was killed to in Afghanistan.</S>
			<S sid ="132" ssid = "35">Of course, it is possible to deterministically undo the transformations in order to obtain a standard dependency tree.</S>
			<S sid ="133" ssid = "36">In this case the extracted headline would still correspond to a subtree of the input (compare Fig.</S>
			<S sid ="134" ssid = "37">1(d) with Fig.</S>
			<S sid ="135" ssid = "38">1(a)).</S>
			<S sid ="136" ssid = "39">Also note that a similar procedure can be implemented for constituency parses.</S>
			<S sid ="137" ssid = "40">The resulting corpus consists of 250K tuples (S, T, H, H*), Appendix provides more examples of source sentences, original headlines and extracted headlines.</S>
			<S sid ="138" ssid = "41">We did not attempt to tune the values for minimum/maximum length and ratio – lower thresholds may have produced comparable results.</S>
			<S sid ="139" ssid = "42">Evaluating data quality.</S>
			<S sid ="140" ssid = "43">The described procedure produces a comparatively large compression corpus but how good are automatically constructed compressions?</S>
			<S sid ="141" ssid = "44">To answer this question, we randomly selected 50 tuples from the corpus and set up an experiment with human raters to validate and assess data quality in terms of readability4 and informativeness5 which are standard measures of compression quality (Clarke &amp; Lapata, 2006).</S>
			<S sid ="142" ssid = "45">Raters were asked to read a sentence and a compression (original H or extracted H* headline) and then rate the compression on two five-point scales.</S>
			<S sid ="143" ssid = "46">Three ratings were collected for every item.</S>
			<S sid ="144" ssid = "47">Table 3 gives 4 Also called grammaticality and fluency..</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Also called importance and representativeness.. " number = "5">
			<S sid ="145" ssid = "1">average ratings with standard deviation.</S>
			<S sid ="146" ssid = "2">AVG read AVG info ORIG.</S>
			<S sid ="147" ssid = "3">HEADLINE 4.36 (0.75) 3.86 (0.79) EXTR.</S>
			<S sid ="148" ssid = "4">HEADLINE 4.26 (1.01) 3.70 (1.04) Table 3: Results for two kinds of headlines In terms of readability and informativeness the extracted headlines are comparable with human- written ones: at 95% confidence there is no statistically significant difference between the two.</S>
			<S sid ="149" ssid = "5">Encouraged by the results of the validation experiment we proceeded to our next question: Can a supervised compression system be successfully trained on this corpus?</S>
			<S sid ="150" ssid = "6">5 System evaluation and discussion.</S>
			<S sid ="151" ssid = "7">From the corpus of 250K tuples we used 100K to get pairs of extracted headlines and sentences for training (on the development set we did not observe much improvement from using more training data), 250 for development and the rest for testing.</S>
			<S sid ="152" ssid = "8">We ran the learning algorithm for 20 iterations, checking the performance on the development set.</S>
			<S sid ="153" ssid = "9">Features which applied to less than 20 edges were pruned, the size of the feature set is about 28K.</S>
			<S sid ="154" ssid = "10">5.1 Evaluation with humans.</S>
			<S sid ="155" ssid = "11">50 pairs of original headlines and sentences (different from the data validation set in Sec.</S>
			<S sid ="156" ssid = "12">4) were randomly selected for an evaluation with humans from the test data.</S>
			<S sid ="157" ssid = "13">As in the data quality validation experiment, we asked raters to assess the readability and informativeness of proposed compressions for the unsupervised system, our system and human- written headlines.</S>
			<S sid ="158" ssid = "14">The latter provide us with upper bounds on the evaluation criteria.</S>
			<S sid ="159" ssid = "15">Three ratings per item per parameter were collected.</S>
			<S sid ="160" ssid = "16">To get comparable results, the unsupervised and our systems used the same compression rate: for both, the requested maximum length was set to the length of the headline.</S>
			<S sid ="161" ssid = "17">Table 4 summarizes the results.</S>
			<S sid ="162" ssid = "18">The results indicate that the trained model significantly outperforms the unsupervised system, getting particularly good marks for readability.</S>
			<S sid ="163" ssid = "19">The difference in readability between our system and original headlines is not statistically significant.</S>
			<S sid ="164" ssid = "20">Note that Table 4: Results for the systems and original headline: † and ‡ stand for significantly better than Unsupervised and Our system at 95% confidence, respectively the unsupervised baseline is also capable of generating readable compressions but does a much poorer job in selecting most important information.</S>
			<S sid ="165" ssid = "21">Our trained model successfully learned to optimize both scores.</S>
			<S sid ="166" ssid = "22">We refer the reader to Appendix for input and compression examples.</S>
			<S sid ="167" ssid = "23">Note that the ratings for the human-written headlines in this experiment are slightly different from the ratings in the data validation experiment because a different data sample was used.</S>
			<S sid ="168" ssid = "24">5.2 Automatic evaluation.</S>
			<S sid ="169" ssid = "25">Our automatic evaluation had the goal of explicitly addressing two relevant questions related to our claims about (1) the benefits of having a large parallel corpus and (2) employing a supervised approach with a rich feature representation.</S>
			<S sid ="170" ssid = "26">1.</S>
			<S sid ="171" ssid = "27">Our primary motivation for collecting parallel.</S>
			<S sid ="172" ssid = "28">data has been that having access to sparse lexical features, which considerably increase the feature space, would benefit compression systems.</S>
			<S sid ="173" ssid = "29">But is it really the case for sentence compression?</S>
			<S sid ="174" ssid = "30">Can a comparable performance be achieved with a closed, moderately sized set of dense, non-lexical features?</S>
			<S sid ="175" ssid = "31">If yes, then a large compression corpus is probably not needed.</S>
			<S sid ="176" ssid = "32">Furthermore, to demonstrate that a large corpus is not only sufficient but also necessary to learn weights for thousands of features, we need to compare the performance of the system when trained on the full data set and a small portion of it.</S>
			<S sid ="177" ssid = "33">2.</S>
			<S sid ="178" ssid = "34">The syntactic and informativeness scores in Eq..</S>
			<S sid ="179" ssid = "35">(3) were calculated over millions of news articles and do provide us with meaninful statistics (see Sec.</S>
			<S sid ="180" ssid = "36">2).</S>
			<S sid ="181" ssid = "37">Is there any benefit in replacing those scores with weights learned for their feature counterparts?</S>
			<S sid ="182" ssid = "38">Recall that one of our feature types in Table 1 is the concatenation of lemma(h) (parent lemma) and label(e) which relies on the same informationas wsynt = P (label(e)|lemma(h)).</S>
			<S sid ="183" ssid = "39">The fea ture counterpart of winfo defined in Eq.</S>
			<S sid ="184" ssid = "40">(5) is lemma(n)–the lemma of the node to which edge points.</S>
			<S sid ="185" ssid = "41">How would the supervised system perform against the unsupervised one, if it only extracted features of these two types?</S>
			<S sid ="186" ssid = "42">To answer these questions, we sampled 1,000 tuples from the unused test data and measured F1 score (Riezler et al., 2003) by comparing the trees of the generated compression and the “correct”, extracted headline.</S>
			<S sid ="187" ssid = "43">The systems we compared are the unsupervised baseline (UNSUP.</S>
			<S sid ="188" ssid = "44">SYSTEM) and the supervised model trained on three kinds of feature sets: (1) SYNT-INFO FEATURES, corresponding to the supervised training of the unsupervised baseline model (i.e., lemma(h)-label(e) and lemma(n)); (2) NON-LEX FEATURES, corresponding to a dense, non-lexical feature representation (i.e., all the feature types from Table 1 excluding the three involving lemmas); (3) ALL FEATURES (same as OUR SYSTEM).</S>
			<S sid ="189" ssid = "45">Additionally, we trained the system on 10% of the data–10K as opposed to 100K tuples, ALL FEATURES (10K)–for 20 iterations ignoring provement in going beyond the closed set of 330 non-lexical features to all, from 79.6 to 84.3 points.</S>
			<S sid ="190" ssid = "46">Moreover, successful training requires a large corpus since the performance of the system degrades if only 10K training instances are used.</S>
			<S sid ="191" ssid = "47">Note that this number already exceeds all the existing compression corpora taken together.</S>
			<S sid ="192" ssid = "48">Hence, sparse lexical features are useful for compression and a large parallel corpus is a requirement for successful supervised training.</S>
			<S sid ="193" ssid = "49">Concerning our second question, learning feature weights from the data produces significantly better results than the handcrafted way of making use of the same information, even if a much larger data set is used to collect statistics.</S>
			<S sid ="194" ssid = "50">We observed a dramatic increase from 52.3 to 75.0 points.</S>
			<S sid ="195" ssid = "51">Thus, we may conclude that training with dense and sparse features directly from data definitely improves the performance of the dependency pruning system.</S>
			<S sid ="196" ssid = "52">5.3 Discussion.</S>
			<S sid ="197" ssid = "53">It is important to note that the data we used is challenging: first sentences in news articles tend to be long, in fact longer than other news sentences, which implies less reliable syntactic analysis and noisier input to the syntax-based systems.</S>
			<S sid ="198" ssid = "54">In the test set we used for the evaluation with humans, the mean sentence length is 165 characters.</S>
			<S sid ="199" ssid = "55">The average com features which applied to less than three edges6.</S>
			<S sid ="200" ssid = "56">As before, the same compression rate was used for all pression rate in characters is 0.46 quite aggressive7.</S>
			<S sid ="201" ssid = "57">Recall that we ± 0.16 which is the very same the systems.</S>
			<S sid ="202" ssid = "58">The results are summarized in Table 5.</S>
			<S sid ="203" ssid = "59">F1 sc or e #features U NS UP . SY ST E M 5 2 . 3 N.A. S Y NT IN FO FE AT U R ES N ON LE X FE AT U R ES A LL FE AT U R ES A LL FE AT U R ES (1 0 K) 7 5 . 0 12,490 7 9 . 6 330 8 4 . 3 27,813 8 1 . 4 22,529 Table 5: Results for the unsupervised baseline and the supervised system trained on three kinds of feature sets Clearly, having more features, lexicalized and unlexicalized, is important: there is a significant im used framework for the unsupervised baseline and our system as well as the same compression rate.</S>
			<S sid ="204" ssid = "60">All the preprocessing errors affect both systems equally and the comparison of the two is fair.</S>
			<S sid ="205" ssid = "61">Predictably, wrong syntactic parses significantly increase chances of an ungrammatical compression, and parser errors seem to be a major source of readability deficiencies.</S>
			<S sid ="206" ssid = "62">A property of the described compression framework is that a desired compression length is expected to be provided by the user.</S>
			<S sid ="207" ssid = "63">This can be seen both as a strength and as a weakness, depending on the application.</S>
			<S sid ="208" ssid = "64">In a scenario where mobile devices with a limited screen size are used, or in a summarization scenario where a total summary length is provided (see the DUC/TAC guidelines8), being able (100K) training set the threshold was set to 20 with no tuning.</S>
			<S sid ="209" ssid = "65">For the 10K training set, we tried values of two, three, five and varied the number of iterations.</S>
			<S sid ="210" ssid = "66">The result we report is the highest we could get for 10K.</S>
			<S sid ="211" ssid = "67">7 We follow the standard terminology where smaller values.</S>
			<S sid ="212" ssid = "68">imply shorter compressions.</S>
			<S sid ="213" ssid = "69">8 http://www.nist.gov/tac/ to specify a length is definitely an advantage.</S>
			<S sid ="214" ssid = "70">However, one can also think of other applications where the user does not have a strict length constraint but wants the text to be somewhat shorter.</S>
			<S sid ="215" ssid = "71">In this case, a reranker which compares compressions generated for a range of possible lengths can be employed to find a single compression (e.g., mean edge weight in the solution or a language model-based score).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions. " number = "6">
			<S sid ="216" ssid = "1">We have addressed a major problem for supervised extractive compression models – the lack of a large parallel corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="217" ssid = "2">To this end, we presented a method to automatically build such a corpus from web documents available on the Internet.</S>
			<S sid ="218" ssid = "3">An evaluation with humans demonstrates that the quality of the corpus is high – the compressions are grammatical and informative.</S>
			<S sid ="219" ssid = "4">We also significantly improved a competitive unsupervised method achieving high readability and informativeness scores by incorporating thousands of features and learning the feature weights from our corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="220" ssid = "5">This result further confirms the practical utility of the automatically obtained data.</S>
			<S sid ="221" ssid = "6">We have shown that employing lexical features is important for sentence compression, and that our supervised module can successfully learn their weights from the corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="222" ssid = "7">To our knowledge, we are the first to empirically demonstrate that sparse features are useful for compression and that a large parallel corpus is a requirement for a successful learning of their weights.</S>
			<S sid ="223" ssid = "8">We believe that other supervised deletion-based systems can benefit from our work.</S>
			<S sid ="224" ssid = "9">Acknowledgements: The authors are thankful to the EMNLP reviewers for their feedback and suggestions.</S>
			<S sid ="225" ssid = "10">Appendix The appendix presents examples of source sentences (S), original headlines (H), extracted headlines (H*), unsupervised baseline (U) and our system (O) compressions.</S>
			<S sid ="226" ssid = "11">SH H* U OCountry star Sara Evans has married former University of Alabama quarterback Jay Barker.</S>
			<S sid ="227" ssid = "12">Country star Sara Evans marries Country star Sara Evans has married Sara Evans has married Jay Barker Sara Evans has married Jay Barker SH H* U OIntel would be building car batteries, expanding its business beyond its core strength, the company said in a statement Intel to build car batteriesIntel would be building car batteries would be building the company said Intel would be building car batteries SH H* U OA New Orleans Saints team spokesan says tight end Jeremy Shockey was taken to a hospita but is doing fine.</S>
			<S sid ="228" ssid = "13">Spokesman: Shockey taken to hospital, doing fine spokesman says Jeremy Shockey was taken to a hospital but is doing fine A New Orleans Saints team spokesman says Jeremy Shockey was taken tight end Jeremy Shocke was taken to a hospital but is doing fine SH H* U OPresident Obama declared a major disaster exists in the State of Florida and ordered Federal aid to supplement State nd local r e c o v e r y e f f o r t s i n t h e a r e a s t r u c k b y s e v e r e s t o r m s , f l o o d i n g , t o r n a d o e s , a n d s t r a i g h t l i n e w i n d s b e g i n n i n g o n M a y 1 7 , 2 0 0 9 , a n d c o n t i n u i n g . P r e s i d e n t O b a m a d e c l a r e s m a j o r d i s a s t e r e x i s t s i n t h e S t a t e o f F l o r i d a P r e s i d e n t O b a m a d e c l a r e d a m a j o r d i s a s t e r e x i s t s i n t h e S t a t e o f F l o r i d a P r e s i d e n t O b a m a d e c l a r e d a m a j o r d i s a s t e r e x i s t s a n d o r d e r e d F e d e r a l a i d P r e s i d e n t O b a m a d e c l a r e d a m a j o r d i s a s t e r e x i s t s i n t h e S t a t e o f F l o r i d a S H H * U O Re gul ato rs Fri day shu t do wn a sm all Flo rida ban k, bri ngi ng to 119 the nu mb er of US ban k fail ure s thi s yea r am id mo unti ng loa n def aul ts.</S>
			<S sid ="229" ssid = "14">R e g u l a t o r s s h u t d o w n s m a l l F l o r i d a b a n k R e g u l a t o r s s h u t d o w n a s m a l l F l o r i d a b a n k s h u t d o w n b r i n g i n g t h e n u m b e r o f f a i l u r e s R e g u l a t o r s s h u t d o w n a s m a l l F l o r i d a b a n k S H H * U O Thr ee me n wer e arr est ed We dne sda y nig ht and Da yto n poli ce sai d the ir arre sts are in con nec tion to a wes t Da yto n ban k rob ber y. 3 me n arr est ed in con nec tion wit h Ba nk rob ber y T h r e e m e n w e r e a r r e s t e d a r e i n c o n n e c t i o n t o a b a n k r o b b e r y w e r e a r r e s t e d a n d D a y t o n p o l i c e s a i d t h e i r a r r e s t s a r e Thr ee me n wer e arr est ed and poli ce sai d the ir arre sts are S H H * U O Th e gov ern me nt and the soc ial par tne rs will res um e the talk s on the intr odu ctio n of the so call ed cris is tax , w h i c h w i l l b e l e v i e d o n a l l s a l a r i e s , p e n s i o n s a n d i n c o m e s o v e r H R K 3 , 0 0 0 . G o v e r n m e n t , s o c i a l p a r t n e r s t o r e s u m e t a l k s o n i n t r o d u c t i o n o f “ c r i s i s ” t a x . T h e g o v e r n m e n t a n d t h e s o c i a l p a r t n e r s w i l l r e s u m e t h e t a l k s o n t h e i n t r o d u c t i o n o f t h e c r i s i s t a x T h e g o v e r n m e n t w i l l r e s u m e t h e t a l k s o n t h e i n t r o d u c t i o n o f t h e c r i s i s t a x w h i c h w i l l b e l e v i e d T h e g o v e r n m e n t a n d t h e s o c i a l p a r t n e r s w i l l r e s u m e t h e t a l k s o n t h e i n t r o d u c t i o n o f t h e c r i s i s t a x S H H * U O E n g l a n d s t a r D a v i d B e c k h a m m a y h a v e t h e c h a n c e t o r e t u r n t o A C M i l a n a f t e r t h e I t a l i a n c l u b ’ s c o a c h s a i d h e w a s o p e n t o h i s m o v e o n S u n d a y . B e c k h a m h a s c h a n c e o f r e t u r n i n g t o M i l a n D a v i d B e c k h a m m a y h a v e t h e c h a n c e t o r e t u r n t o A C M i l a n D a v i d B e c k h a m m a y h a v e t h e c h a n c e t o r e t u r n s a i d s t a r w a s D a v i d B e c k h a m m a y h a v e t h e c h a n c e t o r e t u r n t o A C M i l a n S H H * U O Ea ster n He alth and its ins ura nce co mp any hav e acc ept ed lia bilit y for so me pati ent s inv olv ed in the bre ast ca nc er t e s t i n g s c a n d a l , a c c o r d i n g t o a s t a t e m e n t r e l e a s e d F r i d a y a f t e r n o o n . E a s t e r n H e a l t h a c c e p t s l i a b i l i t y f o r s o m e p a t i e n t s E a s t e r n H e a l t h h a v e a c c e p t e d l i a b i l i t y f o r s o m e p a t i e n t s H e a l t h h a v e a c c e p t e d l i a b i l i t y a c c o r d i n g t o a s t a t e m e n t E a s t e r n H e a l t h h a v e a c c e p t e d l i a b i l i t y f o r s o m e p a t i e n t s S H H * U O Fro ntie r Co mm uni cati ons Cor p., a pro vid er of pho ne, TV and Inte rnet ser vic es, sai d Th urs da y i t h a s s t a r t e d a c a s h t e n d e r o f f e r t o p u r c h a s e u p t o $ 7 0 0 m i l l i o n o f i t s n o t e s . F r o n t i e r C o m m u n i c a t i o n s s t a r t s t e n d e r o f f e r f o r u p t o $ 7 0 0 m i l l i o n o f n o t e s Fro ntie r Co mm uni cati ons has star ted a ten der off er to pur cha se $70 0 mill ion of its not es Fro ntie r Co mm uni cati ons sai d Thu rsd ay a pro vid er has star ted a ten der off er Fro ntie r Co mm uni cati ons has star ted a ten der off er to pur cha se $70 0 mill ion of its not es</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
