<PAPER>
  <S sid="0" ssid="0">Mixed Initiative in Dialogue: An Investigation into Discourse Segmentation Marilyn Walker University of Pennsylvania* Computer Science Dept.</S>
  <S sid="1" ssid="1">Philadelphia, PA 19104 lyn@linc.cis.upenn.edu Steve Whittaker Hewlett Packard Laboratories Bristol, England BS12 6QZ HP Stanford Science Center sjw@hplb.hpl.hp.com Abstract Conversation between two people is usually of MIXED-INITIATIVE, with CONTROL over the con- versation being transferred from one person to an- other.</S>
  <S sid="2" ssid="2">We apply a set of rules for the transfer of control to 4 sets of dialogues consisting of a total of 1862 turns.</S>
  <S sid="3" ssid="3">The application of the control rules lets us derive domain-independent discourse structures.</S>
  <S sid="4" ssid="4">The derived structures indicate that initiative plays a role in the structuring of discourse.</S>
  <S sid="5" ssid="5">In order to explore the relationship of control and initiative to discourse processes like centering, we analyze the distribution of four different classes of anaphora for two data sets.</S>
  <S sid="6" ssid="6">This distribution i dicates that some control segments are hierarchically related to oth- ers.</S>
  <S sid="7" ssid="7">The analysis uggests that discourse partic- ipants often mutually agree to a change of topic.</S>
  <S sid="8" ssid="8">We also compared initiative in Task Oriented and Advice Giving dialogues and found that both allo- cation of control and the manner in which control is transferred is radically different for the two dia- logue types.</S>
  <S sid="9" ssid="9">These differences can be explained in terms of collaborative planning principles.</S>
  <S sid="10" ssid="10">1 Introduct ion Conversation between two people has a number of characteristics that have yet to be modeled ade- quately in human-computer dialogue.</S>
  <S sid="11" ssid="11">Conversa- tion is BIDIRECTIONAL; there is a two way flow of information between participants.</S>
  <S sid="12" ssid="12">Information *This research was partially funded by ARO grants DAAG29-84-K-0061 and DAAL03-89-C0031PRI, DARPA grant N00014-85-K0018, and NSF grant MCS-82-19196 at the University of Pennsylvania, and by Hewlett Packard, U.K. is exchanged by MIXED-INITIATIVE.</S>
  <S sid="13" ssid="13">Each partici- pant will, on occasion, take the conversational lead.</S>
  <S sid="14" ssid="14">Conversational partners not only respond to what others say, but feel free to volunteer information that is not requested and sometimes ask questions of their own[Nic76].</S>
  <S sid="15" ssid="15">As INITIATIVE passes back and forth between the discourse participants, we say that CONTROL over the conversation gets trans- ferred from one discourse participant to another.</S>
  <S sid="16" ssid="16">Why should we, as computational linguists, be interested in factors that contribute to the interac- tivity of a discourse?</S>
  <S sid="17" ssid="17">There are both theoretical and practical motivations.</S>
  <S sid="18" ssid="18">First, we wish to ex- tend formal accounts of single utterances produced by single speakers to explain multi-participant, multi-utterance discourses[Po186, CP86].</S>
  <S sid="19" ssid="19">Previ- ous studies of the discourse structure of multi- participant dialogues have often factored out the role of MIXED-INITIATIVE, by allocating control to one participant[Gro77, Coh84], or by assuming a passive listener[McK85, Coh87].</S>
  <S sid="20" ssid="20">Since conversation is a collaborative process[CWG86, SSJ74], models of conversation can provide the basis for extending planning theories[GS90, CLNO90].</S>
  <S sid="21" ssid="21">When the sit- uation requires the negotiation of a collaborative plan, these theories must account for the interact- ing beliefs and intentions of multiple participants.</S>
  <S sid="22" ssid="22">~,From apractical perspective, there is ample evi- dence that limited mixed-initiative has contributed to lack of system usability.</S>
  <S sid="23" ssid="23">Many researchers have noted that the absence of mixed-initiative gives rise to two problems with expert systems: They dont allow users to participate in the rea- soning process, or to ask the questions they want answered[PHW82, Kid85, FL89].</S>
  <S sid="24" ssid="24">In addition, ques- tion answering systems often fail to take account of the systems role as a conversational partner.</S>
  <S sid="25" ssid="25">70 For example, fragmentary utterances may be inter- preted with respect o the previous user input, but what users say is often in reaction to the systems previous response[CP82, Sid83].</S>
  <S sid="26" ssid="26">In this paper we focus on interactive discourse.</S>
  <S sid="27" ssid="27">We model mixed-initiative using an utterance type classification and a set of rules for transfer of control between discourse participants that were proposed by Whittaker and Stenton[WS88].</S>
  <S sid="28" ssid="28">We evaluate the generality of this analysis by applying the control rules to 4 sets of dialogues, including both advi- sory dialogues (ADs) and task-oriented ialogues (TODs).</S>
  <S sid="29" ssid="29">We analysed both financial and support ADs.</S>
  <S sid="30" ssid="30">The financial ADs are from the radio talk show "Harry Gross: Speaking of Your Money "1 The support ADs resulted from a client phoning an expert o help them diagnose and repair various software faults ~.</S>
  <S sid="31" ssid="31">The TODs are about the construc- tion of a plastic water pump in both telephone and keyboard modality S. The application of the control rules to these dia- logues lets us derive domain-independent discourse segments with each segment being controlled by one or other discourse participant.</S>
  <S sid="32" ssid="32">We propose that control segments correspond to different subgoals in the evolving discourse plan.</S>
  <S sid="33" ssid="33">In addition, we ar- gue that various linguistic devices are necessary for conversational participants to coordinate their con- tributions to the dialogue and agree on their mu- tual beliefs with respect o a evolving plan, for ex- ample, to agree that a particular subgoal has been achieved.</S>
  <S sid="34" ssid="34">A final phenomenon concerns hifts of control and the devices used to achieve this.</S>
  <S sid="35" ssid="35">Con- trol shifts occur because it is unusual for a single participant o be responsible for coordinating the achievement of the whole discourse plan.</S>
  <S sid="36" ssid="36">When a different participant assumes control of a discourse subgoal then a control shift occurs and the par- ticipants must have mechanisms for achieving this.</S>
  <S sid="37" ssid="37">The control framework distinguishes instances in which a control shift is negotiated by the partic- ipants and instances where one participant seizes control.</S>
  <S sid="38" ssid="38">This paper has two objectives: 110 randomly selected ialogues (474 turns) from a corpus that was collected and transcribed by Martha Pollack and Julia Hirschberg[HL87, PHW82].</S>
  <S sid="39" ssid="39">24 dialogues (450 turns) from tapes made at one of Hewlett-Packards customer response centers.</S>
  <S sid="40" ssid="40">35 keyboard (224 turns) and 5 telephone dialogues (714 turns), which were collected in an experiment by Phil Cohen to explore the relationship between modality, interactivity and use of referring expressions[Coh84].</S>
  <S sid="41" ssid="41">To explore the phenomenon of control in rela- tion to ATTENTIONAL STATE [GS86, GJW86, Sid79] 4.</S>
  <S sid="42" ssid="42">We predict shifts of attentional state when shifts in control are negotiated and agreed by all participants, but not when con- trol is seized by one participant without the acceptance of the others.</S>
  <S sid="43" ssid="43">This should be re- flected in different distribution of anaphora in the two cases.</S>
  <S sid="44" ssid="44">To test predictions about the distribution of control in different types of dialogues.</S>
  <S sid="45" ssid="45">Be- cause the TODs embody the master-slave assumption[GSg0], and control is allocated to the expert, our expectation is that control should be located exclusively with one partici- pant in the TODs in contrast with the ADs.</S>
  <S sid="46" ssid="46">2 Rules  for the A l locat ion and Transfer of Control We use the framework for the allocation and trans- fer of control of Whittaker and Stenton[WS88].</S>
  <S sid="47" ssid="47">The analysis is based on a classification of utterances into 4 types 5.</S>
  <S sid="48" ssid="48">UTTERANCE TYPES -- ASSERTIONS: Declarative utterances used to state facts.</S>
  <S sid="49" ssid="49">Yes and No in response to a question were classified as assertions on the basis that they are supplying informa- tion.</S>
  <S sid="50" ssid="50">-- COMMANDS: Utterances intended to in- stigate action.</S>
  <S sid="51" ssid="51">Generally imperative form, but could be indirect such as My suggestion would be that you do ..... -QUESTIONS: Utterances which are in- tended to elicit information, including in- direct forms such as I was wondering whether I should .... -- PROMPTS: Utterances which did not ex- press propositional content, such as Yeah, Okay, Uh-huh .... 4The theory of centering, which is part of attentional state, depends on discourse participants recognizing the be- ginning and end of a discourse segment[BFP87, Wal89].</S>
  <S sid="52" ssid="52">5The relationship between utterance l vel meaning and discourse intentions rests on a theory of joint commitment or shared plans[GSg0, CLNO90, LCN90] 71 Note that prompts are in direct contrast o the other options that a participant has available at any point in the discourse.</S>
  <S sid="53" ssid="53">By indicating that the speaker does not want the floor, prompts function on a number of levels, including the expression of understanding or agreement[Sch82].</S>
  <S sid="54" ssid="54">The rules for the allocation of control are based on the utterance type classification and allow a di- alogue to be divided into segments that correspond to which speaker is the controller of the segment.</S>
  <S sid="55" ssid="55">CONTROL RULES UTTERANCE ASSERT ION COMMAND QUEST ION PROMPT CONTROLLER (ICP) SPEAKER, unless response to a Question SPEAKER SPEAKER, unless response to Question or Command HEARER The definition of controller can be seen to cor- respond to the intuitions behind the term INITI- ATING CONVERSATIONAL PARTICIPANT (ICP), who is defined as the initiator of a given discourse segment[GS86].</S>
  <S sid="56" ssid="56">The OTHER CONVERSATIONAL PARTICIPANT(S), OCP, may speak some utterances in a segment, but the DISCOURSE SEGMENT PUR- POSE, must be the purpose of the ICP.</S>
  <S sid="57" ssid="57">The control rules place a segment boundary whenever the roles of the participants (ICP or OCP) change.</S>
  <S sid="58" ssid="58">For ex- ample: Abdication Example E: "And they are, in your gen youql find that theyve relo- Cated into the labelled common area" (ASSERT - E control) C: "Thats right."</S>
  <S sid="59" ssid="59">(PROMPT - E control) E: "Yeah" (PROMPT - E abdicates control) CONTROL SHIFT TO C - - C: "Ive got two in there.</S>
  <S sid="60" ssid="60">There are two of them."</S>
  <S sid="61" ssid="61">(ASSERT - C control) E: "Right" (PROMPT - C control) C: "And theres another one which is % RESA" (ASSERT - C control) E: "OK urn" (PROMPT - C control) C: "VS" (ASSERT- C control) E: "Right" (PROMPT - C control) C: "Mm" (PROMPT - C abdicates control) CONTROL SHIFT TO E - - - - E: "Right and you havent got - I assume you havent got local labelled common with those labels" (QUESTION - E control) Whittaker and Stenton also performed a post-hoe analysis of the segment boundaries that are defined by the control rules.</S>
  <S sid="62" ssid="62">The boundaries fell into one of three types: ?</S>
  <S sid="63" ssid="63">CONTROL SHIFT  TYPES - ABDICATION: Okay, go on.</S>
  <S sid="64" ssid="64">- REPETITION/SUMMARY: That would be my recommendation a d that will ensure that you get a logically integral set of files.</S>
  <S sid="65" ssid="65">- I N T E R R U P T I O N :  It is something new though urn.</S>
  <S sid="66" ssid="66">ABDICATIONS 6 correspond to those cases where the controller produces a prompt as the last utterance of the segment.</S>
  <S sid="67" ssid="67">The class REPETI- TION/SUMMARY corresponds to the controller pro- ducing a redundant  utterance.</S>
  <S sid="68" ssid="68">The utterance is either an exact repetition of previous propositional content, or a summary that realizes a proposition, P, which could have been inferred from what came before.</S>
  <S sid="69" ssid="69">Thus orderly control shifts occur when the controller explicitly indicates that s/he wishes to relinquish control.</S>
  <S sid="70" ssid="70">What unifies ABDICATIONS and REPETITION/SUMMARIES is that the controller supplies no new propositional content.</S>
  <S sid="71" ssid="71">The re- maining class, INTERRUPTIONS, characterize shifts occurring when the noncontroller displays initia- tive by seizing control.</S>
  <S sid="72" ssid="72">This class is more general than other definitions of Interruptions.</S>
  <S sid="73" ssid="73">It prop- erly contains cross-speaker interruptions that in- volve topic shift, similar to the true-interruptions of Grosz and Sidner[GS86], as well as clarification subdialogues[Sid83, LA90].</S>
  <S sid="74" ssid="74">This classification suggests that the transfer of control is often a collaborative phenomenon.</S>
  <S sid="75" ssid="75">Since a noncontroller(OCP), has the option of seizing con- trol at any juncture in discourse, it would seem that controllers(ICPs), are in control because the noncontroller allows it.</S>
  <S sid="76" ssid="76">These observations address problems raised by Grosz and Sidner, namely how ICPs signal and OCPs recognize segment bound- aries.</S>
  <S sid="77" ssid="77">The claim is that shifts of control often do not occur until the controller indicates the end of a discourse segment by abdicating or producing a repetition/summary.</S>
  <S sid="78" ssid="78">3 Control Segmentation and Anaphora To determine the relationship between the de- rived control segments and ATTENTIONAL STATE we 6Our abdication category was called prompt by [WS88].</S>
  <S sid="79" ssid="79">72 looked at the distribution of anaphora with respect to the control segments in the ADs.</S>
  <S sid="80" ssid="80">All data were analysed statistically by X 2 and all differences cited are significant at the 0.05 level.</S>
  <S sid="81" ssid="81">We looked at all anaphors (excluding first and second person), and grouped them into 4 classes.</S>
  <S sid="82" ssid="82">C lasses  o f  Anaphors - 3RD PERSON: it, they, them, their, she, he, her, him, his - -  ONE/SOME, one of them, one of those, a new one, that one, the other one, some - DEICTIC: Noun phrases, e.g.</S>
  <S sid="83" ssid="83">this, that, this NP, that NP, those NP, these NP - EVENT: Verb Phrases, Sentences, Seg- ments, e.g.</S>
  <S sid="84" ssid="84">this, that, it The class DEICTIC refers to deictic references to material introduced by noun phrases, whereas the class EVENT refers to material introduced clausally.</S>
  <S sid="85" ssid="85">3.1 Hierarchical Relationships The first phenomenon we noted was that the anaphora distribution indicated that some seg- ments are hierarchically related to others 7.</S>
  <S sid="86" ssid="86">This was especially apparent in cases where one dis- course participant interrupted briefly, then imme- diately passed control back to the other.</S>
  <S sid="87" ssid="87">Interrupt/Abdicate 1 A: ... the only way I could do that was to take a to take a one third down and to take back a mortgage (ASSERTION) -INTERRUPT SHIFT TO B- - - 2.</S>
  <S sid="88" ssid="88">B: When you talk about one third put a number on it (QUESTION) 3.</S>
  <S sid="89" ssid="89">A: uh 15 thou (ASSERTION, but response) 4.</S>
  <S sid="90" ssid="90">B: go ahead (PROMPT) - - - -ABDICATE SHIFT BACK TO .4.- 5.</S>
  <S sid="91" ssid="91">A: and then Im a mortgage baz.k for 36 The following example illustrates the same point.</S>
  <S sid="92" ssid="92">Interrupt/Abdicate 2 1.</S>
  <S sid="93" ssid="93">A: The maximum amount ... will be $400 on THEIR tax return.</S>
  <S sid="94" ssid="94">(ASSERTION) INTERRUPT SHIFT TO B 7Similar phenomena h s been noted by many researchers in discourse including[Gro77, Hob79, Sid79, PHg0].</S>
  <S sid="95" ssid="95">B: 400 for the whole year?</S>
  <S sid="96" ssid="96">A: yeah itll be 20% (ASSERTION, but response) 4.</S>
  <S sid="97" ssid="97">B: um hm (PROMPT) - - - - -ABDICATE SHIFT BACK TO A- 5.</S>
  <S sid="98" ssid="98">A: now if indeed THEY pay the $2000 to your wife ....</S>
  <S sid="99" ssid="99">The control segments as defined would treat both of these cases as composed of 3 different segments.</S>
  <S sid="100" ssid="100">But this ignores the fact that utterances (1) and (5) have closely related propositional content in the first example, and that the plural pronoun straddles the central subsegment with the same referents be- ing picked out by they and their in the second ex- ample.</S>
  <S sid="101" ssid="101">Thus we allowed for hierarchical segments by treating the interruptions of 2-4 as subsegments, and utterances 1 and 5 as related parts of the parent segments.</S>
  <S sid="102" ssid="102">All interruptions were treated as embed- dings in this way.</S>
  <S sid="103" ssid="103">However the relationship of the segment after the interruption to the segment be- fore must be determined on independent grounds such as topic or intentional structure.</S>
  <S sid="104" ssid="104">3.2 Distr ibution Once we extended the control framework to allow for the embedding of interrupts, we coded every anaphor with respect o whether its antecedent lay outside or within the current segment.</S>
  <S sid="105" ssid="105">These are la- belled X (cross segment boundary antecedent) NX (no cross segment boundary), in Figure 1.</S>
  <S sid="106" ssid="106">In addi- tion we break these down as to which type of control shift occurred at the previous egment boundary.</S>
  <S sid="107" ssid="107">3rd Pets One Deictic Event x  xlxk xlxi x x I Abdication 1 105 0 10 27 7 18 3  ll01 4 l i31  5 li 5 i Inter pt 7 :7 il 0 I 0 il 8 I 9 i l2  1, I TOTAL 11 165 el 0 I 14 ii 24 I 41 el 1 34 i Figure 1: Distribution of Anaphora in Finance ADs We also looked at the distribution of anaphora in the Support ADs and found similar results.</S>
  <S sid="108" ssid="108">For both dialogues, the distribution of anaphors varies according to which type of control shift oc- curred at the previous segment boundary.</S>
  <S sid="109" ssid="109">When we look at the different ypes of anaphora, we find that third person and one anaphors cross bound- 73 Abdication Summary Interrupt TOTAL 3rd Pets One Deictic Event x ixtvlixl xllx v 4 46 0 4 12 4 4 =6 i l l  4 II 10 16  II 9 =4 6 40 II 0 4 115 I 5 II 5 10 16 11211 1 11 11191 23 Il ls 42 I Figure 2: Distribution of Anaphora in Support ADs aries extremely rarely, but the event anaphors and the deictic pronouns demonstrate a different pat- tern.</S>
  <S sid="110" ssid="110">What does this mean?</S>
  <S sid="111" ssid="111">The fact that anaphora is more likely to cross segment boundaries following interruptions than for summaries or abdications i consistent with the con- trol principles.</S>
  <S sid="112" ssid="112">With both summaries and abdica- tions the speaker gives an explicit signal that s/he wishes to relinquish control.</S>
  <S sid="113" ssid="113">In contrast, interrup- tions are the unprompted attempts of the listener to seize control, often having to do with some prob- lem with the controllers utterance.</S>
  <S sid="114" ssid="114">Therefore, in- terruptions are much more likely to be within topic.</S>
  <S sid="115" ssid="115">But why should deixis and event anaphors be- have differently from the other anaphors?</S>
  <S sid="116" ssid="116">Deixis serves to pick out objects that cannot be selected by the use of standard anaphora, i.e.</S>
  <S sid="117" ssid="117">we should expect he referents for deixis to be outside imme- diate focus and hence more likely to be outside the current segment[Web86].</S>
  <S sid="118" ssid="118">The picture is more com- plex for event anaphora, which seems to serve a number of different functions in the dialogue.</S>
  <S sid="119" ssid="119">It is used to talk about the past events that lead up to the current situation, I did THAT in order to move the place.</S>
  <S sid="120" ssid="120">It is also used to refer to sets of propo- sitions of the preceding discourse, Now THATS  a little background (cf [Web88]).</S>
  <S sid="121" ssid="121">The most prevalent usei however, was to refer to future events or ac- tions, THAT would be the move that I would make - but you have to do IT  the same day.</S>
  <S sid="122" ssid="122">SUMMARY EXAMPLE A: As far as you are concerned THAT could cost you more .... whats your tax bracket?</S>
  <S sid="123" ssid="123">(QUESTION) B: Well Im on pension Harry and my wife hasnt worked at all and ..(ASSERT/RESP) A: No reason at all why you cant do THAT.</S>
  <S sid="124" ssid="124">(ASSERTION) - - -SUMMARY 3HIFT to B .... 13: See my comment was if we should throw even the $2000 into an IRA or something for her.</S>
  <S sid="125" ssid="125">(ASSERTION) --REPETITION SHIFT to A.</S>
  <S sid="126" ssid="126">A: You could do THAT too.</S>
  <S sid="127" ssid="127">(ASSERTION) Since the task in the ADs is to develop a plan, speakers use event anaphora s concise references to the plans they have just negotiated and to discuss the status and quality of plans that have been sug- gested.</S>
  <S sid="128" ssid="128">Thus the frequent cross-speaker references to future events and actions correspond to phases of plan negotiation[PHW82].</S>
  <S sid="129" ssid="129">More importantly these references are closely related to the control struc- ture.</S>
  <S sid="130" ssid="130">The example above illustrates the clustering of event anaphora t segment boundaries.</S>
  <S sid="131" ssid="131">One dis- course participant uses an anaphor to summarize a plan, but when the other participant evaluates this plan there may be a control shift and any reference to the plan will necessarily cross a control boundary.</S>
  <S sid="132" ssid="132">The distribution of event anaphora bears this out, since 23/25 references to future actions are within 2 utterances of a segment boundary (See the ex- ample above).</S>
  <S sid="133" ssid="133">More significantly every instance of event anaphora crossing a segment boundary occurs when the speaker is talking about future events or actions.</S>
  <S sid="134" ssid="134">We also looked at the TODs for instances of anaphora being used to describe a future act in the way that we observed in the ADs.</S>
  <S sid="135" ssid="135">However, over the 938 turns in the TODs, there were only 18 instances of event anaphora, because in the main there were few occasions when it was necessary to talk about the plan.</S>
  <S sid="136" ssid="136">The financial ADs had 45 event anaphors in 474 utterances.</S>
  <S sid="137" ssid="137">4 Cont ro l  and  Co l laborat ive P lans To explore the relationship of control to planning, we compare the TODs with both types of ADs (financial and support).</S>
  <S sid="138" ssid="138">We would expect these dialogues to differ in terms of initiative.</S>
  <S sid="139" ssid="139">In the ADs, the objective is to develop a collaborative plan through a series of conversational exchanges.</S>
  <S sid="140" ssid="140">Both discourse participants believe that the expert has knowledge about the domain, but only has partial information about the situation.</S>
  <S sid="141" ssid="141">They also believe that the advisee must contribute both the prob- lem description and also constraints as to how the problem can be solved.</S>
  <S sid="142" ssid="142">This information must be exchanged, so that the mutual beliefs necessary to develop the collaborative plan are established in the conversation[Jos82].</S>
  <S sid="143" ssid="143">The situation is different 74 in the TODs.</S>
  <S sid="144" ssid="144">Both participants here believe at the outset that the expert has sufficient informa- tion about the situation and complete and correct knowledge about how to execute the Task.</S>
  <S sid="145" ssid="145">Since the apprentice has no need to assert information to change the experts beliefs or to ask questions to verify the experts beliefs or to issue commands, we should not expect the apprentice to have con- trol.</S>
  <S sid="146" ssid="146">S/he is merely present o execute the actions indicated by the knowledgeable participant.</S>
  <S sid="147" ssid="147">The differences in the beliefs and knowledge states of the participants can be interpreted in the terms of the collaborative planning principles of Whittaker and Stenton[WS88].</S>
  <S sid="148" ssid="148">We generalize the principles of INFORMATION QUALITY and PLAN QUALITY, which predict when an interrupt should occur .</S>
  <S sid="149" ssid="149">INFORMATION QUALITY: The listener must be- lieve that the information that the speaker has provided is true, unambiguous and relevant o the mutual goal.</S>
  <S sid="150" ssid="150">This corresponds to the two rules: (A1) TRUTH: If the listener believes a fact P and believes that fact to be relevant and either believes that the speaker believes not P or that the speaker does not know P then inter- rupt; (A2)AMBIGUITY: If the listener believes that the speakers assertion is relevant but am- biguous then interrupt.</S>
  <S sid="151" ssid="151">PLAN QUALITY: The listener must believe that the action proposed by the speaker is a part of an adequate plan to achieve the mutual goal and the action must also be comprehensible to the listener.</S>
  <S sid="152" ssid="152">The two rules to express this are: (B1)EFFECTIVENESS: If the listener believes P and either believes that P presents an ob- stacle to the proposed plan or believes that P ?</S>
  <S sid="153" ssid="153">is part of the proposed plan that has already been satisfied, then interrupt; (B2) AMBIGU- ITY: If  the listener believes that an assertion about the proposed plan is ambiguous, then interrupt.</S>
  <S sid="154" ssid="154">These principles indirectly proyide a means to ensure mutual belief.</S>
  <S sid="155" ssid="155">Since a participant must in- terrupt if any condition for an interrupt holds, then lack of interruption signals that there is no discrep- ancy in mutual beliefs.</S>
  <S sid="156" ssid="156">If there is such a discrep- ancy, the interruption is a necessary contribution to a collaborative plan, not a distraction from the joint activity.</S>
  <S sid="157" ssid="157">We compare ADs to TODs with respect o how Turns/Seg Exp-Contr Abdication Summary Interrupt Finance Support Task-Phone Task-Key 7.49 8.03 15.68 11.27 60?~ 51~ 91% 91% 38~ 38~0 45~ 28% 23?~ 27~ 7~ 6~ 38~ 36?~ 48~ 67% Turns/Seg: Average number of turns between control shifts Exp-Contr: % total turns controlled by expert Abdication: ~ control shifts that are Abdications Summaries: % control shifts that are Reps/Summaries Interrupt: ~ control shifts that are Interrupts Figure 3: Differences in Control for Dialogue Types often control is exchanged by calculating the aver- age number of turns between control shifts .</S>
  <S sid="158" ssid="158">We also investigate whether control is shared equally between participants and what percentage of con- trol shifts are represented by abdications, inter- rupts, and summaries for each dialogue type.</S>
  <S sid="159" ssid="159">Three things are striking about this data.</S>
  <S sid="160" ssid="160">As we predicted, the distribution of control between ex- pert and client is completely different in the ADs and the TODs.</S>
  <S sid="161" ssid="161">The expert has control for around 90% of utterances in the TODs whereas control is shared almost equally in the ADs.</S>
  <S sid="162" ssid="162">Secondly, con- trary to our expectations, we did find some in- stances of shifts in the TODs.</S>
  <S sid="163" ssid="163">Thirdly, the distri- bution of interruptions and summaries differs across dialogue types.</S>
  <S sid="164" ssid="164">How can the collaborative planning principles highlight the differences we observe?</S>
  <S sid="165" ssid="165">There seem to be two reasons why shifts occur in the TODs.</S>
  <S sid="166" ssid="166">First, many interruptions in the TODs result from the apprentice seizing control just to indicate that there is a temporary problem and that plan execution should be delayed.</S>
  <S sid="167" ssid="167">TASK INTERRUPT 1, A is the Instructor A: Its hard to get on (ASSERTION) - - - - - INTERRUPT SHIFT TO B B: Not there yet - ouch yep its there.</S>
  <S sid="168" ssid="168">(ASSERTION) A: Okay (PROMPT) B: Yeah (PROMPT) -ABDICATE SHIFT TO A- - A: All right.</S>
  <S sid="169" ssid="169">Now theres a little blue cap .. Second, control was exchanged when the execu- tion of the task started to go awry.</S>
  <S sid="170" ssid="170">8 We excluded turns  in dialogue openings and closings.</S>
  <S sid="171" ssid="171">75 TASK INTERRUPT 2, A is the Instructor A: And  then the elbow goes over that ... the big end of the elbow.</S>
  <S sid="172" ssid="172">(COMMAND) - - - INTERRUPT SHIFT TO B ~ B: You said that it d idnt  fit tight, but  it doesnt  fit t ight at all, okay ... (ASSERTION) A: Okay (PROMPT) B: Let me try THIS - oo1~ - again(ASSERTION) The problem with the physical situation indicates to the apprentice that the relevant beliefs are no longer shared.</S>
  <S sid="173" ssid="173">The Instructor is not in possession of critical information such as the current state of the apprentices pump.</S>
  <S sid="174" ssid="174">This necessitates an infor- mation exchange to resynchronize mutual beliefs, so that the rest of the plan "~ ~,v be successfully ex- ecuted.</S>
  <S sid="175" ssid="175">However, since control is explicitly allo- cated to the  instructor in TODs, there is no reason for that participant o believe that the other has any contribution to make.</S>
  <S sid="176" ssid="176">Thus there are fewer attempts by the instructor to coordinate activity, such as by using summaries to synchronize mutual beliefs.</S>
  <S sid="177" ssid="177">Therefore, if the apprentice needs to make a contribution, s/he must do so via interruption, explaining why there are many more interruptions in these dialogues.</S>
  <S sid="178" ssid="178">9 In addition, the majority of Interruptions (73%) are initiated by apprentices, in contrast to the ADs in which only 29% are produced by the Clients.</S>
  <S sid="179" ssid="179">Summaries are more frequent in ADs.</S>
  <S sid="180" ssid="180">In the ADs both participants believe that a plan cannot be con- structed without contributions from both of them.</S>
  <S sid="181" ssid="181">Abdications and summaries are devices which al- low these contributions to be coordinated and par- ticipants use these devices to explicitly set up op- portunities for one another to make a contribution, and to ensure mutual bellefs The increased fre- quency of summaries in the ADs may result from the fact that the participants start with discrepant mutual beliefs about the situation and that estab- lishing and maintaining mutual beliefs is a key part of the ADs.</S>
  <S sid="182" ssid="182">5 D iscuss ion It has Often been stated that discourse is an inher- ently collaborative process and that this is man- ifested in certain phenomena, e.g.</S>
  <S sid="183" ssid="183">the use of 9The higher, percentage of Interruptions in the keyboard TODs in comparison with the t ~1 ~ ./.hone TODs parallels Ovi- att and Cohens analysis, showing that participants exploit the Wider bandwidth of the iptoractive spoken channel to break tasks down into subtaskstCoh84 , OC89].</S>
  <S sid="184" ssid="184">anaphora nd cue words [GS86, HL87, Coh87] by which the speaker makes aspects of the discourse structure xplicit.</S>
  <S sid="185" ssid="185">We found shifts of attentional state when shifts in control are negotiated and agreed by all participants, but not when control is seized by one participant without the acceptance of the others.</S>
  <S sid="186" ssid="186">This was reflected in different distri- bution of anaphora in the two cases.</S>
  <S sid="187" ssid="187">Furthermore we found that not all types of anaphora behaved in the same way.</S>
  <S sid="188" ssid="188">Event anaphora clustered at seg- ment boundaries when it was used to refer to pre- ceding segments and was more likely to cross seg- ment boundaries because of its function in talking about the proposed plan.</S>
  <S sid="189" ssid="189">We also found that con- trol was distributed and exchanged ifferently in the ADs and TODs.</S>
  <S sid="190" ssid="190">These results provide support for the control rules.</S>
  <S sid="191" ssid="191">In our analysis we argued for hierarchical orga- nization of the control segments on the basis of specific examples of interruptions.</S>
  <S sid="192" ssid="192">We also be- lieve that there are other levels of structure in dis- course that are not captured by the control rules, e.g.</S>
  <S sid="193" ssid="193">control shifts do not always correspond with task boundaries.</S>
  <S sid="194" ssid="194">There can be topic shifts with- out change of initiation, change of control without a topic shift[WS88].</S>
  <S sid="195" ssid="195">The relationship of cue words, intonational contour[PH90] and the use of modal subordination[Rob86] to the segments derived from the control rules is a topic for future research.</S>
  <S sid="196" ssid="196">A more controversial question concerns rhetori- cal relations and the extent to which these are de- tected and used by listeners[GS86].</S>
  <S sid="197" ssid="197">Hobbs has ap- plied COHERENCE RELATIONS to face-to-face con- versation in which mixed-initiative is displayed by participants[HA85, Hob79].</S>
  <S sid="198" ssid="198">One category of rhetor- ical relation he describes is that of ELABORATION, in which a speaker epeats the propositional con- tent of a previous utterance.</S>
  <S sid="199" ssid="199">Hobbs has some diffi- culties determining the function of this repetition, but we maintain that the function follows from the more general principles of the control rules: speak- ers signal that they wish to shift control by sup- plying no new propositional content.</S>
  <S sid="200" ssid="200">Abdications, repetitions and summaries all add no new informa- tion and function to signal to the listener that the speaker has nothing further to say right now.</S>
  <S sid="201" ssid="201">The listener certainly must recognize this fact.</S>
  <S sid="202" ssid="202">Summaries appear to have an additional function of synchronization, by allowing both participants to agree on what propositions are mutually believed at that point in the discussion.</S>
  <S sid="203" ssid="203">Thus this work highlights aspects of collaboration i discourse, but 76 should be formally integrated with research on collaborative planning[GS90, LCN90], particularly with respect o the relation between control shifts and the coordination of  plans.</S>
  <S sid="204" ssid="204">6 Acknowledgements We would like to thank Aravind Joshi for his sup- port, comments and criticisms.</S>
  <S sid="205" ssid="205">Discussions of joint action with Phil Cohen and the members of CSLIs DIA working group have influenced the first au- thor.</S>
  <S sid="206" ssid="206">We are also indebted to Susan Brennan, Herb Clark, Julia Hirschberg, Jerry Hobbs, Libby Levi- son, Kathy McKeown, Ellen Prince, Penni Sibun, Candy Sidner, Martha Pollack, Phil Stenton, and Bonnie Webber for their insightful comments and criticisms on drafts of this paper.</S>
  <S sid="207" ssid="207">References [BFP87] Susan E. Brennan, Marilyn Walker Friedman, and Carl J. Pollard.</S>
  <S sid="208" ssid="208">A cen- tering approach to pronouns.</S>
  <S sid="209" ssid="209">25th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 155-162, 1987.</S>
  <S sid="210" ssid="210">[CLNO90] Phillip R. Cohen, Hector J. Levesque, Jose H. T. Nunes, and Sharon L. Ovi- att.</S>
  <S sid="211" ssid="211">Task oriented dialogue as a conse- quence of joint activity, 1990.</S>
  <S sid="212" ssid="212">Unpub- lished Manuscript.</S>
  <S sid="213" ssid="213">[Coh84] Phi]lip R. Cohen.</S>
  <S sid="214" ssid="214">The pragmatics of re- ferring and the modality of communica- tion.</S>
  <S sid="215" ssid="215">ComputationalLinguistics, 10:97- 146, 1984.</S>
  <S sid="216" ssid="216">[Coh87] Robin Cohen.</S>
  <S sid="217" ssid="217">Analyzing the structure of argumentative discourse.</S>
  <S sid="218" ssid="218">Computa- tional Linguistics, 13:11-24, 1987.</S>
  <S sid="219" ssid="219">[CP82] Phillip R. Cohen, C. Raymond Per- rault, and James F. Allen 1982.</S>
  <S sid="220" ssid="220">Beyond question answering.</S>
  <S sid="221" ssid="221">In Wendy Lehnert and Martin Ringle, editors, Strategies for Natural Language Processing, pages 245-274.</S>
  <S sid="222" ssid="222">Lawrence Erlbaum Ass.</S>
  <S sid="223" ssid="223">Inc, Hillsdale, N.J., 1982.</S>
  <S sid="224" ssid="224">[CP86] Philip R. Cohen and C. Raymond Perrault.</S>
  <S sid="225" ssid="225">Elements of a plan-based theory of speech acts.</S>
  <S sid="226" ssid="226">In Bonnie [CWG86] [FL89] [GJW86] [Gro77] [GS86] [GS90] [HA85] [HL87] [Hob79] [Jos82] Lynn Webber Barbara J. Grosz, Karen Sparck Jones, editor, Readings in Nat- ural Language Processing, pages 423- 440.</S>
  <S sid="227" ssid="227">Morgan Kauffman, Los Altos, Ca., 1986.</S>
  <S sid="228" ssid="228">Herbert H. Clark and Deanna Wilkes- Gibbs.</S>
  <S sid="229" ssid="229">Referring as a collaborative pro- cess.</S>
  <S sid="230" ssid="230">Cognition, 22:1-39, 1986.</S>
  <S sid="231" ssid="231">David M. Frohlich and Paul Luff.</S>
  <S sid="232" ssid="232">Con- versational resources for situated action.</S>
  <S sid="233" ssid="233">Annual Meeting of the Com- puter Human Interaction of the ACM, 1989.</S>
  <S sid="234" ssid="234">Barbara J. Grosz, Aravind K. Joshi, and Scott Weinstein.</S>
  <S sid="235" ssid="235">Towards a computa- tional theory of discourse interpretation.</S>
  <S sid="236" ssid="236">Unpublished Manuscript, 1986.</S>
  <S sid="237" ssid="237">Barbara J. Grosz.</S>
  <S sid="238" ssid="238">The representation and use of focus in dialogue understand- ing.</S>
  <S sid="239" ssid="239">Technical Report 151, SRI Inter- national, 333 Ravenswood Ave, Menlo Park, Ca.</S>
  <S sid="240" ssid="240">Barbara J. Grosz and Candace L. Sid- net.</S>
  <S sid="241" ssid="241">Attentions, intentions and the structure of discourse.</S>
  <S sid="242" ssid="242">Computational Linguistics, 12:pp.</S>
  <S sid="243" ssid="243">Barbara J. Grosz and Candace L. Sid- her.</S>
  <S sid="244" ssid="244">Plans for discourse.</S>
  <S sid="245" ssid="245">In Cohen, Morgan and Pollack, eds.</S>
  <S sid="246" ssid="246">Intentions in Communication, MIT Press, Cam- bridge, MA., 1990.</S>
  <S sid="247" ssid="247">Jerry R. Hobbs and Michael H. Agar.</S>
  <S sid="248" ssid="248">The coherence of incoherent discourse.</S>
  <S sid="249" ssid="249">Technical Report CSLI-85-38, Center for the Study of Language and Informa- tion, Ventura Hall, Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94305, 1985.</S>
  <S sid="250" ssid="250">Julia Hirschberg and Diane Litman.</S>
  <S sid="251" ssid="251">Now lets talk about now: Identifying cue phrases intonationally.</S>
  <S sid="252" ssid="252">25th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 163- 171, Stanford University, Stanford, Ca., 1987.</S>
  <S sid="253" ssid="253">Jerry R. Hobbs.</S>
  <S sid="254" ssid="254">Coherence and corefer- ence.</S>
  <S sid="255" ssid="255">Cognitive Science, 3:67-90, 1979.</S>
  <S sid="256" ssid="256">Aravind K. Joshi.</S>
  <S sid="257" ssid="257">Mutual beliefs in question-answer systems.</S>
  <S sid="258" ssid="258">In Neil V. 77 [Kid85] [LA90] [LCN90] [McK85] [Nic76] [oc89] [PH90] [PHW82] [Po186] Smith eds.</S>
  <S sid="259" ssid="259">Mutual Knowledge, Aca- demic Press, New York, New York, pages 181-199, 1982.</S>
  <S sid="260" ssid="260">The consultative role of an expert system.</S>
  <S sid="261" ssid="261">In P. Johnson and S. Cook, editors, People and Com- puters: Designing the Interface.</S>
  <S sid="262" ssid="262">Cam- bridge University Press, Cambridge, U.K., 1985.</S>
  <S sid="263" ssid="263">Diane Litman and James Allen.</S>
  <S sid="264" ssid="264">Rec- ognizing and relating discourse inten- tions and task-oriented plans.</S>
  <S sid="265" ssid="265">In Co- hen, Morgan and Pollack, eds.</S>
  <S sid="266" ssid="266">Inten- tions in Communication, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA., 1990.</S>
  <S sid="267" ssid="267">Hector J. Levesque, Phillip R. Cohen, and Jose H. T. Nunes.</S>
  <S sid="268" ssid="268">On acting to- gether.</S>
  <S sid="269" ssid="269">In AAAIgO, 1990.</S>
  <S sid="270" ssid="270">Kathleen R. McKeown.</S>
  <S sid="271" ssid="271">Discourse strategies for generating natural lan- guage text.</S>
  <S sid="272" ssid="272">Artificial Intelligence, 27(1):1-42, September 1985.</S>
  <S sid="273" ssid="273">On converational in- teraction with computers.</S>
  <S sid="274" ssid="274">In SiegFried Treu, editor, User-Oriented Design of Interactive Graphics Systems, pages 101-65.</S>
  <S sid="275" ssid="275">Elsevier Science, 1976.</S>
  <S sid="276" ssid="276">Sharon L. Oviatt and Philip R. Cohen.</S>
  <S sid="277" ssid="277">The effects of interaction on spoken dis- course.</S>
  <S sid="278" ssid="278">27th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 126-134, 1989.</S>
  <S sid="279" ssid="279">Janet Pierrehum- bert and Julia Hirschberg.</S>
  <S sid="280" ssid="280">The meaning of intonational contours in the interpre- tation of discourse.</S>
  <S sid="281" ssid="281">In Cohen, Morgan and Pollack, eds.</S>
  <S sid="282" ssid="282">Intentions in Commu- nication, MIT Press, Cambridge, MA., 1990.</S>
  <S sid="283" ssid="283">Martha Pollack, Julia Hirschberg, and Bonnie Webber.</S>
  <S sid="284" ssid="284">User participation in the reasoning process of expert systems.</S>
  <S sid="285" ssid="285">National Conference on Artifi- cial Intelligence, 1982.</S>
  <S sid="286" ssid="286">Martha Pollack.</S>
  <S sid="287" ssid="287">Inferring domain plans in question answering.</S>
  <S sid="288" ssid="288">Technical Report 403, SRI International - Artificial Intel- ligence Center, 1986.</S>
  <S sid="289" ssid="289">[Rob86] [Sch82] [Sid79] [Sid83] [SSJ74] [Wa189] [Web86] [Web88] [ws88] Craige Roberts.</S>
  <S sid="290" ssid="290">Modal Subordination and Anaphora.</S>
  <S sid="291" ssid="291">PhD thesis, Linguis- tics Dept, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, 1986.</S>
  <S sid="292" ssid="292">Emanuel A. Sehegloff.</S>
  <S sid="293" ssid="293">Discourse as an interactional chievement: Some uses of uh huh and other things that come between sentences.</S>
  <S sid="294" ssid="294">In D. Tannen, ed- itor, Analyzing Discourse: Text and Talk, pages 71-93.</S>
  <S sid="295" ssid="295">Georgetown Univer- sity Press, 1982.</S>
  <S sid="296" ssid="296">Candace L. Sidner.</S>
  <S sid="297" ssid="297">Toward a computa- tional theory of definite anaphora com- prehension i english.</S>
  <S sid="298" ssid="298">Technical Report AI-TR-537, MIT, 1979.</S>
  <S sid="299" ssid="299">Candace Sidner.</S>
  <S sid="300" ssid="300">What the speaker means: the recognition of speakers plans in discourse.</S>
  <S sid="301" ssid="301">International Journal of Computers and Mathematics, 9:71-82, 1983.</S>
  <S sid="302" ssid="302">Harvey Sacks, Emmanuel Schegloff, and Gail Jefferson.</S>
  <S sid="303" ssid="303">A simplest systematics for the organization of turn-taking in conversation.</S>
  <S sid="304" ssid="304">Language, 50:pp.</S>
  <S sid="305" ssid="305">Marilyn A. Walker.</S>
  <S sid="306" ssid="306">Evaluating dis- course processing algorithms.</S>
  <S sid="307" ssid="307">27th Annual Meeting of the A CL, pages 251-261, 1989.</S>
  <S sid="308" ssid="308">Bonnie Lynn Webber.</S>
  <S sid="309" ssid="309">Two steps closer to event reference.</S>
  <S sid="310" ssid="310">Technical Report MS-CIS-86-74, Line Lab 42, Depart- ment of Computer and Information Sci- ence, University of Pennsylvania, 1986.</S>
  <S sid="311" ssid="311">Bonnie Lynn Webber.</S>
  <S sid="312" ssid="312">Discourse deixis: Reference to discourse segments.</S>
  <S sid="313" ssid="313">26th Annual Meeting of the ACL, Association of Computational Linguis- tics, pages 113-123, 1988.</S>
  <S sid="314" ssid="314">Steve Whittaker and Phil Stenton.</S>
  <S sid="315" ssid="315">Cues and control in expert client dialogues.</S>
  <S sid="316" ssid="316">26th Annual Meeting of the ACL, Association of Computational Linguis- tics, pages 123-130, 1988.</S>
</PAPER>
