<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">We present an unsupervised model for coreference resolution that casts the problem as a clustering task in a directed labeled weighted multigraph.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">The model outperforms most systems participating in the English track of the CoNLL’12 shared task.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">Coreference resolution is the task of determining which mentions in a text refer to the same entity.</S>
			<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">With the advent of machine learning and the availability of annotated corpora in the mid 1990s the research focus shifted from rule-based approaches to supervised machine learning techniques.</S>
			<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">Quite recently, however, rule-based approaches regained popularity due to Stanford’s multi-pass sieve approach which exhibits state- of-the-art performance on many standard coreference data sets (Raghunathan et al., 2010) and also won the CoNLL2011 shared task on coreference resolution (Lee et al., 2011; Pradhan et al., 2011).</S>
			<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">These results show that carefully crafted rule-based systems which employ suitable inference schemes can achieve competitive performance.</S>
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">Such a system can be considered unsupervised in the sense that it does not employ training data for optimizing parameters.</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">In this paper we present a graph-based approach for coreference resolution that models a document to be processed as a graph.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">The nodes are mentions and the edges correspond to relations between mentions.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">Coreference resolution is performed via graph clustering.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">Our approach belongs to a class of recently proposed graph models for coreference resolution (Cai and Strube, 2010; Sapena et al., 2010; Martschat et al., 2012) and is designed to be a simplified version of existing approaches.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">In contrast to previous models belonging to this class we do not learn any edge weights but perform inference on the graph structure only which renders our model unsupervised.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">On the English data of the CoNLL’12 shared task the model outperforms most systems which participated in the shared task.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Related Work. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "1">Graph-based coreference resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "2">While not developed within a graph-based framework, factor-based approaches for pronoun resolution (Mitkov, 1998) can be regarded as greedy clustering in a multigraph, where edges representing factors for pronoun resolution have negative or positive weight.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "3">This yields a model similar to the one presented in this paper though Mitkov’s work has only been applied to pronoun resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "4">Nicolae and Nicolae (2006) phrase coreference resolution as a graph clustering problem: they first perform pairwise classification and then construct a graph using the derived confidence values as edge weights.</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "5">In contrast, work by Culotta et al.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "6">(2007), Cai and Strube (2010) and Sapena et al.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "7">(2010) omits the classification step entirely.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "8">Sapena et al.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "9">(2010) and Cai and Strube (2010) perform coreference resolution in one step using graph partitioning approaches.</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "10">These approaches participated in the recent CoNLL’11 shared task (Pradhan et al., 2011; Sapena et al., 2011; Cai et al., 2011b) with excellent results.</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "11">The approach by Cai et al.</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "12">(2011b) has been modified by Martschat et al.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "13">(2012) and ranked second in the English track at the CoNLL’12 shared task (Pradhan et al., 2012).</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "14">The top performing system at the CoNLL’12 shared task (Fernandes et al., 2012) 81 Proceedings of the ACL Student Research Workshop, pages 81–88, Sofia, Bulgaria, August 49 2013.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "15">Qc 2013 Association for Computational Linguistics also represents the problem as a graph by performing inference on trees constructed using the multi-pass sieve approach by Raghunathan et al.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "16">(2010) and Lee et al.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "17">(2011), which in turn won the CoNLL’11 shared task.</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "18">Unsupervised coreference resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "19">Cardie and Wagstaff (1999) present an early approach to unsupervised coreference resolution based on a cent sentences (both in the subject slot), which is also a weak coreference indicator.</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "20">We denote these relations as N Number, P AnaPron and P Subject respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "21">The graphical structure depicted in Figure 1 models these relations between the four mentions Leaders, Paris, recent developments and They.</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "22">straightforward clustering approach.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "23">Angheluta et al.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "24">(2004) build on their approach and devise more sophisticated clustering algorithms.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "25">Haghighi and Klein (2007), Ng (2008) and Charniak and Elsner (2009) employ unsupervised generative models.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "26">Poon and Domingos (2008) present a Markov Logic Network approach to unsupervised coreference resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "27">These approaches reach competitive performance on gold mentions but not on system mentions (Ng, 2008).</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "28">The multi-pass sieve Leaders recent developments P AnaPron P Subject P AnaPron Paris They approach by Raghunathan et al.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "29">(2010) can also be viewed as unsupervised.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="A Multigraph Model" number = "3">
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "1">We aim for a model which directly represents the relations between mentions in a graph structure.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "2">Clusters in the graph then correspond to entities.</S>
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "3">3.1 Motivation.</S>
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "4">To motivate the choice of our model, let us consider a simple made-up example.</S>
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "5">Leaders met in Paris to discuss recent developments.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "6">They left the city today.</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "7">We want to model that Paris is not a likely candidate antecedent for They due to number disagreement, but that Leaders and recent developments are potential antecedents for They.</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "8">We want to express that Leaders is the preferred antecedent, since Leaders and They are in a parallel construction both occupying the subject position in their respective sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "9">In other words, our model should express the following relations for this example: • number disagreement for (They, Paris), which indicates that the mentions are not coreferent,• the anaphor being a pronoun for (They, Lead ers), (They, recent developments) and (They, Paris), which is a weak indicator for coreference if the mentions are close to each other, • syntactic parallelism for (They, Leaders): bothmentions are in a parallel construction in adja Figure 1: An example graph modeling relations between mentions.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "10">A directed edge from a mention m to n indicates that n precedes m and that there is some relation between m and n that indicates coreference or non-coreference.</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "11">Labeled edges describe the relations between the mentions, multiple relations can hold between a pair.</S>
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "12">Edges may be weighted.</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "13">3.2 Multigraphs for Coreference Resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "14">Formally, the model is a directed labeled weighted multigraph.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "15">That is a tuple D = (R, V, A, w) where • R is the set of labels (in our case relations such as P Subject that hold between mentions), • V is the set of nodes (the mentions extracted from a document), • A ⊆ V × V × R is the set of edges (relations between two mentions), • w is a mapping w : A → R ∪ {±∞} (weights for edges).</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "16">Many graph models for coreference resolution operate on A = V ×V . Our multigraph model allows us to have multiple edges with different labels between mentions.</S>
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "17">To have a notion of order we employ a directed graph: We only allow an edge from m to n if m appears later in the text than n. To perform coreference resolution for a document d, we first construct a directed labeled multi- graph (Section 3.3).</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "18">We then assign a weight to each edge (Section 3.4).</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "19">The resulting graph is clustered to obtain the mentions that refer to the same entity (Section 3.5).</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "20">3.3 Graph Construction.</S>
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "21">Given a set M of mentions extracted from a document d, we set V = M , i.e. the nodes of the graph are the mentions.</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "22">To construct the edges A, we consider each pair (m, n) of mentions with n ≺ m. We then check for every relation r ∈ R if r holds for the pair (m, n).</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "23">If this is the case we add the edge (m, n, r) to A. For simplicity, we restrict ourselves to binary relations that hold between pairs of mentions (see Section 4).</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "24">The graph displayed in Figure 1 is the graph constructed for the mentions Leaders, Paris, recent developments and They from the example sentence at the beginning of this Section, where R = {P AnaPron, P Subject, N Number}.</S>
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "25">3.4 Assigning Weights.</S>
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "26">Depending on whether a relation r ∈ R is indicative for non-coreference (e.g. number disagree ment) or for coreference (e.g. string matching) it should be weighted differently.</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "27">We therefore divide R into a set of negative relations R− and a set of positive relations R+.</S>
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "28">Previous work on multigraphs for coreference resolution disallows any edge between mentions for which a negative relations holds (Cai et al., 2011b; Martschat et al., 2012).</S>
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "29">We take a similar approach and set w(m, n, r) = −∞ for (m, n, r) ∈ A when r ∈ R 1.</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "30">Work on graph-based models similar to ours report robustness with regard to the amount of training data used (Cai et al., 2011b; Cai et al., 2011a; Martschat et al., 2012).</S>
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "31">Motivated by their observations we treat every positive relation equally and set w(m, n, r) = 1 for (m, n, r) ∈ A if r ∈ R+.</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "32">In contrast to previous work on similar graph models we do not learn any edge weights from training data.</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "33">We compare this unsupervised scheme with supervised variants empirically in Section 5.</S>
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "34">3.5 Clustering.</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "35">To describe the clustering algorithm used in this work we need some additional terminology.</S>
			<S sid ="78" ssid = "36">If there exists an edge (m, n, r) ∈ A we say that n is a child of m. 1 We experimented with different weighting schemes for negative relations on development data (e.g. setting w(m, n, r) = −1) but did not observe a gain in performance.</S>
			<S sid ="79" ssid = "37">In the graph constructed according to the procedure described in Section 3.3, all children of a mention m are candidate antecedents for m. The relations we employ are indicators for coreference (which get a positive weight) and indicators for non-coreference (which get a negative weight).</S>
			<S sid ="80" ssid = "38">We aim to employ a simple and efficient clustering scheme on this graph and therefore choose 1-nearest-neighbor clustering: for every m, we choose as antecedent m’s child n such that the sum of edge weights is maximal and positive.</S>
			<S sid ="81" ssid = "39">We break ties by choosing the closest mention.</S>
			<S sid ="82" ssid = "40">In the unsupervised setting described in Section 3.4 this algorithm reduces to choosing the child that is connected via the highest number of positive relations and via no negative relation.</S>
			<S sid ="83" ssid = "41">For the graph depicted in Figure 1 this algorithm computes the clusters {They, Leaders}, {Paris} and {recent developments}.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Relations. " number = "4">
			<S sid ="84" ssid = "1">The graph model described in Section 3 is based on expressing relations between pairs of mentions via edges built from such relations.</S>
			<S sid ="85" ssid = "2">We now describe the relations currently used by our system.</S>
			<S sid ="86" ssid = "3">They are well-known indicators and constraints for coreference and are taken from previous work (Cardie and Wagstaff, 1999; Soon et al., 2001; Rahman and Ng, 2009; Lee et al., 2011; Cai et al., 2011b).</S>
			<S sid ="87" ssid = "4">All relations operate on pairs of mentions (m, n), where m is the anaphor and n is a candidate antecedent.</S>
			<S sid ="88" ssid = "5">If a relation r holds for (m, n), the edge (m, n, r) is added to the graph.</S>
			<S sid ="89" ssid = "6">We finalized the set of relations and their distance thresholds on development data.</S>
			<S sid ="90" ssid = "7">4.1 Negative Relations.</S>
			<S sid ="91" ssid = "8">Negative relations receive negative weights.</S>
			<S sid ="92" ssid = "9">They allow us to introduce well-known constraints such as agreement into our model.</S>
			<S sid ="93" ssid = "10">(1) N Gender, (2) N Number: Two mentions do not agree in gender or number.</S>
			<S sid ="94" ssid = "11">We compute number and gender for common nouns using the number and gender data provided by Bergsma and Lin (2006).</S>
			<S sid ="95" ssid = "12">(3) N SemanticClass: Two mentions do not agree in semantic class (we only use the top categories Object, Date and Person from WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998)).</S>
			<S sid ="96" ssid = "13">(4) N ItDist: The anaphor is it or they and the sentence distance to the antecedent is larger than one.</S>
			<S sid ="97" ssid = "14">(5) N Speaker12Pron: Two first person pronouns or two second person pronouns with different speakers, or one first person pronoun and one second person pronoun with the same speaker2.</S>
			<S sid ="98" ssid = "15">(6) N ContraSubObj: Two mentions are in the subject/object positions of the same verb, the anaphor is a non-possessive/reflexive pronoun.</S>
			<S sid ="99" ssid = "16">(7) N Mod: Two mentions have the same syntactic heads, and the anaphor has a nominal modifier which does not occur in the antecedent.</S>
			<S sid ="100" ssid = "17">(8) N Embedding: Two mentions where one embeds the other, which is not a reflexive or possessive pronoun.</S>
			<S sid ="101" ssid = "18">(9) N 2PronNonSpeech: Two second person pronouns without speaker information and not in direct speech.</S>
			<S sid ="102" ssid = "19">4.2 Positive Relations.</S>
			<S sid ="103" ssid = "20">Positive relations are coreference indicators which are added as edges with positive weights.</S>
			<S sid ="104" ssid = "21">(10) P NonPron StrMatch: Applies only if the anaphor is definite or a proper name3.</S>
			<S sid ="105" ssid = "22">This relation holds if after discarding stop words the strings of mentions completely match.</S>
			<S sid ="106" ssid = "23">(11) P HeadMatch: If the syntactic heads of mentions match.</S>
			<S sid ="107" ssid = "24">(12) P Alias: If mentions are aliases of each other (i.e. proper names with partial match, full names and acronyms, etc.).</S>
			<S sid ="108" ssid = "25">(13) P Speaker12Pron: If the speaker of the second person pronoun is talking to the speaker of the first person pronoun (applies only to first/second person pronouns).</S>
			<S sid ="109" ssid = "26">(14) P DSPron: One mention is a speak verb’s subject, the other mention is a first person pronoun within the corresponding direct speech.</S>
			<S sid ="110" ssid = "27">(15) P ReflPronSub: If the anaphor is a reflexive pronoun, and the antecedent is the subject of the sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="111" ssid = "28">(16) P PossPronSub: If the anaphor is a possessive pronoun, and the antecedent is the subject of the anaphor’s sentence or subclause.(17) P PossPronEmb: The anaphor is a posses 2 Like all relations using speaker information, this relation depends on the gold speaker annotation layer in the corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="112" ssid = "29">3 This condition is necessary to cope with the high-recall output of the mention tagger.</S>
			<S sid ="113" ssid = "30">sive pronoun embedded in the antecedent.</S>
			<S sid ="114" ssid = "31">(18) P AnaPron: If the anaphor is a pronoun and none of the mentions is a first or second person pronoun.</S>
			<S sid ="115" ssid = "32">This relation is restricted to a sentence distance of 3.</S>
			<S sid ="116" ssid = "33">(19) P VerbAgree: If the anaphor is a third person pronoun and has the same predicate as the antecedent.</S>
			<S sid ="117" ssid = "34">This relation is restricted to a sentence distance of 1.</S>
			<S sid ="118" ssid = "35">(20) P Subject, (21) P Object: The anaphor is a third person pronoun and both mentions are subjects/objects.</S>
			<S sid ="119" ssid = "36">These relations are restricted to a sentence distance of 1.</S>
			<S sid ="120" ssid = "37">(22) P Pron StrMatch: If both mentions are pronouns and their strings match.</S>
			<S sid ="121" ssid = "38">(23) P Pron Agreement: If both mentions are different pronoun tokens but agree in number, gender and person.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Evaluation. " number = "5">
			<S sid ="122" ssid = "1">5.1 Data and Evaluation Metrics.</S>
			<S sid ="123" ssid = "2">We use the data provided for the English track of the CoNLL’12 shared task on multilingual coreference resolution (Pradhan et al., 2012) which is a subset of the upcoming OntoNotes 5.0 release and comes with various annotation layers provided by state-of-the-art NLP tools.</S>
			<S sid ="124" ssid = "3">We used the official dev/test split for development and evaluation.</S>
			<S sid ="125" ssid = "4">We evaluate the model in a setting that corresponds to the shared task’s closed track, i.e. we use only WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998), the number and gender data of Bergsma and Lin (2006) and the provided annotation layers.</S>
			<S sid ="126" ssid = "5">To extract system mentions we employ the mention extractor described in Martschat et al.</S>
			<S sid ="127" ssid = "6">(2012).</S>
			<S sid ="128" ssid = "7">We evaluate our system with the coreference resolution evaluation metrics that were used for the CoNLL shared tasks on coreference, which are MUC (Vilain et al., 1995), B3 (Bagga and Baldwin, 1998) and CEAFe (Luo, 2005).</S>
			<S sid ="129" ssid = "8">We also report the unweighted average of the three scores, which was the official evaluation metric in the shared tasks.</S>
			<S sid ="130" ssid = "9">To compute the scores we employed the official scorer supplied by the shared task organizers.</S>
			<S sid ="131" ssid = "10">5.2 Results.</S>
			<S sid ="132" ssid = "11">Table 1 displays the performance of our model and of the systems that obtained the best (Fernandes et al., 2012) and the median performance in the MUC B3 CEAFe average R P F1 R P F1 R P F1 CoNLL’12 English development data be st 64.</S>
			<S sid ="133" ssid = "12">88 74.</S>
			<S sid ="134" ssid = "13">74 69.</S>
			<S sid ="135" ssid = "14">46 66.</S>
			<S sid ="136" ssid = "15">53 78.</S>
			<S sid ="137" ssid = "16">28 71.</S>
			<S sid ="138" ssid = "17">93 54.</S>
			<S sid ="139" ssid = "18">93 43.</S>
			<S sid ="140" ssid = "19">68 48.</S>
			<S sid ="141" ssid = "20">66 63.</S>
			<S sid ="142" ssid = "21">35 me dia n 62.</S>
			<S sid ="143" ssid = "22">3 62.</S>
			<S sid ="144" ssid = "23">8 62.</S>
			<S sid ="145" ssid = "24">0 66.</S>
			<S sid ="146" ssid = "25">7 71.</S>
			<S sid ="147" ssid = "26">8 69.</S>
			<S sid ="148" ssid = "27">1 46.</S>
			<S sid ="149" ssid = "28">4 44.</S>
			<S sid ="150" ssid = "29">9 45.</S>
			<S sid ="151" ssid = "30">6 58.</S>
			<S sid ="152" ssid = "31">9 thi s wo rk (w eig hts fra cti on ) 64.</S>
			<S sid ="153" ssid = "32">00 68.</S>
			<S sid ="154" ssid = "33">56 66.</S>
			<S sid ="155" ssid = "34">20 66.</S>
			<S sid ="156" ssid = "35">59 75.</S>
			<S sid ="157" ssid = "36">67 70.</S>
			<S sid ="158" ssid = "37">84 50.</S>
			<S sid ="159" ssid = "38">48 45.</S>
			<S sid ="160" ssid = "39">52 47.</S>
			<S sid ="161" ssid = "40">87 61.</S>
			<S sid ="162" ssid = "41">63 thi s wo rk (w eig hts Ma xE nt) 63.</S>
			<S sid ="163" ssid = "42">72 65.</S>
			<S sid ="164" ssid = "43">78 64.</S>
			<S sid ="165" ssid = "44">73 66.</S>
			<S sid ="166" ssid = "45">60 73.</S>
			<S sid ="167" ssid = "46">76 70.</S>
			<S sid ="168" ssid = "47">00 47.</S>
			<S sid ="169" ssid = "48">46 45.</S>
			<S sid ="170" ssid = "49">30 46.</S>
			<S sid ="171" ssid = "50">36 60.</S>
			<S sid ="172" ssid = "51">36 this wo rk (u ns up erv ise d) 64.</S>
			<S sid ="173" ssid = "52">01 68.</S>
			<S sid ="174" ssid = "53">58 66.</S>
			<S sid ="175" ssid = "54">22 67.</S>
			<S sid ="176" ssid = "55">00 76.</S>
			<S sid ="177" ssid = "56">45 71.</S>
			<S sid ="178" ssid = "57">41 51.</S>
			<S sid ="179" ssid = "58">10 46.</S>
			<S sid ="180" ssid = "59">16 48.</S>
			<S sid ="181" ssid = "60">51 62.</S>
			<S sid ="182" ssid = "61">05 CoNLL’12 English test data be st 65.</S>
			<S sid ="183" ssid = "62">83 75.</S>
			<S sid ="184" ssid = "63">91 70.</S>
			<S sid ="185" ssid = "64">51 65.</S>
			<S sid ="186" ssid = "65">79 77.</S>
			<S sid ="187" ssid = "66">69 71.</S>
			<S sid ="188" ssid = "67">24 55.</S>
			<S sid ="189" ssid = "68">00 43.</S>
			<S sid ="190" ssid = "69">17 48.</S>
			<S sid ="191" ssid = "70">37 63.</S>
			<S sid ="192" ssid = "71">37 me dia n 62.</S>
			<S sid ="193" ssid = "72">08 63.</S>
			<S sid ="194" ssid = "73">02 62.</S>
			<S sid ="195" ssid = "74">55 66.</S>
			<S sid ="196" ssid = "75">23 70.</S>
			<S sid ="197" ssid = "76">45 68.</S>
			<S sid ="198" ssid = "77">27 45.</S>
			<S sid ="199" ssid = "78">74 44.</S>
			<S sid ="200" ssid = "79">74 45.</S>
			<S sid ="201" ssid = "80">23 58.</S>
			<S sid ="202" ssid = "81">68 thi s wo rk (w eig hts fra cti on ) 64.</S>
			<S sid ="203" ssid = "82">25 68.</S>
			<S sid ="204" ssid = "83">31 66.</S>
			<S sid ="205" ssid = "84">22 65.</S>
			<S sid ="206" ssid = "85">44 74.</S>
			<S sid ="207" ssid = "86">20 69.</S>
			<S sid ="208" ssid = "87">54 49.</S>
			<S sid ="209" ssid = "88">18 44.</S>
			<S sid ="210" ssid = "89">71 46.</S>
			<S sid ="211" ssid = "90">84 60.</S>
			<S sid ="212" ssid = "91">87 thi s wo rk (w eig hts Ma xE nt) 63.</S>
			<S sid ="213" ssid = "92">58 64.</S>
			<S sid ="214" ssid = "93">70 64.</S>
			<S sid ="215" ssid = "94">14 65.</S>
			<S sid ="216" ssid = "95">63 72.</S>
			<S sid ="217" ssid = "96">09 68.</S>
			<S sid ="218" ssid = "97">71 45.</S>
			<S sid ="219" ssid = "98">58 44.</S>
			<S sid ="220" ssid = "99">41 44.</S>
			<S sid ="221" ssid = "100">99 59.</S>
			<S sid ="222" ssid = "101">28 this wo rk (u ns up erv ise d) 63.</S>
			<S sid ="223" ssid = "102">95 67.</S>
			<S sid ="224" ssid = "103">99 65.</S>
			<S sid ="225" ssid = "104">91 65.</S>
			<S sid ="226" ssid = "105">47 74.</S>
			<S sid ="227" ssid = "106">93 69.</S>
			<S sid ="228" ssid = "107">88 49.</S>
			<S sid ="229" ssid = "108">83 45.</S>
			<S sid ="230" ssid = "109">40 47.</S>
			<S sid ="231" ssid = "110">51 61.</S>
			<S sid ="232" ssid = "111">10 Table 1: Results of different systems on the CoNLL’12 English data sets.</S>
			<S sid ="233" ssid = "112">CoNLL’12 shared task, which are denoted as best and median respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="234" ssid = "113">best employs a structured prediction model with learned combinations of 70 basic features.</S>
			<S sid ="235" ssid = "114">We also compare with two supervised variants of our model which use the same relations and the same clustering algorithm as the unsupervised model: weights fraction sets the weight of a relation to the fraction of positive instances in training data (as in Martschat et al.</S>
			<S sid ="236" ssid = "115">(2012)).</S>
			<S sid ="237" ssid = "116">weights MaxEnt trains a mention-pair model (Soon et al., 2001) via the maximum entropy classifier implemented in the BART toolkit (Versley et al., 2008) and builds a graph where the weight of an edge connecting two mentions is the classifier’s prediction4.</S>
			<S sid ="238" ssid = "117">We use the official CoNLL’12 English training set for training.</S>
			<S sid ="239" ssid = "118">Our unsupervised model performs considerably better than the median system from the CoNLL’12 shared task on both data sets according to all metrics.</S>
			<S sid ="240" ssid = "119">It also seems to be able to accommodate well for the relations described in Section 4 since it outperforms both supervised variants5.</S>
			<S sid ="241" ssid = "120">The model performs worse than best, the gap according to B3 and CEAFe being considerably smaller than according to MUC.</S>
			<S sid ="242" ssid = "121">While we observe a decrease of 1 point average score when evaluating on test data the model still would have ranked fourth in the English track of the CoNLL’12 shared task with only 0.2 points difference in average score to the second ranked system.</S>
			<S sid ="243" ssid = "122">4 The classifier’s output is a number p ∈ [0, 1].</S>
			<S sid ="244" ssid = "123">In order to have negative weights we use the transformation pi = 2p − 1.</S>
			<S sid ="245" ssid = "124">5 Compared with the supervised variants all improvements in F1 score are statistically significant according to a paired t-test (p &lt; 0.05) except for the difference in MUC F1 to weights fraction.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Error Analysis. " number = "6">
			<S sid ="246" ssid = "1">In order to understand weaknesses of our model we perform an error analysis on the development data.</S>
			<S sid ="247" ssid = "2">We distinguish between precision and recall errors.</S>
			<S sid ="248" ssid = "3">For an initial analysis we split the errors according to the mention type of anaphor and antecedent (name, nominal and pronoun).</S>
			<S sid ="249" ssid = "4">6.1 Precision Errors.</S>
			<S sid ="250" ssid = "5">Our system operates in a pairwise fashion.</S>
			<S sid ="251" ssid = "6">We therefore count one precision error whenever the clustering algorithm assigns two non-coreferent mentions to the same cluster.</S>
			<S sid ="252" ssid = "7">Table 2 shows the NA M N O M PR O NA M 34 13 (21 %) 67 (6 6 %) 11 (4 6 %) N O M 43 (67 %) 21 48 (4 9 %) 9 (8 9 %) PR O 86 8 (32 %) 17 71 (5 5 %) 53 08 (2 4 %) Table 2: Number of clustering decisions made according to mention type (rows anaphor, columns antecedent) and percentage of wrong decisions.</S>
			<S sid ="253" ssid = "8">number of clustering decisions made according to the mention type and in brackets the fraction of decisions that erroneously assign two non-coreferent mentions to the same cluster.</S>
			<S sid ="254" ssid = "9">We see that two main sources of error are nominal-nominal pairs and the resolution of pronouns.</S>
			<S sid ="255" ssid = "10">We now focus on gaining further insight into the system’s performance for pronoun resolution by investigating the performance per pronoun type.</S>
			<S sid ="256" ssid = "11">The results are displayed in Table 3.</S>
			<S sid ="257" ssid = "12">We obtain good performance for I and my which in the majority of cases can be resolved unambiguously by the speaker relations employed by our system.</S>
			<S sid ="258" ssid = "13">The relations we use also seem Anaphor all anaphoric I 1260 (13%) 1239 (11%) my 192 (14%) 181 (9%) he 824 (14%) 812 (13%) . . .</S>
			<S sid ="259" ssid = "14">they 764 (29%) 725 (26%) . . .</S>
			<S sid ="260" ssid = "15">you 802 (41%) 555 (15%) it 1114 (64%) 720 (44%) Table 3: Precision statistics for pronouns.</S>
			<S sid ="261" ssid = "16">Rows are pronoun surfaces, columns number of clustering decisions and percentage of wrong decisions for all and only anaphoric pronouns respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="262" ssid = "17">to work well for he.</S>
			<S sid ="263" ssid = "18">In contrast, the local, shallow approach we currently employ is not able to resolve highly ambiguous pronouns such as they, you or it in many cases.</S>
			<S sid ="264" ssid = "19">The reduction in error rate when only considering anaphoric pronouns shows that our system could benefit from an improved detection of expletive it and you.</S>
			<S sid ="265" ssid = "20">6.2 Recall Errors.</S>
			<S sid ="266" ssid = "21">Estimating recall errors by counting all missing pairwise links would consider each entity many times.</S>
			<S sid ="267" ssid = "22">Therefore, we instead count one recall error for a pair (m, n) of anaphor m and antecedent n if (i) m and n are coreferent, (ii) m and n are not assigned to the same cluster, (iii) m is the first mention in its cluster that is coreferent with n, and (iv) n is the closest mention coreferent with m that is not in m’s cluster.</S>
			<S sid ="268" ssid = "23">This can be illustrated by an example.</S>
			<S sid ="269" ssid = "24">Considering mentions m1, . . .</S>
			<S sid ="270" ssid = "25">, m5, assume that m1, m3, m4 and m5 are coreferent but the system clusters are {m2, m3} and {m4, m5}.</S>
			<S sid ="271" ssid = "26">We then count two recall errors: one for the missing link from m3 to m1 and one for the missing link from m4 to m3.</S>
			<S sid ="272" ssid = "27">According to this definition we count 3528 recall errors on the development set.</S>
			<S sid ="273" ssid = "28">The distribution of errors is displayed in Table 4.</S>
			<S sid ="274" ssid = "29">We see that NA M N O M PR O NA M 32 1 22 0 24 7 N O M 30 6 79 7 33 0 PR O 30 6 47 6 52 5 Table 4: Number of recall errors according to mention type (rows anaphor, columns antecedent).</S>
			<S sid ="275" ssid = "30">the main source of recall errors are missing links of nominal-nominal pairs.</S>
			<S sid ="276" ssid = "31">We randomly extracted 50 of these errors and manually assigned them to different categories.</S>
			<S sid ="277" ssid = "32">29 errors: missing semantic knowledge.</S>
			<S sid ="278" ssid = "33">In these cases lexical or world knowledge is needed to build coreference links between mentions with different heads.</S>
			<S sid ="279" ssid = "34">For example our system misses the link between the sauna and the hotbox sweatbox.</S>
			<S sid ="280" ssid = "35">14 errors: too restrictive N Mod.</S>
			<S sid ="281" ssid = "36">In these cases the heads of the mentions matched but no link was built due to N Mod.</S>
			<S sid ="282" ssid = "37">An example is the missing link between our island’s last remaining forest of these giant trees and the forest of Chilan.</S>
			<S sid ="283" ssid = "38">4 errors: too cautious string match.</S>
			<S sid ="284" ssid = "39">We only apply string matching for common nouns when the noun is definite.</S>
			<S sid ="285" ssid = "40">Three errors could not be attributed to any of the above categories.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions and Future  Work. " number = "7">
			<S sid ="286" ssid = "1">We presented an unsupervised graph-based model for coreference resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="287" ssid = "2">Experiments show that our model exhibits competitive performance on the English CoNLL’12 shared task data sets.</S>
			<S sid ="288" ssid = "3">An error analysis revealed that two main sources of errors of our model are the inaccurate resolution of highly ambiguous pronouns such as it and missing links between nominals with different heads.</S>
			<S sid ="289" ssid = "4">Future work should investigate how semantic knowledge and more complex relations capturing deeper discourse properties such as coherence or information status can be added to the model.</S>
			<S sid ="290" ssid = "5">Processing these features efficently may require a more sophisticated clustering algorithm.</S>
			<S sid ="291" ssid = "6">We are surprised by the good performance of this unsupervised model in comparison to the state-of-the-art which uses sophisticated machine learning techniques (Fernandes et al., 2012) or well-engineered rules (Lee et al., 2011).</S>
			<S sid ="292" ssid = "7">We are not sure how to interpret these results and want to leave different interpretations for discussion: • our unsupervised model is really that good (hopefully), • the evaluation metrics employed are to be questioned (certainly), • efficiently making use of annotated trainingdata still remains a challenge for the state-of the-art (likely).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acknowledgments">
			<S sid ="293" ssid = "8">This work has been funded by the Klaus Tschira Foundation, Germany.</S>
			<S sid ="294" ssid = "9">The author has been supported by a HITS PhD scholarship.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
