<COMMUNITY>
<S sid="0">THE CORRECT AND EFFICIENT IMPLEMENTATION OF APPROPRIATENESS SPECIFICATIONS FOR TYPED FEATURE STRUCTURES</S><S sid ="7" ssid = "7">The practical effect of this is that Troll implements an exhaustive typing strategy which provides the stronger kind of inferencing over descriptions (Gerdemann and King, 1993, 1994) required by standard HPSG theories.</S><S sid ="67" ssid = "51">By contrast, the Troll system described in this paper has an etfeetive algorithm f&lt;&gt;r deciding well-formedness, which is based on the idea of efficiently representing disjunctive possibilities within the feature structure, Call a well-typed feature structure in which all nodes are labelled with species a resolved feature structure and call a set of resolved feature structures that have the same underlying graph (that is, they differ only in their node labellings) a disjunctive resolved feature structure.</S><S sid ="68" ssid = "52">We write fS, ~vf8 and &apos;D~.)c$ for the collections of feature structures, resolved feature structures and disjunctive resolved feature structures respectively.</S><S sid ="69" ssid = "53">Say that F&apos;E RFS is a resolvant of F E FS iff F and F&apos; have the same underlying graph and F subsumes F&apos;.</S><S sid ="70" ssid = "54">Let type resolution be the total function R:-&gt;DRFS such that R(F) is the set of all resolvants of F. Guided by the partition and all-or-nothing conditions, King [13] has formulated a semantics of feature structures and developed a notion of a satisfiable feature structure such that F E FS is satisfiable iff R(F) 0.</S><S sid ="72" ssid = "56">C, erdemann ,% King [8] have also shown that a feature strtlcture l]leets all encoded FCRs ifl&quot; the feature structure is satisfiable.</S><S sid ="73" ssid = "57">The Troll system, which is based on this idea, effectively inqflements type resolution.</S><S sid ="83" ssid = "1">APPROPRIATENES S CONDITIONS A very important property of the class of DRFS is that they are closed under unification, i.e., if F and F&apos;E DRFS then F U F&apos; E DRFS.4 Given this property, it would in principle he possible to use the disjunctive resolved feature structures in an implementation without any additional type inferencing procedure to maintain satisfiability.</S><S sid ="84" ssid = "2">It would, of course, not be very efficient to work with such large disjunctions of feature structures.</S>
</COMMUNITY>