<PAPER>
  <S sid="0" ssid="0">Toward Memory--based Translation Satoshi SATO and Ma.koto NAGAO Dept.</S>
  <S sid="1" ssid="1">of Electrical Engineering, Kyoto  University Yoshida-honmachi,  Sa.kyo, K.yoto, 606, Ja.pan sa.to@kuee.kyoto-u.ac.jp Abst ract An essential problem of example-based transla- tion is how to utilize more than one translation example for translating one source sentence.</S>
  <S sid="2" ssid="2">This 1)aper proposes a method to solve this problem.</S>
  <S sid="3" ssid="3">We introduce tile representation, called .matching e,,z:pressio~z, which tel)resents the combination of fragments of translation ex- amples.</S>
  <S sid="4" ssid="4">The translation process consists of three steps: (.1) Make the source matching ex- pression from lhe source sentence.</S>
  <S sid="5" ssid="5">(2) TransDr the source matching expression into the target matching expression.</S>
  <S sid="6" ssid="6">(3) Construct the target sentence from the target matching expression.</S>
  <S sid="7" ssid="7">This mechanism generates some candidates of translation.</S>
  <S sid="8" ssid="8">To select, the best translation out of them, we define the score of a translation.</S>
  <S sid="9" ssid="9">1 In t roduct ion Use of extracted information fiom examples or example-based translation is becoming the new wave of machine translation.</S>
  <S sid="10" ssid="10">The ba.- sic idea.</S>
  <S sid="11" ssid="11">of example~based translation is very simple: translate a source sentence by imitat- ing the translation example of a similar sen- tence in the database.</S>
  <S sid="12" ssid="12">The idea first appeared in [Nagao 84], and some research has followed it [Sumita 88][Sato 89][Sadler 89a.</S>
  <S sid="13" ssid="13">But a great deal of effort is still needed to im- plemenl the idea.</S>
  <S sid="14" ssid="14">In our previous work, we show how to select.</S>
  <S sid="15" ssid="15">the best target word in case-frame translation based on examples[Sato 89].</S>
  <S sid="16" ssid="16">In this paper, we concentrate on two problems: 1. ltow to combine some fragments of trans- lation examph~s in order to translate one sentence?</S>
  <S sid="17" ssid="17">2. tlow to select tile best tra.nslation out of inany candidates?</S>
  <S sid="18" ssid="18">We show partial solutions for them in MBT2.</S>
  <S sid="19" ssid="19">MBT2 is the second prototype system in our Memory-based Translation Project.. MBT2 ca.n do bi-directional m~nslation between an English word-dependency tree and a Japanese word- dependency tree.</S>
  <S sid="20" ssid="20">It is implemented in Sicstus Prolog.</S>
  <S sid="21" ssid="21">2 Need to Combine  Frag- me nt s The basic idea of example-based translation is very simple: translate a source sentence by im- itating the translation example of similar sen- tencein the database.</S>
  <S sid="22" ssid="22">But in many cases, it is necessary to imitate more than one translation example and combine some fragments of them.</S>
  <S sid="23" ssid="23">Lets consider the translation of the following sentence.</S>
  <S sid="24" ssid="24">(1) He buys a book on international politics.</S>
  <S sid="25" ssid="25">If we know the following translation examt)le (2) and (3), we can translate sentence (1) into sentence (4) by imitating examples and colnbin- ing fragments of them.</S>
  <S sid="26" ssid="26">(2) He buys a notebook.</S>
  <S sid="27" ssid="27">Kate ha nouto wo ka~.</S>
  <S sid="28" ssid="28">(3) I read a boo]~ on international polilics.</S>
  <S sid="29" ssid="29">Watt, hi ha kokusaiseiji nit,suite l:akareta hon wo yomu.</S>
  <S sid="30" ssid="30">(4) Kate ha kokusMseiji nitsuite kM~reta hon WO ka~ll.</S>
  <S sid="31" ssid="31">It is easy for a human to do this, but not so for a machine.</S>
  <S sid="32" ssid="32">The ability to combine some fragments of translation examples is essential to example-based translation.</S>
  <S sid="33" ssid="33">A lack of this abil- ity restricts the power of example-based trans- lation.</S>
  <S sid="34" ssid="34">In this paper, we concentrate on the implementation of this ability on machine.</S>
  <S sid="35" ssid="35">i 24 7 3 Matching Expression To implenrent the ability to combine some frag- ments of t.ra.nslation example in order to trans- late one sentence, we must determine the fol- lowing: ?</S>
  <S sid="36" ssid="36">how to represent translation examples ?</S>
  <S sid="37" ssid="37">what is a fragment ?</S>
  <S sid="38" ssid="38">how to represe.t he combination of flag- lnent.s 3.1 Trans la t ion  Database The translation database is the collection of translation examples.</S>
  <S sid="39" ssid="39">A t~anslation example consists of three parts: ?</S>
  <S sid="40" ssid="40">an English word-dependency tree (EWD) ?</S>
  <S sid="41" ssid="41">a Japanese word-dependency tree (JWD) ?</S>
  <S sid="42" ssid="42">correspondence links For example, in Prolog, ewd e(  [e l ,  [buy ,v  ] , [e2,[he,pron]], [e3, [notebook,n], [e4,   [a ,det  ]  ]  ]  ] )  .</S>
  <S sid="43" ssid="43">%% He buys a notebook.</S>
  <S sid="44" ssid="44">jwd_e(   [ j I ,  [kau,v] , [ j2 ,   [ha ,p  ]  , [ j3,[kare,pron]]], [ j4 ,  [wo,p] , [ j5 ,  [nouto,n]]]]).</S>
  <S sid="45" ssid="45">%% Kare ha nouto wo kau.</S>
  <S sid="46" ssid="46">c l inks([  [el , j l  ] ,  [e2, j3] ,  [e3, j5] ]) .</S>
  <S sid="47" ssid="47">%% el &lt;-&gt; jl, e2 &lt;-&gt; j3, e3 &lt;-&gt; j5 Each number with prefix e or j in word- dependency trees represents the ID of the sub- tree.</S>
  <S sid="48" ssid="48">Each node in a tree contains a word (in root form) and its syntactic ategory.</S>
  <S sid="49" ssid="49">A corre- spondence link is represented as a pair of iDs.</S>
  <S sid="50" ssid="50">3.2 T rans la t ion  Un i t A word-dependency (sub)tree which has a cor- respondence link is transhttable; .g.</S>
  <S sid="51" ssid="51">el,  e2, e3, j l ,  j3, j5.</S>
  <S sid="52" ssid="52">A translatable tree in which some translatable subtrees are removed is also trans- lata.ble; e.g.</S>
  <S sid="53" ssid="53">e l -e2,  e l -e3,  e l -e2-e3,  j l - j3 , j l - j5 ,  j l - j a - jS .</S>
  <S sid="54" ssid="54">Both of them are tra.nslat- M)le fragments.</S>
  <S sid="55" ssid="55">Sadler calls them translation w,,its[Sadler 89a,].</S>
  <S sid="56" ssid="56">3.3 Match ing  Express ion Next we will introduce the concept matching expression.</S>
  <S sid="57" ssid="57">Matching expression(ME) is de- fined as the following: &lt;HE&gt; : :=  [&lt;ID&gt;I&lt;ME-Commands&gt;] &lt;ME-Commands&gt; : : = [] or [&lt;ME-Command&gt; I &lt;ME-Commands&gt;] &lt;ME-Command&gt; : := [d, &lt; ID&gt;] or [r,&lt;ID&gt;, &lt;ME&gt;] or [a,&lt;ID&gt;,&lt;ME&gt;] %% delete &lt;ID&gt; %% rep lace  &lt;ID&gt; %% with &lt;ME&gt; %% add &lt;ME&gt; as a %% ch i ld  of  root %% node o f  &lt;ID&gt; Every ID in an ME should be translatable.</S>
  <S sid="58" ssid="58">We assume the example in Section 3.1 and the following example.</S>
  <S sid="59" ssid="59">ewd_e( fell, freud,v] , [el2, [I ),prOn]] , [el3, [book,n] , [el4, [a,det] ] , [elb, Ion,p] , [el6, [politics,n] , felT, [international, adj] ]  ]  ]  ]1 ) .</S>
  <S sid="60" ssid="60">Y,Y, I read a book on international %% politics.</S>
  <S sid="61" ssid="61">jwd_e([j l l ,  [yomu,v] , [j12, [ha,p] , [j13, [watashi,pron] ]] , [ j14 ,  [wo,p] , [j15, [hon,n] , [ j16 ,   [ ta ,  aux] , [j17, [reru,aux] , [j18, [kaku,v] , [j19, [nitsuite,p] , [j20, [kokusaiseij i,n] 1]  ]11]  ]  ] ) .</S>
  <S sid="62" ssid="62">%% Watash i  ha kokusa ise i j i  n i t su i .</S>
  <S sid="63" ssid="63">te %% kakareta  hon wo yomu.</S>
  <S sid="64" ssid="64">cl inks([el l ,  ] l l  ] ,  [e12, j13] ,  [e13, j15] , [e16 , j20  ]  ] ) .</S>
  <S sid="65" ssid="65">Under this assumption, the word-dependency tree (a) can be represented by the matching ex- pression (b).</S>
  <S sid="66" ssid="66">(a)  [ [buy,v1 , [  [he ,pron  ]  ]  , [[book,hi , [  [a ,det  ]  ]  , [ Ion,p], [[politics,n] , [ [ international,adj]]] ] ] ] %% He buys a book on international Y,Y, polit ics.</S>
  <S sid="67" ssid="67">(b)  [e l ,  [ r ,e3 ,  [e l3  ]  ]  ] 248 2 Source WD (SWD) # Source ME (SME) Target ME (TME) g ~.,ompo~itiol~ ] Target WD (TWD) Figure 1: Flow of Translaton The matching expression (b) consists of two transla,tion units: el-e3, e13.</S>
  <S sid="68" ssid="68">And it has the information to combine them.</S>
  <S sid="69" ssid="69">4 Tlanslation via Matching Expression Figure 1 shows the flow of the translation pro- .</S>
  <S sid="70" ssid="70">The translation process consists of three steps: decomposition, transfer, and composi- tion.</S>
  <S sid="71" ssid="71">This process generates all candidates of translation using Prologs backtrack mecha- nism.</S>
  <S sid="72" ssid="72">4.1 Decompos i t ion In decomposition, the system decomposes a source word-dependency tree(SWD) into trans- lation units, and makes a source matching ex- pression(SME).</S>
  <S sid="73" ssid="73">For example, SWD = [[buy,v], [ [he,pron] ] , [ [book,n] , [  [a,det]  ]  , [[on,p], [ [politics ,n], [ [international, adj] ] ] ] ] ] SME =  [e l ,  [ r ,ea ,  [e l3  ]  ]  ] The main tasks in this step are to retrieve translation units and compare the source WD with retrieved translation units.</S>
  <S sid="74" ssid="74">To retrieve translation units quickly, we use some hashing techniques.</S>
  <S sid="75" ssid="75">There are two program to do the comparison task; one for English WDs and one for Japanese WDs.</S>
  <S sid="76" ssid="76">In comparison of Japanese WDs, the order of subtrees is not inlportant.</S>
  <S sid="77" ssid="77">To reduce the search space and the num- ber of candidates, we define replaceablity be- tween syntactic categories.</S>
  <S sid="78" ssid="78">If two nodes are replaceable, system makes only ~ replace- command.</S>
  <S sid="79" ssid="79">As a result, the the system does not make some matching expressions; e.g.</S>
  <S sid="80" ssid="80">[el, [d,e3] ,  [a,el ,   [e13]]  ] 4.2 Transfer in the transfer step, the system replaces every ID in the source matching expression with its corresponding ID.</S>
  <S sid="81" ssid="81">For example, SME = [el,[r,eS,[el3]]] TME = [j1,[r,jS,[j15]]] 4.3 Compos i t ion in the composition step, the system composes the target word-dependency tree according to the target matching expression.</S>
  <S sid="82" ssid="82">TME =  [ j l ,  [ r , j5 ,   [ j lS  ]  ]  ] TWD = [[kau,v], [ [ha,p] , [ [kare,pron] ] ] , [[wo,p], [ [hon ,n] , [[ta, aux], [ [tern, aux], [ [kaku, v] , [ [nitsuite,p] , [ [kokusaiseiji,n] ] ] ] ] ] ] ] ] ~,~.</S>
  <S sid="83" ssid="83">Kate ha kokusaisei j i  nitsuite ~,~, kakareta hon wo kau.</S>
  <S sid="84" ssid="84">This step divides into two sub-steps; the main composing step and validity checking.</S>
  <S sid="85" ssid="85">In the main composing step, there is no ambi- guity with one exception.</S>
  <S sid="86" ssid="86">Because an add- command [a,&lt;ID&gt;,&lt;ME&gt;] specifies only the parent node(&lt;ID&gt;) to add the tree(&lt;ME&gt;), there are some choices in composing English word- dependency trees.</S>
  <S sid="87" ssid="87">In this step, all possibilities are generated.</S>
  <S sid="88" ssid="88">Validity of the composed word-dependency trees are checked using syntactic categories.</S>
  <S sid="89" ssid="89">Validity is checked in every parent-children unit.</S>
  <S sid="90" ssid="90">For example, in the above target word- dependency tree, [v, [p,p] ] , [p,  [prom ], [p, [n] ], In, [aux] ] .</S>
  <S sid="91" ssid="91">A unit is valid if there is a unit which has the same category pattern in the database.</S>
  <S sid="92" ssid="92">A word-dependency tree is valid if all parent-children units are valid.</S>
  <S sid="93" ssid="93">3 249 z" / 7t2 L 1 " / ~ l I I , 7/5 71,7 .2 .</S>
  <S sid="94" ssid="94">~ ._.___-- res t r i c ted  env iornment  ~ / "  ~" nll  / m2 (= n2) ", mlo / m,8 2 / ,- d Translation Gx~mple Source (or Target) WD Figure 2: Restricted Environments of TU 5 Score o f  T rans la t ion To select the best translation out of all can- didates generated by system, we introduce the score of a tra.nslM.ion.</S>
  <S sid="95" ssid="95">We define it based on the score of the matching expression, because the matching expression determines the translation outi)ut.</S>
  <S sid="96" ssid="96">The scores of.the source matching ex- pression and the target matching expression are calculated separately.</S>
  <S sid="97" ssid="97">5.1 Score  o f  T rans la t ion  Un i t First, we will define the score of a translation unit.</S>
  <S sid="98" ssid="98">The score of a translation unit should reflect the correctness of the translation unit.</S>
  <S sid="99" ssid="99">Which translation unit is better?</S>
  <S sid="100" ssid="100">Two main fac- t.ors are: 1.</S>
  <S sid="101" ssid="101">A larger translation unit is better.</S>
  <S sid="102" ssid="102">A translation unit in a matching expression is a fragment of a source (or target) word- dependency tree, and also a fragment of a translation example.</S>
  <S sid="103" ssid="103">There are two envi- ronments of a translation unit; in a source (or target) tree and in a translation exam- ple.</S>
  <S sid="104" ssid="104">The more similar these two environ- meuts are, the better.</S>
  <S sid="105" ssid="105">To calculate 1, we define the size of a trans- lation unit(TU ).</S>
  <S sid="106" ssid="106">size(TU) = the number of nodes in TU To calculate 2, we need a measure of simi- larity between two environments, i.e.</S>
  <S sid="107" ssid="107">external similarity.</S>
  <S sid="108" ssid="108">To estimate xternal similarity, we introduce a unit called restricted environment.</S>
  <S sid="109" ssid="109">A restricted environment consists of the nodes one link outside of a TU normally.</S>
  <S sid="110" ssid="110">If corre- sponding nodes are same in two environments, those environments are extended one more link outside.</S>
  <S sid="111" ssid="111">Figure 2 illustrates restricted environ- ments of a TU.</S>
  <S sid="112" ssid="112">We estimate xternal similarity as the best matching of two restricted environ- ments.</S>
  <S sid="113" ssid="113">To find the best matching, we first deter- mine the correspondences between odes in two restricted environments.</S>
  <S sid="114" ssid="114">Some nodes have sev- eral candidates of correspondence.</S>
  <S sid="115" ssid="115">For example, n7 corresponds with rn6 or m7.</S>
  <S sid="116" ssid="116">In this case, we select the most similar node.</S>
  <S sid="117" ssid="117">To do this, we assume that similarity values between odes (words) are defined as numeric values between 0 and 1 in a thesaurus.</S>
  <S sid="118" ssid="118">When the best matching is found, we can calculate the matching point between two environments, mpoint(TU, WD).</S>
  <S sid="119" ssid="119">mpoint (TU,  WD)  = summation of similarity values between corre- sponding nodes in two restricted environments ~t the best matching We use this value as a measure of similarity between two environments.</S>
  <S sid="120" ssid="120">Finally, we define the score of a translation unit, seore(TU, WD).</S>
  <S sid="121" ssid="121">score(TU, WD) = size(TU) x (size(Tg) + mpoiut(TU, WD)) For example, we assume that the following similarity vMues are defined in a thesaurus.</S>
  <S sid="122" ssid="122">250 4 s im([book,n] ,   [notebook,n] ,O.8).</S>
  <S sid="123" ssid="123">sire( [buy,v] , [read,v] ,0.5) .</S>
  <S sid="124" ssid="124">sire( [hon,n] , [nouto,n] ,0.8).</S>
  <S sid="125" ssid="125">s im(  [kau,v  ] ,  [yomu,v  ] ,O .5) .</S>
  <S sid="126" ssid="126">Then i.he scores of translation units in the previous section are the followings.</S>
  <S sid="127" ssid="127">[ 0.S I J s___2_JLL 5.2 Score  o f  Match ing  Express ion ]?he score of a nlatching expression is defined as the following.</S>
  <S sid="128" ssid="128">ItD) F~YUCME score(TU, WD) s izc(WD) 2 FOl; exaul ple, [ j l ,   [ r , jS ,  [j15] 5.3 Score  o f  T rans la t ion Finally, we define the score of a translation as the following.</S>
  <S sid="129" ssid="129">SME,  TME,  TWD)  = ~,n i~( seo,~( S ME.</S>
  <S sid="130" ssid="130">S WD), score( T~I E, TW D ) ) For example, the score of the translation in ?</S>
  <S sid="131" ssid="131">the previous section is 0.6.I2.</S>
  <S sid="132" ssid="132">6 Examples The English verb eat corresponds to two Japanese verbs, tabcrv and okasu.</S>
  <S sid="133" ssid="133">(4) The mall eats w.:getabtes.</S>
  <S sid="134" ssid="134">Hito ha yasal wo taberu.</S>
  <S sid="135" ssid="135">(5) Acid eats metal.</S>
  <S sid="136" ssid="136">San ha kinzoku wo oka.qu.</S>
  <S sid="137" ssid="137">Figure 3 shows translation outl)uts based on example (,t) and (5) by MBT2.</S>
  <S sid="138" ssid="138">MBT2 chooses htberu for he cat.s t~ota, toes and okasu for sulfuric acid cals i ron.</S>
  <S sid="139" ssid="139">***  T r&amp;ns la t ion  Source  *** [  [eat ,  v]  , [ the,pron] ] , [ [potato,n] ] ] Y,Y, He eats potatoes.</S>
  <S sid="140" ssid="140">*** Trans lat ion Results  *** No.</S>
  <S sid="141" ssid="141">I (Score = 0.5889) [ [taberu, v] , [ [ha,p], [ [kare,pron] ] ] , [[wo,p], [ [ jagaimo,n] ] ] ] No.</S>
  <S sid="142" ssid="142">2 (Score = 0.4S56) [ [okasu, v], [ [ha, p], [ [kare,pron] ] ] , [ [~o,p], [ [ jagaimo,n]] ]] *** Trans lat ion  Source *** [[eat,v] , [[acid,n] , [  [sulfur ic,adj] ]  ] , [[ iron,n]]] %% Sulfur ic  acid eats iron.</S>
  <S sid="143" ssid="143">*** Trans lat ion Results  *** No.</S>
  <S sid="144" ssid="144">I (Score = 0.5500) [ [okasu, v], [ [ha, p] , [ [ryuusan,n] ] ] , [ [wo,p], [  [ te tsu ,n  ]  ] ]] No.</S>
  <S sid="145" ssid="145">2 (Score = 0.4688) [[taberu, v] , [ [ha, p], [ [ryuusan,n]] ], [[wo,p], [[tetsu,n]] Figure 3: Translation Outputs by MBT2 5 251 7 Discuss ion Although MBT2 is not a full realization of Na- gaos idea., it contains ome merits from the orig- inal idea.</S>
  <S sid="146" ssid="146">It is easy to modify the system.</S>
  <S sid="147" ssid="147">The knowledge of the system is in the form of translation examl)les and thesauri.</S>
  <S sid="148" ssid="148">We can modify the system with addition of translation examples.</S>
  <S sid="149" ssid="149">It can do high quality translation.</S>
  <S sid="150" ssid="150">The system sees as wide a scope as possible in a sentence and uses the largest transla- tion units.</S>
  <S sid="151" ssid="151">It produces high quality trans- lations.</S>
  <S sid="152" ssid="152">It can translate some metaphorical sen- tences.</S>
  <S sid="153" ssid="153">In the system, semantic information is not used as constraints.</S>
  <S sid="154" ssid="154">As a result, the system can translate some metaphorical sentences.</S>
  <S sid="155" ssid="155">Demerits or problems of the system are: 1.</S>
  <S sid="156" ssid="156">A great deal of computation is needed.</S>
  <S sid="157" ssid="157">Can we make good thesauri?</S>
  <S sid="158" ssid="158">The first l)roblem is not serious.</S>
  <S sid="159" ssid="159">Parallel compu- tation or some heuristics will overcome it.</S>
  <S sid="160" ssid="160">But the second problem is serious.</S>
  <S sid="161" ssid="161">We have to study how to construct large thesauri.</S>
  <S sid="162" ssid="162">acknowlegments The authors would like to thank Mort Webster for his proof reading.</S>
  <S sid="163" ssid="163">References [Nagao 84] Makoto Nagao, A Framework of a Mechanical Translation between Japanese and English by Analogy Principle, in ARTI- FICIAL AND tIUMAN INTELMGENCE (A. Elithorn and R. Banerji, editors), El- sevier Science Publishers, B.V, 198.t.</S>
  <S sid="164" ssid="164">[Sadler 89a] Victor Sadler, The Bilingual Knowledge Bank(BKB), BSO/Research, 1989.</S>
  <S sid="165" ssid="165">[Sadler 89b] Victor Sadler, Translating with a simulated Bilingual Knowledge Bank{ BKB), BSO/Research, 1989.</S>
  <S sid="166" ssid="166">[Sato 89] Satoshi Sa.to and Makoto Nagao, Memory-based Translation, IPSJ-WG, NL- 70-9, 1989.</S>
  <S sid="167" ssid="167">(in Japanese) [Sumita 88] E. Sumita and Y. Tsutsumi, A Translation Aid System Using Flexible Text Retrieval Based on Syntax-Matching, TRL Research Report, TR-87-1019, Tokyo Re- search Laboratory, IBM, 1988.</S>
  <S sid="168" ssid="168">8 Conclus ion This paper describes how to combine some translation units in order to translate one sen- tence and how to select tile best translation out of some candidates generated by system.</S>
  <S sid="169" ssid="169">To represent he combination of fragments, we in- troduce the representation called matching ex- pression.</S>
  <S sid="170" ssid="170">To select the best translation, we de- fine the score of translation based on the score of the matching expression.</S>
  <S sid="171" ssid="171">This framework can be applied to not only the translation between word-dependency trees but also the translation between other data struc- tures.</S>
  <S sid="172" ssid="172">We hope that generation can be imple- mented in same framework as the translation from a word-dependency tree to a list or string.</S>
</PAPER>
