<PAPER>
  <S sid="0" ssid="0">Machine Translation Divergences: A Formal Description and Proposed Solution Bonnie J. Dorr* University of Maryland There are many cases in which the natural translation of one language into another esults in a very different form than that of the original.</S>
  <S sid="1" ssid="1">The existence of translation divergences (i.e., cross- linguistic distinctions) makes the straightforward transfer from source structures into target structures impractical.</S>
  <S sid="2" ssid="2">Many existing translation systems have mechanisms for handling diver- gent structures but do not provide a general procedure that takes advantage of the systematic relation between lexical-semantic structure and syntactic structure.</S>
  <S sid="3" ssid="3">This paper demonstrates that a systematic solution to the divergence problem can be derived from the formalization of two types of information: (1) the linguistically grounded classes upon which lexical-semantic divergences are based; and (2) the techniques by which lexical-semantic divergences are resolved.</S>
  <S sid="4" ssid="4">This formalization is advantageous in that it facilitates the design and implementation f the system, allows one to make an evaluation of the status of the system, and provides a basis for proving certain important properties about he system.</S>
  <S sid="5" ssid="5">Introduction There are many cases in which the natural translation of one language into another results in a very different form than that of the original.</S>
  <S sid="6" ssid="6">The existence of translation divergences (i.e., cross-linguistic distinctions) makes the straightforward transfer from source structures into target structures impractical.</S>
  <S sid="7" ssid="7">This paper demonstrates that a sys- tematic solution to the divergence problem can be derived from the formalization of two types of information: (1) the linguistically grounded classes upon which lexical- semantic divergences are based; and (2) the techniques by which lexical-semantic divergences are resolved.</S>
  <S sid="8" ssid="8">An important result of this formalization is the provision of a framework for proving that the lexical-semantic divergence classification proposed in the current approach covers all source-language/target-language distinctions based on lexical-semantic properties.</S>
  <S sid="9" ssid="9">Other types of divergences and mismatches are outside of the scope of this paper; these include distinctions based on purely syntactic informa- tion, idiomatic usage, aspectual knowledge, discourse knowledge, domain knowledge, or world knowledge/ Although other translation approaches have attempted to account for divergences, the main innovation of the current approach is that it provides a formalization of these divergences and the techniques by which they are resolved.</S>
  <S sid="10" ssid="10">This is advantageous from a computational point of view in that it facilitates the design and implementation of ?</S>
  <S sid="11" ssid="11">Department ofComputer Science, University of Maryland, A. V. Williams Building, College Park, MD 20742, USA.</S>
  <S sid="12" ssid="12">1 The reader is referred to Dorr (1993a) for a discussion of how syntactic divergences are handled.</S>
  <S sid="13" ssid="13">Aspectual divergences are treated by Dorr (1992a).</S>
  <S sid="14" ssid="14">The relatio.n of the current framework to other types of knowledge outside of lexical semantics i  discussed by Dorr and Voss (1993b).</S>
  <S sid="15" ssid="15">1994 Association for Computational Linguistics Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 (1) Thematic divergence: E: I like Mary ~ S: Maria me gusta a mi Mary pleases me (2) Promotional divergence: E: John usually goes home 4=~ S: Juan suele i ra casa John tends to go home (3) Demotional divergence: E: I like eating ~ G: Ich esse gem I eat likingly (4) Structural divergence: E: John entered the house 4=~ S: Juan entr6 en la casa John entered in the house (5) Conflational divergence: E: I stabbed John ~ S: Yo le di pu~aladas a Juan I gave knife-wounds to John (6) Categorial divergence: E: I am hungry ~ G: Ich habe Hunger I have hunger (7) Lexical divergence: E: John broke into the room ~ S: Juan forz6 la entrada l cuarto Figure 1 John forced (the) entry to the room Examples of translation divergences with respect o English, Spanish, and German.</S>
  <S sid="16" ssid="16">the system: the problem is clearly defined in terms of a small number  of divergence categories, and the solution is systematically stated in terms of a uniform translation mapping  and a handful of simple lexical-semantic parameters.</S>
  <S sid="17" ssid="17">In addition, the for- malization allows one to make an evaluation of the status of the system.</S>
  <S sid="18" ssid="18">For example, given the formal description of the interlingua nd target-language root words, one is able to judge whether a particular target-language s ntence fully covers the concept that underlies the corresponding source-language s ntence.</S>
  <S sid="19" ssid="19">Finally, the formalization of the divergence types and the associated solution allows one to prove certain proper- ties about the system.</S>
  <S sid="20" ssid="20">For example, one might want to determine whether the system is able to handle two or more simultaneous divergences that interact in some way.</S>
  <S sid="21" ssid="21">With the mechanism of the current approach, one is able to prove formally that such cases are handled in a uniform fashion.</S>
  <S sid="22" ssid="22">This paper will focus on the problem of lexical-semantic divergences and will provide support for the view that it is possible to construct a finite cross-linguistic classification of divergences and to implement a systematic mapping between the interlingual representation and the surface syntactic structure that accommodates all of the divergences in this classification.</S>
  <S sid="23" ssid="23">The types of divergences under consideration are those shown in Figure 1.</S>
  <S sid="24" ssid="24">The first divergence type is thematic: in (1), the theme is realized as the verbal object (Mary) in English but as the subject (Maria) of the main verb in Spanish.</S>
  <S sid="25" ssid="25">The second divergence type, promotional, is one of two head switching divergence types: in (2), the modifier (usually) is realized as an adverbial phrase in English but as the main verb soler in Spanish.</S>
  <S sid="26" ssid="26">The third divergence type, demotional, is another type of head switching divergence: in (3), the word like is realized as a main verb in English but as an adverbial modifier (gern) in German.</S>
  <S sid="27" ssid="27">2The fourth 2 The distinction between promotional nd demotional divergences is not intuitively obvious at first glance.</S>
  <S sid="28" ssid="28">In both (2) and (3), the translation mapping associates a main verb with an adverbial satellite, or vice versa (i.e., in (2), the main verb soler is associated with the adverbial satellite usually, and in (3) the main verb like is associated with the adverbial satellite gern).</S>
  <S sid="29" ssid="29">The distinction between these two 598 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences divergence type is structural: in (4), the verbal object is realized as a noun phrase (the house) in English and as a prepositional phrase (en la casa) in Spanish.</S>
  <S sid="30" ssid="30">The fifth divergence type is conflational.</S>
  <S sid="31" ssid="31">Conflation is the incorporation ofnecessary participants (or arguments) of a given action.</S>
  <S sid="32" ssid="32">In (5), English uses the single word stab for the two Spanish words dar (give) and pu~aladas (knife-wounds); this is because the effect of the action (i.e., the knife-wounds portion of the lexical token) is conflated into the main verb in English.</S>
  <S sid="33" ssid="33">The sixth divergence type is categoriah in (6), the predicate is adjectival (hungry) in English but nominal (Hunger) in German.</S>
  <S sid="34" ssid="34">Finally, the seventh divergence type is a lexical divergence: in (7), the event is lexically realized as the main verb break in English but as a different verb forzar (literally force) in Spanish.</S>
  <S sid="35" ssid="35">The next section discusses the divergence classification given above, comparing the current divergence categories with those of other researchers.</S>
  <S sid="36" ssid="36">Section 3 formally defines the terms used to classify divergences.</S>
  <S sid="37" ssid="37">Section 4 uses this terminology to formalize the divergence classification and to define the solution to the divergence problem in the context of detailed examples.</S>
  <S sid="38" ssid="38">Finally, Section 5 discusses certain issues of relevance to the divergence problem including the resolution of several (recursively) interacting divergence types.</S>
  <S sid="39" ssid="39">Classification of Machine Translation Divergences The divergence problem in machine translation has received increasingly greater at- tention in recent literature (see, for example, Barnett et al.</S>
  <S sid="40" ssid="40">1991a, 1991b; Beaven 1992a, 1992b; Dorr 1990a, 1990b; Kameyama et al.</S>
  <S sid="41" ssid="41">1991; Kinoshita, Phillips, and Tsujii 1992; Lindop and Tsujii 1991; Tsujii and Fujita 1991; Whitelock 1992; related discussion can also be found in work by Melby [1986] and Nirenburg and Nirenburg [1988]).</S>
  <S sid="42" ssid="42">In par- ticular, Barnett et al.</S>
  <S sid="43" ssid="43">(1991a) divide distinctions between the source language and the target language into two categories: translation divergences, in which the same infor- mation is conveyed in the source and target exts, but the structures of the sentences are different (as in previous work by Dorr [1990a, 1990b]); and translation mismatches, in which the information that is conveyed is different in the source and target lan- guages (as described by Kameyama et al.</S>
  <S sid="44" ssid="44">3 Although translation mismatches are a major problem for translation systems that must be addressed, they are outside the scope of the model presented here.</S>
  <S sid="45" ssid="45">(See Barnett et al.</S>
  <S sid="46" ssid="46">1991a, 1991b; Carbonell and Tomita 1987; Meyer, Onyshkevych, and Carlson 1990; Nirenburg, Raskin, and Tucker 1987; Nirenburg and Goodman 1990; Nirenburg and Levin 1989; Wilks 1973; among others, for descriptions of interlingual machine translation approaches that take into account knowledge outside of the domain of lexical semantics.)</S>
  <S sid="47" ssid="47">Although researchers have only recently begun to classify divergence types sys- tematically, the notion of translation divergences i not a new one in the machine translation community.</S>
  <S sid="48" ssid="48">For example, a number of researchers working on the Euro- tra project have sought o solve divergent source-to-target translations, although the divergences were named differently and were resolved by construction-specific trans- fer rules.</S>
  <S sid="49" ssid="49">(For cogent descriptions of the Eurotra project, see, for example, Arnold and des Tombe 1987; Copeland et al.</S>
  <S sid="50" ssid="50">1991; and Johnson, King, and des Tombe 1985).</S>
  <S sid="51" ssid="51">head switching cases will be made clearer in Section 4.3.</S>
  <S sid="52" ssid="52">3 An example of the latter situation is the translation of the English word fish into Spanish: the translation is pez if the fish is still in its natural state, but it is pescado if the fish has been caught and is suitable for food.</S>
  <S sid="53" ssid="53">It is now widely accepted that, in such a situation, the machine translation system must  be able to derive the required information from discourse context and a model  of the domain that is being discussed.</S>
  <S sid="54" ssid="54">599 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 Figure 2 Formal definition of lexical conceptual structure.</S>
  <S sid="55" ssid="55">A comprehensive survey of divergence xamples is presented by Lindop and Tsujii (1991).</S>
  <S sid="56" ssid="56">The term used in this work is "complex transfer," but it describes a class of problems inherent in machine translation itself, not just in the transfer (or interlingual) approaches.</S>
  <S sid="57" ssid="57">One of the claims made by Lindop and Tsujii (1991) is that the non-Eurotra liter- ature rarely goes into great detail when discussing how divergences are handled.</S>
  <S sid="58" ssid="58">An additional claim is that combinations of divergences and interaction effects between divergent and nondivergent translations are not described in the literature.</S>
  <S sid="59" ssid="59">This paper seeks to change this perceived state of affairs by providing a detailed description of a solution to all of the (potentially interacting) divergences shown in Figure 1, not just a subset of them as would typically be found in the description of most translation systems.</S>
  <S sid="60" ssid="60">The framework assumed for the current approach makes use of a linguis- tically grounded classification of divergence types that can be formally defined and systematically resolved.</S>
  <S sid="61" ssid="61">We now turn to a formal description of the terminology used to define the diver- gence problem.</S>
  <S sid="62" ssid="62">Definitions This section formally defines the lexical-semantic representation that serves as the interlingua of the system (Definitions 1-3).</S>
  <S sid="63" ssid="63">This representation, which is influenced primarily by Jackendoff (1983, 1990), has been described in detail elsewhere (see, for example, Dorr 1992b, 1993a) and thus will not be the focus of this paper.</S>
  <S sid="64" ssid="64">In addition to a formal description of the lexical-semantic representation, definitions are provided for syntactic phrases (Definition 4) and two translation mappings (Definitions 5 and 6).</S>
  <S sid="65" ssid="65">Definition 1 A lexical conceptual structure (LCS) is a modified version of the representation proposed by Jackendoff (1983, 1990) that conforms to the following structural form: [T(X) X ([T(W) Wt], [T(Zq) Ztl] "" [T(Z,,) Ztn] [T(Q,) QI] - "  [T(Q,,,) Qm])] This corresponds to the tree-like representation shown in Figure 2, in which (1) X is the logical head; (2) W is the logical subject; (3) Z~... Z~ are the logical arguments; and (4) Q~ ... Q~m are the logical modifiers.</S>
  <S sid="66" ssid="66">These four positions are relevant o the mapping 600 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences ( oo .</S>
  <S sid="67" ssid="67">1 I JOHN TOLo c HAPPILY ?</S>
  <S sid="68" ssid="68">Thing path Manner !</S>
  <S sid="69" ssid="69">I 1 Thing Location Figure 3 CLCS representation for John went happily to school.</S>
  <S sid="70" ssid="70">between the interlingual representation and the surface syntactic representation.</S>
  <S sid="71" ssid="71">In addition, T(~) is the logical type (Event, State, Path, Position, etc.)</S>
  <S sid="72" ssid="72">corresponding to the primitive ~ (CAUSE, LET, GO, STAY, BE, etc.</S>
  <S sid="73" ssid="73">); Primitives are further categorized into fields (e.g., Possessional, Identificational, Temporal, Locational, etc.).</S>
  <S sid="74" ssid="74">4 Example 1 The LCS representation f John went happily to school is [Event GOLoc ([Thing JOHN], [Path TOLoc ([Position ATLoc ([Thing JOHN], [Location SCHOOL])])] [M .</S>
  <S sid="75" ssid="75">HAPPILY])] This corresponds to the tree-like representation shown in Figure 3, in which (1) the logical head is GOLoc (of type Event); (2) the logical subject is JOHN (of type Thing); (3) the logical argument is TOcoc (of type Path); and (4) the logical modifier is HAPPILY (of type Manner).</S>
  <S sid="76" ssid="76">Note that the logical argument is itself a LCS that contains a logical argument, SCHOOL (of type Location), i.e., LCSs are recursively defined.</S>
  <S sid="77" ssid="77">The LCS representation is used both in the lexicon and in the interlingual repre- sentation.</S>
  <S sid="78" ssid="78">The former is identified as a root LCS (RLCS) and the latter is identified as a composed LCS (CLCS): Definition 2 A RLCS (i.e., a root LCS) is an uninstantiated LCS that is associated with a word definition in the lexicon (i.e., a LCS with unfilled variable positions).</S>
  <S sid="79" ssid="79">Example 2 The RLCS associated with the word go (from Example 1) is [Event GOLoc ([Thing X], [Path TOLoc ([Position ATLoc ([Thing X], [Location Z])])])] 4 The validity of the primitives and their compositional properties i not discussed here.</S>
  <S sid="80" ssid="80">The LCS has been studied as the basis of a representation for multiple languages (see, for example, Hale and Keyser 1986a, 1986b, 1989; Hale and Laughren 1983; Levin and Rappaport 1986; Zubizarreta 1982, 1987) and is discussed in the context of machine translation by Dorr (1992b).</S>
  <S sid="81" ssid="81">601 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 ( { ) x /  ... , l Position ) I (   [ x 7.</S>
  <S sid="82" ssid="82">Thing Location Figure 4 RLCS representation forgo.</S>
  <S sid="83" ssid="83">which corresponds to the tree-like representation shown in Figure 4.</S>
  <S sid="84" ssid="84">Definition 3 A CLCS (i.e., a composed LCS) is an instantiated LCS that is the result of combining two or more RLCSs by means of unification (roughly).</S>
  <S sid="85" ssid="85">This is the interlingua, or language- independent, form that serves as the pivot between the source and target languages.</S>
  <S sid="86" ssid="86">Example 3 If we compose the RLCS for go (in Figure 4) with the RLCSs for John ([ThingJOHN]), school ([Location SCHOOL]), and happily ([Manner HAPPILY]), we get the CLCS corre- sponding to John went happily to school (shown in Figure 3).</S>
  <S sid="87" ssid="87">Each (content) word in the lexicon is associated with a RLCS, whose variable positions may have certain restrictions.</S>
  <S sid="88" ssid="88">The CLCS is a structure that results from com- bining the lexical items of a source-language sentence into a single underlying pivot form by means of LCS composition.</S>
  <S sid="89" ssid="89">5 The notion of unification (as used in Definition 3) differs from that of the standard unification frameworks (see, for example, Shieber et al.</S>
  <S sid="90" ssid="90">1989, 1990; Kaplan and Bresnan 1982; Kaplan et al.</S>
  <S sid="91" ssid="91">1989; Kay 1984; etc.)</S>
  <S sid="92" ssid="92">in that it is not directly invertible.</S>
  <S sid="93" ssid="93">That is, the generation process operates on the CLCS in a unification-like fashion that roughly mirrors the LCS composition process, but it is not a direct inverse of this process.</S>
  <S sid="94" ssid="94">The notion of unification used here also differs from others in that it is a more "relaxed" notion: those words that are mapped in a relaxed way are associated with special exical information (i.e., the :INT, :EXT, :PROMOTE, :DEMOTE, ,, :CAT, and :CONFLATED parameters, each of which will be formalized shortly).</S>
  <S sid="95" ssid="95">A fundamental component of the mapping between the interlingual representation and the surface syntactic representation is the syntactic phrase.</S>
  <S sid="96" ssid="96">Definition 4 A syntactic phrase is a maximal projection that conforms to the following structural form: 5 This process is described in detail in Dorr (1992b).</S>
  <S sid="97" ssid="97">602 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences Y-MAX Q-MAXj+I  ... Q -MAXk Y -MAX Q-MAXk+ I ... Q .MAX m W-MAX X-MAX X Z-MAX1 ... Z-MAX a Q-MAX 1 ... Q-MAXi X Q-MAXi+ 1 ... Q-MAXj F igure  5 Formal definition of syntactic phrase.</S>
  <S sid="98" ssid="98">[Y-MAX Q-MAXj+~ ... Q-MAXk [Y-MAX W-MAX [X-MAX [X Q-MAX1 .. .</S>
  <S sid="99" ssid="99">Q-MAXi X Q-MAXi+I ... Q-MAX i] Z-MAX1 .. .</S>
  <S sid="100" ssid="100">Z-MAXn]] Q-MAXk+1 .. .</S>
  <S sid="101" ssid="101">Q-MAXm] 6 This corresponds to the tree-like representation shown in Figure 5, in which (1) X is the syntactic head (of category V, N, A, P, I, or C); (2) W-MAX is the external argument; (3) Z-MAX1, ... ,  Z-MAXn are the internal arguments; and (4) Q-MAX1 .</S>
  <S sid="102" ssid="102">Q-MAXm are the syntactic adjuncts.</S>
  <S sid="103" ssid="103">Example  4 The syntactic phrase corresponding to John went happily to school is [C-MAX [I-MAX [N-MAX John] [V-MAX [v went] [ADV happily] [P-MAX to [N-MAX school]]]]] This corresponds to the tree-like representation shown in Figure 6, in which (1) the syntactic head is [v went]; (2) the external argument is [N-MAX John]; (3) the internal argument is [P-MAX a ...]; and (4) the syntactic adjunct is [ADV happily].</S>
  <S sid="104" ssid="104">Note that the internal argument constituent is itself a syntactic phrase that contains an internal argument, [N-MAX school], i.e., syntactic phrases are recursively defined.</S>
  <S sid="105" ssid="105">In addition to the representations involved in the translation mapping,  it is also possible to formalize the mapping itself.</S>
  <S sid="106" ssid="106">The current approach is to map between 6 These syntactic structures are based on the X framework of government-binding theory (see Chomsky 1981, 1982, 1986a, 1986b).</S>
  <S sid="107" ssid="107">For ease of illustration, the word order used in all formal definitions i head-initial/spec-initial ( .e., the setting for English).</S>
  <S sid="108" ssid="108">The syntactic operations that determine word order are completely independent from the lexical-semantic operations that use these definitions.</S>
  <S sid="109" ssid="109">Thus, the formal definitions can be stated in terms of an arbitrary ordering of constituents, without loss of generality, as long as it is understood that the constituent order is independently determined.</S>
  <S sid="110" ssid="110">603 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 / N-MAX A John C-MAX I I -MAX  V-MAX V ADV P-MAX I I / went happily to N-MAX school Figure 6 Syntactic phrase representation forJohn went happily to school.</S>
  <S sid="111" ssid="111">the LCS representation a d the surface syntactic form by means of two routines that are grounded in linguistic theory: a generalized linking routine (G?T4) and a canonical syntactic realization (CST4).</S>
  <S sid="112" ssid="112">These routines are defined formally here: Definition 5 The ~?T4 systematically relates syntactic positions from Definition 1 and lexical- semantic positions from Definition 4 as follows: 1.</S>
  <S sid="113" ssid="113">Qm Example 5 The correspondence b tween the LCS of Example 1 and the syntactic structure of Example 4 (i.e., for the sentence John went happily to school) is (1) X ~ = GOLoc 4=~ X = Iv went]; (2) W = JOHN 4=~ W = [N-MAX John]; (3) Z = TOcoc 4~ Z = [pp to .</S>
  <S sid="114" ssid="114">]; and (4) Q = HAPPILY ~ Q ~--~[ADV happily].</S>
  <S sid="115" ssid="115">Definition 6 The CST4 systematically relates a lexical-semantic type T(~) to a syntactic ategory CAT(h), where ~t is a CLCS constituent related to the syntactic onstituent ?&gt; by the ~?~.</S>
  <S sid="116" ssid="116">Example 6 The LCS type Thing corresponds to the syntactic ategory N, which is ultimately projected up to a maximal level (i.e., N-MAX).</S>
  <S sid="117" ssid="117">The full range of realization possibilities is given in Figure 7.</S>
  <S sid="118" ssid="118">604 Bonnie J. Dorr  Machine Translat ion Divergences LCS Type EVENT STATE THING PROPERTY PATH POSITION LOCATION TIME MANNER INTENSIFIER PURPOSE Syntactic Category V V N A P P ADV ADV ADV ADV ~ DILl, Figure 7 CST4 mapp ing  between LCS types and  syntactic ategories.</S>
  <S sid="119" ssid="119">Now that  we  have  fo rmal ly  de f ined  the  representat ions  and  mapp ings  used  dur - ing  t rans la t ion ,  we  wi l l  tu rn  to a c lass i f i ca t ion  of  d ivergences  that  is based  on  these de f in i t ions .</S>
  <S sid="120" ssid="120">The Divergence Problem: Formal Classification and Solution In  genera l ,  t rans la t ion  d ivergences  occur  when there  is an  except ion  e i ther  to the ~?T4 or  to the  CST4 (or  to both)  in  one  language,  but  not  in  the  other .</S>
  <S sid="121" ssid="121">7 Th is  p remise a l lows  one  to de f ine  fo rmal ly  a c lass i f i ca t ion  of  al l  l ex ica l - semant ic  d ivergences  that ar i se  dur ing  t rans la t ion  (i.e., d ivergences  based  on  proper t ies  assoc ia ted  w i th  lex ica l 7 Most of the examples in this paper seem to suggest hat a divergence is defined in terms of a language-to-language phenomenon: a divergence occurs when a sentence in language L1 translates into a sentence in L2 in a very different form (i.e., differently shaped parse trees or similarly shaped trees with different basic categories).</S>
  <S sid="122" ssid="122">This definition implies that a divergence may arise between two languages L1 and L2, independent of the way the translation is done (i.e., direct, transfer, or interlingual).</S>
  <S sid="123" ssid="123">However, it is also possible to define a divergence from an interlingual point of view, i.e., with respect to an underlying representation (lexical conceptual structure) that has been chosen to describe the source and target language sentences.</S>
  <S sid="124" ssid="124">From this point of view, a divergent mapping may apply even in cases in which the source- and target-language pairs do not exhibit any distinctions on the surface (e.g., the translation of the German sentence Hans kuflt Marie gern as the equivalent Dutch sentence Hans kust Marie graag, both of which literally translate to Hans kisses Mary likingly).</S>
  <S sid="125" ssid="125">In such cases, there are generally two occurrences of a language-to-interlingua divergence: one from the surface structure and one to the surface structure.</S>
  <S sid="126" ssid="126">(The terms language-to-language nd language-to-interlingua are taken from Dorr and Voss 1993a.)</S>
  <S sid="127" ssid="127">At first glance, it might seem odd to introduce the notion of a language-to-interlingua divergence for cases that do not exhibit a language-to-language divergence.</S>
  <S sid="128" ssid="128">However, it is clearly the case that language-to-language divergences--a special case of language-to-interlingua divergences--do exist regardless of the translation approach adopted.</S>
  <S sid="129" ssid="129">Thus, we can view divergences more generally as a consequence of the internal mapping between the surface structure and the interlingual representation rather than as an external distinction that shows up on the surface.</S>
  <S sid="130" ssid="130">The result is that the interlingua ppears to have been simplified to the extent hat it accommodates constructions in one language (without any special information) more readily than it accommodates the corresponding construction i another language.</S>
  <S sid="131" ssid="131">However, as one reviewer points out, this is not an undesirable consequence, since the development of a suitable representation is where the interlingua builder has a choice and should choose the simplest representation format.</S>
  <S sid="132" ssid="132">The appropriate question to ask is whether an approach that addresses the divergence problem from a language-to-interlingua perspective is an improvement over an approach that addresses the problem strictly from a language-to-language point of view.</S>
  <S sid="133" ssid="133">This paper argues that the language-to-interlingua approach is the correct one given that the alternative would be to handle language-to-language divergences by constructing detailed source-to-target transfer ules for each lexical entry in the source and target language.</S>
  <S sid="134" ssid="134">Introducing the notion of language-to-interlingua divergence allows the translation mapping to be defined in terms of a representation that is general enough to carry over to several different language pairs.</S>
  <S sid="135" ssid="135">605 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 CLCS: Syntax: Y-MAX Y-~x Q W X-MAX IN X Z Figure 8 G?T?</S>
  <S sid="136" ssid="136">mapping between the CLCS and the syntactic structure.</S>
  <S sid="137" ssid="137">entries that are not based on purely syntactic information, idiomatic usage, aspectual knowledge, discourse knowledge, domain knowledge, or world knowledge).</S>
  <S sid="138" ssid="138">Before we define and resolve each divergence type, we will first make some revi- sions to the representations used in Definitions 1 and 4 to simplify the presentation.</S>
  <S sid="139" ssid="139">The representation given in Definition 1 is revised so that Z is used to denote a logical argument from the set {Z~l ... Z~n} and Q is used to denote a logical modifier from the set {QI ... Qm}.</S>
  <S sid="140" ssid="140">The resulting representation is considerably simplified: (8) [T(X) X ([T(W) Wt],  [T(Z) Z  ] ,  [T(Q) Q])] Similarly, the representation given in Definition 4 is revised so that W is used to denote the external argument, Z is used to denote an internal argument from the set {Z-MAX1 ... Z-MAXn}, and Q is used to denote a syntactic adjunct from the set {Q-MAXI ... Q-MAXm}.</S>
  <S sid="141" ssid="141">The resulting representation has the following simplified form: (9) [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W IX-MAX X Z]] Q]8 With these simplifications, the G?T4 can be conceptualized asthe following set of relations: (10) Simplified G?T4: 1.</S>
  <S sid="142" ssid="142">Q ~Q Figure 8 shows the simplified ~?T4 in terms of tree-like representations.</S>
  <S sid="143" ssid="143">9 We are now prepared to define and resolve the translation divergences of Fig- ure 1 on the basis of the simplified formalization presented in (8)-(10) above.</S>
  <S sid="144" ssid="144">The 8 For the purposes of this discussion, we will retain the convention that syntactic adjuncts occur on the right at the maximal level.</S>
  <S sid="145" ssid="145">Note that this is not always the case: the setting of an adjunction parameter (described by Dorr [1993b]) determines the side and level at which a particular adjunct will occur.</S>
  <S sid="146" ssid="146">9 For ease of illustration, this diagram omits the type specification.</S>
  <S sid="147" ssid="147">(There is no loss of generality, since the G?R mapping does not make use of this specification.)</S>
  <S sid="148" ssid="148">We will retain this convention throughout the rest of this paper.</S>
  <S sid="149" ssid="149">606 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences (a) Thematic Divergence CLCS: Syntax: Y-MAX I Y-MAX Q / I X-MAX I X W (b) Promotional Divergence CLCS: Syntax: Y-MAX / i X-MAX !</S>
  <S sid="150" ssid="150">Q X (c) Demofional Divergence CLCS: Syntax: I Y-MAX X X-MAX I Z (d) Structural Divergence CLCS: ~ Y-M~0C Y-MAX O X-MAX IN X R I Z (e) Conflational Divergence CLCS: Syntax: / I X-MAX I x Q Figure 9 Translation mappings for cases in which G?~ default positions are overridden.</S>
  <S sid="151" ssid="151">solution to the divergence problem relies solely on three types of information: the G?T4; the CST4; and a small set of parametric mechanisms.</S>
  <S sid="152" ssid="152">The G?T4 and C$T4 are intended to be language independent, whereas the parameters are intended to encode language-specific information about lexical items.</S>
  <S sid="153" ssid="153">Because the interlingual representa- tion preserves relevant lexical-semantic relations, these three types of information are all that are required for providing a systematic solution to the divergence types shown in Figure 1.</S>
  <S sid="154" ssid="154">In particular, the solution given here eliminates the need for transfer rules and relies instead on parameterized mappings that are defined and applied uniformly across all languages.</S>
  <S sid="155" ssid="155">Seven parameters are used to invoke exceptions to the ~?T4 and C$T4 functions in the context of translation divergences: :INT, :EXT, :PROMOTE, :DE- MOTE, ,, :CAT, and :CONFLATED.</S>
  <S sid="156" ssid="156">We will now present a formal description of each divergence type and its associated parameter.</S>
  <S sid="157" ssid="157">4.1 Thematic Divergence The first divergence type to be formalized is the one for thematic divergence, i.e., the repositioning ofarguments with respect to a given head.</S>
  <S sid="158" ssid="158">This type of divergence arises 607 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 in cases in which the ~?T4 invokes the following sets of relations in place of steps 2 and 3 of (10): (11) 2.</S>
  <S sid="159" ssid="159">W ~ Z 3/Z  l ~ W Figure 9a shows the revised mapping.</S>
  <S sid="160" ssid="160">Thematic divergence arises only in cases in which there is a logical subject.</S>
  <S sid="161" ssid="161">An example of thematic divergence is the reversal of the subject with an object, as in the thematic divergence xample given earlier in (1).</S>
  <S sid="162" ssid="162">The syntactic structures and corresponding CLCS are shown here: (12) [C-MAX [I--MAX IN-MAX I] [V-MAX [V like] [N-MAX Mary]]]] [State BEIdent ([Thing II, [Position aTIdent ([Thing I], [Thing MARY])], [Manner LIKINGLY])] [C-MAX [I-MAX IN-MAX Maria] [V-MAX IV me gusta]l]] 1?</S>
  <S sid="163" ssid="163">Here the object Mary has reversed places with the subject I in the Spanish translation.</S>
  <S sid="164" ssid="164">The result is that the object Mary turns into the subject Maria, and the subject I turns into the object me.</S>
  <S sid="165" ssid="165">This argument reversal is resolved by means of the :INT and :EXT parameters, which force the ~?T4 mapping to be overridden with respect o the positioning of the logical subject and logical argument in Spanish.</S>
  <S sid="166" ssid="166">The lexical entries for like and gustar illustrate the difference in the use of these parameters: (13) (i) (ii) Lexical entry for like: [State BEIdent ([Thing W], [Position aTIdent ([Thing Wl, [Thing Z])], [Manner LIKINGLYI)] Lexical entry for gustar: [State BEldent ([Thing :INT W], [Position aTIdent ([Thing W], [Thing :EXT Z])], [Manner LIKINGLY])] Because the English entry does not include these parameters, the translation relies on the default argument positionings imposed by the ~?T4.</S>
  <S sid="167" ssid="167">By contrast, the :INT/:EXT markers specified in the Spanish entry force the internal and external arguments to swap places in the syntactic structure.</S>
  <S sid="168" ssid="168">10 For the purposes of this discussion, the Spanish sentence is given in its uninverted form.</S>
  <S sid="169" ssid="169">There are other ways of realizing this sentence.</S>
  <S sid="170" ssid="170">In particular, anative speaker of Spanish will frequently invert the subject o post-verbal position: [C-MAX [I--MAX ei [V-MAX IV--MAX [V me gusta]] IN--MAX Mafia]i]]].</S>
  <S sid="171" ssid="171">However, this does not affect he internal/external reversal scheme described here, since inversion is a syntactic operation that takes place independently of the process that handles thematic divergences.</S>
  <S sid="172" ssid="172">608 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences The general solution to thematic divergence is diagrammed as follows: (14) RLCS 1: [T(X,) X ([T(W) W], [r(z,) Z] [T(Q) Q])] RLCS 2: [r(x,) X ([r(w) :INT W], [T(Z) :EXT Z] [T(Q) QI)] Trans la t ion :  [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W [X-MAX X Z]]  Q] [T(X) X  ([T(W) W  ] ,  [T(Z) Z   ]  [T(Q) Q])] [Y-MAX [Y-MAX Z [X-MAX X Wll QI This assumes that there is only one external argument and zero or more internal arguments.</S>
  <S sid="173" ssid="173">If the situation arises in which more than one variable is associated with the :EXT markers, it is assumed that there is an error in the word definition.</S>
  <S sid="174" ssid="174">N Note that the :INT and :EXT markers how up only in the RLCS.</S>
  <S sid="175" ssid="175">The CLCS does not include any such markers, since it is intended to be a language-independent r presentation for the source- and target-language sentences.</S>
  <S sid="176" ssid="176">Thematic divergence is one of three types of possible positioning variations that force the G?T4 to be overridden.</S>
  <S sid="177" ssid="177">Two additional positioning variations are promo- tional and demotional divergences, which will be defined in the next two sections.</S>
  <S sid="178" ssid="178">Whereas thematic divergence involves a repositioning of two satellites relative to a head, promotional and demotional divergences involve a repositioning of the head itself] 2 We will see in Section 5.1 that these three divergences account for the entire range of repositioning possibilities.</S>
  <S sid="179" ssid="179">4.2 Promotional Divergence Promotional divergence is characterized by the promotion (placement "higher up") of a logical modifier into a main verb position (or vice versa), as shown in Figure 9b.</S>
  <S sid="180" ssid="180">In such a situation, the logical modifier is associated with the syntactic head position, and the logical head is then associated with an internal argument position.</S>
  <S sid="181" ssid="181">Thus, promotional divergence overrides the G?T4, invoking the following sets of relations in place of steps 1 and 4 of (10): (15) 1.</S>
  <S sid="182" ssid="182">~ Z 13 4.Q ?~X Figure 9b shows the revised mapping.</S>
  <S sid="183" ssid="183">11 The parameters associated with the RLCS are assumed to be correctly specified for the purposes of this formal description.</S>
  <S sid="184" ssid="184">However, in practice, there might be errors in the lexical entries, since they are constructed by hand in the current implementation.</S>
  <S sid="185" ssid="185">Eventually, the intent is to automate the process of lexical entry construction so that these errors can be avoided.</S>
  <S sid="186" ssid="186">12 The notions of demotion and promotion are not the same as the notions of demotion and advancement in the theory of relational grammar (see Perlmutter 1983).</S>
  <S sid="187" ssid="187">Dorr (1993b, pp.</S>
  <S sid="188" ssid="188">269-274) argues that, although the relational representation might be a convenient tool for illustrating the promotion and demotion operations as used in the current approach, this representation is not an appropriate vehicle for interlingual translation for a number of reasons.</S>
  <S sid="189" ssid="189">13 This relation does not mean that X replaces Z (if there is a Z), but that X retains the same structural relation with Z (i.e., Z remains an internal argument of X).</S>
  <S sid="190" ssid="190">To simplify the current description, Z is not shown in the syntactic structure of Figure 9b.</S>
  <S sid="191" ssid="191">609 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 An example of promotional divergence is the case given earlier in (2).</S>
  <S sid="192" ssid="192">The syntactic structures and corresponding CLCS are shown here: (16) [C-MAX [I-MAX [N--MAX John] [V-MAX IV usually Iv goes]] IN-MAX home]]]l [Event OLoc ([Thing JOHN], [Path TOcoc ([Position ATcoc ([Thing JOHN], [Location HOUSE])])], [Manner HABITUALLY])] [C-MAX [I--MAX IN-MAX Juan] [V-MAX Iv suele] [V-MAX [V ir] [P-MAX a casa]]]]] Here the main verb go is modified by an adverbial adjunct usually, but in Spanish, usually has been placed into a higher position as the main verb soler, and the "going home" event has been realized as the internal argument of this verb.</S>
  <S sid="193" ssid="193">Promotional divergence is resolved by the :PROMOTE parameter, which forces the ~?T4 mapping to be overridden with respect to the positioning of the logical head and the logical modifier.</S>
  <S sid="194" ssid="194">The lexical entries for usually and soler illustrate the difference in the use of this parameter: (17) (i) (ii) Lexical entry for usually: [Manner HABITUALLY] Lexical entry for soler: [Manner :PROMOTE HABITUALLY] Because the English entry does not use this parameter, the translation relies on the de- fault argument positionings imposed by the G?T4.</S>
  <S sid="195" ssid="195">By contrast, he :PROMOTE marker specified in the Spanish entry forces the head and adjunct o swap places in the syn- tactic structure.</S>
  <S sid="196" ssid="196">The general solution to promotional divergence is diagrammed as follows: (18) RLCS 1: [T(Q) Q] RLCS 2: [T(Q) :PROMOTE Q] Translation: [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W [X--MAX X Z]] Q] [T(X) X ([T(W) W], [T(Z) Z] [T(Q) Q])] [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W [X-MAX Q [ ... X Z]]]] 4.3 Demotional Divergence Demotional divergence is characterized by the demotion (placement "lower down") of a logical head into an internal argument position (or vice versa), as shown in Figure 9c.</S>
  <S sid="197" ssid="197">In such a situation, the logical head is associated with the syntactic adjunct position, and the logical argument is then associated with a syntactic head position.</S>
  <S sid="198" ssid="198">Thus, 610 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences demotional divergence overrides the g?T4, invoking the following sets of relations in place of steps 1 and 3 of (10): (19) 1.</S>
  <S sid="199" ssid="199">Z 4:&gt; X Figure 9(c) shows the revised mapping.</S>
  <S sid="200" ssid="200">An example of demotional divergence is the case given earlier in (3).</S>
  <S sid="201" ssid="201">The syntactic structures and corresponding CLCS are shown here: is (20) [C-MAX [I-MAX IN-MAX I]i IV-MAX IV l ike] [C-MAX PROi  to eat]]]] [State BEcirc ([Thing I], [Position ATcirc ([Thing I], [Event EAT ([Thing I], [Thing FOOD])  ] )  ] [Manner LIKINGLY])] [C-MAX [I-MAX IN-MAX Ich] IV-MAX IV [ADV gern] Iv esse]]]]] 16 Here the main verb like takes the "to eat" event as an internal argument; but in German, like has been placed into a lower position as the adjunct gern, and the "eat" event has been realized as the main verb.</S>
  <S sid="202" ssid="202">The distinction between promotional and demotional divergences may not be in- tuitively obvious at first glance.</S>
  <S sid="203" ssid="203">In both cases, the translation mapping appears to associate a main verb with an adverbial satellite, or vice versa.</S>
  <S sid="204" ssid="204">However, the dis- tinction between these two head switching cases becomes more apparent when we consider the status of the participating lexical tokens more carefully.</S>
  <S sid="205" ssid="205">In the case of soler-usually, the main verb soler is, in some sense, the token that "triggers" the head switching operation: its presence forces the adverbial satellite usually to appear in En- glish, even if we were to substitute some other event for ir in Spanish (e.g., correr a la tienda, leer un libro, etc.).</S>
  <S sid="206" ssid="206">By contrast, in the case of like-gern, the triggering element is not the main verb like, since we are able to use like in other contexts that do not require gern (e.g., I like the car ~ Mir gefdllt der Wagen); instead, the triggering element is the adverbial satellite gern: its presence forces the verb like to appear in English even if we were to substitute some other event in place of essen in German (e.g., zum Geschdft laufen, das Buch lesen, etc.).</S>
  <S sid="207" ssid="207">We will return to this point in Section 5.2.</S>
  <S sid="208" ssid="208">Demotional divergence is resolved by the :DEMOTE parameter, which forces the ~?T4 mapping to be overridden with respect o the positioning of the logical head and the logical argument.</S>
  <S sid="209" ssid="209">The lexical entries for like and gern illustrate the difference in the use of this parameter: 17 14 This relation does not mean that X replaces Q (if there is a Q), but that X retains the same structural relation with Q (i.e., Q remains a syntactic adjunct of X).</S>
  <S sid="210" ssid="210">To simplify the current description, Q is not shown in the syntactic structure of Figure 9c.</S>
  <S sid="211" ssid="211">15 The default object being eaten is FOOD, although this argument does not appear on the surface for the current example.</S>
  <S sid="212" ssid="212">16 The German syntactic structure is shown here in the uninverted base form.</S>
  <S sid="213" ssid="213">In the German surface structure, the verb is moved up into verb-second position and the subject is topicalized: [C--MAX IN--MAX IchJ/ Iv esse]j [I--MAX IN--MAX t]l IV--MAX Iv [ADV gem] Iv t]/]]/].</S>
  <S sid="214" ssid="214">17 Both definitions of like in (21) use the circumstantial field, which means that the Y argument must be an Event (e.g., like ta eat) rather than a Thing (e.g., like Mary).</S>
  <S sid="215" ssid="215">Thus, the definitions for like and gern are slightly different from the definitions of like given earlier in (13) (i.e., these are additional lexical entries for like).</S>
  <S sid="216" ssid="216">611 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 (21) (i) (ii) Lexical entry for like: [State BEcirc ([Thing W], [position ATcirc ([Thing W], [Event Z])], [Manner LIKINGLY])] Lexical entry for gem: [State BECirc ([Thing W], [Position ATCirc ([Thing W], [Event :DEMOTE Z])], [Manner LIKINGLY])] Because the English entry does not use this parameter, the translation relies on the default argument positionings imposed by the ~?T4.</S>
  <S sid="217" ssid="217">By contrast, he :DEMOTE marker specified in the German entry forces the head and internal argument to swap places in the syntactic structure.</S>
  <S sid="218" ssid="218">The general solution to demotional divergence is diagrammed as follows: (22) RLCS 1: [v(x) X ([T(W) W], [T(Z) Z] [T(Q) Q])] RLCS 2: [T(X) X ([T(W) W], [T(Z) :DEMOTE Z] [T(Q) Q])] Translation: [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W IX-MAX X Z]] Q] [v(x) X ([T(W/ W], [T(Z) Z] [T(Q/ Q])l [Y--MAX [Y-MAX W IX-MAX Z] [ ... X QI]] 4.4 Structural Divergence Structural divergence differs from the last three divergence types in that it does not alter the positions used in the ~?T4 mapping, but it changes the nature of the relation between the different positions (i.e., the "4=~" correspondence).</S>
  <S sid="219" ssid="219">Figure 9d characterizes the alteration that takes place.</S>
  <S sid="220" ssid="220">Note that the mapping of Z to the corresponding internal argument position is altered so that it is positioned under the constituent that corresponds to W. An example of structural divergence is the case given earlier in (4).</S>
  <S sid="221" ssid="221">The syntactic structures and corresponding CLCS are shown here: (23) [C-MAX [I-MAX IN-MAX John] IV-MAX IV entered] [N-MAX the house]]]] [Event GOLoc ([Thing JOHN], [Path TOcoc ([Position INcoc ([Thing JOHN], [Location HOUSE])])])] [C-MAX [I-MAX IN-MAX Juan] [V-MAX IV entr6] [P-MAX en [N-MAX la casa]]]]] Here the verbal object is realized as a noun phrase (the house) in English and as a prepositional phrase (en la casa) in Spanish.</S>
  <S sid="222" ssid="222">Structural divergence is resolved by means of the * marker, which forces logical constituents obe realized compositionally atdifferent levels.</S>
  <S sid="223" ssid="223">In particular, the * serves as a pointer to a RLCS position that must be combined with another RLCS in order to arrive at a (portion of a) CLCS.</S>
  <S sid="224" ssid="224">The lexical entries for enter and entrar illustrate the difference in the use of this parameter: 612 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences (24) (i) (ii) Lexical entry for enter: [Event GOLoc ([Thing W], [Path TOLoc ([Position INLoc ([Thing W], [Location * Z])])])] Lexical entry for entrar: [Event GOLoc ([Thing W], [Path * TOLoc ([Position INcoc ([Thing W], [Location Z])])])] Because the English entry contains a * marker in the [Location Z[ position, this constituent is realized on the surface as the object (i.e., the house) of the main verb.</S>
  <S sid="225" ssid="225">By contrast, the ?</S>
  <S sid="226" ssid="226">marker is associated with a "higher" position [Path TOcoc ...] in the Spanish entry, thus forcing this constituent to have a more complex realization (i.e., en la casa) in the syntactic structure.</S>
  <S sid="227" ssid="227">The general solution to structural divergence is diagrammed as follows: (25) RLCS 1: [T(X,) X ([T(W) W], [T(R) R ([T(Z) * Z])] [r(Q,) Q])] RLCS 2: [r(x,) X ([r(w,) W], [r(R) * R ([r(z) Z])] [T(Q) Q])] Translation: [Y-MAX [Y-MAX [r(x,) X ([T(W) [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W [X-MAX X Z]] Q] W], [T(Z) Z] [T(Q) Q])] W [X-MAX X [ ... R Z]]] Q] Note that the logical argument R is associated with a * marker in the RLCS of the target language, but not in the RLCS of the source language.</S>
  <S sid="228" ssid="228">This forces the target language syntactic structure to realize a phrase R that dominates Z; in contrast, no such dominating phrase occurs in the source-language structure.</S>
  <S sid="229" ssid="229">4.5 Conflational Divergence Conflational divergence is another case in which the "~"  correspondence is changed.</S>
  <S sid="230" ssid="230">In particular, conflational divergence is characterized by the suppression of a CLCS constituent (or the inverse of this process).</S>
  <S sid="231" ssid="231">The constituent generally occurs in logical argument or logical modifier position; thus, the "4=&gt;" correspondence of either step 3 or step 4 of the ~?T4 is changed, depending on which position is conflated.</S>
  <S sid="232" ssid="232">Figure 9e characterizes the alteration that takes place.</S>
  <S sid="233" ssid="233">Note that the Z position in the CLCS does not have a corresponding realization in the syntax.</S>
  <S sid="234" ssid="234">An example of conflational divergence is the case given earlier in (5).</S>
  <S sid="235" ssid="235">The syntactic structures and corresponding LCS are shown here: (26) [C-MAX [I-MAX IN-MAX I] [V-MAX [V stabbed[ [N-MAX John]][[ [Event CAUSE ([Thing I], [Event GOposs ([Thing KNIFE-WOUND], [Path TOWARDposs ([Position ATposs (/Thing KNIFE-WOUND], [Thing JOHN])])[)])] [C-MAX [I-MAX IN-MAX Yo] [V-MAX [v le di] [N-MAX pufialadas] [P-MAX a Juan][]] 613 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 Here, English uses the single word stab for the two Spanish words dar (give) and pu~aladas (knife-wounds); this is because the effect of the action (i.e., the knife-wound portion of the lexical token) is incorporated into the main verb in English.</S>
  <S sid="236" ssid="236">Conflational divergence is resolved by means of the :CONFLATED marker, which suppresses the realization of the filler of a particular position.</S>
  <S sid="237" ssid="237">The lexical entries for stab and dar illustrate the difference in the use of this parameter: is (27) (i) (ii) Lexical entry for stab: [Event CAUSE ([Thing W] , [Event GOposs ([Thing :CONFLATED KNIFE-WOUND], [Path TOWARDposs ([Position ATposs ([Thing KNIFE-WOUND], [Thing Z])])])])l Lexical entry for dar: [Event CAUSE ([Thing W], [Event GOposs ([Thing ~ Y], [Path TOWARDposs ([Position ATposs ([Thing Y], [Thing ZI)])])])] Because the English entry contains a :CONFLATED marker in the logical position cor- responding to KNIFE-WOUND, this constituent is suppressed in the syntactic struc- ture.</S>
  <S sid="238" ssid="238">By contrast, this marker does not appear in the corresponding position in Span- ish, thus forcing this constituent to be overtly realized (i.e., puflaladas) in the svntactic structure.</S>
  <S sid="239" ssid="239">The general solution to conflational divergence is diagrammed as follows: (28) RLCS 1: [~(x,) X ([T(W) W], [T(Z) * Z] [T(Q) Q])] RLCS 2: [T(X) X ([z(w) W], [T(Z) :CONFLATED Z] [T(Q) Q])] Trans lat ion:  [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W [X-MAX X Z]] Q] [T(X~ X ([T(W/ W], [T(Z} Z] [r;Qq Q])] [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W [X-MAX XI[ QI Note that the logical argument Z is associated with a :CONFLATED marker in the RLCS of the target language, but not in the RLCS of the source language.</S>
  <S sid="240" ssid="240">This forces the target language syntactic structure to suppress the realization of this constituent.</S>
  <S sid="241" ssid="241">18 Note that the :CONFLATED marker appears to be in complementary distribution with the ?</S>
  <S sid="242" ssid="242">In fact, one might consider the use of the :CONFLATED marker to be unnecessary, since its presence could be implied by the absence of the * marker.</S>
  <S sid="243" ssid="243">However, the :CONFLATED marker plays an important role in the lexical-semantic representation: it specifies that the "constant" term (e.g., the KNIFE-WOUND of the stab RLCS) must obligatorily fill the position and, moreover, that this constant must be a legal LCS primitive of the system.</S>
  <S sid="244" ssid="244">In addition, there is an inherent asymmetry between the :CONFLATED marker and the * marker: whereas the former always occurs in a leaf node position, the latter may occur in any position in the RLCS.</S>
  <S sid="245" ssid="245">Because the notion of conflation is not meaningful in non-leaf node positions, it would be unreasonable to make the assumption that every non-leaf position without the * marker is conflated.</S>
  <S sid="246" ssid="246">The :CONFLATED marker is used to identify truly conflated positions, not just those positions without the * marker.</S>
  <S sid="247" ssid="247">614 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences 4.6 Categorial Divergence Unlike the previous five divergence types, categorial divergence affects the operation of the C$/~, not the ~?T4.</S>
  <S sid="248" ssid="248">It is characterized by a situation in which CAT(0) is forced to have a different value than would normally be assigned to T(~ ~) by means of the mapping specified in Figure 7.</S>
  <S sid="249" ssid="249">Thus, categorial divergence is formally described as follows: a lexical-semantic type T(~) is related to a syntactic category CAT(~), where CAT(~) ~ CST4(T(~)).</S>
  <S sid="250" ssid="250">In such a case, CAT(~) must be specified through lexical parameterization.</S>
  <S sid="251" ssid="251">An example of categorial divergence is the case given earlier in (6).</S>
  <S sid="252" ssid="252">The syntactic structures and corresponding CLCS are shown here: (29) [C-MAX [I-MAX [N-MAX I] [V-MAX [V am]  [A--MAX hungry]]]] [State BEIdent ([Thing I], [Position aTIdent ([Thing I], [Property HUNGRY])])] [C-MAX [I-MAX [N-MAX Ich] [V-MAX IN-MAX Hunger] [v habe]]]] 19 Here, the predicate is adjectival (hungry) in English but nominal (Hunger) in German.</S>
  <S sid="253" ssid="253">Categorial divergence is resolved by means of the :CAT parameter.</S>
  <S sid="254" ssid="254">The lexical entries for be and haben illustrate the difference in the use of this parameter: 2?</S>
  <S sid="255" ssid="255">(30) (i) (ii) Lexical entry for be: [State BEIdent ([Thing W], [Position aTIdent ([Thing W], [Property Y])])] Lexical entry for haben: [State BEIdent ([Thing W], [Position aTIdent ([Thing W], [Property :CAT(N) Y])])] Because the English entry does not contain a :CAT marker in the position correspond- ing to [Property Y], this constituent is realized in the syntactic structure as C$/~(Property) Adjective (i.e., hungry).</S>
  <S sid="256" ssid="256">By contrast, the :CAT(N) marker specified in the German entry forces the default C$T4 category to be overridden and the Property argument is realized as a noun form (i.e., Hunger).</S>
  <S sid="257" ssid="257">19 The German structure shown here is the base form of the following surface syntactic tree: [C-MAX IN-MAX Ich]i [C Iv babe]j] [I--MAX [N--MAX tli [V-MAX [N-MAX Hunger] [v t]jI [I e]]] This form is derived by the syntactic processor after lexical-semantic processing is complete (see Dorr 1993a, for details).</S>
  <S sid="258" ssid="258">20 As might be expected, there are two lexical entries for the verb haben, only one of which is listed here.</S>
  <S sid="259" ssid="259">The one not shown here corresponds to the possessional sense of haben, i.e., the meaning corresponding to the word have in English.</S>
  <S sid="260" ssid="260">This entry does not contain a :CAT marker.</S>
  <S sid="261" ssid="261">615 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 The general solution to categorial divergence is diagrammed as follows: (31) RLCS 1: [T(X,) X ([T(W) W], IT(Z,) :Z] [T(Q) Q])] RLCS 2: It(x,) X ([7(w) W], IT(Z,) (:CAT 6) Z] [~(Q,) Q])] Translation: [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W IX-MAX X Z]] Q] [T(X) X ([T(W) W], [T(Z) Z] [T(Q) Q])I [Y-MAX [Y-MAX W [X-MAX X a]] QI where CAT(Z) = &amp;MAX.</S>
  <S sid="262" ssid="262">4.7 Lexical Divergence Lexical divergence arises only in the context of other divergence types.</S>
  <S sid="263" ssid="263">21 This is be- cause the choice of lexical items in any language relies crucially on the realization and composition properties of those lexical items.</S>
  <S sid="264" ssid="264">Because the six preceding divergences potentially alter these properties, lexical divergence is viewed as a side effect of other divergences.</S>
  <S sid="265" ssid="265">Thus, the formalization thereof is considered to be some combination of those given above.</S>
  <S sid="266" ssid="266">Unlike the first six divergence types, lexical divergence is solved during the pro- cess of lexical selection.</S>
  <S sid="267" ssid="267">22Thus, there is no specific override marker that is used for this type of divergence.</S>
  <S sid="268" ssid="268">For example, in the lexical divergence (7), a conflational di- vergence forces the occurrence of a lexical divergence.</S>
  <S sid="269" ssid="269">The syntactic structures and corresponding CLCS for this example are shown here: (32) [C-MAX [I-MAX [N-MAX John] IV--MAX IV broke] [P-MAX into IN--MAX the room]]]]] [Event CAUSE ([Thing JOHN], [Event GOLoc ([Thing JOHN], [Path TOLoc ([Position INcoc ([Thing JOHN], [Location ROOMI)])I)] [Manner FORCEFULLY])] [C-MAX [I-MAX [N-MAX Juan] IV-MAX IV forz6] IN-MAX la entrada] [P-MAX al cuarto]]]] Because the word-particle pair break into subsumes two concepts (forceful spatial mo- tion and entry to a location), it is crucial that the word forzar (literally, force) be selected in conjunction with entrada (literally, entry) for the underlying break-into concept.</S>
  <S sid="270" ssid="270">21 As noted by a reviewer, this is not strictly true, since there are many cases in which a source-language word maps to more than one target-language word without he simultaneous occurrence of another divergence type.</S>
  <S sid="271" ssid="271">An example of such a case is the English word eat, which maps to essen (for humans) or fressen (for animals).</S>
  <S sid="272" ssid="272">Such cases are considered to be outside of the classes of lexical-semantic divergences considered here (see Footnote 3).</S>
  <S sid="273" ssid="273">However, a simple approach to resolving such cases would be to use featural restrictions during syntactic processing.</S>
  <S sid="274" ssid="274">22 The solution to lexical divergence is trivial for transfer machine translation systems, ince transfer entries map source-language words directly to their target-language equivalents.</S>
  <S sid="275" ssid="275">In general, exical selection is not seen as a problem in these systems.</S>
  <S sid="276" ssid="276">616 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences There is also a structural divergence in this example, since the prepositional phrase into the room must be translated into a noun phrase entrada al cuarto.</S>
  <S sid="277" ssid="277">This divergence compounds the lexical divergence problem, since it is necessary to choose the target- language word a in the absence of a source-language counterpart.</S>
  <S sid="278" ssid="278">Lexical divergence also shows up in three previously presented examples, (12), (29), and (26), owing to the presence of thematic, categorial, and conflational diver- gences, respectively: in (12) the word like is chosen for the word gustar (literally, to please); in (29) the word haben (literally, to have) is chosen for the word be; and in (26) the word dar (literally, to give) is chosen for the word stab.</S>
  <S sid="279" ssid="279">Discussion This section discusses certain issues of relevance to the formal classification and reso- lution of translation divergences.</S>
  <S sid="280" ssid="280">In particular, we will discuss (1) the limits imposed on the range of repositioning possibilities; (2) the justification for distinguishing be- tween promotional nd demotional divergences; (3) the notion of full coverage in the context of lexical selection; and (4) the resolution of interacting divergence types.</S>
  <S sid="281" ssid="281">5.1 Limits on Repositioning Divergences In Section 4.1 we made the claim that the thematic, promotional, and demotional divergences account for the entire range of repositioning possibilities.</S>
  <S sid="282" ssid="282">We will now explore the validity of this claim.</S>
  <S sid="283" ssid="283">There are two potential types of syntactic relations that exist between a head and a satellite: the first is complementation (i.e., involving the internal argument), and the second is adjunction.</S>
  <S sid="284" ssid="284">23 Given these two types of relations, there are only a small number of ways syntactic entities may be repositioned.</S>
  <S sid="285" ssid="285">The three CLCS positions that are involved in these relations are X, Z ~, and Q.</S>
  <S sid="286" ssid="286">If we compute the repositionings combinatorically, there are 33 = 27 configurations (i.e., X ~, Z, and Q~ would map into any of three positions).</S>
  <S sid="287" ssid="287">However, we can eliminate 15 of these (since a CLCS must contain exactly one head), thus leaving only 12 possible configurations.</S>
  <S sid="288" ssid="288">One of these corresponds to the default G?~ mapping (i.e., the logical head, logical argument, and logical modifier map into canonical positions).</S>
  <S sid="289" ssid="289">The remaining 11 configurations can be factored into three cases as follows: 1.</S>
  <S sid="290" ssid="290">X 4=&gt; X 1.1 Q ~ Z; Z 1 4=~ Z.</S>
  <S sid="291" ssid="291">1.2 Z ~ Q; Q 4=~ Q.</S>
  <S sid="292" ssid="292">1.3 Q &lt;~ Z; Z ~ Q.</S>
  <S sid="293" ssid="293">X 2.1 X ~ 4=~ Z; Z ??</S>
  <S sid="294" ssid="294">2.2 X ~Z;Z  ~&lt;=~Q.</S>
  <S sid="295" ssid="295">23 We have left out the possibility of an external argument as a participant in the head-satellite r lation.</S>
  <S sid="296" ssid="296">Of course, the external argument is a satellite with respect to the head, but it turns out that the external argument, which corresponds to the logical subject in the CLCS, has a special status and does not have the same repositioning potential that internal arguments and syntactic adjuncts have.</S>
  <S sid="297" ssid="297">In particular, the external argument has the unique property that it never participates as the incorporated argument of a conflational verb.</S>
  <S sid="298" ssid="298">Hale and Keyser (1989) provide evidence that this property holds across all languages.</S>
  <S sid="299" ssid="299">Thus, we take the external argument to have a special status (universally) that exempts it from participating in divergences other than thematic divergence.</S>
  <S sid="300" ssid="300">617 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 (a) Case 1.1 CLCS: X ~  Y-MAX] Y-MAX 71 X-MAX IN x Q (b) Case 1.2 CLCS: Syntax: Y-MAX I   Y-MAX Z / I X-MAX I x (e) Case 2.3 CLCS: Syntax: IN Y-MAX X / I Z~, X-MAX t ?</S>
  <S sid="301" ssid="301">Q z (d) Case 3.2 CLCS: Syntax: Y-MAX X-MAX IN Z X Q Figure 10 Illegal translation mappings for natural language.</S>
  <S sid="302" ssid="302">2.3 X ~ Q; Z 4~ Z.</S>
  <S sid="303" ssid="303">Z ~X 3.1 X ~Z;Q ~Z.</S>
  <S sid="304" ssid="304">3.2 x &lt;=~ Z; Q ~=~ Q.</S>
  <S sid="305" ssid="305">3.3 X ~ Q; Q &lt;=~ Z.</S>
  <S sid="306" ssid="306">3.4 X &lt;=~ Q; Q &lt;=~ Q.</S>
  <S sid="307" ssid="307">We will discuss in detail how four of these cases, i.e., the ones characterized in Fig- ure 10, are ruled out.</S>
  <S sid="308" ssid="308">Of the remaining, 2.1 and 3.4 correspond to the definitions of promotional and demotional divergences illustrated in Figures 9b and 9c, respectively; cases 1.3, 2.2, 2.4, 3.1, and 3.3 are ruled out for the same reasons that cases 1.1 and 1.2 are ruled out (as we will see shortly), namely, that an internal argument Z can never be associated with a logical modifier Q and that a syntactic adjunct (Q) can never be associated with a logical argument Z.</S>
  <S sid="309" ssid="309">It cannot be the case that a logical modifier maps to an internal argument position (case 1.1) because a logical modifier is an optional participant of a particular action, i.e., it need not be "governed" by the lexical item that it modifies.</S>
  <S sid="310" ssid="310">Internal argument positions are reserved for cases in which a government relation must hold; thus, logical modifiers must necessarily be mapped into syntactic adjunct positions.</S>
  <S sid="311" ssid="311">Similarly, it also cannot be the case that a logical argument maps to a syntactic adjunct position (case 1.2).</S>
  <S sid="312" ssid="312">A logical argument is a necessary participant of a particular action, and as such, it must be "governed" by the lexical item that selects it.</S>
  <S sid="313" ssid="313">By contrast, adjunct positions are reserved for optional modifying participants that do not need to be governed by the lexical item that they are modifying; thus, logical arguments must necessarily be mapped into internal argument positions.</S>
  <S sid="314" ssid="314">618 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences Another case that is eliminated is the renaming of a logical head as a syntactic adjunct whose head corresponds to a logical modifier (case 2.3).</S>
  <S sid="315" ssid="315">The idea is simply that modification is a one-way relation.</S>
  <S sid="316" ssid="316">If a logical head has a modifier, the head cannot become an adjunct of that modifier because the modifying relation would be reversed (i.e., the logical head would modify the syntactic head rather than the other way around).</S>
  <S sid="317" ssid="317">In contrast, a logical head of a CLCS can be mapped to an internal argument position in cases in which a logical modifier is mapped to a syntactic head (i.e., the case of promotional divergence presented earlier), since there is no violation of the one-way relation.</S>
  <S sid="318" ssid="318">A similar argument is used to eliminate the case in which a logical head is mapped to an internal argument whose head corresponds toa logical argument (case 3.2).</S>
  <S sid="319" ssid="319">The idea is that heads and arguments participate in a one-way relation.</S>
  <S sid="320" ssid="320">If a logical head has an argument, he head cannot become an internal argument of that argument because the head-argument relation would be reversed (i.e., the logical head would be an argument of the syntactic head rather than the other way around).</S>
  <S sid="321" ssid="321">In contrast, he logical head of a CLCS can be mapped to an adjunct (i.e., modifier) position in cases in which a logical argument is mapped to a syntactic head (i.e., the case of demotional divergence presented earlier), since these is no violation of the one-way relation.</S>
  <S sid="322" ssid="322">The argument for the elimination of the last two cases could be viewed as an appeal to a constraint that is analogous to the 0-criterion in syntax.</S>
  <S sid="323" ssid="323">Essentially, this constraint states that all arguments and modifiers must be licensed (see Chomsky 1986a; Abney 1989) in order to appear either in the syntactic structure or in the conceptual structure.</S>
  <S sid="324" ssid="324">In the context of conceptual structure, a logical modifier may license the realization of a logical head in an internal argument position, but not in an adjunct position, since the modifier elation is already satisfied by virtue of the relation between the head and the modifier.</S>
  <S sid="325" ssid="325">Similarly, a logical argument may license the realization of a logical head in a syntactic adjunct position, but not in an internal argument position, since the head-argument relation is already satisfied by virtue of the relation between the head and the argument.</S>
  <S sid="326" ssid="326">Having eliminated the meaningless possibilities, we are left with the promotional nd demotional cases presented above.</S>
  <S sid="327" ssid="327">5.2 Promotional versus Demotional Divergences We will now provide justification for the earlier claim that promotional and demo- tional divergence should be classified ifferently, even though they exhibit some of the same properties.</S>
  <S sid="328" ssid="328">It might be argued that these divergences are essentially the same, since both cases involve an association of a main verb with an adverbial satellite or vice versa.</S>
  <S sid="329" ssid="329">In the examples given earlier, the promotional divergence r ferred to a map- ping between the adverbial usually and the main verb soler and demotional divergence referred to a mapping between the adverbial gern and the main verb like.</S>
  <S sid="330" ssid="330">However, as mentioned in Section 4.3, these are taken to be in distinct classes: the difference between these two cases is determined by the "triggering" element (i.e., promotion is triggered by a main verb such as soler, whereas demotion is triggered by an adverb such as gern).</S>
  <S sid="331" ssid="331">Another factor that distinguishes between promotional and demotional diver- gences is the fact that verbs such as like and verbs such as soler do not have parallel syntactic distributions, nor do they have analogous logical interpretations.</S>
  <S sid="332" ssid="332">The verb like may take a sentential complement that has its own event structure (as in I like to eat), or it may take a nominal complement without an event structure (as in I like the car).</S>
  <S sid="333" ssid="333">In either case, the verb like generally means the same thing (i.e., it describes a state in which an event or a thing is somehow desirable to that person).</S>
  <S sid="334" ssid="334">By contrast, the verb soler is a modal verb that contributes an aspectual component of meaning 619 Computational Linguistics Volume 20, Number 4 that crucially relies on a verbal complement with an event structure; in a sense, soler is analogous to the modal must in English in that it cannot be used in isolation, but requires the presence of a verbal complement in order for it to be interpretable.</S>
  <S sid="335" ssid="335">In such a configuration, the modal soler allows the event to be interpreted as being habitual in nature.</S>
  <S sid="336" ssid="336">Given these distinctions, it would not be appropriate to consider the head switch- ing mapping to be the same for the soler-usually and like-gern cases.</S>
  <S sid="337" ssid="337">Not only do they have different triggering elements (i.e., the main verb in the former and the adverb in the latter), but they do not have identical syntactic distributions and their logical in- terpretations are not analogous.</S>
  <S sid="338" ssid="338">Thus, they are taken to be two independent mappings with entirely different syntactic and lexical-semantic ramifications.</S>
  <S sid="339" ssid="339">The handling of promotional and demotional divergences i  a topic that has re- ceived recent attention, although it has been labeled differently, depending on how it is manifested.</S>
  <S sid="340" ssid="340">An example of such a case is the way construction.</S>
  <S sid="341" ssid="341">This phenomenon has been studied by Jackendoff (1990) in his extended version of the original LCS framework: (33) Bill belched his way out of the restaurant In such cases, Jackendoff claims that belching is subordinated toa higher predicate like GO, "in effect demoting the meaning of the lexical verb to a subordinate accompani- ment or means modifier" (Jackendoff 1990, p. 214).</S>
  <S sid="342" ssid="342">This characterization is essentially equivalent to that of the soler-usually example (i.e., promotional divergence) given earlier.</S>
  <S sid="343" ssid="343">24 5.3 Lexical Selection: Full Coverage Constraint Because of the compositional nature of the LCS representation, the current framework automatically imposes a full coverage constraint during the lexical selection process.</S>
  <S sid="344" ssid="344">Formally, this constraint is defined as follows: (34) Full coverage constraint: A RLCS R matches a CLCS C if and only if R fully covers C. where R fully covers C under the following conditions: (35) A RLCS R fully covers a CLCS C if and only if: (a) there is no portion of R that does not match C; 24 Jackendoffs approach to handling the way construction has been criticized by Marantz (1992) for its use of arbitrary exceptions to the "usual mappings."</S>
  <S sid="345" ssid="345">Marantz takes issue with the characterization f such cases as an idiosyncratic relation between syntax and semantics and proposes, instead, that the conceptual structure looks different from what Jackendoff envisions.</S>
  <S sid="346" ssid="346">Whichever of these proposals i correct, neither Jackendoff nor Marantz considers their proposals in the context of interlingual machine translation.</S>
  <S sid="347" ssid="347">If the exceptional mappings are indeed arbitrary, then one needs to explain how this affects the handling of different languages.</S>
  <S sid="348" ssid="348">Moreover, neither Jackendoff nor Marantz mentions the possibility that the number of exceptional mappings might not be arbitrarily large, but that there might be a fixed number of exceptions, delineated in such a way that only a handful need to be considered at any time for any given language.</S>
  <S sid="349" ssid="349">This is why the formalization described in this paper is a valuable resource: it provides a means for proving that only certain types of exceptions are allowed and that the number of such exceptions i  actually quite small.</S>
  <S sid="350" ssid="350">Finally, neither Jackendoff nor Marantz considers keeping Jackendoffs version of the LCS intact and using a single parameterized mapping along the lines proposed in the current framework.</S>
  <S sid="351" ssid="351">620 Bonnie J. Dorr Machine Translation Divergences (b) either R completely matches C (i.e., there is no portion of C that does not match R) or R matches all of C except some portion C (i.e., a subcomponent of C) that is fully covered by some other RLCS R/.</S>
  <S sid="352" ssid="352">In cases in which more than one lexical entry matches a current concept, his constraint is used to determine which possibil</S>
</PAPER>
