<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">This paper introduces a system for categorizing unknown words.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">The system is based on a multi-component architecture where each component is responsible for identifying one class of unknown words.</S>
		<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">The focus of this paper is the components that identify names and spelling errors.</S>
		<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">Each component uses a decision tree architecture to combine multiple types of evidence about the unknown word.</S>
		<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">The system is evaluated using data from live closed captions - a genre replete with a wide variety of unknown words.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">In any real world use, a Natural Language Processing (NLP) system will encounter words that are not in its lexicon, what we term &apos;unknown words&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">Unknown words are problematic because a NLP system will perform well only if it recognizes the words that it is meant to analyze or translate: the more words a system does not recognize the more the system&apos;s performance will degrade.</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">Even when unknown words are infrequent, they can have a disproportionate effect on system quality.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">For example, Min (1996) found that while only 0.6% of words in 300 emails were misspelled, this meant that 12% of the sentences contained an error (discussed in (Min and Wilson, 1998)).</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">Words may be unknown for many reasons: the word may be a proper name, a misspelling, an abbreviation, a number, a morphological variant of a known word (e.g. recleared),or missing from the dictionary.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">The first step in dealing with unknown words is to identify the class of the unknown word; whether it is a misspelling, a proper name, an abbreviation etc. Once this is known, the proper action can be taken, misspellings can be corrected, abbreviations can be expanded and so on, as deemed necessary by the particular text processing application.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">In this paper we introduce a system for categorizing unknown words.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">The system is based on a multi- component architecture where each component is responsible for identifying one category of unknown words.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">The main focus of this paper is the components that identify names and spelling errors.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">Both components use a decision tree architecture to combine multiple types of evidence about the unknown word.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">Results from the two components are combined using a weighted voting procedure.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">The system is evaluated using data from live closed captions -a genre replete with a wide variety of unknown words.</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">This paper is organized as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">In section 2 we outline the overall architecture of the unknown word categorizer.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "20">The name identifier and the misspelling identifier are introduced in section 3.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "21">Performance and evaluation issues are discussed in section 4.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "22">Section 5 considers portability issues.</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "23">Section 6 compares the current system with relevant preceding research.</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "24">Concluding comments can be found in section 6..</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="System Architecture. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "1">The goal of our research is to develop a system that automatically categorizes unknown words.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "2">According to our definition, an unknown word is a word that is not contained in the lexicon of an NLP system.</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "3">As defined, &apos;unknown-ness&apos; is a relative concept: a word that is known to one system may be unknown to another system.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "4">Our research is motivated by the problems that we have experienced in translating live closed captions: live captions are produced under tight time constraints and contain many unknown words.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "5">Typically, the caption transcriber has a five second window to transcribe the broadcast dialogue.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "6">Because of the live nature of the broadcast, there is no opportunity to post-edit the transcript in any way.</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "7">Although motivated by our specific requirements, the unknown word categorizer would benefit any NLP system that encounters unknown words of differing categories.</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "8">Some immediately obvious domains where unknown words are frequent include email messages, internet chat rooms, data typed in by call centre operators, etc. To deal with these issues we propose a multi-component architecture where individual components specialize in identifying one particular type of 173 unknown word.</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "9">For example, the misspelling identifier will specialize in identifying misspellings, the abbreviation component will specialize in identifying abbreviations, etc. Each component will return a confidence measure of the reliability of its prediction, c.f.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "10">(Elworthy, 1998).</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "11">The results from each component are evaluated to determine the final category of the word.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "12">There are several advantages to this approach.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "13">Firstly, the system can take advantage of existing research.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "14">For example, the name recognition module can make use of the considerable research that exists on name recognition, e.g.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "15">(McDonald, 1996), (Mani et al., 1996).</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "16">Secondly, individual components can be replaced when improved models are available, without affecting other parts of the system.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "17">Thirdly, this approach is compatible with incorporating multiple components of the same type to improve performance (cf.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "18">(van Halteren et al., 1998) who found that combining the results of several part of speech taggers increased performance).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="The Current System. " number = "3">
</PAPER>
