<COMMUNITY>
<S sid ="80" ssid = "1">In order to see whether combination of the component tuggers is likely to lead to improvements of tagging quality, we first examine the results of the individual taggers when applied to Tune.</S><S sid ="89" ssid = "10">We accept that we are measuring quality in relation to a specific tagging</S>
<S sid ="97" ssid = "18">5 The most straightforward selection method is an n-way vote.</S>
<S sid ="100" ssid = "21">The most democratic option is to give each tagger one vote (Majority).</S>
<S sid ="101" ssid = "22">However, it appears more useful to give more weight to taggers which have proved their quality.</S>
<S sid ="102" ssid = "23">This can be general quality, e.g. each tagger votes its overall precision (TotPrecision), or quality in relation to the current situation, e.g. each tagger votes its precision on the suggested tag (Tag- Precision).</S>
<S sid ="103" ssid = "24">The information about each tagger&apos;s quality is derived from an inspection of its results on Tune.</S>
<S sid ="107" ssid = "28">Table 2: Accuracy of individual taggers and combination methods.</S>
<S sid ="109" ssid = "52">Each classi.er votes for its classi.cation and every pair of classi.ers votes for the sense that is most likely given the joint classi.cation.</S> 
<S sid ="116" ssid = "37">A next step is to examine them in pairs.</S><S sid ="117" ssid = "38">We can investigate all situations where one tagger suggests T1 and the other T2 and estimate the probability that in this situation the tag should actually be Tx.</S>
<S sid ="117" ssid = "38">We can investigate all situations where one tagger suggests T1 and the other T2 and estimate the probability that in this situation the tag should actually be Tx.</S>
<S sid ="118" ssid = "39">When combining the taggers, every tagger pair is taken in turn and allowed to vote (with the probability described above) for each possible tag, i.e. not just the ones suggested by the component taggers.</S>
S sid ="124" ssid = "45">When used on Test, the pairwise voting strategy (TagPair) clearly outperforms the other voting strategies, 8 but does not yet approach the level where all tying majority votes are handled correctly (98.31%).</S>
</COMMUNITY>