<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">We introduce the novel problem of automatic related work summarization.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">Givenmultiple articles (e.g., conference/journalpapers) as input, a related work sum-marization system creates a topic-biasedsummary of related work specific to thetarget paper.</S>
		<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">Our prototype Related WorkSummarization system, ReWoS, takes inset of keywords arranged in a hierarchicalfashion that describes a target paper’s topics, to drive the creation of an extractivesummary using two different strategies forlocating appropriate sentences for generaltopics as well as detailed ones.</S>
		<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">Our initialresults show an improvement over genericmulti-document summarization baselinesin a human evaluation.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">In many fields, a scholar needs to show an understanding of the context of his problem and relatehis work to prior community knowledge.</S>
			<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">A related work section is often the vehicle for this purpose; it contextualizes the scholar’s contributionsand helps readers understand the critical aspectsof the previous works that current work addresses.Creating such a summary requires the author toposition his own work within the contextual research to showcase the advantages of his method.</S>
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">We envision an NLP application that assists increating a related work summary.</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">We propose thisrelated work summarization task as a challengeto the automatic summarization community.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">Inits full form, it is a topic-biased, multi-document summarization problem that takes as input a target scientific document for which a related worksection needs to be drafted.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">The output goal is tocreate a related work section that finds the relevantrelated works and contextually describes them inrelationship to the scientific document at hand.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">We dissect the full challenge as bringing together work of disparate interests; 1) in findingrelevant documents; 2) in identifying the salientaspects of these documents in relation to the current work worth summarizing; and 3) in generating the final topic-biased summary.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">While it isclear that current NLP technology does not let usbuild a complete solution for this task, we believethat tackling the individual components will helpbring us towards an eventual solution.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">In fact, existing works in the NLP and recommendation systems communities have alreadybegun work that fits towards the completion ofthe first two tasks.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">Citation prediction (Nallapatiet al., 2008) is a growing research area that hasaimed both at predicting citation growth over timewithin a community and at individual paper citation patterns.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">This year, an automatic keyphraseextraction task from scientific articles was firstfielded in SemEval2, partially addressing Task11.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">Also, automatic survey generation (Mohammad et al., 2009) is becoming a growing fieldwithin the summarization community.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">However,to date, we have not yet seen any work that examines topic-biased summarization of multiple scientific articles.</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">For these reasons, we focus onTask 3 here – the creation of a related work section, given a structured input of the topics for summary..</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">The remaining contributions of our paper 1http://semeval2.fbk.eu/semeval2.php 427 consists of work towards this goal:• We conduct a study of the argumentative patterns used in related work sections, to describe theplausible summarization tactics for their creationin Section 3.• We describe our approach to generate an extractive related work summary given an input topic hierarchy tree, using two separate strategies to differentiate between summarizing shallow internalnodes from deep detailed leaf nodes of the topictree in Section 4.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Related Work. " number = "2">
</PAPER>
