<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">A formal treatment of typed feature structures(TFSs) is developed to augment TFSs, so that negative descriptions of them can be treated.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">Negative descriptions of TFSs can make linguistic descriptionscompact and thus easy to understand.</S>
		<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">Negative descriptions can be classified into three primitive negative descriptions: (1) negations of type symbols, (2) negations of feature existences, and (3) negations of feature-address value agreements.</S>
		<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">The formalizationproposed in this paper is based on AitKaci&amp;apos;s complex terms.</S>
		<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">The first description is treated by extending type symbol lattices to include complement typesymbols.</S>
		<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">The second and third are treated by augmenting terns structures with structures representingthese negations.</S>
		<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">Algorithms for augmented-WS unification have been developed using graph unification,and programs using these algorithms have been written in Common Lisp.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">In unification-based or information-based linguisticframeworks, the most important objects are struc tures called &amp;apos;feature structures&amp;apos; (FSs), which are usedto describe linguistic objects and phenomena.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">A fea ture structure is either atomic or complex: an atomic FS is denoted by an atomic symbol; a complex FS consists of a set of feature-value pairs each of which describes an aspect of an object.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">Partial information on an object is merged by applying the unification operation to FSs.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">Research on unification-based linguistic theories has been accompanied by research on FSs themselves.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">Several extensions on FSs or on feature descriptions and formal treatments of the extensions have been proposed.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">Disjunctive and negative descriptions on FSs help make the linguistic descriptions simple, compact, andthus easy to understand.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">For disjunctive feature descriptions, Kay[14] introduces them into FUG (Functional Unification Grammar) and gives the procedural semantics.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">Karttunen[111 also proposes proce dural treatments of disjunctions in conjunction with relatively simple negations.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">Rounds and Kasper[19, 13] propose a logic-based formalism—feature logic—which uses automata to model FSs and can treat disjunctive feature descriptions, and they obtain impor tant results.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">For negative descriptions of FSs, one of the mostfundamental properties of FSs, the partiality of in formation they carry, makes its insufficient to adopt relatively simple treatments.</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">Classical interpretation of negation, for example, does not allow evaluation of negations to be freely interleaved with unification.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">Moshier and Rounds[171 propose a formal framework which treats negative feature descriptions on the basis of intuitionistic logic.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "20">However, their formalism has trouble treating double negations.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "21">Dawar[5] proposes a formal treatment based on three-valued logic.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "22">In order to treat feature domains of complex FSsand to treat taxonomic hierarchies of symbolic feature values, type (or sort) hierarchies have been in troduced, allowing definition of typed (or sorted) feature-structures (Ms).</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "23">A TI&amp;apos;S consists of a type symbol from a lattice and a set of feature-value pairs.</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "24">A TFS can be seen as a generalized concept of bothatomic and complex FSs.</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "25">Pollard and Sag[ I8) intro duce sorts into II PSG (Head-driven Phrase Structtire Grammar) and use sorted P.is to describe linguistic objects.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "26">AH-Kaci[ll proposes an algebraic framework usingthe sit-types and c-types, one of promising formalizations of 1TSs, based on lattice theory.</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "27">This formalization was originally aimed at formalizing and in tegrating various kinds of knowledge representation frameworks in Al. In this approach, types are defined as equivalence classes of complex term structures.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "28">Asubsumption relation is defined on these term structures.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "29">The join and meet operations on them correspond to the generalization and an opera tions on TFSs, respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "30">This approach essentially adopts &amp;apos;type-as-set&amp;apos; semantics.</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "31">Subtype relationships on type correspond to subsumption relationships on denotations of types.</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "32">Based on this frau a&amp;apos; work, an extension to Prolog,, LOGIN (2], has been developed.</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "33">Smolka[20] proposes a feature logic with subsoils.In this approach, negative descriptions can be decoin posed into three kinds of primitive negations, namely, negations of sorts or complement sorts which denotethe complements of sets that positive counterparts de note, negations of feature existences, and negationsof feature-address agreement or feature-address dis agreement.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "34">Smolka extends feature descriptions buta feature-structure interpretation of an extended de scription does not include negative in fort nation and corresponds to a simple TI&amp;apos;S.Some WS-based natural language processing systems have been developed[7, 24, 12, 15, 8, 22].</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "35">Car penter and Pollard [4] propose an interface to build type lattices.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "36">Formalizations of extended FSs and of extended feature-descriptions, described above, are classified into two classes: (1) extensions of FSs themselves, and (2) extensions not of Pis themselves hut of feature-descriptions.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "37">Previous attempts to introducetype hierarchies fall into the former class while previous treatments of disjunctive and negative descrip tions mainly fall into the latter.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "38">Acres us COLINGt92, NANTES, 2328 Am-Yr 1992 380 PROC.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "39">OF COLING92, NANTES, AuG, 2328, 1992 This paper proposes an extension to Aithaci&amp;apos;sV&amp;apos; type that incorporates three kinds of the primitive negative descriptions described below into the 0-type.</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "40">AitKaci&amp;apos;s 0-type formalization uses ter in structures.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "41">In this paper, both these type structures and the type symbol lattice on which term structures are definedare extended to treat negative descriptions.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "42">Nega tions of type symbols are treated by extending type symbol lattices, and negations of feature existwicesand feature-address disagreements are treated by ex tending term structures.</S>
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "43">This extension can be seen as intuitionistic.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "44">The extension is classified into class (1) above.Based on this paper&apos;s formalization, unification al gorithms have been developed using graph unificationtechniques[23, 16].</S>
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "45">Programs based on these algo rithms have been implemented in Common Lisp.</S>
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "46">&lt;/bodyText&gt; &lt;sectionHeader confidence=&quot;0.650502&quot; genericHeader=&quot;method&quot;&gt;</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Requirements of Negative. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "1">&lt;/sectionHeader&gt; &lt;subsectionHeader confidence=&quot;0.434954&quot;&gt; Descriptions of TFSs &lt;/subsectionHeader&gt; &lt;bodyText confidence=&quot;0.971192533333333&quot;&gt;In describing linguistic information using (typed) feature structures, negative descriptions make the description compact, intuitive, and hence easy to understand.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "2">For example, we want to describe the grammatical agreement for an English verb, say &amp;amp;quot;eat&amp;amp;quot;, nat urally as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "3">syn[ ( agreement igr{ t; number s person 3rd -\ This description specifies compactly and directly that it is not the case that the person attribute is third and that the number attribute is singular.</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "4">If we could not use such complex negative descriptions, wewould write it using disjunctive descriptions with sim ple complement types as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "5">&lt;/bodyText&gt; &lt;equation confidence=&quot;0.674182333333333&quot;&gt; isyn( agreement up{ person --,3rd] 1 syn( agreement up{ number I ] Or &lt;/equation&gt; &lt;bodyText confidence=&quot;0.998926764705882&quot;&gt; {syn1 agreement apt person 1st]] syn( agreement nut person 2nd] ] syn( agreement awl number pil ] In this case, (1) is easier to understand than (2) or (3).In the above case, we can describe the informa tion because the complex negative descriptions can be transformed into the disjunction of simple negativedescriptions (with an almost, same intended mean ing) and because both person and number features take their values from {1st, 2nd, 3rd) and Isg,p1).However, it is not always the case that such transfor mations are possible and that feature takes its value from a finite set.Let us consider more complicated cases using dif ference lists expressed using feature structures.1 The empty list of categories is represented as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "6">&lt;/bodyText&gt; &lt;equation confidence=&quot;0.976748&quot;&gt; (Hist{ in X1 : list] OW X1 (4) &lt;/equation&gt; &lt;bodyText confidence=&quot;0.999914857142857&quot;&gt; In the above example, the tag symbol, X1 shows that features in and out must take the same value.</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "7">&amp;apos;In 11PSG and JPSG (Japanese Phrase StructureGrammar), a difference fist is very convenient for express ing subcat and stash feature values.</S>
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "8">How can only non-emptiness be expressed&amp;apos;?</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "9">Iii isis impossible using complement, type symbols or dis junctions because we Call consider the set of all finite length lists whose elements cant be taken from infinite sets.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "10">Direct or indirect extension of feature structures is required.So far, we have discussed the requirenient of nega tive descriptions of type symbols and of feature-valueagreements front the viewpoint cif capability of describing linguistic information.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "11">There are other ad vantages of allowing negative descriptions.</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "12">Consider,for example, debugging processes of grammatical descriptions by parsing sample sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "13">We may ob tain unexpected results such as a TES with an ittype symbol, a &amp;apos;IFS with an unexpected fea ture value agreement and so on.</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "14">In such situations, negative descriptions can be useful tools for detecting their reasons.</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "15">&amp;apos;lb make linguistic descriptions compact and thuseasy to understand, to treat natural language efficiently, and to detect error reasons rapidly, it is necessary to develop formalizations and methods of treat.</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "16">Mg negative descriptions.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Formal Treatment of Negative. " number = "3">
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "1">Descriptions of TFSs As stated earlier, a typed feature structure (TI&amp;apos;S) consists of a type symbol and a set of feature-value pairs.</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "2">l&amp;apos;hus, descriptions of TF,Ss are classified into descriptions of TFSs having:(I) a certain type symbol (or having a subtype sym bol of it certain type symbol), (2) a feature, and (3) two feature-address values that agree.</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "3">A TFS can be described by using conjunctions anddisjunctions of such kinds of descriptions.</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "4">A conjunctive and disjunctive TFS can be formalized as Alt aci&amp;apos;s 0-type and e-type, respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "5">&amp;apos;that is, a 0-type, which has a complex term structure called a 0-term as its syntax, represents a conjunction of such kinds of descriptions or a conjunctive typed feature structure, and an n-type is a maximal set of 0-types representing the disjunction of them.</S>
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "6">Negative counterparts of these descriptions are classified nito descriptions of TFSs: (1&amp;apos;) not having a certain type symbol (or having a type symbol which is not subsumed by a certain type symbol), (2&amp;apos;) not having it certain feature, and (3&amp;apos;) having two feature-address values that do not agree.Ily incorporating structures representing such neg ative descriptions into a 0-term, a &amp;apos;[&amp;apos;F&amp;apos;S with the neg..</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "7">ative descriptions can be formalized.</S>
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "8">Such it term iscalled an augmented thterm and a type with an aug mented 0-term as its syntax is called an augmented0-type.</S>
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "9">From augmented 0-terms, an augmented ( term can be constructed in the same manner that an e- term is constructed from 0-terms.</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "10">Next, augmented 0,-terms and 0-types are defined.</S>
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "11">&amp;apos;Fenn structures are first augmented with structures representing in features and disagreement of feature address values.</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "12">Then, type symbol lattices are extended to include complement type symbols as suggested in [1].</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "13">(1) Acres DE COLING92, NAnn ES, 2328 min&amp;apos; 1992 3 8 1 Pxoc.</S>
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "14">OF COLING92, NANTES, AUG. 2328, 1992 3.1 Typed Feature Structures as.</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "15">Augmented g&amp;apos;TypesIn order to define complex term structures, a signa ture is used to specify their vocabulary.</S>
			<S sid ="78" ssid = "16">It serves as the interface between their syntax and semantics.</S>
			<S sid ="79" ssid = "17">A signature is formally defined as follows, Definition 1 A signature is a quadruple (7, &amp;lt;7 V) consisting of: 1.</S>
			<S sid ="80" ssid = "18">a set T of type symbols containing T and 2.</S>
			<S sid ="81" ssid = "19">a partial order &amp;lt;7 on T such that (a) I. is the least and T is the greatest element, and (b) every pair of type symbols a, b E 7 have a least upper bound or join, which is denoted by a VT b and a greatest lower bound or meet, which is denoted by a AT b, 3.</S>
			<S sid ="82" ssid = "20">a set T of feature symbols, and 4.</S>
			<S sid ="83" ssid = "21">a set V of tag symbols where T, F and V are pairwise disjoint.</S>
			<S sid ="84" ssid = "22">A simple &amp;apos;type-as-set&amp;apos; semantics is adopted for these objects, That is, a type symbol in T denotes a set of objects in an interpretation, Here, T and .1 denote the sets called the universe, written as U, and the empty set 0, respectively.</S>
			<S sid ="85" ssid = "23">Another element a denotes a nonempty subset of U, written as [a].The partial order &amp;lt;T denotes the subsumption rela tion between these sets; for any type symbols a, b, and c, 1.</S>
			<S sid ="86" ssid = "24">a &amp;lt;7 b if and only if[a C [b], 2.</S>
			<S sid ="87" ssid = "25">a VT b = c if and only if [a] U [b] = [cil, and 3.</S>
			<S sid ="88" ssid = "26">a AT b = c if and only if lain 114 = A feature symbol denotes a function from a subset of U to U. A feature path is a finite string of feature symbols and denotes the function obtained by the composition of the functions that the feature symbols denote.</S>
			<S sid ="89" ssid = "27">A term is defined from a signature.</S>
			<S sid ="90" ssid = "28">First, a term domain is defined as a skeleton built from feature symbols.</S>
			<S sid ="91" ssid = "29">Definition 2 A term domain A on T is a set of finite strings of feature symbols in (including the empty string e) such that 1.</S>
			<S sid ="92" ssid = "30">A is prefix-closed: Vp, q E I&amp;apos;, if p • g E A, then p E A; and 2.</S>
			<S sid ="93" ssid = "31">A is finitely branching: if p E A, then If E E A} is finite where is the string concatenation operator.</S>
			<S sid ="94" ssid = "32">An element of a term domain is called a feature address or a feature path.</S>
			<S sid ="95" ssid = "33">By definition, the empty string c must belong to all term domains and is called the root address.</S>
			<S sid ="96" ssid = "34">A term domain is represented by a rooted directed graph within which each arc has a feature symbol as its label.</S>
			<S sid ="97" ssid = "35">A subdomain of a term domain, corresponding to a subgraph, is defined as follows, Definition 3 Given a term domain A and a feature address p E A, the subdomain of A at p is defined to be the term domain A/p := {P&amp;apos; I P • P&amp;apos; E A}.</S>
			<S sid ="98" ssid = "36">The set of all subdomains of A is denoted by Subdom(A).Next, flesh is put on the term structure&amp;apos;s skele ton as defined as a term domain by assigning several kinds of objects to each feature address.</S>
			<S sid ="99" ssid = "37">AltKaci&amp;apos;s term structure, the basis of the tit-type, is defined by assigning a type symbol and a tag symbol to each feature address as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="100" ssid = "38">Definition 4 A term is a triple (Ar, v) where A is a term domain on .F, r is a type symbol function from .7 to T such that r(T* — A) = IT), and v is a tag symbol function from A to V. Given a tag symbol function v, Addl.., denotes the function from a tag symbol to the set of addresses: Addr,(X) := Al v(p) = X}.</S>
			<S sid ="101" ssid = "39">(5) In order to treat negations of feature existences andfeature-address value disagreement, the term structure defined above is augmented by assigning addi tional objects, a set of inhibited features and a set of disagreement tag symbols, to each feature address.</S>
			<S sid ="102" ssid = "40">Definition 5 An augmented term is a quintuple (A, r, v, rn, x) where A is a term domain on r is a type symbol function from ,F* to T such that r(T* — A) _-= {T), v is a tag symbol function from A to V, tO is an inhibited feature function front ,T* to 2Y such that 0(p) is finite for any p E A and(b(TI* — A) = 10), and x is a disagreement tag sym bol function from .T* to 2v such that x(p) is finite for any p E A and x(T* — A) =The inhibited feature function specifies which fea tures cannot exist at a given address.</S>
			<S sid ="103" ssid = "41">There is thus inconsistency if there is an address p in A such that tb(P)n{f E.FIP•f EA} 0.</S>
			<S sid ="104" ssid = "42">(6) The disagreement tag symbol function x specifies,for a given address, substructures with which its ar gument disagrees.</S>
			<S sid ="105" ssid = "43">There is thus inconsistency if there is an address p in A such that v(P) E X(P).</S>
			<S sid ="106" ssid = "44">(7) The disagreement address function Disagr5 from A to 2F., based on v and x, takes an address as its argument, and gives the set of addresses with whichthe argument address must disagree, called the dis agreement address set and defined as: Disagr„,x(p) U Addr„(X).</S>
			<S sid ="107" ssid = "45">(8) XEx(p) Augmented terms are hereafter referred to simply as terms unless stated otherwise.</S>
			<S sid ="108" ssid = "46">Definition 6 Given a term = (A, r, v, rP, x) and a feature address p in A, the subterin of t at the address p is the term tip = (A/ p,r/p,v/p, (pip, x/p) where r/p : T* v/p : A/p V, 5b/p : 2, and — 2v are defined by (r/p)(g) := r(p • q), (9a) (v/P)(q) v(P 4), (9b) (44P)(q) := 56(p • 9), (Sc) (WOW := X(P • 9).</S>
			<S sid ="109" ssid = "47">(9d)For a term t = (A, r, 0, X), a type symbol a (sim ilarly, a tag symbol or a term V) is said to occur in t if there is a feature address p in A such that r(p) = a (similarly, v(p) = X or X C x(p), or th = I&amp;apos;).</S>
			<S sid ="110" ssid = "48">A term I = (A, r, v, x) is said to be regular if the set of all subtertns of t, Subterm(t) := {Ur I p E A), is finite.</S>
			<S sid ="111" ssid = "49">Hereafter, we will consider only regular terms.</S>
			<S sid ="112" ssid = "50">In a regular term, only finite numbers of type symbols and tag symbols occur.</S>
			<S sid ="113" ssid = "51">&amp;apos;For any set S, 2s denotes the set of subsets of S. ACIE.S DE COLING92, NAMES, 2328 Aoirr 1992 382 PROC.</S>
			<S sid ="114" ssid = "52">OF COLING92, NArrres, Ann.</S>
			<S sid ="115" ssid = "53">2328, 1992 te.pty Xi : {} dlist in X2 : {first} {} : T { out X2 trsonemply [X3 : () : {} : dlist X4 : {} : {X6} : list In [first X5 : {) : {) out X6 : {) : {X4} : list Figure I: Examples of Augmented Terms in Matrix Notation Gmtall tnonempty Xl:{):{):dlist X3:{}:{):dlist in out X4:1):(X6) X2: {first): (I list . first Est X5:1):{} Figure 2: Examples of Augmented Terms in Directed Graph Notation In a term, any two feature addresses bearing thesame symbol are said to corefer.</S>
			<S sid ="116" ssid = "54">Thus, the corefer ence relation a of a term is a relation defined on A as the kernel of the tag function v; i.e., a := Ker(v) =00.</S>
			<S sid ="117" ssid = "55">here, a is an equivalence relation and a a class is called a coreference class.</S>
			<S sid ="118" ssid = "56">Definition 7 A term t is referentially consistent if the same subterm occurs at all feature addresses in a coreference class.If a term is referentially consistent, then by defini tion, for any pi, P2 E A, if v(pi) = v(p2) then, for all p such that pi • p E A, it follows that p2 • p E A andv(pi • p) = v(p2 • p).</S>
			<S sid ="119" ssid = "57">Therefore, if a term is referen tially consistent, a is a right-invariant equivalence or right-congruence on A. That is, for any pi, P2 E A, if pocp2 then (pi p)tc(P2 p) for any p such that PI P C A. Definition 8 A well-formed term (wft.)</S>
			<S sid ="120" ssid = "58">is a referentially-consistent regular term.</S>
			<S sid ="121" ssid = "59">The set of all well-formed terms is denoted by W.TT.A term can be represented in matrix notation.</S>
			<S sid ="122" ssid = "60">Ex amples of terms are shown in Figure 1.</S>
			<S sid ="123" ssid = "61">In this figure, T, dlist and list are type symbols, in, oat and firstare feature symbols, and Xl, X2, ... are tag sym bols.</S>
			<S sid ="124" ssid = "62">A matrix represents a set of feature-value pairspreceded by a tag symbol, followed by a set of inhib ited features and followed by a set of disagreement tag symbols.</S>
			<S sid ="125" ssid = "63">In the term 4„,,,ty, its subterms at in and atout corefer while i,,o„,„,p iy is a term in which its sub terms at in and at out should not corefer.</S>
			<S sid ="126" ssid = "64">The term lUnpmy should not have the feature address in • first while tnoflsmpCy has that address.</S>
			<S sid ="127" ssid = "65">A term can also be represented by directed graphs (DGs).</S>
			<S sid ="128" ssid = "66">1mjiy and 1,,,„,„,pi y in Figure I are shown as DGs in Figure 2.</S>
			<S sid ="129" ssid = "67">The set 14./Y7&amp;apos; of well-formed terms includes many terms that have the same type symbol function, the same coreference relations, the same inhibited featurefunction, and the same disagreement address func tion but different tag symbol functions.</S>
			<S sid ="130" ssid = "68">These terms have the same information and can describe the same linguistic object or the same linguistic phenomena.These terms construct equivalence classes by renarn nig tag symbols in a certain manner.</S>
			<S sid ="131" ssid = "69">Definition 9 Two terms ti = , 01A , xi) and 12 = (A2, r2, v2,02, X2) are alphabetical variants of each other if and only if 1.</S>
			<S sid ="132" ssid = "70">Al = A2,.</S>
			<S sid ="133" ssid = "71">2.</S>
			<S sid ="134" ssid = "72">Ker(m) = Ker(v2),.</S>
			<S sid ="135" ssid = "73">3.</S>
			<S sid ="136" ssid = "74">r = r2r 5.</S>
			<S sid ="137" ssid = "75">Disagr„,x,.</S>
			<S sid ="138" ssid = "76">This is written as ti 012.</S>
			<S sid ="139" ssid = "77">According to &amp;apos;type-as-set&amp;apos; semantics, the symbols T and _1 denote, respectively, the least informative type- -the whole universe U and the overdefined or inconsistency type—the empty set (6.</S>
			<S sid ="140" ssid = "78">Therefore, aterm containing A_ should be interpreted as inconsistent.</S>
			<S sid ="141" ssid = "79">Such an inconsistency is called a type inconsis tency.</S>
			<S sid ="142" ssid = "80">To treat, such inconsistency, a relation 41 on 311.1.TY is defined as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="143" ssid = "81">Definition 10 For any two terms (1, 12 G W_TT, ti1,11 12 if and only if I occurs in both ti and 12.</S>
			<S sid ="144" ssid = "82">There are other kinds of inconsistency as mentioned earlier.</S>
			<S sid ="145" ssid = "83">If a term contains an address p such that tjt(p)D {J. p f E it is inconsistent because it [mans that there are features that should not exist at the address.</S>
			<S sid ="146" ssid = "84">Such an inconsistency is called a feature inconsistency.</S>
			<S sid ="147" ssid = "85">In addition, if a term contains an address p such that v(p) E x(p), it is inconsistent because it means that the subterm at p does not agree with itself.</S>
			<S sid ="148" ssid = "86">Such an inconsistency is called a tag inconsistency.</S>
			<S sid ="149" ssid = "87">lien cc, the three kinds of inconsistency are treatedintegratedly by a relation ff on W.FT defined as fol lows.</S>
			<S sid ="150" ssid = "88">Definition 11 For any two terms 1i, 12 E WTT, 11 1,1 12 if and only if each of them contains at least one address p such that 1.</S>
			<S sid ="151" ssid = "89">TOO.</S>
			<S sid ="152" ssid = "90">2.</S>
			<S sid ="153" ssid = "91">0(p)(1{,/ eYlpICA) (4, or 3.</S>
			<S sid ="154" ssid = "92">1-)(P) C X(1)).</S>
			<S sid ="155" ssid = "93">Clearly, if I occurs in a term, it also occurs in allterms in its a-class.</S>
			<S sid ="156" ssid = "94">This is also true for feature incon sistency and tag inconsistency.</S>
			<S sid ="157" ssid = "95">Hence, the relations aand 1,1 are such that their [&amp;apos;Mon becomes an equiv alence relation.</S>
			<S sid ="158" ssid = "96">Thus, we can defined the augmented 0-types as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="159" ssid = "97">Definition 12 An augmented tp-type (or 1,G-type for short) [1] is an element of the quotient set sit := 34)4iritaicTiC structures of augmented 8/-types will becalled augmented 0-terms.</S>
			<S sid ="160" ssid = "98">An augmented typed feature-structure can be formalized as an augmented 1Pt3Te•The set of type symbols T lots the partial order •(7 which denotes a subsnmption relation between the set denoted by type symbols.</S>
			<S sid ="161" ssid = "99">The partial ordering on 7- can be extended to augmented 0-terms and types.</S>
			<S sid ="162" ssid = "100">The subsumption orders on W.TT and on sP are defined as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="163" ssid = "101">T] out — — — X6:0:1X41 fist ACTES DE COLING92, NiorrEs, 2328 Aoirr 1992 383 PRoc.</S>
			<S sid ="164" ssid = "102">OF COLING92, NastrEs, AUG. 2328, 1992 Definition 13 Let tt = (AI, rt, v1,01, xi) and 12 =(A2,12,v2,562, X2) be WFTs.</S>
			<S sid ="165" ssid = "103">ti is said to be sub sumed by t2, written tt &amp;lt; 12, if and only if either ti 1 or 1.</S>
			<S sid ="166" ssid = "104">A2 C At, 2.</S>
			<S sid ="167" ssid = "105">Ker(u2) C Ker(vi),.</S>
			<S sid ="168" ssid = "106">3.</S>
			<S sid ="169" ssid = "107">Vp E P TI(P) r2(P),.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Vp E P462(P) C Ot(P), and. " number = "4">
			<S sid ="170" ssid = "1">The subsumption order on IP are defined by [Ii] &amp;lt; [12] if ti &amp;lt;12 is well-defined.Lattice operations on P can be defined to be com patible with the above subsumption order relation as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="171" ssid = "2">Theorem 1 If (7;&amp;lt;r) is a lattice, then so is IP.Proof.</S>
			<S sid ="172" ssid = "3">This theorem can be proved in a very simi lar manner to the counterpart for AltKaci&amp;apos;s 0-terms.</S>
			<S sid ="173" ssid = "4">Therefore, instead of providing the proof in detail, only the definitions of the least upper bounds— or joins—and greatest lower bounds—or meets—are provided below.</S>
			<S sid ="174" ssid = "5">Let ti = (A1,T1,4u,01,X1) and 12 - (412, 1&amp;apos;29 2,21 021 X2) be WFTs.</S>
			<S sid ="175" ssid = "6">First, the join of ti and 12, 13 = ti V l2 is defined as follows: A3 = n A2 03 : A30 V such that Ker(v3) = n and Vp Er3(p) = OAP) = X3(P) = 4(p) ( q )1 przpq, i = 1,21, (11d) and X4(P) = Uly4(9) qtzgr, r (Disagr„,„(p) UDisagr,,(p)))(11e) V 1,,0„„,„‘„ X7 : : {} : dlist in X8 : {} : () : list 1 out X9 {} : () : list J A X10 : : 1) : dlist X11 : (first) : (X11) list = [151 [first X12 : {) : {) : T ] out X11 Figure 3: Examples of Join and Meet of Augmented 0-Terms ° 41&amp;amp;quot;V&amp;amp;quot;, for is = 0, K141 = u {(Pi P, P2 • P) I Pi On-111121, for n &amp;gt; 1 and a:f&amp;amp;quot;u°&amp;apos; is the reflexive extension of Ki from A; to Ai U A2 for i = 1, 2.The conditions (11a11e) define a meet, that col lapses to _L whenever conditions (11cTle) produce some address p such that type inconsistency, feature inconsistency, or tag inconsistency occurs at p. The V is a join operation and A is a meet operationwhich are compatible with the subsumption order de fined in Definition 13.Examples of join and meet operations on aug mented 03-terms are shown in Figure 3.</S>
			<S sid ="176" ssid = "7">The join and meet operations on augmented 0-types correspond to the generalization and unification operations on TFSs.Nit-Kaci defines an c-type as a maximal set of 0types.</S>
			<S sid ="177" ssid = "8">It is also possible to &amp;lt;lave an augmented ( type as a maximal set of augmented 1P-types in thesame manlier, making disjunctive and negative de scriptions possible.</S>
			<S sid ="178" ssid = "9">3.2 Type Symbol Lattice Extension to.</S>
			<S sid ="179" ssid = "10">Include Complement Type SymbolsTreating a negative description of a given type sym bol, say a, requires a type symbol b such that b ha,sonly information that unification of it with is yields in consistency, or such that a VT h = T and aAr b = I. Such a symbol is called a complement type symbol of a and written as a&amp;apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="180" ssid = "11">If a given type symbol lattice (T; &amp;lt;r) is a Boolean lattice, that is, a complemented3 distributive lattice, we do not need to do anything.</S>
			<S sid ="181" ssid = "12">Otherwise, we must extend the lattice to include the complements of the type symbols contained in the given lattice.</S>
			<S sid ="182" ssid = "13">For a finite type symbol lattice T, for example, a Boolean lattice 7&amp;apos; can be constructed as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="183" ssid = "14">Let A : fat, , aN1 be the set of atoms of 7, that is, type symbols which cover 1.4 If there arenon-atomic type symbols which cover only one sym bol, for each such symbol a, a new atom is added &amp;apos;A lattice is called complemented if its all elements have complements.[3] &amp;apos;a is said to cover 13 if b &amp;lt;7 a and b &amp;lt;7 c &amp;lt;-r a implies c = b. r1(p) VT T2(P), (10c) 01(P) n 02(0, and (10d) -{u3(q) I q E (Disagr„,,,(p) (Oil.</S>
			<S sid ="184" ssid = "15">(10e) Next, the meet of ti and 13, 14= A 12 = (A4,14, V4 /59, X4), is defined as follows: P4 = At*1&amp;apos;(11a) : V such that Ker(v4) = kit (11b) and Vp 74(p) = Vrfri(q) I ptcpq, i = 1,21,(11c) U At&amp;amp;quot;1&amp;apos; nc--0 / Li A2 for = 0, co ,14) = U&amp;apos;1&amp;amp;quot;1&amp;apos; n=0 where U IP E I ptcHq q E for n &amp;gt; 1, Acne DE COLING92, NANTES, 2328 main.</S>
			<S sid ="185" ssid = "16">1992 384 PROC.</S>
			<S sid ="186" ssid = "17">or COLING92, NANres, Auo.</S>
			<S sid ="187" ssid = "18">2328, 1992 node structure 111=111111110M11= rinIMINI/a set o arc structures 11=121111111= IEZZEINIMINI=ED 011=1111111111=12=11M011■1 MIIIIIIIIIMIEMIE 1/4=11•1111ELIMMTIM 111121MIMICIIMEDIEED Figure 4: Data Structures Function Unify(nodel , nodc2) begin node] := Dereference(nodel); riode2 :-= Dereference(ruxle2); if node] = node then return( node 1); nodel . forward := node2 ; node2.tsymbol := node] .tsurnbol AT node2.tsymbol; if node2.tsymbol = _I_ then return(i) node2.ileatures node] .ifeatures U node2 :ilea tures ; if node2.ifeaturesn { arc. feature I arc E node] .arcs U node .nrcs) 0 then returri(1.); node2.dnodes := node!</S>
			<S sid ="188" ssid = "19">.dnodes U node2.dnodes; if {nodel , node2} fl node2.dnodes tt then rettirn(..t.); arcpairs := Shared _Arc_Pairs(nodel , node2); for (arc] , arc2) in °repairs do begin value := Unify(orcl :value, arc2.value); if value -= then return(±); end; arcs := Coroplement_Ares(node I , node!]); node!]</S>
			<S sid ="189" ssid = "20">.arcs ::= arcs U node . arcs; ovturn(node2); end Figure 5: A Destructive Graph Unification Functionso that a covers an additional type symbol.</S>
			<S sid ="190" ssid = "21">The ex tended lattice T&amp;apos; is the set of subsets of A with set inclusion ordering.</S>
			<S sid ="191" ssid = "22">An element failiE/ E T&amp;apos; denotes U,51Ea1.</S>
			<S sid ="192" ssid = "23">The join and meet operations on arethe set-union and set-intersection operations, respec tively.</S>
			<S sid ="193" ssid = "24">The complement of an element fadiej iii T&amp;apos; is the set-complement of it with respect to A, that is, EAla taibc/}• 4 Implementation of Augmented TFS.</S>
			<S sid ="194" ssid = "25">Unification The unification operation for augmented tk-terms or augmented TFSs has been implemented using graphunification techniques.</S>
			<S sid ="195" ssid = "26">A term structure is repre sented as a directed graph by assigning a graph nodeto each K-class as in Figure 2.</S>
			<S sid ="196" ssid = "27">The unification oper ation for such DGs corresponds to a graph merging operation.</S>
			<S sid ="197" ssid = "28">This takes two DGs and merges hi-classes of the same feature-address into a K-class.</S>
			<S sid ="198" ssid = "29">In a destructive graph unification method, winch is very simple, such a graph is represented by the data structures in Figure 4.</S>
			<S sid ="199" ssid = "30">A node structure consists of five fields: tsymbol for a type symbol, arcs for a set of feature-value pairs, gestures for a set of inhibitedfeatures, dnodes for a set of disagreement nodes- i.e., disagreement K-classes, and forward.</S>
			<S sid ="200" ssid = "31">The field forward is used for the Union-Find algorithm[9] to calculate unions of K-classes in the same manner as Duct&amp;apos;s algorithm[10].</S>
			<S sid ="201" ssid = "32">By traversing two DGs&amp;apos; nodeswith the same feature-address simultaneously, calcu lating the union of their K-classes, and copying arcs, their unification can be calculated as in Figure 5.</S>
			<S sid ="202" ssid = "33">The function Unify takes two input nodes and puts them in a K.-class by letting one input be the forward field values.</S>
			<S sid ="203" ssid = "34">The function then examines three kindsof inconsistency; namely, type inconsistency, feature inconsistency, and tag inconsistency.</S>
			<S sid ="204" ssid = "35">The func tion finally treats arcs in order to make the result graph right-congruent.</S>
			<S sid ="205" ssid = "36">For treating arcs, the function Unify assumes two functions, Shared_Arc_Pairs and Comylemeni_Arcs.</S>
			<S sid ="206" ssid = "37">The function Shared_Arc_Pairs takes two nodes as its inputs and gives a set of arc pairs each consisting of both inputs&amp;apos; arcs widi a shared feature.</S>
			<S sid ="207" ssid = "38">The function Complemenl_A re S also takes two nodes and gives a set of arcs whose features exist in the first node but not in the second.</S>
			<S sid ="208" ssid = "39">An inhibited feature function is implemented using the gestures field of nodes.</S>
			<S sid ="209" ssid = "40">When unification of two nodes results in a node with an arc with a feature in ifeatures, it yields I because of feature inconsistency.</S>
			<S sid ="210" ssid = "41">A disagreement tag symbol function is implemented using dnodes.</S>
			<S sid ="211" ssid = "42">Unification of two nodes which have each other in their dnodes yields 1 because of tag inconsistency.</S>
			<S sid ="212" ssid = "43">These computations require negligible additional computation.</S>
			<S sid ="213" ssid = "44">To simplify the explanation, the destructive version of graph unification is used above.</S>
			<S sid ="214" ssid = "45">Other versions based on more efficient graph unification methods such as Wroblewski&apos;s and Kogure&apos;s method [23, 16) have also been developed.</S>
			<S sid ="215" ssid = "46">Furthermore, it is easy to modify other graph unification inethods[21, 61 to allow augmented 1TSs.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusion. " number = "5">
			<S sid ="216" ssid = "1">This paper has proposed an augmentation of feature structures (FSs) which introduces negative in formation into FSs in unification-based formalisms.Unification-based linguistic formalisms use lbs to describe linguistic objects and phenomena.</S>
			<S sid ="217" ssid = "2">Because lin guistic information can be described compactly usingdisjunctive and negative descriptions, l&amp;apos;Ss and feature descriptions are required to treat such descrip tions.</S>
			<S sid ="218" ssid = "3">In this paper, FSs have been augmented, using a promising method of for AltKaci&amp;apos;s type, to allow three kinds of negative descriptions of them to be treated.In a formalization of typed feature structures, neg ative descriptions can be decomposed into three kinds of negations: negations of type symbols, negations of feature existences, and negations of feature-address value agreements.</S>
			<S sid ="219" ssid = "4">It is shown that the second andthird kinds can be treated by augmenting term struc tures to include structures representing such kinds of descriptions.</S>
			<S sid ="220" ssid = "5">Subsumption relations on augmented terms are defined.</S>
			<S sid ="221" ssid = "6">It is also shown that the first kind can be treated by extending type symbol lattices to include complement type symbols.&amp;apos;Die proposed formalization can provide efficient al AcrEs 05 COLING92, NANTES, 2328 °art 1992 3 8 5 PROC.</S>
			<S sid ="222" ssid = "7">OF COLING92, NANTES, AuG. 2328, 1992 gorithms for generalization and unification operationsas well as treat primitive negations.</S>
			<S sid ="223" ssid = "8">The formaliza tion can be integrated with logic-based frameworkssuch as [20] which can treat wider ranges of descrip tions but which do not have such efficient algorithms for these operations.</S>
			<S sid ="224" ssid = "9">Logic-based frameworks can be used to obtain the data structures for this paper&amp;apos;s formalization.Unification algorithms for augmented terms or augmented TFSs have been developed using graph uni fication techniques.</S>
			<S sid ="225" ssid = "10">Unification programs based on these algorithms have been developed in Common Lisp.The augmentation of TFSs makes linguistic de scriptions compact and easy to understand, In an HPSG-based grammar, for example, non-emptinessof a subcat or slash feature value can be easily de scribed by using feature-address value disagreement.Moreover, negative descriptions make debugging pro cesses of grammatical descriptions easier.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acknowledgments">
			<S sid ="226" ssid = "11">This research was performed in the VCAT project of the Takeuchi Research Group in NTT Basic Research Laboratories.</S>
			<S sid ="227" ssid = "12">The author would like to thank Ikuo Takeuchi, Akira Shimazu, Shozo Naito, Masahito Kawamori, Mikio Nakano, and other colleagues of the group for their encouragement and thought-provoking discussions.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
