<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">Text Segmentation Based On Similarity Between Words</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">This paper proposes a new indicator of text structure, called the lexical cohesion profile (LCP), which locates segment boundaries in a text.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">A text segment is a coherent scene; the words in a segment are linked together via lexical cohesion relations.</S>
    <S sid="3" ssid="3">LCP records mutual similarity of words in a sequence of text.</S>
    <S sid="4" ssid="4">The similarity of words, which represents their cohesiveness, is computed using a semantic network.</S>
    <S sid="5" ssid="5">Comparison with the text segments marked by a number of subjects shows that LCP closely correlates with the human judgments.</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="6">LCP may provide valuable information for resolving anaphora and ellipsis.</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="INTRODUCTION" number="1">
    <S sid="7" ssid="1">A text is not just a sequence of words, but it has coherent structure.</S>
    <S sid="8" ssid="2">The meaning of each word can not be determined until it is placed in the structure of the text.</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="3">Recognizing the structure of text is an essential task in text understanding, especially in resolving anaphora and ellipsis.</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="4">One of the constituents of the text structure is a text segment.</S>
    <S sid="11" ssid="5">A text segment, whether or not it is explicitly marked, as are sentences and paragraphs, is defined as a sequence of clauses or sentences that display local coherence.</S>
    <S sid="12" ssid="6">It resembles a scene in a movie, which describes the same objects in the same situation.</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="7">This paper proposes an indicator, called the lexical cohesion profile (LCP), which locates segment boundaries in a narrative text.</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="8">LCP is a record of lexical cohesiveness of words in a sequence of text.</S>
    <S sid="15" ssid="9">Lexical cohesiveness is defined as word similarity (Kozima and Furugori, 1993) computed by spreading activation on a semantic network.</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="10">Hills and valleys of LCP closely correlate with changing of segments.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="SEGMENTS AND COHERENCE" number="2">
    <S sid="17" ssid="1">Several methods to capture segment boundaries have been proposed in the studies of text structure.</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="2">For example, cue phrases play an important role in signaling segment changes.</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="3">(Grosz and Sidner, 1986) However, such clues are not directly based on coherence which forms the clauses or sentences into a segment.</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="4">Youmans (1991) proposed VMP (vocabulary management profile) as an indicator of segment boundaries.</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="5">VMP is a record of the number of new vocabulary terms introduced in an interval of text.</S>
    <S sid="22" ssid="6">However, VMP does not work well on a high-density text.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="7">The reason is that coherence of a segment should be determined not only by reiteration of words but also by lexical cohesion.</S>
    <S sid="24" ssid="8">Morris and Hirst (1991) used Roget's thesaurus to determine whether or not two words have lexical cohesion.</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="9">Their method can capture almost all the types of lexical cohesion, e.g. systematic and non-systematic semantic relation.</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="10">However it does not deal with strength of cohesiveness which suggests the degree of contribution to coherence of the segment.</S>
    <S sid="27" ssid="11">Kozima and Furugori (1993) defined lexical cohesiveness as semantic similarity between words, and proposed a method for measuring it.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="12">Similarity between words is computed by spreading activation on a semantic network which is systematically constructed from an English dictionary (LDOCE).</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="13">The similarity (TOD, w') E [0,1] between words to, w' is computed in the following way: (1) produce an activated pattern by activating the node w; (2) observe activity of the node w1 in the activated pattern.</S>
    <S sid="30" ssid="14">The following examples suggest the feature of the similarity cr: pet) = 0.133722 , hat) = 0.001784 , restaurant) = 0.175699 , restaurant) = 0.006260 .</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="15">The similarity a- depends on the significance s(w) E [0, 1], i.e. normalized information of the word w in West's corpus (1953).</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="16">For example: The following examples show the relationship between the word significance and the similarity:</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="LEXICAL COHESION PROFILE" number="3">
    <S sid="33" ssid="1">LCP of the text T = {w1,&#8226; &#8226; &#8226;, wN} is a sequence {c(Si),&#8226; &#8226; &#8226;, c(SN)} of lexical cohesiveness c(Si).</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="2">Si is the word list which can be seen through a fixedwidth window centered on the i-th word of T: LCP treats the text T as a word list without any punctuation or paragraph boundaries.</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="3">Lexical cohesiveness c(Si) of the word list Si is defined as follows: where a(P(Si), tv) is the activity value of the node w in the activated pattern P(S).</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="4">P(Si) is produced by activating each node w E Si with strength s(w)2/ s(w).</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="5">Figure 1 shows a sample pattern of {red, alcoholic, drink).</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="6">(Note that it has highly activated nodes like bottle and wine.)</S>
    <S sid="39" ssid="7">The definition of c(Si) above expresses that c(Si) represents semantic homogeneity of Si, since P(Si) represents the average meaning of w E Si.</S>
    <S sid="40" ssid="8">For example: c(&amp;quot;Molly saw a cat.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="9">It was her family pet.</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="10">She wished to keep a lion.&amp;quot; = 0.403239 (cohesive), c(&amp;quot;There is no one but me.</S>
    <S sid="43" ssid="11">Put on your clothes.</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="12">I can not walk more.&amp;quot; = 0.235462 (not cohesive).</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="LCP and Its Feature" number="4">
    <S sid="45" ssid="1">A graph of LCP, which plots c(Si) at the text position i, indicates changing of segments: As shown in Figure 2, the segment boundaries can be detected by the valleys (minimum points) of LCP.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="2">The LCP, shown in Figure 3, has large hills and valleys, and also meaningless noise.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="3">The graph is so complicated that one can not easily determine which valley should be considered as a segment boundary.</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="4">The shape of the window, which defines weight of words in it for pattern production, makes LCP smooth.</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="5">Experiments on several window shapes (e.g. triangle window, etc.) shows that Harming window is best for clarifying the macroscopic features of LCP.</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="6">The width of the window also has effect on the macroscopic features of LCP, especially on separability of segments.</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="7">Experiments on several window widths (A =5 &#8212; 60) reveals that the Hanning window of A =25 gives the best correlation between LCP and segments.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="VERIFICATION OF LCP" number="5">
    <S sid="52" ssid="1">This section inspects the correlation between LCP and segment boundaries perceived by the human judgments.</S>
    <S sid="53" ssid="2">The curve of Figure 4 shows the LCP of the simplified version of 0.Henry's &amp;quot;Springtime a la Carte&amp;quot; (Thornley, 1960).</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="3">The solid bars represent the histogram of segment boundaries reported by 16 subjects who read the text without paragraph structure.</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="4">It is clear that the valleys of the LCP correspond mostly to the dominant segment boundaries.</S>
    <S sid="56" ssid="5">For example, the clear valley at i = 110 exactly corresponds to the dominant segment boundary (and also to the paragraph boundary shown as a dotted line).</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="6">Note that LCP can detect segment changing of a text regardless of its paragraph structure.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="7">For example, i = 156 is a paragraph boundary, but neither a valley of the LCP nor a segment boundary; i = 236 is both a segment boundary and approximately a valley of the LCP, but not a paragraph boundary.</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="8">However, some valleys of the LCP do not exactly correspond to segment boundaries.</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="9">For example, the valley near i = 450 disagree with the segment boundary at i = 465.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="10">The reason is that lexical cohesion can not cover all aspect of coherence of a segment; all incoherent piece of text can be lexically cohesive.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="CONCLUSION" number="6">
    <S sid="62" ssid="1">This paper proposed LCP, all indicator of segment changing, which concentrates on lexical cohesion of a text. segment.</S>
    <S sid="63" ssid="2">The experiment proved that LCP closely correlate with the segment boundaries captured by the human judgments, and that lexical cohesion plays main role in forming a sequence of words into segments.</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="3">Text segmentation described here provides basic information for text understanding: Segment boundaries provide valuable restriction for determination of the referents.</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="4">Segment boundaries can be considered as segment switching (push and pop) in hierarchical structure of text.</S>
    <S sid="66" ssid="5">The segmentation can be applied also to text summarizing.</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="6">(Consider a list of average meaning of segments.)</S>
    <S sid="68" ssid="7">In future research, the author needs to examine validity of LCP for other genres &#8212; Hearst (1993) segments expository texts.</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="8">Incorporating other clues (e.g. cue phrases, tense and aspect, etc.) is also needed to make this segmentation method more robust.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="ACKNOWLEDGMENTS" number="7">
    <S sid="70" ssid="1">The author is very grateful to Dr. Teiji Furugori, University of Electro-Communications, for his insightful suggestions and comments on this work.</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
