<PAPER>
	<S sid="0">Single Malt or Blended? A Study in Multilingual Parser Optimization</S><ABSTRACT>
		<S sid="1" ssid="1">We describe a two-stage optimization of the MaltParser system for the ten languages in the multilingual track of the CoNLL 2007 shared task on dependency parsing.</S>
		<S sid="2" ssid="2">The first stage consists in tuning a single-parsersystem for each language by optimizing parameters of the parsing algorithm, the fea ture model, and the learning algorithm.</S>
		<S sid="3" ssid="3">Thesecond stage consists in building an ensemble system that combines six different parsing strategies, extrapolating from the opti mal parameters settings for each language.</S>
		<S sid="4" ssid="4">When evaluated on the official test sets, the ensemble system significantly outperforms the single-parser system and achieves the highest average labeled attachment score.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number="1">
			<S sid="5" ssid="5">In the multilingual track of the CoNLL 2007 shared task on dependency parsing, a single parser must be trained to handle data from ten different languages: Arabic (Hajic?</S>
			<S sid="6" ssid="6">et al, 2004), Basque (Aduriz et al, 2003), Catalan, (Mart??</S>
			<S sid="7" ssid="7">et al, 2007), Chinese (Chen et al, 2003), Czech (Bo?hmova?</S>
			<S sid="8" ssid="8">et al, 2003), English (Marcus et al, 1993; Johansson and Nugues, 2007), Greek (Prokopidis et al, 2005), Hungarian (Csendes et al, 2005), Italian (Montemagni et al, 2003), and Turkish (Oflazer et al, 2003).1 Our contribution is a study in multilingual parser optimization using the freely available MaltParser system, which performs 1For more information about the task and the data sets, see Nivre et al (2007).deterministic, classifier-based parsing with history based feature models and discriminative learning, and which was one of the top performing systems in the CoNLL 2006 shared task (Nivre et al, 2006).In order to maximize parsing accuracy, optimiza tion has been carried out in two stages, leading to two different, but related parsers.</S>
			<S sid="9" ssid="9">The first of these is a single-parser system, similar to the one describedin Nivre et al (2006), which parses a sentence deterministically in a single left-to-right pass, with post processing to recover non-projective dependencies, and where the parameters of the MaltParser system have been tuned for each language separately.</S>
			<S sid="10" ssid="10">We call this system Single Malt, to emphasize the fact that it consists of a single instance of MaltParser.</S>
			<S sid="11" ssid="11">The second parser is an ensemble system, which combines the output of six deterministic parsers, each of which is a variation of the Single Malt parser with parameter settings extrapolated from the first stage of optimization.</S>
			<S sid="12" ssid="12">It seems very natural to call this system Blended.</S>
			<S sid="13" ssid="13">Section 2 summarizes the work done to optimize the Single Malt parser, while section 3 explains how the Blended parser was constructed from the Single Malt parser.</S>
			<S sid="14" ssid="14">Section 4 gives a brief analysis of the experimental results, and section 5 concludes.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="The Single Malt Parser. " number="2">
			<S sid="15" ssid="1">The parameters available in the MaltParser system can be divided into three groups: parsing algorithmparameters, feature model parameters, and learn ing algorithm parameters.2 Our overall optimization 2For a complete documentation of these parameters, see http://w3.msi.vxu.se/users/nivre/research/MaltParser.html.</S>
			<S sid="16" ssid="2">933 strategy for the Single Malt parser was as follows: 1.</S>
			<S sid="17" ssid="3">Define a good baseline system with the same.</S>
			<S sid="18" ssid="4">parameter settings for all languages.</S>
			<S sid="19" ssid="5">2.</S>
			<S sid="20" ssid="6">Tune parsing algorithm parameters once and.</S>
			<S sid="21" ssid="7">for all for each language (with baseline settingsfor feature model and learning algorithm pa rameters).</S>
			<S sid="22" ssid="8">parameters in an interleaved fashion for each language.</S>
			<S sid="23" ssid="9">We used nine-fold cross-validation on 90% of the training data for all languages with a training set sizesmaller than 300,000 tokens and an 80%?10% train devtest split for the remaining languages (Catalan, Chinese, Czech, English).</S>
			<S sid="24" ssid="10">The remaining 10% of the data was in both cases saved for a final dry run, where the parser was trained on 90% of the data for each language and tested on the remaining (fresh) 10%.</S>
			<S sid="25" ssid="11">We consistently used the labeled attachment score (LAS) as the single optimization criterion.</S>
			<S sid="26" ssid="12">Below we describe the most important parameters in each group, define baseline settings, and report notable improvements for different languages during development.</S>
			<S sid="27" ssid="13">The improvements for each language from step 1 (baseline) to step 2 (parsing algorithm) and step 3 (feature model and learning algorithm) can be tracked in table 1.3 2.1 Parsing Algorithm.</S>
			<S sid="28" ssid="14">MaltParser implements several parsing algorithms, but for the Single Malt system we stick to the one used by Nivre et al (2006), which performs labeled projective dependency parsing in linear time, using a stack to store partially processed tokens and an input queue of remaining tokens.</S>
			<S sid="29" ssid="15">There are three basic parameters that can be varied for this algorithm: 1.</S>
			<S sid="30" ssid="16">Arc order: The baseline algorithm is arc-.</S>
			<S sid="31" ssid="17">eager, in the sense that right dependents are attached to their head as soon as possible, but there is also an arc-standard version, where theattachment of right dependents has to be postponed until they have found all their own de pendents.</S>
			<S sid="32" ssid="18">The arc-standard order was found 3Complete specifications of all parameter settings for all languages, for both Single Malt and Blended, are available at http://w3.msi.vxu.se/users/jha/conll07/.</S>
			<S sid="33" ssid="19">to improve parsing accuracy for Chinese, while the arc-eager order was maintained for all other languages.</S>
			<S sid="34" ssid="20">2.</S>
			<S sid="35" ssid="21">Stack initialization: In the baseline version.</S>
			<S sid="36" ssid="22">the parser is initialized with an artificial root node (with token id 0) on the stack, so that arcsoriginating from the root can be added explicitly during parsing.</S>
			<S sid="37" ssid="23">But it is also possible to ini tialize the parser with an empty stack, in whichcase arcs from the root are only added implicitly (to any token that remains a root after pars ing is completed).</S>
			<S sid="38" ssid="24">Empty stack initialization (which reduces the amount of nondeterminismin parsing) led to improved accuracy for Cata lan, Chinese, Hungarian, Italian and Turkish.4</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Post-processing: The baseline parser performs. " number="3">
			<S sid="39" ssid="1">a single left-to-right pass over the input, but it is possible to allow a second pass where onlyunattached tokens are processed.5 Such post processing was found to improve results for Basque, Catalan, Czech, Greek and Hungarian.</S>
			<S sid="40" ssid="2">Since the parsing algorithm only produces projective dependency graphs, we may use pseudo-projective parsing to recover non-projective dependencies, i.e., projectivize training data and encode information about these transformations in extended arc labels to support deprojectivization of the parser output(Nivre and Nilsson, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="41" ssid="3">Pseudo-projective parsing was found to have a positive effect on over all parsing accuracy only for Basque, Czech, Greek and Turkish.</S>
			<S sid="42" ssid="4">This result can probably be explainedin terms of the frequency of non-projective depen dencies in the different languages.</S>
			<S sid="43" ssid="5">For Basque, Czech, Greek and Turkish, more than 20% of the sentences have non-projective dependency graphs; for all the remaining languages the corresponding4For Arabic, Basque, Czech, and Greek, the lack of im provement can be explained by the fact that these data sets allow more than one label for dependencies from the artificial root.With empty stack initialization all such dependencies are assigned a default label, which leads to a drop in labeled attach ment score.</S>
			<S sid="44" ssid="6">For English, however, empty stack initialization did not improve accuracy despite the fact that dependencies from the artificial root have a unique label.</S>
			<S sid="45" ssid="7">5This technique is similar to the one used by Yamada and Matsumoto (2003), but with only a single post-processing pass parsing complexity remains linear in string length.</S>
			<S sid="46" ssid="8">934 Attributes Tokens FORM LEMMA CPOSTAG POSTAG FEATS DEPREL S: Top + + + + + + S: Top?1 + I: Next + + + + + I: Next+1 + + I: Next+2 + I: Next+3 + G: Head of Top + G: Leftmost dependent of Top + G: Rightmost dependent of Top + G: Leftmost dependent of Next + Figure 1: Baseline feature model (S = Stack, I = Input, G = Graph).</S>
			<S sid="47" ssid="9">figure is 10% or less.6 The cumulative improvement after optimization of parsing algorithm parameters was a modest 0.32 percentage points on average over all ten languages, with a minimum of 0.00 (Arabic, English) and a maximum of 0.83 (Czech) (cf.</S>
			<S sid="48" ssid="10">table 1).</S>
			<S sid="49" ssid="11">2.2 Feature Model.</S>
			<S sid="50" ssid="12">MaltParser uses a history-based feature model for predicting the next parsing action.</S>
			<S sid="51" ssid="13">Each feature of this model is an attribute of a token defined relative to the current stack S, input queue I, or partially built dependency graph G, where the attribute can be anyof the symbolic input attributes in the CoNLL for mat: FORM, LEMMA, CPOSTAG, POSTAG and FEATS (split into atomic attributes), as well as the DEPREL attribute of tokens in the graph G. The baseline feature model is depicted in figure 1, where rows denote tokens, columns denote attributes, and each cell containing a plus sign represents a model feature.7 This model is an extrapolation from many previous experiments on different languages and usually represents a good starting point for further optimization.</S>
			<S sid="52" ssid="14">The baseline model was tuned for each of the ten languages using both forward and backward feature 6In fact, for Arabic, which has about 10% sentences with non-projective dependencies, it was later found that, with anoptimized feature model, it is beneficial to projectivize the train ing data without trying to recover non-projective dependencies in the parser output.</S>
			<S sid="53" ssid="15">This was also the setting that was used for Arabic in the dry run and final test.</S>
			<S sid="54" ssid="16">7The names Top and Next refer to the token on top of the stack S and the first token in the remaining input I, respectively.</S>
			<S sid="55" ssid="17">selection.</S>
			<S sid="56" ssid="18">The total number of features in the tuned models varies from 18 (Turkish) to 56 (Hungarian)but is typically between 20 and 30.</S>
			<S sid="57" ssid="19">This feature se lection process constituted the major development effort for the Single Malt parser and also gave the greatest improvements in parsing accuracy, but since feature selection was to some extent interleaved with learning algorithm optimization, we only report the cumulative effect of both together in table 1.</S>
			<S sid="58" ssid="20">2.3 Learning Algorithm.</S>
			<S sid="59" ssid="21">MaltParser supports several learning algorithms butthe best results have so far been obtained with sup port vector machines, using the LIBSVM package (Chang and Lin, 2001).</S>
			<S sid="60" ssid="22">We use a quadratic kernel K(xi, xj) = (?xTi xj + r)2 and LIBSVM?s builtin one-versus-one strategy for multi-class classifica tion, converting symbolic features to numerical ones using the standard technique of binarization.</S>
			<S sid="61" ssid="23">As our baseline settings, we used ? = 0.2 and r = 0 forthe kernel parameters, C = 0.5 for the penalty para meter, and ? = 1.0 for the termination criterion.</S>
			<S sid="62" ssid="24">In order to reduce training times during development, we also split the training data for each language intosmaller sets and trained separate multi-class classi fiers for each set, using the POSTAG of Next as the defining feature for the split.</S>
			<S sid="63" ssid="25">The time spent on optimizing learning algorithm parameters varies between languages, mainly due to lack of time.</S>
			<S sid="64" ssid="26">For Arabic, Basque, and Catalan, the baseline settings were used also in the dry run and final test.</S>
			<S sid="65" ssid="27">For Chinese, Greek and Hungarian, 935 Development Dry Run Test Test: UAS Language Base PA F+L SM B SM B SM B Arabic 70.31 70.31 71.67 70.93 73.09 74.75 76.52 84.21 85.81 Basque 73.86 74.44 76.99 77.18 80.12 74.97 76.92 80.61 82.84 Catalan 85.43 85.51 86.88 86.65 88.00 87.74 88.70 92.20 93.12 Chinese 83.85 84.39 87.64 87.61 88.61 83.51 84.67 87.60 88.70 Czech 75.00 75.83 77.74 77.91 82.17 77.22 77.98 82.35 83.59 English 85.44 85.44 86.35 86.35 88.74 85.81 88.11 86.77 88.93 Greek 72.67 73.04 74.42 74.89 78.17 74.21 74.65 80.66 81.22 Hungarian 74.62 74.64 77.40 77.81 80.04 78.09 80.27 81.71 83.55 Italian 81.42 81.64 82.50 83.37 85.16 82.48 84.40 86.26 87.77 Turkish 75.12 75.80 76.49 75.87 77.09 79.24 79.79 85.04 85.77 Average 77.78 78.10 79.81 79.86 82.12 79.80 81.20 84.74 86.13 Table 1: Development results for Single Malt (Base = baseline, PA = parsing algorithm, F+L = feature model and learning algorithm); dry run and test results for Single Malt (SM) and Blended (B) (with corrected test scores for Blended on Chinese).</S>
			<S sid="66" ssid="28">All scores are labeled attachment scores (LAS) except the last two columns, which report unlabeled attachment scores (UAS) on the test sets.</S>
			<S sid="67" ssid="29">slightly better results were obtained by not splittingthe training data into smaller sets; for the remain ing languages, accuracy was improved by using the CPOSTAG of Next as the defining feature for the split (instead of POSTAG).</S>
			<S sid="68" ssid="30">With respect to the SVMparameters (?, r, C, and ?), Arabic, Basque, Catalan, Greek and Hungarian retain the baseline settings, while the other languages have slightly dif ferent values for some parameters.</S>
			<S sid="69" ssid="31">The cumulative improvement after optimization of feature model and learning algorithm parameters was 1.71 percentage points on average over all ten languages, with a minimum of 0.69 (Turkish) and a maximum of 3.25 (Chinese) (cf.</S>
			<S sid="70" ssid="32">table 1).</S>
			<S sid="71" ssid="33">3 The Blended Parser.</S>
			<S sid="72" ssid="34">The Blended parser is an ensemble system based on the methodology proposed by Sagae and Lavie (2006).</S>
			<S sid="73" ssid="35">Given the output dependency graphs Gi(1 ? i ? m) of m different parsers for an input sen tence x, we construct a new graph containing all the labeled dependency arcs proposed by some parser and weight each arc a by a score s(a) reflecting its popularity among the m parsers.</S>
			<S sid="74" ssid="36">The output of the ensemble system for x is the maximum spanning tree of this graph (rooted at the node 0), which can be extracted using the Chu-Liu-Edmonds algorithm, as shown by McDonald et al (2005).</S>
			<S sid="75" ssid="37">Following Sagae and Lavie (2006), we let s(a) = ?m i=1 w c iai, where wci is the average labeled attachment score of parser i for the word class c8 of the dependent of a, and ai is 1 if a ? Gi and 0 otherwise.</S>
			<S sid="76" ssid="38">The Blended parser uses six component parsers, with three different parsing algorithms, each of which is used to construct one left-to-right parser and one right-to-left parser.</S>
			<S sid="77" ssid="39">The parsing algorithmsused are the arc-eager baseline algorithm, the arc standard variant of the baseline algorithm, and the incremental, non-projective parsing algorithm first described by Covington (2001) and recently used for deterministic classifier-based parsing by Nivre (2007), all of which are available in MaltParser.</S>
			<S sid="78" ssid="40">Thus, the six component parsers for each language were instances of the following: 1.</S>
			<S sid="79" ssid="41">Arc-eager projective left-to-right.</S>
			<S sid="80" ssid="42">2.</S>
			<S sid="81" ssid="43">Arc-eager projective right-to-left.</S>
			<S sid="82" ssid="44">3.</S>
			<S sid="83" ssid="45">Arc-standard projective left-to-right.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Arc-standard projective right-to-left. " number="4">
			<S sid="84" ssid="1">6.</S>
			<S sid="85" ssid="2">Covington non-projective right-to-left.</S>
			<S sid="86" ssid="3">8We use CPOSTAG to determine the part of speech.</S>
			<S sid="87" ssid="4">936 root 1 2 3?6 7+ Parser R P R P R P R P R P Single Malt 87.01 80.36 95.08 94.87 86.28 86.67 77.97 80.23 68.98 71.06 Blended 92.09 74.20 95.71 94.92 87.55 88.12 78.66 83.02 65.29 78.14 Table 2: Recall (R) and precision (P) of Single Malt and Blended for dependencies of different length, averaged over all languages (root = dependents of root node, regardless of length).</S>
			<S sid="88" ssid="5">The final Blended parser was constructed by reusingthe tuned Single Malt parser for each language (arcstandard left-to-right for Chinese, arc-eager left-to right for the remaining languages) and training five additional parsers with the same parameter settings except for the following mechanical adjustments: 1.</S>
			<S sid="89" ssid="6">Pseudo-projective parsing was not used for the.</S>
			<S sid="90" ssid="7">two non-projective parsers.</S>
			<S sid="91" ssid="8">2.</S>
			<S sid="92" ssid="9">Feature models were adjusted with respect to.</S>
			<S sid="93" ssid="10">the most obvious differences in parsing strategy (e.g., by deleting features that could never be informative for a given parser).</S>
			<S sid="94" ssid="11">3.</S>
			<S sid="95" ssid="12">Learning algorithm parameters were adjusted.</S>
			<S sid="96" ssid="13">to speed up training (e.g., by always splitting the training data into smaller sets).</S>
			<S sid="97" ssid="14">Having trained all parsers on 90% of the training data for each language, the weights wci for each parser i and coarse part of speech c was determined by the labeled attachment score on the remaining 10% of the data.</S>
			<S sid="98" ssid="15">This means that the results obtained in the dry run were bound to be overly optimistic for the Blended parser, since it was then evaluated on the same data set that was used to tune the weights.</S>
			<S sid="99" ssid="16">Finally, we want to emphasize that the time for developing the Blended parser was severely limited, which means that several shortcuts had to be taken, such as optimizing learning algorithm parametersfor speed rather than accuracy and using extrapolation, rather than proper tuning, for other important parameters.</S>
			<S sid="100" ssid="17">This probably means that the per formance of the Blended system can be improved considerably by optimizing parameters for all six parsers separately.</S>
			<S sid="101" ssid="18">4 Results and Discussion.</S>
			<S sid="102" ssid="19">Table 1 shows the labeled attachment score results from our internal dry run (training on 90% of the training data, testing on the remaining 10%) and the official test runs for both of our systems.</S>
			<S sid="103" ssid="20">It should be pointed out that the test score for the Blended parser on Chinese is different from the official one (75.82), which was much lower than expected dueto a corrupted specification file required by Malt Parser.</S>
			<S sid="104" ssid="21">Restoring this file and rerunning the parser on the Chinese test set, without retraining the parser or changing any parameter settings, resulted in thescore reported here.</S>
			<S sid="105" ssid="22">This also improved the aver age score from 80.32 to 81.20, the former being the highest reported official score.</S>
			<S sid="106" ssid="23">For the Single Malt parser, the test results are on average very close to the dry run results, indicating that models have not been overfitted (although there is considerably variation between languages).</S>
			<S sid="107" ssid="24">For the Blended parser, there is a drop of almost one percentage point, which can be explained by the fact that weights could not be tuned on held-out data for the dry run (as explained in section 3).</S>
			<S sid="108" ssid="25">Comparing the results for different languages, we see a tendency that languages with rich morphology, usually accompanied by flexible word order, get lower scores.</S>
			<S sid="109" ssid="26">Thus, the labeled attachment score isbelow 80% for Arabic, Basque, Czech, Greek, Hungarian, and Turkish.</S>
			<S sid="110" ssid="27">By comparison, the more con figurational languages (Catalan, Chinese, English,and Italian) all have scores above 80%.</S>
			<S sid="111" ssid="28">Linguis tic properties thus seem to be more important than, for example, training set size, which can be seen by comparing the results for Italian, with one of the smallest training sets, and Czech, with one of the largest.</S>
			<S sid="112" ssid="29">The development of parsing methods that are better suited for morphologically rich languages with flexible word order appears as one of the most important goals for future research in this area.</S>
			<S sid="113" ssid="30">Comparing the results of our two systems, we see that the Blended parser outperforms the SingleMalt parser for all languages, with an average im 937 provement of 1.40 percentage points, a minimum of 0.44 (Greek) and a maximum of 2.40 (English).</S>
			<S sid="114" ssid="31">As shown by McDonald and Nivre (2007), the Single Malt parser tends to suffer from two problems: errorpropagation due to the deterministic parsing strat egy, typically affecting long dependencies more thanshort ones, and low precision on dependencies orig inating in the artificial root node due to fragmented parses.9 The question is which of these problems isalleviated by the multiple views given by the compo nent parsers in the Blended system.</S>
			<S sid="115" ssid="32">Table 2 throwssome light on this by giving the precision and recall for dependencies of different length, treating de pendents of the artificial root node as a special case.As expected, the Single Malt parser has lower preci sion than recall for root dependents, but the Blendedparser has even lower precision (and somewhat bet ter recall), indicating that the fragmentation is even more severe in this case.10 By contrast, we see that precision and recall for other dependencies improve across the board, especially for longer dependencies,which probably means that the effect of error propa gation is mitigated by the use of an ensemble system,even if each of the component parsers is determinis tic in itself.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusion. " number="5">
			<S sid="116" ssid="1">We have shown that deterministic, classifier-based dependency parsing, with careful optimization, can give highly accurate dependency parsing for a wide range of languages, as illustrated by the performanceof the Single Malt parser.</S>
			<S sid="117" ssid="2">We have also demonstrated that an ensemble of deterministic, classifier based dependency parsers, built on top of a tuned single-parser system, can give even higher accuracy, as shown by the results of the Blended parser, whichhas the highest labeled attachment score for five lan guages (Arabic, Basque, Catalan, Hungarian, and 9A fragmented parse is a dependency forest, rather than a tree, and is automatically converted to a tree by attaching all (other) roots to the artificial root node.</S>
			<S sid="118" ssid="3">Hence, children of the root node in the final output may not have been predicted as such by the treebank-induced classifier.</S>
			<S sid="119" ssid="4">10This conclusion is further supported by the observation that the single most frequent ?frame confusion?</S>
			<S sid="120" ssid="5">of the Blended parser, over all languages, is to attach two dependents with the label ROOT to the root node, instead of only one.</S>
			<S sid="121" ssid="6">The frequency of this error is more than twice as high for the Blended parser (180) as for the Single Malt parser (83).</S>
			<S sid="122" ssid="7">Italian), as well as the highest multilingual average score.</S>
			<S sid="123" ssid="8">Acknowledgements We want to thank all treebank providers for making the data available for the shared task and the (other) organizers for their efforts in organizing it.</S>
			<S sid="124" ssid="9">Special thanks to Ryan McDonald, for fruitful discussions and assistance with the error analysis, and to Kenji Sagae, for showing us how to produce a good blend.</S>
			<S sid="125" ssid="10">Thanks also to two reviewers for useful comments.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
