<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">The integration of semantic properties into morphological analyzers can significantly enhance the performance of any tool that uses their output as input, e.g., for derivation or for syntactic parsing.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">In this paper will be presented my approach to the integration of aspectually relevant properties of verbs into a morphological analyzer for English.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">Heid, Radtke and Klosa (2012) have recently surveyed morphological analyzers and interactive online dictionaries for German and French.</S>
			<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">They have established that most of them do not utilize semantic properties.</S>
			<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">The integration of semantic properties into morphological analyzers can significantly enhance the performance of any tool that uses their output as input, e.g., for derivation or for syntactic parsing.</S>
			<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">In this paper will be presented my approach to the integration of aspectually relevant properties of verbs into a morphological analyzer for English.</S>
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">In section 2 I will describe a prototypical finite- state morphological analyzer for English that doesn’t utilize semantic properties.</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">Some classifications of English verbs with respect to the aspectually relevant properties that they lexicalize will be outlined in section 3.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">In section 4 will be presented my approach to the integration the semantic classes in the lexicon.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">I will describe the modified morphological analyzer for English in section 5 and point out in section 6 the challenges that inflectionally-rich languages present to the techniques outlined in section 4.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">Finally, in section 7 I will draw some conclusions and outline future work on other languages.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="A   Prototypical   Finite-State   Morpho- " number = "2">
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "1">logical Analyzer for English English is an inflectionally-poor language which for this reason has been chosen to illustrate my approach to the integration of grammatically relevant lexicalized meaning into morphological analyzers.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "2">It has a finite number of irregular (strong) verbs.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "3">The rest of the verbs are regular and constitute a single inflectional class.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "4">This prototypical morphological analyzer for English has parallel implementations in xfst (cf.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "5">Beesley and Karttunen (2003)) and foma (cf.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "6">Hul- den (2009a) and (2009b)).</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "7">It consists of a lexicon that describes the morphotactics of the language, and of phonological and orthographical alternations and realizational rules that are handled by finite-state replace rules elsewhere.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "8">The bases of the regular verbs are stored in a single text file.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "9">Here is an excerpt from the lexc lexicon without semantic features: LEXICON Root Verb ; … LEXICON Verb ^VREG VerbReg ; … LEXICON VerbReg +V:0 VerbRegFlex ; … ! This lexicon contains the morpho- tactic rules.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "10">LEXICON VerbRegFlex &lt; [&quot;+Pres&quot;] [&quot;+3P&quot;] [&quot;+Sg&quot;] &gt; # ; &lt; [&quot;+Pres&quot;] [&quot;+Non3PSg&quot;] &gt; # ; &lt; [&quot;+Past&quot;] &gt; # ; &lt; [&quot;+PrPart&quot;|&quot;+PaPart&quot;] &gt; # ; &lt; [&quot;+Inf&quot;] &gt; # ; 30 Proceedings of the 10th International Workshop on Finite State Methods and Natural Language Processing, pages 30–34, Donostia–San Sebastia´n, July 23–25, 2012.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "11">Qc 2012 Association for Computational Linguistics</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Aspectually    Relevant    Properties    of. " number = "3">
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "1">Verbs The information that is provided by the prototypical analyzer described above contains lemma, W(ord)-features (morphosyntactic features that exhibit different specifications in different cells of the same inflectional paradigm) and L(exeme)- features that “specify a lexeme’s invariant morphosyntactic properties” (e.g., gender of nouns, cf.</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "2">Stump (2001), p. 137, emphasis mine).</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "3">L-features should not be confused with lexical- ized meaning.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "4">I adopt the definition in Rappaport Hovav and Levin (2010), p. 23: “In order to distinguish lexicalized meaning from inferences derived from particular uses of verbs in sentences, we take lexicalized meaning to be those components of meaning that are entailed in all uses of (a single sense of) a verb, regardless of context” (emphasis mine).</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "5">Obviously, this definition is applicable not only to verbs but to all word classes.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "6">However, in this paper I will limit myself to the description of lexicalized aspectually relevant properties of verbs.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "7">3.1 Vendler’s Classification.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "8">In his famous paper “Verbs and Times” Vendler (1957) introduced his “time schemata presupposed by various verbs” (ibid.).</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "9">He proposes four time schemata: states, activities, accomplishments and achievements.</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "10">It is important to point out from the beginning that although he didn’t declare explicitly that he was classifying VPs, he did imply this: “Obviously these differences cannot be explained in terms of time alone: other factors, like the presence or absence of an object, conditions, intended state of affairs, also enter the picture.” (ibid., p. 143, emphasis mine).</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "11">The properties that are often used to define Vendler’s classes are dynamicity, duration and telicity.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "12">States are non-dynamic, achievements are non-durative.</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "13">States and activities are inherently unbounded (non-telic); accomplishments and achievements are inherently bounded.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "14">Since three features are needed to differentiate between only four classes that cannot be represented as, e.g., a right-branching tree one wonders if these are the right features to be used for the classification.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "15">Vendler’s classification was widely accepted and is used in most current studies on aspect.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "16">However, Vendlerian classes cannot be implemented in a lexc lexicon for the following reasons:  Vendler does not classify verbs but VPs Part of the features used to differentiate be tween the classes are not lexicalized by the verb but can be determined at the VP level  This classification allows multiple class membership even for the same word sense.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "17">Thus run can be activity and accomplishment, cf.</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "18">above running/running a mile.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "19">3.2 Levin and Rappaport Hovav’s Approach.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "20">to English Verb classes Sets of semantically related verbs that share a range of linguistic properties form verb classes.</S>
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "21">There are different criteria for grouping and granularity, e.g., Levin (1993) classifies the verbs in two ways: a) according to semantic content with 48 broad classes and 192 smaller classes; b) according to their participation in argument alternations with 79 alternations.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "22">The account of Beth Levin and Malka Rappaport Hovav for verb classes developed over the years in a steady and consistent way that can be trailed in the following publications: (Levin 1993; Levin and Rappaport Hovav 1991, 1995, 2005; Rappaport Hovav 2008; Rappaport Hovav and Levin 1998, 2001, 2005, 2010), among others.</S>
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "23">Here I will just summarize the most important ideas and implications for the non-stative verbs: Dynamic verbs either lexicalize scales (sca lar verbs) or do not (non-scalar verbs)  Non-scalar verbs lexicalize manner  Scalar verbs lexicalize result  Scalar verbs lexicalize two major types of scales – multi-point scales and two-point scales  The chosen aspectually relevant properties are complementary  All lexical distinctions described here have grammatical consequences which are relevant to aspectual composition.</S>
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "24">This interpretation of non-stative verbs has some very attractive properties:  The verbs fall into disjunctive classes.</S>
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "25">There is no multiple class membership (for the same word sense). The aspectual properties are lexicalized ex clusively by the verb and are not computed at the VP level. The lexicalized aspectual properties con strain the syntactical behavior of the verb.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "26"> Manner verbs in English show a uniform argument-realization pattern: they can appear with unspecified and non- subcategorized objects.</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "27"> Result verbs are more constrained and less uniform in their argument realization patterns.</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "28">Transitivity (in contrast to the manner verbs) is an issue.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Intersection  of  Semantic  Classes  and. " number = "4">
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "1">Inflectional Classes The main difficulties here arise from the fact that the set of bases that belong to one inflectional class of verbs usually is not identical with the set of bases that lexicalize a particular aspectually relevant property.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "2">As a rule, it has intersections with more than one semantic class.</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "3">The situation is relatively manageable in inflectionally-poor languages like English but becomes very complicated in inflectionally-rich languages.</S>
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "4">The distribution of verbs in inflectional classes is in general complementary.</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "5">There are some exceptions that will not be discussed here.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "6">Vendler’s approach to the verb classification described in 3.1 has the undesirable property that most of the verbs have multiple class membership, while the approach of Levin and Rappaport Hovav described in 3.2 has advantages which make the task easier.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "7">Thus, for English we have the set of bases of regular verbs that is monolithic, and the same set of bases but this time divided into complementary subsets of aspectual semantic classes in the sense of Levin and Rappaport Hovav.</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "8">The cross product of the number of subsets in the first set and the number of subsets in the second set equals the number of aspectual semantic classes since there is only one inflectional class of regular verbs.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="The modified Prototypical Lexicon for. " number = "5">
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "1">English The following modifications need to be introduced to the lexicon in order to incorporate the aspectual properties of English verbs.</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "2">The single placeholder pointing to the single file containing the bases of regular verbs must be replaced with several placeholders that point to the files containing the complementary subsets of bases of verbs belonging to the different aspectual classes.</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "3">New continuation lexicons introducing each as- pectual class must be added immediately after LEXICON Verb.</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "4">Since the union of the sets of aspectual-class bases of regular verbs is identical with the set of the bases of the regular verbs, all aspectual-class lexicons have the same continuation lexicon: LEXICON VerbRegFlex.</S>
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "5">Irregular verbs get the semantic tags added to the lexical entry and suppletive verbs get them in the master lexicon.</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "6">Multichar_Symbols +V +VIrrTT %&lt;manner%&gt; … LEXICON Root Verb ; VerbSuppl ; … LEXICON VerbSuppl go%&lt;resmulpo%&gt;+V+Inf:go # ; go%&lt;resmulpo%&gt;+V+Pres+3P+Sg:goes # ; go%&lt;resmulpo%&gt;+V+Pres+Non3PSg:go # ; go%&lt;resmulpo%&gt;+V+Past:went # ; go%&lt;resmulpo%&gt;+V+PaPart:gone # ; go%&lt;resmulpo%&gt;+V+PrPart:going # ; … LEXICON Verb ^VREGM VerbRegManner ; … LEXICON VerbRegManner +V%&lt;manner%&gt;:0 VerbRegFlex ; LEXICON VerbRegFlex … Below is an excerpt from the file holding the bases of irregular verbs that build identical past- tense and perfect-participle forms by adding ‘-t’: … {creep&lt;manner&gt;}:{creep} | {feel} | {keep} | {sleep} | {sweep&lt;manner&gt;}:{sweep} | … In order to be able to rewrite the semantic-class tags, which appear only on the lexical (upper) side of the transducer containing the lexicon, I invert the network, apply the semantic-tag rewriting rules and invert the resulting net again.</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "7">The network is then composed with the realization rules and the phonological and orthographical alternations that operate on the surface (lower) side of the transducer: ! Semantic-features tag-rewriting define LEX2 [LEX1.i] ; define LEX2 [LEX1.i] ; define Mnr [ %&lt; m a n n e r %&gt; -&gt; %&lt;%+SV%&gt;%&lt;%+SVO%&gt;%&lt;%+SVOOC%&gt; ] ; ! alternative RRG tags !define Mnr [%&lt; m a n n e r %&gt; -&gt; !%&lt;do´ %(x%, %[predicate´ %(x%) or ! %(x%, y%)%]%)%&gt;] ; define LEX3 [LEX2 .o. Mnr] ; define LEX [LEX3.i] ; ! Inflectional morphology: realization … Here is the output of the analysis of ‘swept’ with dependency-grammar valency-pattern tags (S=subject, V=verb, O=object, OC=object complement): swept sweep&lt;+SV&gt;&lt;+SVO&gt;&lt;+SVOOC&gt;+V+Past sweep&lt;+SV&gt;&lt;+SVO&gt;&lt;+SVOOC&gt;+V+PaPart and the alternative output with Role and Reference Grammar logical structures: swept sweep&lt;do´(x,[predicate´(x)or(x,y)])&gt;+V+Past sweep&lt;do´(x,[predicate´(x)or(x,y)])&gt;+V+PaPart Valency information is necessary for syntactic parsing and has been used in Constraint Grammar shallow parsers and in dependency parsers.</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "8">The advantage of this approach to already existing morphological analyzers for English is that the valency-pattern tags are added to classes of verbs rather than to individual lexical entries.</S>
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "9">The ability to provide alternative outputs for the integrated aspectually relevant semantic information is a novelty of this morphological analyzer.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Beyond English: the Challenges of In-. " number = "6">
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "1">flectionally-Rich Languages We have seen a simplified example that shows the modeling and the implementation of a morphological analyzer that utilizes semantic-class tags for aspectually relevant lexical properties of English verbs.</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "2">Things become much more challenging if we want to model inflectionally-rich languages such as Bulgarian, Russian or Finnish.</S>
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "3">Bulgarian verbs, for example, can be divided (depending on the modeling) into some 15 complementary inflectional classes.</S>
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "4">This number multiplied by 4 LevinRappaport-Hovav classes would result in some 60 sets of verb bases that share the same inflectional class and LevinRappaport-Hovav class.</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "5">If a finer- grained semantic classification is adopted, the number of classes will considerably increase and this will lead to a lexicon that exclusively requires manual lexicographical work.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusion. " number = "7">
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "1">This paper illustrates the integration of aspectually relevant properties of verbs into a morphological analyzer for English.</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "2">I showed that these features can be integrated while the computational efficiency of the analyzer can still be maintained if the linguistic modelling is adequate.</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "3">However, this only scratches the surface of the challenge of integrating semantic features into morphological analyzers.</S>
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "4">In the future, it is planned (together with other researchers) to extend the integration of semantic features to nouns, adjectives and adverbs.</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "5">We also plan to model and implement morphological analyzers for other languages such as German, Russian, Polish and Bulgarian.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
