<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">We present an efficient and robust reference reso­ lution algorithm in an end-to-end state-of-the-art information extraction system, which must work with a considerably impoverished syntactic analy­ sis of the input sentences.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">Considering this disad­ vantage, the basic setup to collect, filter, then order by salience does remarkably well with third-person pronou ns, but needs more semantic and discourse information to improve the treatments of other ex­ pression types.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">Anaphora resolution is a component technology of an overall discourse understanding system.</S>
			<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">This paper focuses on reference resolution in an infor­ mation extraction system, which performs a par­ tial and selective &apos;understanding&apos; of unrestricted discourses.</S>
			<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">Reference Resolution in IE An information extraction (IE) system automat­ ically extracts certain predefined target informa­ tion from real-world online texts or speech tran­ scripts.</S>
			<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">The target information, typically of the form &quot;who did what to whom where when,&quot; is ex­ tracted from natural language sentences or format­ ted tables, and fills parts of predefined template data structures with slot values.</S>
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">Partially filled template data objects about the same entities, en­ tity relationships, and events are then merged to updating and summary generation.</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">1 In this IE context, reference resolution takes the form of merging partial data objects about the same entities, entity relationships, and events de­ scribed at different discourse positions.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">Merging in IE is very difficult, accounting for a significant portion of IE errors in the final output.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">This pa­ per focuses on the referential relationships among entities rather than the more complex problem of event merging.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">An IE system recognizes particular target infor­ mation instances, ignoring anything deemed irrel­ evant.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">Reference resolution within IE, however, cannot operate only on those parts that describe target information because anaphoric expressions within target linguistic patterns may have an­ tecedents outside of the target, and those that oc­ cur in an apparently irrelevant pattern may ac­ tually resolve to target entities.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">For this reason, reference resolution in the IE system needs ac­ cess to all of the text rather than some selective parts.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">Furthermore, it is reasonable to assume that a largely domain-independent method of reference resolution can be developed, which need not be tailored anew each time a new target is defined.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">In this paper, I discuss one such entity refer­ ence resolution algorithm for a general geo political business domain developed for SRI&apos;s FASTUS™ system (Hobbs et al., 1996) , one of the leading IE systems, which can also be seen as a representative of today&apos;s IE technology.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">create a network of related data objects.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">These 1The IE technology has undergone a rapid development template data objects depicting instances of the target information are the raw output of IE, ready for a wide range of applications such as database in the 1990s driven by the series of Message Understand­ ing Conferences (MUCs) in the U.S. government-sponsored TIPSTER program (http://www .t ipster .org).</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">46 The Input to Reference Resolution Multiple top-scoring sites working on IE have con­ verged on the use of finite-state linguistic patterns applied in stages of smaller to larger units.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">This finite-state transduction approach to IE, first intro­ duced in SRl&apos;s FASTUS, has proven effective for real-world texts because full parsing is far too am­ biguous, slow, and brittle against real-world sen­ tences.</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "20">This means that we cannot assume correct and full syntactic structures in the input to ref­ erence resolution in a typical IE system.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "21">The in­ put is a set of (often overlapping or discontiguous) finite-state approximations of sentence parts.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "22">We must approximate fine-grained theoretical propos­ als about referential dependencies, and adapt them to the context of sparse and incomplete syntactic input.</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "23">The input to reference resolution in the the­ oretical literature is assumed to be fully parsed sentences, often with syntactic attributes such as grammatical functions and thematic roles on the constituents (Webber, 1978; Sidner, 1979; Hobbs, 1978; Grosz, Joshi, and Weinstein, 1995).</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "24">In im­ plemented reference resolution systems, for pro­ noun resolution in particular, there seems to be a trade-off between the completeness of syntac­ tic input and the robustness with real-world sen­ tences.</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "25">In short, more robust and partial parsing gives us wider coverage, but less syntactic infor­ mation also leads to less accUJ1ate reference reso­ lution.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "26">For instance, Lappin and Leass {1994) re­ port an 86% accuracy for a resolution algorithm for third-person pronouns using fully parsed sen­ tences as input.</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "27">Kennedy and Boguraev {1996) then report a 75% accuracy for an algorithm that approximates Lappin and Leass&apos;s with more robust and coarse-grained syntactic input.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "28">After describ­ ing the algorithm in the next section, I will briefly compare the present approach with these pronoun resolution approaches.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "29">Algorit hmThis algorithm was first implemented for the MUC 6 FASTUS system (Appelt et al., 1995) , and prod.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "30">uced one of the top scores (a recall of 59% and precision of 72%) in the MUC6 Coreference Task, which evaluated systems&apos; ability to recog nize coreference among noun phrases (Sund heim, 1995).</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "31">Note that only identity of reference was evaluated there.2 The three main factors in this algorithm are (a) accessible text regions, (b) semantic consistency, and {c) dynamic syntactic preference.</S>
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "32">The algo­ rithm is invoked for each sentence after the earlier finite-state transd uction phases have determined the best sequence(s) of nominal and verbal expres­ sions.</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "33">Crucially, each nominal expression is associ­ ated with a set of template data objects that record various linguistic and textual attributes of the re­ ferring expressions contained in it.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "34">These data ob­ jects are similar to discourse referents in discourse semantics (Karttunen, 1976; Kamp, 1981; Heim, 1982; Kamp and Reyle, 1993) , in that anaphoric expressions such as she are also associated with corresponding anaphoric entities.</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "35">A pleonastic it has no associated entities.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "36">Quantificational nomi­ nals such as each company are associated with en­ tity objects because they are &apos;anaphoric&apos; to group entities accessible in the context.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "37">In this setup, the effect of reference resolution is merging of multiple entity objects.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "38">Here is the algorithm.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "39">1.</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "40">INPUT: Template entities with the.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "41">following textual, syntactic, and semantic features: {a) determiner type (e.g., DEF, INDEF, PRON) (b) grammatical or numerical number (e.g., SG, PL, 3) (c) head string (e.g., automaker) {d) the head string sort in a sort hierarchy (e.g., automaker-+company-+organiz ation) (e) modifier strings (e.g., newly founded , with the pilots ) {f) text span {the start and end byte positions) (g) sentence and paragraph positions3 {h) text region type (e.g., HEADLINE, TEXT) 20ther referential relationships such as subset and part­ whole did not reach sufficiently reliable interannotator agreements.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "42">Only identity of reference had a sufficiently high agreement rate (about 85%) between two human annotators.</S>
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "43">3Higher text structure properties such as subsections and sections should also be considered if there are any.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "44">Exact accessibility computation using complex hierarchical text structures is a future topic of study.</S>
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "45">47</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="FOR EACH potentially  anaphoric entity object. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "1">in the current sentence, in the left-to-right order, DO (1) COLLECT antecedent entity objects from the accessible text region.</S>
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "2">• For an entity in a HEADLINE text region, the entire TEXT is accessible because the headline summarizes the text.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "3">• For an entity in a TEXT region, everything preceding its text span is accessible (except for the HEADLINE).</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "4">Intrasentential cataphora is allowed only for first-person pronouns.</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "5">• In addition, a locality assumption on anaphora sets a (soft) window of search for each referring expression type-the entire preceding text for proper names, narrower for definite noun phrases, even narrower for pro­ nouns, and only the current sentence for re­ flexives.</S>
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "6">In the MUC6 system, the window size was arbitrarily set to ten sentences for definites and three sentences for pronou ns, ignoring paragraph boundaries, and no an­ tecedents beyond the limit were considered.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "7">This clearly left ample room for refinement.4 (2) FILTER with semantic consistency between the anaphoric entity E1 and the potential an­ tecedent entity E2.</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "8">• Number Consistency: E1&apos;s number must be consistent with E2&apos;s number-for example, twelve is consistent with PLURAL, but not with SINGULAR.</S>
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "9">As a special case, plural pronouns (they, we) can take singular organi­ zation antecedents.</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "10">• Sort Consistency: E1&apos;s sort must either EQUAL or SUBSUME E2&apos;s sort.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "11">This reflects a monotonicity assumption on anaphora-for example, since company sub­ sumes automaker, the company can take a Chicago-based automaker as an antecedent, but it is too risky to allow the automaker to take a Chicago-based company as an antecedent.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "12">On the other hand, since 4 For example, in a more recent FASTUS system, para­ graphs are also considered in setting the limit, and at most one candidate beyond the limit is proposed when no candi­ dates are found within the limit.</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "13">automaker and airline are neither the same sort nor in a subsumption relation, an au­ tomaker and the airline cannot corefer.</S>
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "14">(The system&apos;s sort hierarchy is still sparse and in­ complete.)</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "15">• Modifier Consistency: E1&apos;s modifiers must be consistent with E2 &apos;s modifiers for ex­ ample, French and British are inconsistent, but French and multinational are consistent.</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "16">(The system doesn&apos;t have enough knowledge to do this well.)</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "17">(3) ORDER by dynamic syntactic preference.</S>
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "18">The following ordering approximates the relative salience of entities.</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "19">The basic underlying hypothesis is that intrasentential candidates are more salient than intersentential candi­ dates as proposed, for example, in Hobbs (1978) and Kameyama (in press) , and that fine grained syntax-based salience fades with time.</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "20">Since fine-grained syntax with gram­ matical functions is unavailable, the syntactic prominence of subjects and leftdislocation is approximated by the left right linear ordering.</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "21">1.</S>
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "22">the preceding part of the same sentence in the left-right order ii.</S>
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "23">the immediately preceding sentence in the left-right order iii.</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "24">other preceding sentences within the &apos;limit&apos; (see above) in the right-left order</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="OUTPUT: After each anaphoric  entity  has. " number = "3">
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "1">found an ordered set of potential antecedent entities, there are destructive (indefeasible) and nonde­ structive (defeasible) options.</S>
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "2">(a) Destructive Option: MERGE the anaphoric entity into the preferred antecedent entity .</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "3">(b) Nondestructive Option: RECORD the an­ tecedent entity list in the anaphoric entity to allow reordering (i.e., preference revisions) by event merging or overall model selection.</S>
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "4">The MUC6 system took the destructive op­ tion.</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "5">The nondest ructive option has been im­ plemented in a more recent system.</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "6">These basic steps of &quot;COLLECT, FILTER, and ORDER by salience&quot; are analogous to Lappin and 48 Leass&apos;s (1994) pronou n resolution algorithm, but each step in FASTUS relies on considerably poorer syntactic input.</S>
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "7">The present algorithm thus pro­ vides an interesting case of what happens with extremely poor syntactic input, even poorer than in Kennedy and Boguraev&apos;s (1996) system.</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "8">This comparison will be discussed later.</S>
			<S sid ="78" ssid = "9">Name Alias Recognition In addition to the above general algorithm, a special-purpose alias recognition algorithm is in­ voked for coreference resolution of proper names.5 1.</S>
			<S sid ="79" ssid = "10">INPUT: The input English text is in mixed.</S>
			<S sid ="80" ssid = "11">cases.</S>
			<S sid ="81" ssid = "12">An earlier transd uction phase has rec­ ognized unknown names as well as specific­ type names for persons, locations, or organizat ions using name-internal pattern matching and known name lists.</S>
			<S sid ="82" ssid = "13">2.</S>
			<S sid ="83" ssid = "14">FOR EACH new sentence, FOR EACH unknown.</S>
			<S sid ="84" ssid = "15">name, IF it is an alias or acronym of an­ other name already recognized in the given text, MERGE the two-an alias is a selective sub­ string of the full name (e.g., Colonial for Colo­ nial Beef) , and acronym is a selective sequence of initial characters in the full name (e.g., GM for General Motors).</S>
			<S sid ="85" ssid = "16">Overall Performance The MUC6 FASTUS reference resolution algo­ rithm handled only coreference (i.e., identity of ref­ erence) of proper names, definites, and pronouns.</S>
			<S sid ="86" ssid = "17">These are the &apos;core&apos; anaphoric expression types whose dependencies tend to be constrained by sur­ face textual factors such as locality.</S>
			<S sid ="87" ssid = "18">The MUC6 Coreference Task evaluation included coreference of bare nominals, possessed nominals, and indefi­ nites as well, which the system did not handle be­ cause we didn&apos;t have a reliable algorithm for these mostly &apos;accidental&apos; coreferences that seemed to re­ quire deeper inferences.</S>
			<S sid ="88" ssid = "19">Nevertheless, the system scored a recall of 59% and precision of 72% in the blind evaluation of thirty newspaper articles.</S>
			<S sid ="89" ssid = "20">5 In addition, a specific-type name may be converted into another type in certain linguistic contexts.</S>
			<S sid ="90" ssid = "21">For instance in a subsidiar y of M rs.</S>
			<S sid ="91" ssid = "22">Field, M rs.</S>
			<S sid ="92" ssid = "23">Field is converted fro a person name into a company name.</S>
			<S sid ="93" ssid = "24">Expression Type Number of Occurrences Correctly Resolved Definites 61 28(46%) Pronouns 39 24(62%) Proper Names 32 22(69%) Reflexives 1 1(100%) TOTAL 133 75(56%) Table 1: Core Discou rse Anaphors in Five Articles Grammatical Person lntra/lnter-S Antecedent Number of Occurrences Correctly Resolved 3rd person intra-S 27 21(78%) 3rd person interS 6 2(33%) that interS 1 0(0%) 1st/2nd person interS 5 1(20%) reflexive intra-S 1 1(100%) Table 2: Pronou ns in Five Articles Table 1 shows the system&apos;s performance in re­ solving the core discou rse anaphors in five ran­ domely selected articles from the development set.</S>
			<S sid ="94" ssid = "25">Only five articles were examined here because the process was highly time-consuming.</S>
			<S sid ="95" ssid = "26">The perfor­ mance for each expression type varies widely from article to article because of unexpected features of the articles.</S>
			<S sid ="96" ssid = "27">For instance, one of the five articles is a letter to the editor with a text structure drasti­ cally different from news reports.</S>
			<S sid ="97" ssid = "28">On average, we see that the resolution accuracy (i.e., recall) was the highest for proper names (69%) , followed by pronou ns (62%) and definites (46%).</S>
			<S sid ="98" ssid = "29">There were not enough instances of reflexives to compare.</S>
			<S sid ="99" ssid = "30">Table 2 shows the system&apos;s performance for pro­ nouns broken down by two parameters, gram­ matical person and inter- vs. intrasentential antecedent.</S>
			<S sid ="100" ssid = "31">The system did quite well (78%) with third-person pronouns with intrasentential antecedents, the largest class of such pronouns.</S>
			<S sid ="101" ssid = "32">Part of the pronoun resolution performance here enables a preliminary comparison with the results reported in (1) Lappin and Leass (1994) and (2) Kennedy and Boguraev (1996).</S>
			<S sid ="102" ssid = "33">For the third­ person pronouns and reflexives, the performance was (1) 86% of 560 cases in five computer manu­ als and (2) 75% of 306 cases in twenty-seven Web page texts.</S>
			<S sid ="103" ssid = "34">The present FASTUS system correctly 49 resolved 71% of 34 cases in five newspaper arti des.</S>
			<S sid ="104" ssid = "35">This progressive decline in performance cor­ responds to the progressive decline in the amount of syntactic information in the input to reference resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="105" ssid = "36">To summarize the latter decline, Lap­ pin and Leass (1994) had the following components in their algorithm.</S>
			<S sid ="106" ssid = "37">1.</S>
			<S sid ="107" ssid = "38">INPUT: fully parsed sentences with grammati­.</S>
			<S sid ="108" ssid = "39">cal roles and head-argument and head-adjunct relations 2.</S>
			<S sid ="109" ssid = "40">Intrasentential syntactic filter based on syntactic.</S>
			<S sid ="110" ssid = "41">noncoreference 3.</S>
			<S sid ="111" ssid = "42">Morphological filter based on person, number,.</S>
			<S sid ="112" ssid = "43">and gender features</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Pleonastic pronoun recognition. " number = "4">
			<S sid ="113" ssid = "1">rocals 6.</S>
			<S sid ="114" ssid = "2">Salience computation based on grammatical.</S>
			<S sid ="115" ssid = "3">role, grammatical parallelism, frequency of men­ tion, proximity, and sentence recency 7.</S>
			<S sid ="116" ssid = "4">Global salience computation for noun phrases.</S>
			<S sid ="117" ssid = "5">(NPs) in equivalence classes (with seven salience factors) 8.</S>
			<S sid ="118" ssid = "6">Decision proced ure for choosing among equally.</S>
			<S sid ="119" ssid = "7">preferred candidate antecedents Kennedy and Boguraev (1996) approximated the above components with a poorer syntactic input, which is an output of a part-of-speech tagger with grammatical function information, plus NPs recog­ nized by finite-state patterns and NPs&apos; adjunct and subordination contexts recognized by heuristics.</S>
			<S sid ="120" ssid = "8">With this input, grammatical functions and prece­ dence relations were used to approximate 2 and</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Finite-state patterns approximated 4. Three. " number = "5">
			<S sid ="121" ssid = "1">additional salience factors were used in 7, and a preference for intraclausal antecedents was added in 6; 3 and 8 were the same.</S>
			<S sid ="122" ssid = "2">The present algorithm works with an even poorer syntactic input, as summarized here.</S>
			<S sid ="123" ssid = "3">1.</S>
			<S sid ="124" ssid = "4">INPUT: a set of finite-state approximations of.</S>
			<S sid ="125" ssid = "5">sentence parts, which can be overlapping or dis­ contiguous, with no grammatical function, sub­ ordination, or adjunct information.</S>
			<S sid ="126" ssid = "6">2.</S>
			<S sid ="127" ssid = "7">No disjoint reference filter is used..</S>
			<S sid ="128" ssid = "8">3.</S>
			<S sid ="129" ssid = "9">Morphological filter is used..</S>
			<S sid ="130" ssid = "10">4.</S>
			<S sid ="131" ssid = "11">Pleonastic pronouns are recognized with.</S>
			<S sid ="132" ssid = "12">finite­ state patterns.</S>
			<S sid ="133" ssid = "13">5.</S>
			<S sid ="134" ssid = "14">Reflexives simply limit the search to the.</S>
			<S sid ="135" ssid = "15">current sentence, with no attempt at recognizing coar­ guments.</S>
			<S sid ="136" ssid = "16">No reciprocals are treated.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Salience is approximated by computation. " number = "6">
			<S sid ="137" ssid = "1">based on linear order and recency.</S>
			<S sid ="138" ssid = "2">No grammatical parallelism is recognized.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Equivalence classes correspond to merged. " number = "7">
			<S sid ="139" ssid = "1">entity objects whose &apos;current&apos; positions are always the most recent mentions.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Candidates are deterministically ordered, so. " number = "8">
			<S sid ="140" ssid = "1">no decision procedure is needed.</S>
			<S sid ="141" ssid = "2">Given how little syntactic information is used in FASTUS reference resolution, the 71% accuracy in pronoun resolution is perhaps unexpectedly high.</S>
			<S sid ="142" ssid = "3">This perhaps shows that linear ordering and re­ cency are major indicators of salience, especially because grammatical functions correspond to con­ stituent ordering in English.</S>
			<S sid ="143" ssid = "4">The lack of disjoint reference filter is not the most frequent source of errors, and a coarse grained treatment of reflexives does not hurt very much, mainly because of the in­ frequency of reflexives.</S>
			<S sid ="144" ssid = "5">An Example Analysis In the IE context, the task of entity reference res­ olution is to recognize referential links among par­ tially described entities wit hin and across docu­ ments, which goes beyond third person pronouns and identity of reference.</S>
			<S sid ="145" ssid = "6">The expression types to be handled include bare nominals, possessed nomi­ nals, and indefinites, whose referential links tend to be more &apos;accidental&apos; than textually signaled, and the referential links to be recognized include sub­ set, membership, and part-whole.</S>
			<S sid ="146" ssid = "7">Consider one of the five articles evaluated, the one wit h the most num ber and variety of referential links, for which FASTUS&apos;s performance was the poorest.</S>
			<S sid ="147" ssid = "8">Even for the &apos;core&apos; anaphoric expressions of 20 definites, 14 pronouns, and 7 names limited 50 Expression Type Number of Occurrences Correctly Resolved Definites 25 10(40%) Pronouns 14 10(71%) Bare Nominals 12 3(25%) Proper Names 7 2(29%) Possessed Nominals 6 0(0%) Indefinites 3 0(0%) TOTAL 67 25( 37%) Table 3: Referential Links in the Exam ple to coreference, for which the code was prepared, the recall was only 51%.</S>
			<S sid ="148" ssid = "9">Figu re 1 shows this article annotated with ref­ erential indices.</S>
			<S sid ="149" ssid = "10">The same index indicates corefer­ ence.</S>
			<S sid ="150" ssid = "11">Index subscripts (such as 4a) indicate subset, part, or membership of another expression (e.g., indexed 4).</S>
			<S sid ="151" ssid = "12">The index number ordering, l,...,N, has no significance.</S>
			<S sid ="152" ssid = "13">Each sentence in the TEXT region is numbered with paragraph and sentence numbers, so, for instance, 21 is the first sentence in the second paragraph.</S>
			<S sid ="153" ssid = "14">Note that not all of these referential links need be recognized for each particular IE application.</S>
			<S sid ="154" ssid = "15">However, since reference resolution must consider all of the text for any particular application for the reason mentioned above, it is reasonable to assume that an ideal domain-independent reference resolu­ tion component should be able to recognize all of these.</S>
			<S sid ="155" ssid = "16">Is this a realistic goal, especially in an IE context?</S>
			<S sid ="156" ssid = "17">This question is left open for now.</S>
			<S sid ="157" ssid = "18">Error Analysis Table 3 shows the system&apos;s performance in recog­ nizing the referential links in this article, grouped by referring expression types.</S>
			<S sid ="158" ssid = "19">These exclude the initial mention of each referential chain.</S>
			<S sid ="159" ssid = "20">Notable sources of errors and necessary extensions are sum­ marized for each expression type here.</S>
			<S sid ="160" ssid = "21">Pronouns: Of the four pronoun resolution errors, one is due to a parse error ( American in 71 was incorrectly parsed as a person entity, to which she in 81 was resolved), that in 62 is a discourse deixis (Webber, 1988), beyond the scope of the current approach, and two errors ( it in 31 and its in 71) were due to the left-right ordering of intrasentential candidates.</S>
			<S sid ="161" ssid = "22">Recognition of par- 51 allelism among clause conjuncts and a stricter locality preference for possessive pronouns may help here.</S>
			<S sid ="162" ssid = "23">Definites: Of the fifteen incorrect resolutions of definites, five have nonidentity referential rela­ tionships, and hence were not handled.</S>
			<S sid ="163" ssid = "24">These nonidentity cases must be handled to avoid er­ roneous identity-only resolutions.</S>
			<S sid ="164" ssid = "25">Two errors were due to the failure to distinguish between generic and specific events.</S>
			<S sid ="165" ssid = "26">Token-referring def­ inites ( the union in 82 and the company in 91) were incorrectly resolved to recently mentioned types.</S>
			<S sid ="166" ssid = "27">Three errors were due to the failure to recognize synonyms between, for example, call (3 2) vs. request (31) and campaign (91) vs. strateg y (91).</S>
			<S sid ="167" ssid = "28">Other error sources are a failure in recognizing an appositive pattern (91), the left-right ordering of the candidates in the pre­ vious sentence (92) , and three &apos;bugs&apos;.</S>
			<S sid ="168" ssid = "29">Proper Names: Name alias recognition was un­ usually poor (2 out of 7) because American was parsed as a person-denoting noun.</S>
			<S sid ="169" ssid = "30">The lower­ case print in Patt gibbs also made it difficult to link it with Ms. Gibbs.</S>
			<S sid ="170" ssid = "31">Such parse errors and input anomalies hurt performance.</S>
			<S sid ="171" ssid = "32">Bare Nominals: Since bare nominals were not explicitly resolved, the only correct resolutions (3 out of 12) were due to recognition of ap­ positive patterns.</S>
			<S sid ="172" ssid = "33">How can the other cases be treated?</S>
			<S sid ="173" ssid = "34">We need to understand the discou rse semantics of bare nominals better before devel­ oping an effective algorithm.</S>
			<S sid ="174" ssid = "35">Possessed Nominals: A systematic treatment of possessed nominals is a necessary extension.</S>
			<S sid ="175" ssid = "36">The basic algorithm will look like this-resolve the possessor entity A of the possessed nominal A&apos;s B, then if there is already an entity of type B associated with A mentioned anywhere in the preceding text, then this is the referent of B. Pos­ sessed nominal resolution also requires a &apos;syn­ onymy&apos; computation to resolve, for example, its battle (91) to its corporate campaign (71).</S>
			<S sid ="176" ssid = "37">It also needs &apos;inferences&apos; that rely on multiple suc­ cessful resolutions.</S>
			<S sid ="177" ssid = "38">For instance, her members in 81 must first resolve her to Ms. Gibbs, who HEADLINE: American Airlines1 Calls for Mediation1s In Its1 Union4 Talks2 DOCUMENT DATE: 02/09/87 SOURCE: WALL STREET JOURNAL 11 Amr corp.&apos;s American Airlines1 unit said it1 has called for federal mediation1s in its1 contract talks2 with unions4 representing its1 pilots15 and flight attendants17.</S>
			<S sid ="178" ssid = "39">21 A spokesman for the company1 said American1 officials &quot;felt talks2 had reached a point where mediation 1s would be helpful.&quot;</S>
			<S sid ="179" ssid = "40">22 Negotiations2a with the pilots1s have been going on for 11 months; talks2b with flight attendants17 began six months ago.</S>
			<S sid ="180" ssid = "41">31 The presidents of the Association of Professional Flight Attendants40, which represents American 1&apos;s more than 10,000 flight attendants17, called the request3 for mediation1s &quot;premature&quot; and characterized it3 as a bargaining tactic that could lead to a lockout.</S>
			<S sid ="181" ssid = "42">32 Patt gibbss, presidents of the association 40 , said talks2b with the company 1 seemed to be progressing well and the call3 for mediation 1s came as a surprise.</S>
			<S sid ="182" ssid = "43">41 The major outstanding issue in the negotiations 2b with the flight attendants17 is a two-tier wage scale, in which recent employees&apos; salaries increase on a different scale than the salaries of employees who have worked at american 1 for a longer time.</S>
			<S sid ="183" ssid = "44">42 The union4a wants to narrow the differences between the new scale and the old one.</S>
			<S sid ="184" ssid = "45">51 The company1 declined to comment on the negotiations2b or the outstanding issues.</S>
			<S sid ="185" ssid = "46">52 Representatives for the 5,400-member Allied Pilots Association4b didn&apos;t return phone calls.</S>
			<S sid ="186" ssid = "47">61 Under the Federal Railway Labor Act, [if the mediator1sa fails to bring the two sides7 together and the two sides7 don&apos;t agree to binding arbitration, a 30-day cooling-off period follows]s. 62 After thats, the union7a can strike or the company70 can lock the union70 out.</S>
			<S sid ="187" ssid = "48">71 Ms. Gibbss said that in response to the companyi&apos;s move, hers union4a will be &quot;escalating&quot; its4a &quot;corporate campaign&quot; against American 1 over the next couple of months.</S>
			<S sid ="188" ssid = "49">72 In a corporate campaign10, a union9 tries to get a companys&apos;s financiers, investors, directors and other financial partners to pressure the companys to meet union9 demands.</S>
			<S sid ="189" ssid = "50">81 A corporate campaign10, shes said, appeals to hers members17 because &quot;it10 is a nice, clean way to take a job action, and our4a women11 are hired to be nice.&quot;</S>
			<S sid ="190" ssid = "51">82 the union4a has decided not to strike, shes said.</S>
			<S sid ="191" ssid = "52">91 The union4a has hired a number of professional consultants14 in its4a battle1s with the company1, including Ray Rogersl4a of Corporate Campaign Inc., the New York labor consultant 140 who developed the strategy12 at Geo.</S>
			<S sid ="192" ssid = "53">A. Hormel &amp; Co.13 &apos;s Austin, Minn., meatpacking plant last year.</S>
			<S sid ="193" ssid = "54">92 That campaign12, which included a strike, faltered when the companyu hired new workers and the International Meatpacking Union wrested control of the local union from Rogers14a &apos; supporters.</S>
			<S sid ="194" ssid = "55">Figure 1: Example Ar ticle Annotated with Referential Links 52 is president of the association, and this &apos;associa­ tion&apos; is the Association of Professional Flight At­ tendants.</S>
			<S sid ="195" ssid = "56">After it is understood as &apos;the members of the Association of Professional Flight Atten­ dants,&apos; the coreference with the flight attendants can be inferred.</S>
			<S sid ="196" ssid = "57">Similarly for our women in 81.</S>
			<S sid ="197" ssid = "58">Indefinites: Some indefinites are &apos;coreferential&apos; to generic types, for example, a corporate campaign (72, 81).</S>
			<S sid ="198" ssid = "59">Given the difficulty in distinguishing between generic and specific event descriptions, it is u nclear whether it will ever be treated in a systematic way.</S>
			<S sid ="199" ssid = "60">Conclusions In an operational end-to-end discourse understand­ ing system, a reference resolution component must work with input data containing parse errors, lex­ icon gaps, and mistakes made by earlier reference resolution.</S>
			<S sid ="200" ssid = "61">In a state-of-the-art IE system such as SRI&apos;s FASTUS, reference resolution must work wit h considerably impoverished syntactic analysis of the input sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="201" ssid = "62">The present reference res­ olution approach within an IE system is robust and efficient, and performs pronoun resolution to an almost comparable level with a high-accuracy algorithm in the literature.</S>
			<S sid ="202" ssid = "63">Desirable extensions include nonidentity referential relationships, treat­ ments of bare nominals, possessed nominals, and indefinites, type-token distinctions, and recogni­ tion of synonyms.</S>
			<S sid ="203" ssid = "64">Another future direction is to turn this component into a corpus-based statisti­ cal approach using the relevant factors identified in the rule-based approach.</S>
			<S sid ="204" ssid = "65">The need for a large tagged corpus may be difficult to satisfy, however.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acknowledgment">
			<S sid ="205" ssid = "66">This work was in part supported by U.S. govern­.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
