<PAPER>
  <S sid="0">Transformation-Based-Error-Driven Learning And Natural Language Processing: A Case Study In Part-Of-Speech Tagging</S>
  <ABSTRACT>
    <S sid="1" ssid="1">Recently, there has been a rebirth of empiricism in the field of natural language processing.</S>
    <S sid="2" ssid="2">Manual encoding of linguistic information is being challenged by automated corpus-based learning as a method of providing a natural language processing system with linguistic knowledge.</S>
    <S sid="3" ssid="3">Although corpus-based approaches have been successful in many different areas of natural language processing, it is often the case that these methods capture the linguistic information they are modelling indirectly in large opaque tables of statistics.</S>
    <S sid="4" ssid="4">This can make it difficult to analyze, understand and improve the ability of these approaches to model underlying linguistic behavior.</S>
    <S sid="5" ssid="5">In this paper, we will describe a simple rule-based approach to automated learning of linguistic knowledge.</S>
    <S sid="6" ssid="6">This approach has been shown for a number of tasks to capture information in a clearer and more direct fashion without a compromise in performance.</S>
    <S sid="7" ssid="7">We present a detailed case study of this learning method applied to part-of-speech tagging.</S>
  </ABSTRACT>
  <SECTION title="" number="1">
    <S sid="8" ssid="1">Recently, there has been a rebirth of empiricism in the field of natural language processing.</S>
    <S sid="9" ssid="2">Manual encoding of linguistic information is being challenged by automated corpus-based learning as a method of providing a natural language processing system with linguistic knowledge.</S>
    <S sid="10" ssid="3">Although corpus-based approaches have been successful in many different areas of natural language processing, it is often the case that these methods capture the linguistic information they are modelling indirectly in large opaque tables of statistics.</S>
    <S sid="11" ssid="4">This can make it difficult to analyze, understand and improve the ability of these approaches to model underlying linguistic behavior.</S>
    <S sid="12" ssid="5">In this paper, we will describe a simple rule-based approach to automated learning of linguistic knowledge.</S>
    <S sid="13" ssid="6">This approach has been shown for a number of tasks to capture information in a clearer and more direct fashion without a compromise in performance.</S>
    <S sid="14" ssid="7">We present a detailed case study of this learning method applied to part-of-speech tagging.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="1." number="2">
    <S sid="15" ssid="1">It has recently become clear that automatically extracting linguistic information from a sample text corpus can be an extremely powerful method of overcoming the linguistic knowledge acquisition bottleneck inhibiting the creation of robust and accurate natural language processing systems.</S>
    <S sid="16" ssid="2">A number of part-of-speech taggers are readily available and widely used, all trained and retrainable on text corpora (Church 1988; Cutting et al. 1992; Brill 1992; Weischedel et al.</S>
    <S sid="17" ssid="3">1993).</S>
    <S sid="18" ssid="4">Endemic structural ambiguity, which can lead to such difficulties as trying to cope with the many thousands of possible parses that a grammar can assign to a sentence, can be greatly reduced by adding empirically derived probabilities to grammar rules (Fujisaki et al. 1989; Sharman, Jelinek, and Mercer 1990; Black et al.</S>
    <S sid="19" ssid="5">1993) and by computing statistical measures of lexical association (Hindle and Rooth 1993).</S>
    <S sid="20" ssid="6">Word-sense disambiguation, a problem that once seemed out of reach for systems without a great deal of handcrafted linguistic and world knowledge, can now in some cases be done with high accuracy when all information is derived automatically from corpora (Brown, Lai, and Mercer 1991; Yarowsky 1992; Gale, Church, and Yarowsky 1992; Bruce and Wiebe 1994).</S>
    <S sid="21" ssid="7">An effort has recently been undertaken to create automated machine translation systems in which the linguistic information needed for translation is extracted automatically from aligned corpora (Brown et al. 1990).</S>
    <S sid="22" ssid="8">These are just a few of the many recent applications of corpus-based techniques in natural language processing.</S>
    <S sid="23" ssid="9">Along with great research advances, the infrastructure is in place for this line of research to grow even stronger, with on-line corpora, the grist of the corpus-based natural language processing grindstone, getting bigger and better and becoming more readily available.</S>
    <S sid="24" ssid="10">There are a number of efforts worldwide to manually annotate large corpora with linguistic information, including parts of speech, phrase structure and predicate-argument structure (e.g., the Penn Treebank and the British National Corpus (Marcus, Santorini, and Marcinkiewicz 1993; Leech, Garside, and Bryant 1994)).</S>
    <S sid="25" ssid="11">A vast amount of on-line text is now available, and much more will become available in the future.</S>
    <S sid="26" ssid="12">Useful tools, such as large aligned corpora (e.g., the aligned Hansards (Gale and Church 1991)) and semantic word hierarchies (e.g., Wordnet (Miller 1990)), have also recently become available.</S>
    <S sid="27" ssid="13">Corpus-based methods are often able to succeed while ignoring the true complexities of language, banking on the fact that complex linguistic phenomena can often be indirectly observed through simple epiphenomena.</S>
    <S sid="28" ssid="14">For example, one could accurately assign a part-of-speech tag to the word race in (1-3) without any reference to phrase structure or constituent movement: One would only have to realize that, usually, a word one or two words to the right of a modal is a verb and not a noun.</S>
    <S sid="29" ssid="15">An exception to this generalization arises when the word is also one word to the right of a determiner.</S>
    <S sid="30" ssid="16">It is an exciting discovery that simple stochastic n-gram taggers can obtain very high rates of tagging accuracy simply by observing fixed-length word sequences, without recourse to the underlying linguistic structure.</S>
    <S sid="31" ssid="17">However, in order to make progress in corpus-based natural language processing, we must become better aware of just what cues to linguistic structure are being captured and where these approximations to the true underlying phenomena fail.</S>
    <S sid="32" ssid="18">With many of the current corpus-based approaches to natural language processing, this is a nearly impossible task.</S>
    <S sid="33" ssid="19">Consider the part-of-speech tagging example above.</S>
    <S sid="34" ssid="20">In a stochastic n-gram tagger, the information about words that follow modals would be hidden deeply in the thousands or tens of thousands of contextual probabilities (P(Tag, I Tagi_iTag1_2)) and the result of multiplying different combinations of these probabilities together.</S>
    <S sid="35" ssid="21">Below, we describe a new approach to corpus-based natural language processing, called transformation-based error-driven learning.</S>
    <S sid="36" ssid="22">This algorithm has been applied to a number of natural language problems, including part-of-speech tagging, prepositional phrase attachment disambiguation, and syntactic parsing (Brill 1992; Brill 1993a; Brill 1993b; Brill and Resnik 1994; Brill 1994).</S>
    <S sid="37" ssid="23">We have also recently begun exploring the use of this technique for letter-to-sound generation and for building pronunciation networks for speech recognition.</S>
    <S sid="38" ssid="24">In this approach, the learned linguistic information is represented in a concise and easily understood form.</S>
    <S sid="39" ssid="25">This property should make transformation-based learning a useful tool for further exploring linguistic modeling and attempting to discover ways of more tightly coupling the underlying linguistic systems and our approximating models.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="2." number="3">
    <S sid="40" ssid="1">Figure 1 illustrates how transformation-based error-driven learning works.</S>
    <S sid="41" ssid="2">First, unannotated text is passed through an initial-state annotator.</S>
    <S sid="42" ssid="3">The initial-state annotator can range in complexity from assigning random structure to assigning the output of a sophisticated manually created annotator.</S>
    <S sid="43" ssid="4">In part-of-speech tagging, various initialstate annotators have been used, including: the output of a stochastic n-gram tagger; labelling all words with their most likely tag as indicated in the training corpus; and naively labelling all words as nouns.</S>
    <S sid="44" ssid="5">For syntactic parsing, we have explored initialstate annotations ranging from the output of a sophisticated parser to random tree structure with random nonterminal labels.</S>
    <S sid="45" ssid="6">Once text has been passed through the initial-state annotator, it is then compared to the truth.</S>
    <S sid="46" ssid="7">A manually annotated corpus is used as our reference for truth.</S>
    <S sid="47" ssid="8">An ordered list of transformations is learned that can be applied to the output of the initial-state annotator to make it better resemble the truth.</S>
    <S sid="48" ssid="9">There are two components to a transformation: a rewrite rule and a triggering environment.</S>
    <S sid="49" ssid="10">An example of a rewrite rule for part-of-speech tagging is: and an example of a triggering environment is: The preceding word is a determiner.</S>
    <S sid="50" ssid="11">Taken together, the transformation with this rewrite rule and triggering environment when applied to the word can would correctly change the mistagged: where A, B and C can be either terminals or nonterminals.</S>
    <S sid="51" ssid="12">One possible set of triggering environments is any combination of words, part-of-speech tags, and nonterminal labels within and adjacent to the subtree.</S>
    <S sid="52" ssid="13">Using this rewrite rule and the triggering environment A = the, the bracketing: ( the ( boy ate ) ) would become: ( ( the boy) ate) In all of the applications we have examined to date, the following greedy search is applied for deriving a list of transformations: at each iteration of learning, the transformation is found whose application results in the best score according to the objective function being used; that transformation is then added to the ordered transformation list and the training corpus is updated by applying the learned transformation.</S>
    <S sid="53" ssid="14">Learning continues until no transformation can be found whose application results in an improvement to the annotated corpus.</S>
    <S sid="54" ssid="15">Other more sophisticated search techniques could be used, such as simulated annealing or learning with a look-ahead window, but we have not yet explored these alternatives.</S>
    <S sid="55" ssid="16">Figure 2 shows an example of learning transformations.</S>
    <S sid="56" ssid="17">In this example, we assume there are only four possible transformations, Ti through T4, and that the objective function is the total number of errors.</S>
    <S sid="57" ssid="18">The unannotated training corpus is processed by the initial-state annotator, and this results in an annotated corpus with 5,100 errors, determined by comparing the output of the initial-state annotator with the manually derived annotations for this corpus.</S>
    <S sid="58" ssid="19">Next, we apply each of the possible transformations in turn and score the resulting annotated corpus.'</S>
    <S sid="59" ssid="20">In this example, applying transformation T2 results in the largest reduction of errors, so 12 is learned as the first transformation.</S>
    <S sid="60" ssid="21">T2 is then applied to the entire corpus, and learning continues.</S>
    <S sid="61" ssid="22">At this stage of learning, transformation 13 results in the largest reduction of error, so it is learned as the second transformation.</S>
    <S sid="62" ssid="23">After applying the initial-state annotator, followed by T2 and then T3, no further reduction in errors can be obtained from applying any of the transformations, so learning stops.</S>
    <S sid="63" ssid="24">To annotate fresh text, this text is first annotated by the initial-state annotator, followed by the application of transformation T2 and then by the application of T3.</S>
    <S sid="64" ssid="25">To define a specific application of transformation-based learning, one must specify the following: In cases where the application of a particular transformation in one environment could affect its application in another environment, two additional parameters must be specified: the order in which transformations are applied to a corpus, and whether a transformation is applied immediately or only after the entire corpus has been examined for triggering environments.</S>
    <S sid="65" ssid="26">For example, take the sequence:</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="AAAAAA" number="4">
    <S sid="66" ssid="1">and the transformation: If the effect of the application of a transformation is not written out until the entire file has been processed for that one transformation, then regardless of the order of processing the output will be: ABBBBB, since the triggering environment of a transformation is always checked before that transformation is applied to any surrounding objects in the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="67" ssid="2">If the effect of a transformation is recorded immediately, then processing the string left to right would result in: ABABAB, whereas processing right to left would result in: ABBBBB.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="3." number="5">
    <S sid="68" ssid="1">The technique employed by the learner is somewhat similar to that used in decision trees (Breiman et al. 1984; Quinlan 1986; Quinlan and Rivest 1989).</S>
    <S sid="69" ssid="2">A decision tree is trained on a set of preclassified entities and outputs a set of questions that can be asked about an entity to determine its proper classification.</S>
    <S sid="70" ssid="3">Decision trees are built by finding the question whose resulting partition is the purest,2 splitting the training data according to that question, and then recursively reapplying this procedure on each resulting subset.</S>
    <S sid="71" ssid="4">We first show that the set of classifications that can be provided via decision trees is a proper subset of those that can be provided via transformation lists (an ordered list of transformation-based rules), given the same set of primitive questions.</S>
    <S sid="72" ssid="5">We then give some practical differences between the two learning methods.</S>
    <S sid="73" ssid="6">We prove here that for a fixed set of primitive queries, any binary decision tree can be converted into a transformation list.</S>
    <S sid="74" ssid="7">Extending the proof beyond binary trees is straightforward.</S>
    <S sid="75" ssid="8">Given the following primitive decision tree, where the classification is A if the answer to the query X? is yes, and the classification is B if the answer is no: Brill Transformation-Based Error-Driven Learning this tree can be converted into the following transformation list: Assume that two decision trees T1 and T2 have corresponding transformation lists L1 and L2.</S>
    <S sid="76" ssid="9">Assume that the arbitrary label names chosen in constructing Ll are not used in L2, and that those in L2 are not used in L1.</S>
    <S sid="77" ssid="10">Given a new decision tree T3 constructed from T1 and T2 as follows: X? we construct a new transformation list L3.</S>
    <S sid="78" ssid="11">Assume the first transformation in L1 is: Label with S' and the first transformation in L2 is: Label with S&amp;quot; The first three transformations in L3 Will then be: followed by all of the rules in L1 other than the first rule, followed by all of the rules in L2 other than the first rule.</S>
    <S sid="79" ssid="12">The resulting transformation list will first label an item as S' if X is true, or as S&amp;quot; if X is false.</S>
    <S sid="80" ssid="13">Next, the tranformations from L1 will be applied if X is true, since S' is the initial-state label for L1.</S>
    <S sid="81" ssid="14">If X is false, the transformations from L2 will be applied, because S&amp;quot; is the initial-state label for L2.</S>
    <S sid="82" ssid="15">0 We show here that there exist transformation lists for which no equivalent decision trees exist, for a fixed set of primitive queries.</S>
    <S sid="83" ssid="16">The following classification problem is one example.</S>
    <S sid="84" ssid="17">Given a sequence of characters, classify a character based on whether the position index of a character is divisible by 4, querying only using a context of two characters to the left of the character being classified.</S>
    <S sid="85" ssid="18">Assuming transformations are applied left to right on the sequence, the above classification problem can be solved for sequences of arbitrary length if the effect of a transformation is written out immediately, or for sequences up to any prespecified length if a transformation is carried out only after all triggering environments in the corpus are checked.</S>
    <S sid="86" ssid="19">We present the proof for the former case.</S>
    <S sid="87" ssid="20">Given the input sequence: the underlined characters should be classified as true because their indices are 0, 4, and 8.</S>
    <S sid="88" ssid="21">To see why a decision tree could not perform this classification, regardless of order of classification, note that, for the two characters before both A3 and A4, both the characters and their classifications are the same, although these two characters should be classified differently.</S>
    <S sid="89" ssid="22">Below is a transformation list for performing this classification.</S>
    <S sid="90" ssid="23">Once again, we assume transformations are applied left to right and that the result of a transformation is written out immediately, so that the result of applying transformation x to character a, will always be known when applying transformation x to ai+i.</S>
    <S sid="91" ssid="24">The extra power of transformation lists comes from the fact that intermediate results from the classification of one object are reflected in the current label of that object, thereby making this intermediate information available for use in classifying other objects.</S>
    <S sid="92" ssid="25">This is not the case for decision trees, where the outcome of questions asked is saved implicitly by the current location within the tree.</S>
    <S sid="93" ssid="26">There are a number of practical differences between transformation-based error-driven learning and learning decision trees.</S>
    <S sid="94" ssid="27">One difference is that when training a decision tree, each time the depth of the tree is increased, the average amount of training material available per node at that new depth is halved (for a binary tree).</S>
    <S sid="95" ssid="28">In transformationbased learning, the entire training corpus is used for finding all transformations.</S>
    <S sid="96" ssid="29">Therefore, this method is not subject to the sparse data problems that arise as the depth of the decision tree being learned increases.</S>
    <S sid="97" ssid="30">Transformations are ordered, with later transformations being dependent upon the outcome of applying earlier transformations.</S>
    <S sid="98" ssid="31">This allows intermediate results in 550 &#8226; Brill Transformation-Based Error-Driven Learning classifying one object to be available in classifying other objects.</S>
    <S sid="99" ssid="32">For instance, whether the previous word is tagged as to-infinitival or to-preposition may be a good cue for determining the part of speech of a word.'</S>
    <S sid="100" ssid="33">If, initially, the word to is not reliably tagged everywhere in the corpus with its proper tag (or not tagged at all), then this cue will be unreliable.</S>
    <S sid="101" ssid="34">The transformation-based learner will delay positing a transformation triggered by the tag of the word to until other transformations have resulted in a more reliable tagging of this word in the corpus.</S>
    <S sid="102" ssid="35">For a decision tree to take advantage of this information, any word whose outcome is dependent upon the tagging of to would need the entire decision tree structure for the proper classification of each occurrence of to built into its decision tree path.</S>
    <S sid="103" ssid="36">If the classification of to were dependent upon the classification of yet another word, this would have to be built into the decision tree as well.</S>
    <S sid="104" ssid="37">Unlike decision trees, in transformation-based learning, intermediate classification results are available and can be used as classification progresses.</S>
    <S sid="105" ssid="38">Even if decision trees are applied to a corpus in a left-to-right fashion, they are allowed only one pass in which to properly classify.</S>
    <S sid="106" ssid="39">Since a transformation list is a processor and not a classifier, it can readily be used as a postprocessor to any annotation system.</S>
    <S sid="107" ssid="40">In addition to annotating from scratch, rules can be learned to improve the performance of a mature annotation system by using the mature system as the initial-state annotator.</S>
    <S sid="108" ssid="41">This can have the added advantage that the list of transformations learned using a mature annotation system as the initial-state annotator provides a readable description or classification of the errors the mature system makes, thereby aiding in the refinement of that system.</S>
    <S sid="109" ssid="42">The fact that it is a processor gives a transformation-based learner greater than the classifier-based decision tree.</S>
    <S sid="110" ssid="43">For example, in applying transformation-based learning to parsing, a rule can apply any structural change to a tree.</S>
    <S sid="111" ssid="44">In tagging, a rule such as: Change the tag of the current word to X, and of the previous word to Y, if Z holds can easily be handled in the processor-based system, whereas it would be difficult to handle in a classification system.</S>
    <S sid="112" ssid="45">In transformation-based learning, the objective function used in training is the same as that used for evaluation, whenever this is feasible.</S>
    <S sid="113" ssid="46">In a decision tree, using system accuracy as an objective function for training typically results in poor performance' and some measure of node purity, such as entropy reduction, is used instead.</S>
    <S sid="114" ssid="47">The direct correlation between rules and performance improvement in transformation-based learning can make the learned rules more readily interpretable than decision tree rules for increasing population purity.'</S>
    <S sid="115" ssid="48">In this section we describe the practical application of transformation-based learning to part-of-speech tagging.'</S>
    <S sid="116" ssid="49">Part-of-speech tagging is a good application to test the learner, for several reasons.</S>
    <S sid="117" ssid="50">There are a number of large tagged corpora available, allowing for a variety of experiments to be run.</S>
    <S sid="118" ssid="51">Part-of-speech tagging is an active area of research; a great deal of work has been done in this area over the past few years (e.g., Jelinek 1985; Church 1988; Derose 1988; Hindle 1989; DeMarcken 1990; Merialdo 1994; Brill 1992; Black et al. 1992; Cutting et al.</S>
    <S sid="119" ssid="52">1992; Kupiec 1992; Charniak et al. 1993; Weischedel et al.</S>
    <S sid="120" ssid="53">1993; Schutze and Singer 1994).</S>
    <S sid="121" ssid="54">Part-of-speech tagging is also a very practical application, with uses in many areas, including speech recognition and generation, machine translation, parsing, information retrieval and lexicography.</S>
    <S sid="122" ssid="55">Insofar as tagging can be seen as a prototypical problem in lexical ambiguity, advances in part-of-speech tagging could readily translate to progress in other areas of lexical, and perhaps structural, ambiguity, such as wordsense disambiguation and prepositional phrase attachment disambiguation.'</S>
    <S sid="123" ssid="56">Also, it is possible to cast a number of other useful problems as part-of-speech tagging problems, such as letter-to-sound translation (Huang, Son-Bell, and Baggett 1994) and building pronunciation networks for speech recognition.</S>
    <S sid="124" ssid="57">Recently, a method has been proposed for using part-of-speech tagging techniques as a method for parsing with lexicalized grammars (Joshi and Srinivas 1994).</S>
    <S sid="125" ssid="58">When automated part-of-speech tagging was initially explored (Klein and Simmons 1963; Harris 1962), people manually engineered rules for tagging, sometimes with the aid of a corpus.</S>
    <S sid="126" ssid="59">As large corpora became available, it became clear that simple Markov-model based stochastic taggers that were automatically trained could achieve high rates of tagging accuracy (Jelinek 1985).</S>
    <S sid="127" ssid="60">Markov-model based taggers assign to a sentence the tag sequence that maximizes Prob(word J tag)*Prob(tag I previous n tags).</S>
    <S sid="128" ssid="61">These probabilities can be estimated directly from a manually tagged corpus.'</S>
    <S sid="129" ssid="62">These stochastic taggers have a number of advantages over the manually built taggers, including obviating the need for laborious manual rule construction, and possibly capturing useful information that may not have been noticed by the human engineer.</S>
    <S sid="130" ssid="63">However, stochastic taggers have the disadvantage that linguistic information is captured only indirectly, in large tables of statistics.</S>
    <S sid="131" ssid="64">Almost all recent work in developing automatically trained part-of-speech taggers has been on further exploring Markovmodel based tagging (Jelinek 1985; Church 1988; Derose 1988; DeMarcken 1990; Merialdo 1994; Cutting et al. 1992; Kupiec 1992; Charniak et al.</S>
    <S sid="132" ssid="65">1993; Weischedel et al. 1993; Schutze and Singer 1994).</S>
    <S sid="133" ssid="66">Transformation-based part of speech tagging works as follows.'</S>
    <S sid="134" ssid="67">The initial-state annotator assigns each word its most likely tag as indicated in the training corpus.</S>
    <S sid="135" ssid="68">The method used for initially tagging unknown words will be described in a later section.</S>
    <S sid="136" ssid="69">An ordered list of transformations is then learned, to improve tagging accuracy based on contextual cues.</S>
    <S sid="137" ssid="70">These transformations alter the tagging of a word from X to Y iff In taggers based on Markov models, the lexicon consists of probabilities of the somewhat counterintuitive but proper form P(WORD I TAG).</S>
    <S sid="138" ssid="71">In the transformationbased tagger, the lexicon is simply a list of all tags seen for a word in the training corpus, with one tag labeled as the most likely.</S>
    <S sid="139" ssid="72">Below we show a lexical entry for the word half in the transformation-based tagger.1&#176; half: CD DT JJ NN PDT RB VB This entry lists the seven tags seen for half in the training corpus, with NN marked as the most likely.</S>
    <S sid="140" ssid="73">Below are the lexical entries for half in a Markov model tagger, extracted from the same corpus: It is difficult to make much sense of these entries in isolation; they have to be viewed in the context of the many contextual probabilities.</S>
    <S sid="141" ssid="74">First, we will describe a nonlexicalized version of the tagger, where transformation templates do not make reference to specific words.</S>
    <S sid="142" ssid="75">In the nonlexicalized tagger, the transformation templates we use are: Change tag a to tag b when: where a, b, z and w are variables over the set of parts of speech.</S>
    <S sid="143" ssid="76">To learn a transformation, the learner, in essence, tries out every possible transformation,&amp;quot; and counts the number of tagging errors after each one is applied.</S>
    <S sid="144" ssid="77">After all possible transformations have been tried, the transformation that resulted in the greatest error reduction is chosen.</S>
    <S sid="145" ssid="78">Learning stops when no transformations can be found whose application reduces errors beyond some prespecified threshold.</S>
    <S sid="146" ssid="79">In the experiments described below, processing was done left to right.</S>
    <S sid="147" ssid="80">For each transformation application, all triggering environments are first found in the corpus, and then the transformation triggered by each triggering environment is carried out.</S>
    <S sid="148" ssid="81">The search is data-driven, so only a very small percentage of possible transformations really need be examined.</S>
    <S sid="149" ssid="82">In figure 3, we give pseudocode for the learning algorithm in the case where there is only one transformation template: In each learning iteration, the entire training corpus is examined once for every pair of tags X and Y, finding the best transformation whose rewrite changes tag X to tag Y.</S>
    <S sid="150" ssid="83">For every word in the corpus whose environment matches the triggering environment, if the word has tag X and X is the correct tag, then making this transformation will result in an additional tagging error, so we increment the number of errors caused when making the transformation given the part-of-speech tag of the previous word (lines 8 and 9).</S>
    <S sid="151" ssid="84">If X is the current tag and Y is the correct tag, then the transformation will result in one less error, so we increment the number of improvements caused when making the transformation given the part-of-speech tag of the previous word (lines 6 and 7).</S>
    <S sid="152" ssid="85">In certain cases, a significant increase in speed for training the transformationbased tagger can be obtained by indexing in the corpus where different transformations can and do apply.</S>
    <S sid="153" ssid="86">For a description of a fast index-based training algorithm, see Ramshaw and Marcus (1994).</S>
    <S sid="154" ssid="87">In figure 4, we list the first twenty transformations learned from training on the Penn Treebank Wall Street Journal Corpus (Marcus, Santorini, and Marcinkiewicz 1993).12 The first transformation states that a noun should be changed to a verb if 12 Version 0.5 of the Penn Treebank was used in all experiments reported in this paper. the previous tag is TO, as in: to/TO conflictINNVB with.</S>
    <S sid="155" ssid="88">The second transformation fixes a tagging such as: might/MD vanishIVBP&#8212;*VB.</S>
    <S sid="156" ssid="89">The third fixes might/MD not reply/NN&#8212;VB.</S>
    <S sid="157" ssid="90">The tenth transformation is for the token 's, which is a separate token in the Penn Treebank.</S>
    <S sid="158" ssid="91">'s is most frequently used as a possessive ending, but after a personal pronoun, it is a verb (John 's, compared to he 's).</S>
    <S sid="159" ssid="92">The transformations changing IN to WDT are for tagging the word that, to determine in which environments that is being used as a synonym of which.</S>
    <S sid="160" ssid="93">In general, no relationships between words have been directly encoded in stochastic n-gram taggers.'</S>
    <S sid="161" ssid="94">In the Markov model typically used for stochastic tagging, state transition probabilities (P(Tag, Tag,_i .Tagi_,,)) express the likelihood of a tag immediately following n other tags, and emit probabilities (P(Wordi I Tag,)) express the likelihood of a word, given a tag.</S>
    <S sid="162" ssid="95">Many useful relationships, such as that between a word and the previous word, or between a tag and the following word, are not directly captured by Markov-model based taggers.</S>
    <S sid="163" ssid="96">The same is true of the nonlexicalized transformation-based tagger, where transformation templates do not make reference to words.</S>
    <S sid="164" ssid="97">To remedy this problem, we extend the transformation-based tagger by adding contextual transformations that can make reference to words as well as part-of-speech tags.</S>
    <S sid="165" ssid="98">The transformation templates we add are: Change tag a to tag b when: 8.</S>
    <S sid="166" ssid="99">The current word is w, the preceding (following) word is w2 and the preceding (following) tag is t. where w and x are variables over all words in the training corpus, and z and t are variables over all parts of speech.</S>
    <S sid="167" ssid="100">Below we list two lexicalized transformations that were learned, training once again on the Wall Street Journal.</S>
    <S sid="168" ssid="101">Change the tag: The Penn Treebank tagging style manual specifies that in the collocation as ...as, the first as is tagged as an adverb and the second is tagged as a preposition.</S>
    <S sid="169" ssid="102">Since as is most frequently tagged as a preposition in the training corpus, the initial-state tagger will mistag the phrase as tall as as: The first lexicalized transformation corrects this mistagging.</S>
    <S sid="170" ssid="103">Note that a bigram tagger trained on our training set would not correctly tag the first occurrence of as.</S>
    <S sid="171" ssid="104">Although adverbs are more likely than prepositions to follow some verb form tags, the fact that P(as I IN) is much greater than P(as I RB), and P(JJ I IN) is much greater than P(JJ RB) lead to as being incorrectly tagged as a preposition by a stochastic tagger.</S>
    <S sid="172" ssid="105">A trigram tagger will correctly tag this collocation in some instances, due to the fact that P(IN I RB JJ) is greater than P(IN I IN JJ), but the outcome will be highly dependent upon the context in which this collocation appears.</S>
    <S sid="173" ssid="106">The second transformation arises from the fact that when a verb appears in a context such as We do n't eat or We did n't usually drink, the verb is in base form.</S>
    <S sid="174" ssid="107">A stochastic trigram tagger would have to capture this linguistic information indirectly from frequency counts of all trigrams of the form shown in figure 5 (where a star can match any part-of-speech tag) and from the fact that P(n't I RB) is fairly high.</S>
    <S sid="175" ssid="108">In Weischedel et al. (1993), results are given when training and testing a Markovmodel based tagger on the Penn Treebank Tagged Wall Street journal Corpus.</S>
    <S sid="176" ssid="109">They cite results making the closed vocabulary assumption that all possible tags for all words in the test set are known.</S>
    <S sid="177" ssid="110">When training contextual probabilities on one million words, an accuracy of 96.7% was achieved.</S>
    <S sid="178" ssid="111">Accuracy dropped to 96.3% when contextual probabilities were trained on 64,000 words.</S>
    <S sid="179" ssid="112">We trained the transformation-based tagger on the same corpus, making the same closed-vocabulary assumption.'</S>
    <S sid="180" ssid="113">When training contextual rules on 600,000 words, an accuracy of 97.2% was achieved on a separate 150,000 word test set.</S>
    <S sid="181" ssid="114">When the training set was reduced to 64,000 words, accuracy dropped to 96.7%.</S>
    <S sid="182" ssid="115">The transformation-based learner achieved better performance, despite the fact that contextual information was captured in a small number of simple nonstochastic rules, as opposed to 10,000 contextual probabilities that were learned by the stochastic tagger.</S>
    <S sid="183" ssid="116">These results are summarized in table 1.</S>
    <S sid="184" ssid="117">When training on 600,000 words, a total of 447 transformations were learned.</S>
    <S sid="185" ssid="118">However, transformations toward the end of the list contribute very little to accuracy: applying only the first 200 learned transformations to the test set achieves an accuracy of 97.0%; applying the first 100 gives an accuracy of 96.8%.</S>
    <S sid="186" ssid="119">To match the 96.7% accuracy achieved by the stochastic tagger when it was trained on one million words, only the first 82 transformations are needed.</S>
    <S sid="187" ssid="120">To see whether lexicalized transformations were contributing to the transformationbased tagger accuracy rate, we first trained the tagger using the nonlexical transformation template subset, then ran exactly the same test.</S>
    <S sid="188" ssid="121">Accuracy of that tagger was 97.0%.</S>
    <S sid="189" ssid="122">Adding lexicalized transformations resulted in a 6.7% decrease in the error rate (see table 1).16 We found it a bit surprising that the addition of lexicalized transformations did not result in a much greater improvement in performance.</S>
    <S sid="190" ssid="123">When transformations are allowed to make reference to words and word pairs, some relevant information is probably missed due to sparse data.</S>
    <S sid="191" ssid="124">We are currently exploring the possibility of incorporating word classes into the rule-based learner, in hopes of overcoming this problem.</S>
    <S sid="192" ssid="125">The idea is quite simple.</S>
    <S sid="193" ssid="126">Given any source of word class information, such as WordNet (Miller 1990), the learner is extended such that a rule is allowed to make reference to parts of speech, words, and word classes, allowing for rules such as This approach has already been successfully applied to a system for prepositional phrase attachment disambiguation (Brill and Resnik 1994).</S>
    <S sid="194" ssid="127">So far, we have not addressed the problem of unknown words.</S>
    <S sid="195" ssid="128">As stated above, the initial-state annotator for tagging assigns all words their most likely tag, as indicated in a training corpus.</S>
    <S sid="196" ssid="129">Below we show how a transformation-based approach can be taken for tagging unknown words, by automatically learning cues to predict the most likely tag for words not seen in the training corpus.</S>
    <S sid="197" ssid="130">If the most likely tag for unknown words can be assigned with high accuracy, then the contextual rules can be used to improve accuracy, as described above.</S>
    <S sid="198" ssid="131">In the transformation-based unknown-word tagger, the initial-state annotator naively assumes the most likely tag for an unknown word is &amp;quot;proper noun&amp;quot; if the word is capitalized and &amp;quot;common noun&amp;quot; otherwise.'</S>
    <S sid="199" ssid="132">Below, we list the set of allowable transformations.</S>
    <S sid="200" ssid="133">Change the tag of an unknown word (from X) to Y if: 17 If we change the tagger to tag all unknown words as common nouns, then a number of rules are learned of the form: change tag to proper noun if the prefix is &amp;quot;E&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;A&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;B&amp;quot;, etc., since the learner is not provided with the concept of upper case in its set of transformation templates.</S>
    <S sid="201" ssid="134">The first 20 transformations for unknown words.</S>
    <S sid="202" ssid="135">An unannotated text can be used to check the conditions in all of the above transformation templates.</S>
    <S sid="203" ssid="136">Annotated text is necessary in training to measure the effect of transformations on tagging accuracy.</S>
    <S sid="204" ssid="137">Since the goal is to label each lexical entry for new words as accurately as possible, accuracy is measured on a per type and not a per token basis.</S>
    <S sid="205" ssid="138">Figure 6 shows the first 20 transformations learned for tagging unknown words in the Wall Street Journal corpus.</S>
    <S sid="206" ssid="139">As an example of how rules can correct errors generated by prior rules, note that applying the first transformation will result in the mistagging of the word actress.</S>
    <S sid="207" ssid="140">The 18th learned rule fixes this problem.</S>
    <S sid="208" ssid="141">This rule states: suffix ss.</S>
    <S sid="209" ssid="142">Keep in mind that no specific affixes are prespecified.</S>
    <S sid="210" ssid="143">A transformation can make reference to any string of characters up to a bounded length.</S>
    <S sid="211" ssid="144">So while the first rule specifies the English suffix &amp;quot;s&amp;quot;, the rule learner was not constrained from considering such nonsensical rules as: Also, absolutely no English-specific information (such as an affix list) need be prespecified in the learner.&amp;quot; We then ran the following experiment using 1.1 million words of the Penn Treebank Tagged Wall Street Journal Corpus.</S>
    <S sid="212" ssid="145">Of these, 950,000 words were used for training and 150,000 words were used for testing.</S>
    <S sid="213" ssid="146">Annotations of the test corpus were not used in any way to train the system.</S>
    <S sid="214" ssid="147">From the 950,000 word training corpus, 350,000 words were used to learn rules for tagging unknown words, and 600,000 words were used to learn contextual rules; 243 rules were learned for tagging unknown words, and 447 contextual tagging rules were learned.</S>
    <S sid="215" ssid="148">Unknown word accuracy on the test corpus was 82.2%, and overall tagging accuracy on the test corpus was 96.6%.</S>
    <S sid="216" ssid="149">To our knowledge, this is the highest overall tagging accuracy ever quoted on the Penn Treebank Corpus when making the open vocabulary assumption.</S>
    <S sid="217" ssid="150">Using the tagger without lexicalized rules, an overall accuracy of 96.3% and an unknown word accuracy of 82.0% is obtained.</S>
    <S sid="218" ssid="151">A graph of accuracy as a function of transformation number on the test set for lexicalized rules is shown in figure 7.</S>
    <S sid="219" ssid="152">Before applying any transformations, test set accuracy is 92.4%, so the transformations reduce the error rate by 50% over the baseline.</S>
    <S sid="220" ssid="153">The high baseline accuracy is somewhat misleading, as this includes the tagging of unambiguous words.</S>
    <S sid="221" ssid="154">Baseline accuracy when the words that are unambiguous in our lexicon are not considered is 86.4%.</S>
    <S sid="222" ssid="155">However, it is difficult to compare taggers using this figure, as the accuracy of the system depends on the particular lexicon used.</S>
    <S sid="223" ssid="156">For instance, in our training set the word the was tagged with a number of different tags, and so according to our lexicon the is ambiguous.</S>
    <S sid="224" ssid="157">If we instead used a lexicon where the is listed unambiguously as a determiner, the baseline accuracy would be 84.6%.</S>
    <S sid="225" ssid="158">For tagging unknown words, each word is initially assigned a part-of-speech tag based on word and word-distribution features.</S>
    <S sid="226" ssid="159">Then, the tag may be changed based on contextual cues, via contextual transformations that are applied to the entire corpus, both known and unknown-words.</S>
    <S sid="227" ssid="160">When the contextual rule learner learns transformations, it does so in an attempt to maximize overall tagging accuracy, and not unknown-word tagging accuracy.</S>
    <S sid="228" ssid="161">Unknown words account for only a small percentage of the corpus in our experiments, typically two to three percent.</S>
    <S sid="229" ssid="162">Since the distributional behavior of unknown words is quite different from that of known words, and transformations are not English-specific, the set of transformation templates would have to be extended to process languages with dramatically different morphology. since a transformation that does not increase unknown-word tagging accuracy can still be beneficial to overall tagging accuracy, the contextual transformations learned are not optimal in the sense of leading to the highest tagging accuracy on unknown words.</S>
    <S sid="230" ssid="163">Better unknown-word accuracy may be possible by training and using two sets of contextual rules, one maximizing known-word accuracy and the other maximizing unknown-word accuracy, and then applying the appropriate transformations to a word when tagging, depending upon whether the word appears in the lexicon.</S>
    <S sid="231" ssid="164">We are currently experimenting with this idea.</S>
    <S sid="232" ssid="165">In Weischedel et al. (1993), a statistical approach to tagging unknown words is shown.</S>
    <S sid="233" ssid="166">In this approach, a number of suffixes and important features are prespecified.</S>
    <S sid="234" ssid="167">Then, for unknown words: Using this equation for unknown word emit probabilities within the stochastic tagger, an accuracy of 85% was obtained on the Wall Street Journal corpus.</S>
    <S sid="235" ssid="168">This portion of the stochastic model has over 1,000 parameters, with 108 possible unique emit probabilities, as opposed to a small number of simple rules that are learned and used in the rule-based approach.</S>
    <S sid="236" ssid="169">In addition, the transformation-based method learns specific cues instead of requiring them to be prespecified, allowing for the possibility of uncovering cues not apparent to the human language engineer.</S>
    <S sid="237" ssid="170">We have obtained comparable performance on unknown words, while capturing the information in a much more concise and perspicuous manner, and without prespecifying any information specific to English or to a specific corpus.</S>
    <S sid="238" ssid="171">In table 2, we show tagging results obtained on a number of different corpora, in each case training on roughly 9.5 x 105 words total and testing on a separate test set of 1.5-2 x 108 words.</S>
    <S sid="239" ssid="172">Accuracy is consistent across these corpora and tag sets.</S>
    <S sid="240" ssid="173">In addition to obtaining high rates of accuracy and representing relevant linguistic information in a small set of rules, the part-of-speech tagger can also be made to run extremely fast.</S>
    <S sid="241" ssid="174">Roche and Schabes (1995) show a method for converting a list of tagging transformations into a deterministic finite state transducer with one state transition taken per word of input; the result is a transformation-based tagger whose tagging speed is about ten times that of the fastest Markov-model tagger.</S>
    <S sid="242" ssid="175">There are certain circumstances where one is willing to relax the one-tag-per-word requirement in order to increase the probability that the correct tag will be assigned to each word.</S>
    <S sid="243" ssid="176">In DeMarcken (1990) and Weischedel et al. (1993), k-best tags are assigned within a stochastic tagger by returning all tags within some threshold of probability of being correct for a particular word.</S>
    <S sid="244" ssid="177">We can modify the transformation-based tagger to return multiple tags for a word by making a simple modification to the contextual transformations described above.</S>
    <S sid="245" ssid="178">The initial-state annotator is the tagging output of the previously described one-best transformation-based tagger.</S>
    <S sid="246" ssid="179">The allowable transformation templates are the same as the contextual transformation templates listed above, but with the rewrite rule: change tag X to tag Y modified to add tag X to tag Y or add tag X to word W. Instead of changing the tagging of a word, transformations now add alternative taggings to a word.</S>
    <S sid="247" ssid="180">When allowing more than one tag per word, there is a trade-off between accuracy and the average number of tags for each word.</S>
    <S sid="248" ssid="181">Ideally, we would like to achieve as large an increase in accuracy with as few extra tags as possible.</S>
    <S sid="249" ssid="182">Therefore, in training we find transformations that maximize the function: Number of corrected errors Number of additional tags In table 3, we present results from first using the one-tag-per-word transformation-based tagger described in the previous section and then applying the k-best tag transformations.</S>
    <S sid="250" ssid="183">These transformations were learned from a separate 240,000 word corpus.</S>
    <S sid="251" ssid="184">As a baseline, we did k-best tagging of a test corpus.</S>
    <S sid="252" ssid="185">Each known word in the test corpus was tagged with all tags seen with that word in the training corpus and the five most likely unknown-word tags were assigned to all words not seen in the training corpus.'</S>
    <S sid="253" ssid="186">This resulted in an accuracy of 99.0%, with an average of 2.28 tags per word.</S>
    <S sid="254" ssid="187">The transformation-based tagger obtained the same accuracy with 1.43 tags per word, one third the number of additional tags as the baseline tagger.'</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="5." number="6">
    <S sid="255" ssid="1">In this paper, we have described a new transformation-based approach to corpus-based learning.</S>
    <S sid="256" ssid="2">We have given details of how this approach has been applied to part-ofspeech tagging and have demonstrated that the transformation-based approach obtains competitive performance with stochastic taggers on tagging both unknown and known words.</S>
    <S sid="257" ssid="3">The transformation-based tagger captures linguistic information in a small number of simple nonstochastic rules, as opposed to large numbers of lexical and contextual probabilities.</S>
    <S sid="258" ssid="4">This learning approach has also been applied to a number of other tasks, including prepositional phrase attachment disambiguation (Brill and Resnik 1994), bracketing text (Brill 1993a) and labeling nonterminal nodes (Brill 1993c).</S>
    <S sid="259" ssid="5">Recently, we have begun to explore the possibility of extending these techniques to other problems, including learning pronunciation networks for speech recognition and learning mappings between syntactic and semantic representations.</S>
  </SECTION>
  <SECTION title="Acknowledgments" number="7">
    <S sid="260" ssid="1">This work was funded in part by NSF grant IRI-9502312.</S>
    <S sid="261" ssid="2">In addition, this work was done in part while the author was in the Spoken Language Systems Group at Massachusetts Institute of Technology under ARPA grant N00014-89+1332, and by DARPA/AFOSR grant AFOSR-90-0066 at the University of Pennsylvania.</S>
    <S sid="262" ssid="3">Thanks to Mitch Marcus, Mark Villain, and the anonymous reviewers for many useful comments on earlier drafts of this paper.</S>
  </SECTION>
</PAPER>
