<PAPER>
	<S sid="0">SemEval-2007 Task 07: Coarse-Grained English All-Words Task</S><ABSTRACT>
		<S sid="1" ssid="1">This paper presents the coarse-grained En glish all-words task at SemEval-2007.</S>
		<S sid="2" ssid="2">We describe our experience in producing acoarse version of the WordNet sense inven tory and preparing the sense-tagged corpusfor the task.</S>
		<S sid="3" ssid="3">We present the results of participating systems and discuss future direc tions.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number="1">
			<S sid="4" ssid="4">It is commonly thought that one of the major obstacles to high-performance Word Sense Disambiguation (WSD) is the fine granularity of sense inventories.</S>
			<S sid="5" ssid="5">State-of-the-art systems attained a disam biguation accuracy around 65% in the Senseval-3 all-words task (Snyder and Palmer, 2004), whereWordNet (Fellbaum, 1998) was adopted as a ref erence sense inventory.</S>
			<S sid="6" ssid="6">Unfortunately, WordNet is a fine-grained resource, encoding sense distinctionsthat are difficult to recognize even for human an notators (Edmonds and Kilgarriff, 2002).</S>
			<S sid="7" ssid="7">MakingWSD an enabling technique for end-to-end applications clearly depends on the ability to deal with rea sonable sense distinctions.</S>
			<S sid="8" ssid="8">The aim of this task was to explicitly tackle the granularity issue and study the performance of WSD systems on an all-words basis when a coarser set of senses is provided for the target words.</S>
			<S sid="9" ssid="9">Given the need of the NLP community to work on freelyavailable resources, the solution of adopting a dif ferent computational lexicon is not viable.</S>
			<S sid="10" ssid="10">On the other hand, the production of a coarse-grained sense inventory is not a simple task.</S>
			<S sid="11" ssid="11">The main issue is certainly the subjectivity of sense clusters.</S>
			<S sid="12" ssid="12">To overcome this problem, different strategies can be adopted.</S>
			<S sid="13" ssid="13">For instance, in the OntoNotes project (Hovy et al, 2006) senses are grouped until a 90% inter-annotator agreement is achieved.</S>
			<S sid="14" ssid="14">In contrast, as we describe in this paper, our approach is based on a mapping to a previously existing inventory which encodes sense distinctions at different levelsof granularity, thus allowing to induce a sense clus tering for the mapped senses.We would like to mention that another SemEval 2007 task dealt with the issue of sense granularityfor WSD, namely Task 17 (subtask #1): Coarse grained English Lexical Sample WSD.</S>
			<S sid="15" ssid="15">In this paper, we report our experience in organizing Task 07.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Task Setup. " number="2">
			<S sid="16" ssid="1">The task required participating systems to annotate open-class words (i.e. nouns, verbs, adjectives, and adverbs) in a test corpus with the most appropriate sense from a coarse-grained version of the WordNet sense inventory.</S>
			<S sid="17" ssid="2">2.1 Test Corpus.</S>
			<S sid="18" ssid="3">The test data set consisted of 5,377 words of run ning text from five different articles: the first three (in common with Task 17) were obtained from the WSJ corpus, the fourth was the Wikipedia entry for computer programming1, the fifth was an excerpt of Amy Steedman?s Knights of the Art, biographies of Italian painters2.</S>
			<S sid="19" ssid="4">We decided to add the last two 1http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer programming 2http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/529 30 article domain words annotated d001 JOURNALISM 951 368 d002 BOOK REVIEW 987 379 d003 TRAVEL 1311 500 d004 COMPUTER SCIENCE 1326 677 d005 BIOGRAPHY 802 345 total 5377 2269 Table 1: Statistics about the five articles in the test data set.</S>
			<S sid="20" ssid="5">texts to the initial dataset as we wanted the corpus to have a size comparable to that of previous editions of all-words tasks.In Table 1 we report the domain, number of run ning words, and number of annotated words for the five articles.</S>
			<S sid="21" ssid="6">We observe that articles d003 and d004 are the largest in the corpus (they constitute 51.87% of it).</S>
			<S sid="22" ssid="7">2.2 Creation of a Coarse-Grained Sense.</S>
			<S sid="23" ssid="8">Inventory To tackle the granularity issue, we produced acoarser-grained version of the WordNet sense inven tory3 based on the procedure described by Navigli(2006).</S>
			<S sid="24" ssid="9">The method consists of automatically map ping WordNet senses to top level, numbered entries in the Oxford Dictionary of English (ODE, (Soanesand Stevenson, 2003)).</S>
			<S sid="25" ssid="10">The semantic mapping be tween WordNet and ODE entries was obtained intwo steps: first, we disambiguated with the SSI algo rithm (Navigli and Velardi, 2005) the definitions ofthe two dictionaries, together with additional infor mation (hypernyms and domain labels); second, foreach WordNet sense, we determined the best match ing ODE coarse entry.</S>
			<S sid="26" ssid="11">As a result, WordNet senses mapped to the same ODE entry were assigned to the same sense cluster.</S>
			<S sid="27" ssid="12">WordNet senses with no match were associated with a singleton sense.</S>
			<S sid="28" ssid="13">In contrast to the automatic method above, thesense mappings for all the words in our test cor pus were manually produced by the third author, anexpert lexicographer, with the aid of a mapping in terface.</S>
			<S sid="29" ssid="14">Not all the words in the corpus could be mapped directly for several reasons: lacking entries in ODE (e.g. adjectives underlying and shivering), 3We adopted WordNet 2.1, available from: http://wordnet.princeton.edu different spellings (e.g. after-effect vs. aftereffect, halfhearted vs. half-hearted, etc.), derivatives (e.g. procedural, gambler, etc.).</S>
			<S sid="30" ssid="15">In most of the cases, weasked the lexicographer to map senses of the orig inal word to senses of lexically-related words (e.g. WordNet senses of procedural were mapped to ODE senses of procedure, etc.).</S>
			<S sid="31" ssid="16">When this mapping was not straightforward, we just adopted the WordNet sense inventory for that word.We released the entire sense groupings (those in duced from the manual mapping for words in the test set plus those automatically derived on the other words) and made them available to the participants.</S>
			<S sid="32" ssid="17">2.3 Sense Annotation.</S>
			<S sid="33" ssid="18">All open-class words (i.e. nouns, verbs, adjectives, and adverbs) with an existing sense in the WordNetinventory were manually annotated by the third author.</S>
			<S sid="34" ssid="19">Multi-word expressions were explicitly iden tified in the test set and annotated as such (this wasmade to allow a fair comparison among systems independent of their ability to identify multi-word ex pressions).</S>
			<S sid="35" ssid="20">We excluded auxiliary verbs, uncovered phrasal and idiomatic verbs, exclamatory uses, etc. The annotator was allowed to tag words with multiple coarse senses, but was asked to make a single sense assignment whenever possible.</S>
			<S sid="36" ssid="21">The lexicographer annotated an overall numberof 2,316 content words.</S>
			<S sid="37" ssid="22">47 (2%) of them were excluded because no WordNet sense was deemed ap propriate.</S>
			<S sid="38" ssid="23">The remaining 2,269 content words thusconstituted the test data set.</S>
			<S sid="39" ssid="24">Only 8 of them were as signed more than one sense: specifically, two coarse senses were assigned to a single word instance4 and two distinct fine-grained senses were assigned to 7 word instances.</S>
			<S sid="40" ssid="25">This was a clear hint that the sense clusters were not ambiguous for the vast majority of words.In Table 2 we report information about the polysemy of the word instances in the test set.</S>
			<S sid="41" ssid="26">Over all, 29.88% (678/2269) of the word instances weremonosemous (according to our coarse sense inven tory).</S>
			<S sid="42" ssid="27">The average polysemy of the test set with the coarse-grained sense inventory was 3.06 compared to an average polysemy with the WordNet inventory 4d005.s004.t015 31 polysemy N V A R all monosemous 358 86 141 93 678 polysemous 750 505 221 115 1591 total 1108 591 362 208 2269 Table 2: Statistics about the test set polysemy (N = nouns, V = verbs, A = adjectives, R = adverbs).</S>
			<S sid="43" ssid="28">of 6.18.</S>
			<S sid="44" ssid="29">2.4 Inter-Annotator Agreement.</S>
			<S sid="45" ssid="30">Recent estimations of the inter-annotator agreement when using the WordNet inventory report figures of 72.5% agreement in the preparation of the English all-words test set at Senseval-3 (Snyder and Palmer,2004) and 67.3% on the Open Mind Word Expert an notation exercise (Chklovski and Mihalcea, 2002).As the inter-annotator agreement is often considered an upper bound for WSD systems, it was de sirable to have a much higher number for our task, given its coarse-grained nature.</S>
			<S sid="46" ssid="31">To this end, besidethe expert lexicographer, a second author indepen dently performed part of the manual sense mapping (590 word senses) described in Section 2.2.</S>
			<S sid="47" ssid="32">The pairwise agreement was 86.44%.</S>
			<S sid="48" ssid="33">We repeated the same agreement evaluation onthe sense annotation task of the test corpus.</S>
			<S sid="49" ssid="34">A sec ond author independently annotated part of the test set (710 word instances).</S>
			<S sid="50" ssid="35">The pairwise agreement between the two authors was 93.80%.</S>
			<S sid="51" ssid="36">This figure, compared to those in the literature for fine-grained human annotations, gives us a clear indication that the agreement of human annotators strictly depends on the granularity of the adopted sense inventory.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Baselines. " number="3">
			<S sid="52" ssid="1">We calculated two baselines for the test corpus: a random baseline, in which senses are chosen at random, and the most frequent baseline (MFS), in which we assign the first WordNet sense to each word in the dataset.</S>
			<S sid="53" ssid="2">Formally, the accuracy of the random baseline was calculated as follows: BLRand = 1|T | |T |?</S>
			<S sid="54" ssid="3">i=1 1 |CoarseSenses(wi)| where T is our test corpus, wi is the i-th word instance in T , and CoarseSenses(wi) is the set ofcoarse senses for wi according to the sense cluster ing we produced as described in Section 2.2.</S>
			<S sid="55" ssid="4">The accuracy of the MFS baseline was calculated as: BLMFS = 1|T | |T |?</S>
			<S sid="56" ssid="5">i=1 ?(wi, 1) where ?(wi, k) equals 1 when the k-th sense ofword wi belongs to the cluster(s) manually associ ated by the lexicographer to word wi (0 otherwise).</S>
			<S sid="57" ssid="6">Notice that our calculation of the MFS is based on the frequencies in the SemCor corpus (Miller et al, 1993), as we exploit WordNet sense rankings.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Results. " number="4">
			<S sid="58" ssid="1">12 teams submitted 14 systems overall (plus two systems from a 13th withdrawn team that we will not report).</S>
			<S sid="59" ssid="2">According to the SemEval policy for task organizers, we remark that the system labelled as UOR-SSI was submitted by the first author (thesystem is based on the Structural Semantic Inter connections algorithm (Navigli and Velardi, 2005)with a lexical knowledge base composed by Word Net and approximately 70,000 relatedness edges).Even though we did not specifically enrich the al gorithm?s knowledge base on the task at hand, we list the system separately from the overall ranking.The results are shown in Table 3.</S>
			<S sid="60" ssid="3">We calculated a MFS baseline of 78.89% and a random baseline of 52.43%.</S>
			<S sid="61" ssid="4">In Table 4 we report the F1 mea sures for all systems where we used the MFS as abackoff strategy when no sense assignment was at tempted (this possibly reranked 6 systems - marked in bold in the table - which did not assign a sense to all word instances in the test set).</S>
			<S sid="62" ssid="5">Comparedto previous results on fine-grained evaluation exer cises (Edmonds and Kilgarriff, 2002; Snyder and Palmer, 2004), the systems?</S>
			<S sid="63" ssid="6">results are much higher.</S>
			<S sid="64" ssid="7">On the other hand, the difference in performancebetween the MFS baseline and state-of-the-art sys tems (around 5%) on coarse-grained disambiguationis comparable to that of the Senseval-3 all-words ex ercise.</S>
			<S sid="65" ssid="8">However, given the novelty of the task webelieve that systems can achieve even better perfor 32 System A P R F1 NUS-PT 100.0 82.50 82.50 82.50 NUS-ML 100.0 81.58 81.58 81.58 LCC-WSD 100.0 81.45 81.45 81.45 GPLSI 100.0 79.55 79.55 79.55 BLMFS 100.0 78.89 78.89 78.89 UPV-WSD 100.0 78.63 78.63 78.63 TKB-UO 100.0 70.21 70.21 70.21 PU-BCD 90.1 69.72 62.80 66.08 RACAI-SYNWSD 100.0 65.71 65.71 65.71 SUSSX-FR 72.8 71.73 52.23 60.44 USYD 95.3 58.79 56.02 57.37 UOFL 92.7 52.59 48.74 50.60 SUSSX-C-WD 72.8 54.54 39.71 45.96 SUSSX-CR 72.8 54.30 39.53 45.75 UOR-SSI?</S>
			<S sid="66" ssid="9">100.0 83.21 83.21 83.21 Table 3: System scores sorted by F1 measure (A =attempted, P = precision, R = recall, F1 = F1 mea sure, ?: system from one of the task organizers).</S>
			<S sid="67" ssid="10">mance by heavily exploiting the coarse nature of the sense inventory.</S>
			<S sid="68" ssid="11">In Table 5 we report the results for each of the five articles.</S>
			<S sid="69" ssid="12">The interesting aspect of the table is that documents from some domains seem to havepredominant senses different from those in Sem Cor.</S>
			<S sid="70" ssid="13">Specifically, the MFS baseline performs more poorly on documents d004 and d005, from the COMPUTER SCIENCE and BIOGRAPHY domains respectively.</S>
			<S sid="71" ssid="14">We believe this is due to the fact that these documents have specific predominant senses, which correspond less often to the most frequent sense in SemCor than for the other three documents.</S>
			<S sid="72" ssid="15">It is also interesting to observe that different systemsperform differently on the five documents (we high light in bold the best performing systems on each article).</S>
			<S sid="73" ssid="16">Finally, we calculated the systems?</S>
			<S sid="74" ssid="17">performance by part of speech.</S>
			<S sid="75" ssid="18">The results are shown in Table 6.</S>
			<S sid="76" ssid="19">Again, we note that different systems show dif-.</S>
			<S sid="77" ssid="20">ferent performance depending on the part-of-speechtag.</S>
			<S sid="78" ssid="21">Another interesting aspect is that the performance of the MFS baseline is very close to state-of the-art systems for adjectives and adverbs, whereas it is more than 3 points below for verbs, and around 5 for nouns.</S>
			<S sid="79" ssid="22">System F1 NUS-PT 82.50 NUS-ML 81.58 LCC-WSD 81.45 GPLSI 79.55 BLMFS 78.89 UPV-WSD 78.63 SUSSX-FR 77.04 TKB-UO 70.21 PU-BCD 69.72 RACAI-SYNWSD 65.71 SUSSX-C-WD 64.52 SUSSX-CR 64.35 USYD 58.79 UOFL 54.61 UOR-SSI?</S>
			<S sid="80" ssid="23">83.21 Table 4: System scores sorted by F1 measure with MFS adopted as a backoff strategy when no sense assignment is attempted (?: system from one of the task organizers).</S>
			<S sid="81" ssid="24">Systems affected are marked in bold.</S>
			<S sid="82" ssid="25">System N V A R NUS-PT 82.31 78.51 85.64 89.42 NUS-ML 81.41 78.17 82.60 90.38 LCC-WSD 80.69 78.17 85.36 87.98 GPLSI 80.05 74.45 82.32 86.54 BLMFS 77.44 75.30 84.25 87.50 UPV-WSD 79.33 72.76 84.53 81.25 TKB-UO 70.76 62.61 78.73 74.04 PU-BCD 71.41 59.69 66.57 55.67 RACAI-SYNWSD 64.02 62.10 71.55 75.00 SUSSX-FR 68.09 51.02 57.38 49.38 USYD 56.06 60.43 58.00 54.31 UOFL 57.65 48.82 25.87 60.80 SUSSX-C-WD 52.18 35.64 42.95 46.30 SUSSX-CR 51.87 35.44 42.95 46.30 UOR-SSI?</S>
			<S sid="83" ssid="26">84.12 78.34 85.36 88.46 Table 6: System scores by part-of-speech tag (N = nouns, V = verbs, A = adjectives, R = adverbs) sorted by overall F1 measure (best scores are marked in bold, ?: system from one of the task organizers).</S>
			<S sid="84" ssid="27">33 d001 d002 d003 d004 d005 System P R P R P R P R P R NUS-PT 88.32 88.32 88.13 88.13 83.40 83.40 76.07 76.07 81.45 81.45 NUS-ML 86.14 86.14 88.39 88.39 81.40 81.40 76.66 76.66 79.13 79.13 LCC-WSD 87.50 87.50 87.60 87.60 81.40 81.40 75.48 75.48 80.00 80.00 GPLSI 83.42 83.42 86.54 86.54 80.40 80.40 73.71 73.71 77.97 77.97 BLMFS 85.60 85.60 84.70 84.70 77.80 77.80 75.19 75.19 74.20 74.20 UPV-WSD 84.24 84.24 80.74 80.74 76.00 76.00 77.11 77.11 77.10 77.10 TKB-UO 78.80 78.80 72.56 72.56 69.40 69.40 70.75 70.75 58.55 58.55 PU-BCD 77.16 67.94 75.52 67.55 64.96 58.20 68.86 61.74 64.42 60.87 RACAI-SYNWSD 71.47 71.47 72.82 72.82 66.80 66.80 60.86 60.86 59.71 59.71 SUSSX-FR 79.10 57.61 73.72 53.30 74.86 52.40 67.97 48.89 65.20 51.59 USYD 62.53 61.69 59.78 57.26 60.97 57.80 60.57 56.28 47.15 45.51 UOFL 61.41 59.24 55.93 52.24 48.00 45.60 53.42 47.27 44.38 41.16 SUSSX-C-WD 66.42 48.37 61.31 44.33 55.14 38.60 50.72 36.48 42.13 33.33 SUSSX-CR 66.05 48.10 60.58 43.80 59.14 41.40 48.67 35.01 40.29 31.88 UOR-SSI?</S>
			<S sid="85" ssid="28">86.14 86.14 85.49 85.49 79.60 79.60 86.85 86.85 75.65 75.65 Table 5: System scores by article (best scores are marked in bold, ?: system from one of the task organizers).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Systems Description. " number="5">
			<S sid="86" ssid="1">In order to allow for a critical and comparative inspection of the system results, we asked the partici pants to answer some questions about their systems.</S>
			<S sid="87" ssid="2">These included information about whether: 1.</S>
			<S sid="88" ssid="3">the system used semantically-annotated and unannotated resources; 2.</S>
			<S sid="89" ssid="4">the system used the MFS as a backoff strategy; 3.</S>
			<S sid="90" ssid="5">the system used the coarse senses provided by the organizers; 4.</S>
			<S sid="91" ssid="6">the system was trained on some corpus.</S>
			<S sid="92" ssid="7">We believe that this gives interesting information to provide a deeper understanding of the results.</S>
			<S sid="93" ssid="8">Wesummarize the participants?</S>
			<S sid="94" ssid="9">answers to the questionnaires in Table 7.</S>
			<S sid="95" ssid="10">We report about the use of semantic resources as well as semantically annotated corpora (SC = SemCor, DSO = Defence Science Organ isation Corpus, SE = Senseval corpora, OMWE =Open Mind Word Expert, XWN = eXtended Word Net, WN = WordNet glosses and/or relations, WND = WordNet Domains), as well as information about the use of unannotated corpora (UC), training (TR), MFS (based on the SemCor sense frequencies), and the coarse senses provided by the organizers (CS).</S>
			<S sid="96" ssid="11">As expected, several systems used lexico-semantic information from the WordNet semantic networkand/or were trained on the SemCor semantically annotated corpus.Finally, we point out that all the systems perform ing better than the MFS baseline adopted it as a backoff strategy when they were not able to output a sense assignment.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions and Future Directions. " number="6">
			<S sid="97" ssid="1">It is commonly agreed that Word Sense Disambiguation needs emerge and show its usefulness in end to-end applications: after decades of research in the field it is still unclear whether WSD can provide a relevant contribution to real-world applications, such as Information Retrieval, Question Answering,etc. In previous Senseval evaluation exercises, state of-the-art systems achieved performance far below70% and even the agreement between human annotators was discouraging.</S>
			<S sid="98" ssid="2">As a result of the discus sion at the Senseval-3 workshop in 2004, one of the aims of SemEval-2007 was to tackle the problems at the roots of WSD.</S>
			<S sid="99" ssid="3">In this task, we dealt with the granularity issue which is a major obstacle to bothsystem and human annotators.</S>
			<S sid="100" ssid="4">In the hope of over coming the current performance upper bounds, we 34 System SC DSO SE OMWE XWN WN WND OTHER UC TR MFS CS GPLSI ? ?</S>
			<S sid="101" ssid="5">LCC-WSD ? ?</S>
			<S sid="102" ssid="6">NUS-ML ? ?</S>
			<S sid="103" ssid="7">NUS-PT ? ?</S>
			<S sid="104" ssid="8">Parallel corpus ? ?</S>
			<S sid="105" ssid="9">PU-BCD ? ?</S>
			<S sid="106" ssid="10">RACAI-SYNWSD ? ?</S>
			<S sid="107" ssid="11">SUSSX-C-WD ? ?</S>
			<S sid="108" ssid="12">SUSSX-CR ? ?</S>
			<S sid="109" ssid="13">SUSSX-FR ? ?</S>
			<S sid="110" ssid="14">TKB-UO ? ?</S>
			<S sid="111" ssid="15">UOFL ? ?</S>
			<S sid="112" ssid="16">UOR-SSI?</S>
			<S sid="113" ssid="17">SSI LKB ? ?</S>
			<S sid="114" ssid="18">UPV-WSD ? ?</S>
			<S sid="115" ssid="19">USYD ? ?</S>
			<S sid="116" ssid="20">Table 7: Information about participating systems (SC = SemCor, DSO = Defence Science Organisation Corpus, SE = Senseval corpora, OMWE = Open Mind Word Expert, XWN = eXtended WordNet, WN = WordNet glosses and/or relations, WND = WordNet Domains, UC = use of unannotated corpora, TR = use of training, MFS = most frequent sense backoff strategy, CS = use of coarse senses from the organizers, ?: system from one of the task organizers).proposed the adoption of a coarse-grained sense inventory.</S>
			<S sid="117" ssid="21">We found the results of participating sys tems interesting and stimulating.</S>
			<S sid="118" ssid="22">However, some questions arise.</S>
			<S sid="119" ssid="23">First, it is unclear whether, given the novelty of the task, systems really achieved the state of the art or can still improve their performancebased on a heavier exploitation of coarse- and finegrained information from the adopted sense inven tory.</S>
			<S sid="120" ssid="24">We observe that, on a technical domain suchas computer science, most supervised systems per formed worse due to the nature of their training set.</S>
			<S sid="121" ssid="25">Second, we still need to show that coarse senses can be useful in real applications.</S>
			<S sid="122" ssid="26">Third, a full coarse sense inventory is not yet available: this is a majorobstacle to large-scale in vivo evaluations.</S>
			<S sid="123" ssid="27">We be lieve that these aspects deserve further investigation in the years to come.</S>
			<S sid="124" ssid="28">Acknowledgments This work was partially funded by the Interop NoE (508011), 6th European Union FP.</S>
			<S sid="125" ssid="29">We would like to thank Martha Palmer for providing us the first three texts of the test corpus.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
