<PAPER>
	<S sid="0">Recognising Textual Entailment With Logical Inference</S><ABSTRACT>
		<S sid="1" ssid="1">We use logical inference techniques for recognising textual entailment.</S>
		<S sid="2" ssid="2">As the performance of theorem proving turnsout to be highly dependent on not read ily available background knowledge, we incorporate model building, a technique borrowed from automated reasoning, and show that it is a useful robust method to approximate entailment.</S>
		<S sid="3" ssid="3">Finally, we use machine learning to combine these deep semantic analysis techniques with simpleshallow word overlap; the resulting hy brid model achieves high accuracy on the RTE testset, given the state of the art.</S>
		<S sid="4" ssid="4">Ourresults also show that the different techniques that we employ perform very dif ferently on some of the subsets of the RTE corpus and as a result, it is useful to use the nature of the dataset as a feature.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number="1">
			<S sid="5" ssid="5">Recognising textual entailment (RTE) is the task to find out whether some text T entails a hypothesis H. This task has recently been the focus of a challenge organised by the PASCAL network in 2004/5.1 In Example 1550 H follows from T whereas this is not the case in Example 731.</S>
			<S sid="6" ssid="6">1All examples are from the corpus released as part of the RTE challenge.</S>
			<S sid="7" ssid="7">It is downloadable from http://www.pascal-network.org/Challenges/RTE/.</S>
			<S sid="8" ssid="8">The exam ple numbers have also been kept.</S>
			<S sid="9" ssid="9">Each example is marked for entailment as TRUE if H follows from T and FALSE otherwise.</S>
			<S sid="10" ssid="10">The dataset is described in Section 4.1.</S>
			<S sid="11" ssid="11">Example: 1550 (TRUE) T: In 1998, the General Assembly of the Nippon Sei Ko Kai (Anglican Church in Japan) voted to accept female priests.</S>
			<S sid="12" ssid="12">H: The Anglican church in Japan approved the ordination of women.</S>
			<S sid="13" ssid="13">Example: 731 (FALSE) T: The city Tenochtitlan grew rapidly and was the center of the Aztec?s great empire.</S>
			<S sid="14" ssid="14">H: Tenochtitlan quickly spread over the island, marshes, and swamps.</S>
			<S sid="15" ssid="15">The recognition of textual entailment is without doubt one of the ultimate challenges for any NLPsystem: if it is able to do so with reasonable accuracy, it is clearly an indication that it has some thor ough understanding of how language works.</S>
			<S sid="16" ssid="16">Indeed, recognising entailment bears similarities to Turing?s famous test to assess whether machines can think, as access to different sources of knowledge and theability to draw inferences seem to be among the primary ingredients for an intelligent system.</S>
			<S sid="17" ssid="17">Moreover, many NLP tasks have strong links to entailment: in summarisation, a summary should be en tailed by the text; paraphrases can be seen as mutualentailment between T and H; in IE, the extracted in formation should also be entailed by the text.In this paper, we discuss two methods for recog nising textual entailment: a shallow method relyingmainly on word overlap (Section 2), and deep se mantic analysis, using state-of-the-art off-the-shelf inference tools, namely a theorem prover and amodel builder (Section 3).</S>
			<S sid="18" ssid="18">These tools rely on Dis course Representation Structures for T and H as well as lexical and world knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="19" ssid="19">To our knowledge, few approaches to entailment currently use theorem provers and none incorporate model building (see 628 Section 5 for a discussion of related work).</S>
			<S sid="20" ssid="20">Both methods are domain-independent to increasetransferrability and have not been tailored to any par ticular test suite.</S>
			<S sid="21" ssid="21">In Section 4 we test their accuracy and robustness on the RTE datasets as one of the few currently available datasets for textual inference.</S>
			<S sid="22" ssid="22">We also combine the two methods in a hybrid approach using machine learning.</S>
			<S sid="23" ssid="23">We discuss particularly the following questions:?</S>
			<S sid="24" ssid="24">Can the methods presented improve significantly over the baseline and what are the per formance differences between them?</S>
			<S sid="25" ssid="25">Does thehybrid system using both shallow and deep se mantic analysis improve over the individual use of these methods?</S>
			<S sid="26" ssid="26">How far does deep semantic analysis suffer from a lack of lexical and world knowledge and how can we perform logical inference in the face of potentially large knowledge gaps??</S>
			<S sid="27" ssid="27">How does the design of the test suite affect per formance?</S>
			<S sid="28" ssid="28">Are there subsets of the test suitethat are more suited to any particular textual en tailment recognition method?</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Shallow Semantic Features. " number="2">
			<S sid="29" ssid="1">We use several shallow surface features to model the text, hypothesis and their relation to each other.</S>
			<S sid="30" ssid="2">Most importantly, we expect some dependencybetween surface string similarity of text and hypothesis and the existence of entailment.</S>
			<S sid="31" ssid="3">Our string sim ilarity measure uses only a form of extended wordoverlap between text and hypothesis, taking into account equality of words, synonymy and morpholog ical derivations.</S>
			<S sid="32" ssid="4">WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998) is usedas the knowledge source for synonymy and deriva tions.</S>
			<S sid="33" ssid="5">The exact procedure is as follows:Both text and hypothesis are tokenised and lem matised.</S>
			<S sid="34" ssid="6">A lemma l1 in the hypothesis is said to be related to a lemma l2 in the text iff l1 and l2 are equal, belong to the same WordNet synset (e.g., ?murder?</S>
			<S sid="35" ssid="7">and ?slay?), are related via WordNet derivations (e.g. ?murder?</S>
			<S sid="36" ssid="8">and ?murderer?)</S>
			<S sid="37" ssid="9">or arerelated via a combination of synonymy and deriva tions (e.g. ?murder?</S>
			<S sid="38" ssid="10">via ?murderer?</S>
			<S sid="39" ssid="11">to ?liquidator?).</S>
			<S sid="40" ssid="12">No word sense disambiguation is performed and all synsets for a particular lemma are considered.In addition, each lemma in the hypothesis is as signed its inverse document frequency, accessing the Web as corpus via the GoogleAPI, as its weight.</S>
			<S sid="41" ssid="13">This standard procedure allows us to assign more importance to less frequent words.</S>
			<S sid="42" ssid="14">The overlap measure wnoverlap between text and hypothesis is initialised as zero.</S>
			<S sid="43" ssid="15">Should a lemma in the hypothesis be related to a lemma in the text, its weight is added to wnoverlap, otherwise it is ignored.</S>
			<S sid="44" ssid="16">In the end wnoverlap is normalised by dividing it by the sum of all weights of the lemmas in the hypothesis.</S>
			<S sid="45" ssid="17">This ensures that wnoverlap isalways a real number between 0 and 1 and also en sures independence of the length of the hypothesis.</S>
			<S sid="46" ssid="18">Apart from wnoverlap we take into account length (as measured by number of lemmas) of text and hypothesis, because in most of the observed cases for true entailments the hypothesis is shorter than the text as it contains less information.</S>
			<S sid="47" ssid="19">This is covered by three numerical features measuring the length of the text, of the hypothesis and the relative length of hypothesis with regard to the text.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Deep Semantic Analysis. " number="3">
			<S sid="48" ssid="1">3.1 Semantic Interpretation.</S>
			<S sid="49" ssid="2">We use a robust wide-coverage CCG-parser (Bos etal., 2004) to generate fine-grained semantic representations for each T/H-pair.</S>
			<S sid="50" ssid="3">The semantic representation language is a first-order fragment of the DRS language used in Discourse Representation Theory(Kamp and Reyle, 1993), conveying argument struc ture with a neo-Davidsonian analysis and includingthe recursive DRS structure to cover negation, dis junction, and implication.</S>
			<S sid="51" ssid="4">Consider for example: Example: 78 (FALSE) T: Clinton?s new book is not big seller here.</S>
			<S sid="52" ssid="5">H: Clinton?s book is a big seller.</S>
			<S sid="53" ssid="6">drs(T): x1 x2 x3 book(x1) book(x2) ? x1=x2 clinton(x3) of(x1,x3) ? e4 x5 big(x5) seller(x5) be(e4) agent(e4,x1) patient(e4,x5) loc(e4,here) drs(H): x1 x2 e3 x4 book(x1) clinton(x2) of(x1,x2) big(x4) seller(x4) be(e3) agent(e3,x1) patient(e3,x4) 629 Proper names and definite descriptions are treated as anaphoric, and bound to previously introduceddiscourse referents if possible, otherwise accommodated.</S>
			<S sid="54" ssid="7">Some lexical items are specified as presup position triggers.</S>
			<S sid="55" ssid="8">An example is the adjective ?new?</S>
			<S sid="56" ssid="9">which has a presuppositional reading, as shown by the existence of two different ?book?</S>
			<S sid="57" ssid="10">entities in drs(T).</S>
			<S sid="58" ssid="11">Scope is fully specified.</S>
			<S sid="59" ssid="12">To check whether an entailment holds or not, weuse two kinds of automated reasoning tools: Vam pire, a theorem prover (Riazanov and Voronkov, 2002), and Paradox, a model builder (Claessen and So?rensson, 2003).</S>
			<S sid="60" ssid="13">Both tools are developed to deal with inference problems stated in first-order logic.We use the standard translation from DRS to firstorder logic (Kamp and Reyle, 1993) to map our se mantic representation onto the format required by the inference tools.</S>
			<S sid="61" ssid="14">3.2 Theorem Proving.</S>
			<S sid="62" ssid="15">Given a T/H pair, a theorem prover can be used to find answers to the following conjectures: 1.</S>
			<S sid="63" ssid="16">T implies H (shows entailment) 2.</S>
			<S sid="64" ssid="17">T+H are inconsistent (shows no entailment)Assume that the function DRS denotes the DRS cor responding to T or H, and FOL the function that translates a DRS into first-order logic.</S>
			<S sid="65" ssid="18">Then, if the theorem prover manages to find a proof for FOL(DRS(T))?FOL(DRS(H)) (A) we know that we are dealing with a true entailment.In addition, to use a theorem prover to detect incon sistencies in a T/H pair, we give it: ?FOL(DRS(T);DRS(H)) (B) If the theorem prover returns a proof for (B), we know that T and H are inconsistent and T definitelydoesn?t entail H (assuming that T and H are them selves consistent).Examples The theorem prover will find that T im plies H for the following examples: Example: 1005 (TRUE) T: Jessica Litman, a law professor at Michigan?s Wayne State University, has specialized in copyright law and Internet law for more than 20 years.</S>
			<S sid="66" ssid="19">H: Jessica Litman is a law professor.</S>
			<S sid="67" ssid="20">Example: 1977 (TRUE) T: His family has steadfastly denied the charges.</S>
			<S sid="68" ssid="21">H: The charges were denied by his family.</S>
			<S sid="69" ssid="22">Example: 898 (TRUE) T: After the war the city was briefly occupied by the Allies and then was returned to the Dutch.</S>
			<S sid="70" ssid="23">H: After the war, the city was returned to the Dutch.</S>
			<S sid="71" ssid="24">Example: 1952 (TRUE) T: Crude oil prices soared to record levels.</S>
			<S sid="72" ssid="25">H: Crude oil prices rise.These examples show how deep semantic analy sis deals effectively with apposition, active-passive alternation, coordination, and can integrate lexical knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="73" ssid="26">The RTE dataset only contains a few inconsistent T/H pairs.</S>
			<S sid="74" ssid="27">Even although Example 78 might look like a case in point, it is not inconsistent: It would be if the T in the example would have been Clinton?s new book is not a big seller.</S>
			<S sid="75" ssid="28">The addition of the adverb here makes T+H consistent.</S>
			<S sid="76" ssid="29">3.3 Background Knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="77" ssid="30">The theorem prover needs background knowledge to support its proofs.</S>
			<S sid="78" ssid="31">Finding a proof for Example 1952 above is only possible if the theorem prover knows that soaring is a way of rising.How does it know this?</S>
			<S sid="79" ssid="32">Because in addi tion to the information from T and H alone, we also supply relevant background knowledge in the form of first-order axioms.</S>
			<S sid="80" ssid="33">Instead of giving justFOL(DRS(T);DRS(H)) to the theorem prover, we sup ply it with (BK ? FOL(DRS(T);DRS(H))) where BK is short for the relevant background knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="81" ssid="34">We generate background knowledge using threekinds of sources: generic knowledge, lexical knowl edge, and geographical knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="82" ssid="35">Axioms forgeneric knowledge cover the semantics of possessives, active-passive alternation, and spatial knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="83" ssid="36">There are about 20 different axioms in the current system and these are the only manually gener ated axioms.</S>
			<S sid="84" ssid="37">An example is ?e?x?y(event(e)?agent(e,x)?in(e,y)?in(x,y)) which states that if an event is located in y, then so is the agent of that event.</S>
			<S sid="85" ssid="38">Lexical knowledge is created automatically from WordNet.</S>
			<S sid="86" ssid="39">A hyponymy relation between two 630 synsets A and B is converted into ?x(A(x)?B(x)).</S>
			<S sid="87" ssid="40">Two synset sisters A and B are translated into ?x(A(x)?</S>
			<S sid="88" ssid="41">?B(x)).</S>
			<S sid="89" ssid="42">Here the predicate symbols from the DRS are mapped to WordNet synsets using a variant of Lesk?s WSD algorithm (Manning and Schuetze, 1999).</S>
			<S sid="90" ssid="43">Examples 78 and 1952 would be supported by knowledge similar to: ?x(clinton(x)?person(x)) ?x(book(x)?artifact(x)) ?x(artifact(x)?</S>
			<S sid="91" ssid="44">?person(x)) ?x(soar(x)?rise(x)) Finally, axioms covering geographical knowledge about capitals, countries and US states are extracted automatically from the CIA factbook.</S>
			<S sid="92" ssid="45">An example: ?x?y(paris(x)?france(y)?in(x,y)) 3.4 Model Building.</S>
			<S sid="93" ssid="46">While theorem provers are designed to prove that a formula is a theorem (i.e., that the formula is true in any model), they are generally not good at deciding that a formula is not a theorem.</S>
			<S sid="94" ssid="47">Model builders are designed to show that a formula is true in at least one model.</S>
			<S sid="95" ssid="48">To exploit these complementary approaches to inference, we use both a theorem prover and amodel builder for any inference problem: the theo rem prover attempts to prove the input whereas the model builder simultaneously tries to find a model for the negation of the input.</S>
			<S sid="96" ssid="49">If the model builder finds a model for ?FOL(DRS(T))?FOL(DRS(H)) (= ?A) we know that there can?t be a proof for its negation (hence no entailment).</S>
			<S sid="97" ssid="50">And if the model builder is able to generate a model for FOL(DRS(T);DRS(H)) (= ?B)we know that T and H are consistent (maybe entailment).</S>
			<S sid="98" ssid="51">(In practice, this is also a good way to termi nate the search for proofs or models: if the theorem prover finds a proof for ??, we can halt the model builder to try and find a model for ?</S>
			<S sid="99" ssid="52">(because there won?t be one), and vice versa.)</S>
			<S sid="100" ssid="53">Another attractive property of a model builder is that it outputs a model for its input formula (only of course if the input is satisfiable).</S>
			<S sid="101" ssid="54">A model is here the logical notion of a model, describing a situation in which the input formula is true.</S>
			<S sid="102" ssid="55">Formally, a model is a pair ?D,F ? where D is the set of entities in thedomain, and F a function mapping predicate sym bols to sets of domain members.</S>
			<S sid="103" ssid="56">For instance, the model returned for fol(drs(T)) in Example 78 is one where the domain consists of three entities (domain size = 3): D = {d1,d2,d3} F(loc) = {} F(book) = {d1,d2} F(seller) = {} F(clinton) = {d3} F(be) = {} F(of) = {(d1,d3)} F(agent) = {} F(big) = {} F(patient) = {}Model builders like Paradox generate finite mod els by iteration.</S>
			<S sid="104" ssid="57">They attempt to create a model for domain size 1.</S>
			<S sid="105" ssid="58">If they fail, they increase the domain size and try again, until either they find a model ortheir resources run out.</S>
			<S sid="106" ssid="59">Thus, although there are in finitely many models satisfying fol(drs(T)), modelbuilders generally build a model with a minimal do main size.</S>
			<S sid="107" ssid="60">(For more information on model building consult (Blackburn and Bos, 2005)).</S>
			<S sid="108" ssid="61">3.5 Approximating Entailment.</S>
			<S sid="109" ssid="62">In an ideal world we calculate all the required back ground knowledge and by either finding a proof ora countermodel, decide how T and H relate with re spect to entailment.</S>
			<S sid="110" ssid="63">However, it is extremely hard to acquire all the required background knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="111" ssid="64">This is partly due to the limitations of word sense disambiguation, the lack of resources like WordNet, and the lack of general knowledge in a form suitable for automatic inference tasks.To introduce an element of robustness into our ap proach, we use the models as produced by the modelbuilders to measure the ?distance?</S>
			<S sid="112" ssid="65">from an entail ment.</S>
			<S sid="113" ssid="66">The intuition behind it is as follows.</S>
			<S sid="114" ssid="67">If His entailed by T, the model for T+H is not informa tive compared to the one for T, and hence does not introduce new entities.</S>
			<S sid="115" ssid="68">Put differently, the domain size for T+H would equal the domain size of T. Incontrast, if T does not entail H, H normally intro duce some new information (except when it contains negated information), and this will be reflected in the domain size of T+H, which then is larger than the domain size of T. It turns out that this differencebetween the domain sizes is a useful way of measur ing the likelihood of entailment.</S>
			<S sid="116" ssid="69">Large differences are mostly not entailments, small differences mostly are.</S>
			<S sid="117" ssid="70">Consider the following example: 631 Example: 1049 (TRUE) T: Four Venezuelan firefighters who were traveling to a training course in Texas were killed when their sport utility vehicle drifted onto the shoulder of a highway and struck a parked truck.</S>
			<S sid="118" ssid="71">H: Four firefighters were killed in a car accident.Although this example is judged as a true entail ment, Vampire doesn?t find a proof because it lacks the background knowledge that one way of causing acar accident is to drift onto the shoulder of the high way and strike something.</S>
			<S sid="119" ssid="72">It generates a model withdomain size 11 for fol(drs(T)), and a model with do main size 12 for fol((drs(T);drs(H))).</S>
			<S sid="120" ssid="73">The absolute difference in domain sizes is small, and thereforelikely to indicate an entailment.</S>
			<S sid="121" ssid="74">Apart from the absolute difference we also compute the difference rel ative to the domain size.</S>
			<S sid="122" ssid="75">For the example above the relative domain size yields 1/12 = 0.083.</S>
			<S sid="123" ssid="76">The domain size only tells us something about the number of entities used in a model?not about the number of established relations between the model?s entities.</S>
			<S sid="124" ssid="77">Therefore, we also introduce the notion ofmodel size.</S>
			<S sid="125" ssid="78">The model size is defined here by count ing the number of all instances of two-place relations (and three-place relations, if there are any) in the model, and multiplying this with the domain size.</S>
			<S sid="126" ssid="79">For instance, the following model D = {d1,d2,d3} F(cat) = {d1,d2} F(john) = {d3} F(of) = {(d1,d3)} F(like) = {(d3,d1),(d3,d2)} has a domain size of 3 and 3 instantiated two-place relations, yielding a model size of 3 ? 3 = 9.</S>
			<S sid="127" ssid="80">3.6 Deep Semantic Features.</S>
			<S sid="128" ssid="81">Given our approach to deep semantic analysis,we identified eight features relevant for recognising textual entailment.</S>
			<S sid="129" ssid="82">The theorem prover provides us with two features: entailed determin ing whether T implies H, and inconsistentdetermining whether T together with H is incon sistent.</S>
			<S sid="130" ssid="83">The model builder gives us six features: domainsize and modelsize for T+H as well as the absolute and relative difference between the sizes of T and T+H, both for the size of the domains (domainsizeabsdif, domainsizereldif) and the size of the models (modelsizeabsdif, modelsizereldif).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Experiments. " number="4">
			<S sid="131" ssid="1">There are not many test suites available for textual inference.</S>
			<S sid="132" ssid="2">We use throughout this section the dataset made available as part of the RTE challenge.</S>
			<S sid="133" ssid="3">4.1 Dataset Design and Evaluation Measures.</S>
			<S sid="134" ssid="4">The organisers released a development set of 567 sentence pairs and a test set of 800 sentence pairs.In both sets, 50% of the sentence pairs were anno tated as TRUE and 50% as FALSE, leading to a 50% most frequent class baseline for automatic systems.</S>
			<S sid="135" ssid="5">The examples are further distinguished according to the way they were designed via a so-called Task variable.</S>
			<S sid="136" ssid="6">For examples marked CD (Comparable Documents), sentences with high lexical overlap in comparable news articles were selected, whereas thehypotheses of examples marked QA (Question An swering) were formed by translating questions from e.g., TREC into statements.</S>
			<S sid="137" ssid="7">The other subsets are IE (Information extraction), MT (Machine Translation)RC (Reading Comprehension), PP (Paraphrase Acquisition) and IR (Information Retrieval).</S>
			<S sid="138" ssid="8">The dif ferent examples and subsets cover a wide variety of different aspects of entailment, from incorporationof background knowledge to lexical to syntactic en tailment and combinations of all these.</S>
			<S sid="139" ssid="9">For a more exhaustive description of dataset design we refer the reader to (Dagan et al, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="140" ssid="10">4.2 Experiment 1: Human Upper bound.</S>
			<S sid="141" ssid="11">To establish a human upper bound as well as inves tigate the validity of the datasets issued, one of the authors annotated all 800 examples of the test set for entailment, using the short RTE annotation rules.</S>
			<S sid="142" ssid="12">The annotation was performed before the release of the gold standard annotation for the test set and was therefore independent of the organisers?</S>
			<S sid="143" ssid="13">annotation.</S>
			<S sid="144" ssid="14">The organisers?</S>
			<S sid="145" ssid="15">and the author?s annotation yielded a high percentage agreement of 95.25%.</S>
			<S sid="146" ssid="16">However, 33% of the originally created examples were alreadyfiltered out of the corpus before release by the organisers because of agreement-related problems.</S>
			<S sid="147" ssid="17">Therefore we expect that human agreement on textual en tailment in general is rather lower.</S>
			<S sid="148" ssid="18">632 4.3 Decision trees for entailment recognition.</S>
			<S sid="149" ssid="19">We expressed each example pair as a feature vector, using different subsets of the features described in Section 2 and Section 3 for each experiment.</S>
			<S sid="150" ssid="20">We then trained a decision tree for classification into TRUE and FALSE entailment on the development set, using the Weka machine learning tool (Witten and Frank, 2000), and tested on the test set.</S>
			<S sid="151" ssid="21">Apartfrom a classification, Weka also computes a confi dence value for each decision, dependent on the leaf in the tree that the classified example falls into: if the leaf covers x examples in the training set, of which y examples are classified wrongly, then the error rate is y/x and the confidence value is 1?</S>
			<S sid="152" ssid="22">y/x. Our evaluation measures are accuracy (acc) as the percentage of correct judgements as well asconfidence-weighted average score (cws), which rewards the system?s ability to assign a higher confi dence score to correct judgements than wrong ones (Dagan et al, 2005): after the n judgements are sorted in decreasing order by their confidence value, the following measure is computed: cws = 1 n n?</S>
			<S sid="153" ssid="23">i=1 #correct-up-rank-i i All evaluation measures are computed over the whole test set as well as on the 7 different subsets(CD, IE, etc.).</S>
			<S sid="154" ssid="24">The results are summarised in Table 1.</S>
			<S sid="155" ssid="25">We also computed precision, recall and F measure for both classes TRUE and FALSE and will discuss the results in the text whenever of interest.Experiment 2: Shallow Features In this experi ment only the shallow features (see Section 2) were used.</S>
			<S sid="156" ssid="26">The overall accuracy of 56.9% is significantly higher than the baseline.2Column 2 in Table 1 shows that this decent per formance is entirely due to excellent performanceon the CD subset.</S>
			<S sid="157" ssid="27">(Recall that the CD set was de signed explicitly with examples with high lexicaloverlap in mind.)</S>
			<S sid="158" ssid="28">In addition, the method overes timates the number of true entailments, achieving a Recall of 0.926 for the class TRUE, but a precision of only 0.547 on the same class.</S>
			<S sid="159" ssid="29">In contrast, it has2We used the z-test for the difference between two propor tions to measure whether the difference in accuracy between two algorithms or an algorithm and the baseline is statistically significant at the 5% level.</S>
			<S sid="160" ssid="30">good precision (0.761) but low recall (0.236) for theFALSE class.</S>
			<S sid="161" ssid="31">Thus, there is a correspondence be tween low word overlap and FALSE examples (see Example 731 in the Introduction, where important words in the hypothesis like ?swamps?</S>
			<S sid="162" ssid="32">or ?marshes?</S>
			<S sid="163" ssid="33">are not matched in the text); high overlap, however, is normally necessary but not sufficient for TRUE entailment (see also Example 78 in Section 3).Experiment 3: Strict entailment To test the potential of entailment as discovered by theorem prov ing alone, we now use only the entailment and inconsistent features.</S>
			<S sid="164" ssid="34">As to be expected, the decision tree shows that, if a proof for T implies H has been found, the example should be classified as TRUE, otherwise as FALSE.3 The precision (0.767) for the class TRUE is reasonably high: if a proof is found, then an entailment is indeed very likely.</S>
			<S sid="165" ssid="35">However, recall is very low (0.058) as only 30 proofs were found on the test set (for some examples see Section 3).</S>
			<S sid="166" ssid="36">This yields an F-measure of only 0.10for the TRUE class.</S>
			<S sid="167" ssid="37">Due to the low recall, the over all accuracy of the system (0.52, see Table 1) is not significantly higher than the baseline.</S>
			<S sid="168" ssid="38">Thus, this feature behaves in the opposite way to shallow lexical overlap and overgenerates the FALSE class.</S>
			<S sid="169" ssid="39">Missing lexical and background knowledge is the major cause for missing proofs.</S>
			<S sid="170" ssid="40">Experiment 4: Approximating entailment As discussed in Section 3.5 we now try to compensate for missing knowledge and improve recall for TRUE entailments by approximating entailment with the features that are furnished by the model builder.</S>
			<S sid="171" ssid="41">Thus, Experiment 4 uses all eight deep semantic analysis features, including the features capturing differences in domain- and modelsizes.</S>
			<S sid="172" ssid="42">The recallfor the TRUE class indeed jumps to 0.735.</S>
			<S sid="173" ssid="43">Al though, unavoidably, the FALSE class suffers, the resulting overall accuracy (0.562, see Column 4 in Table 1) is significantly higher than when using the features provided by the theorem prover alone (as in Experiment 3).</S>
			<S sid="174" ssid="44">The confidence weighted score also rises substantially from 0.548 to 0.608.</S>
			<S sid="175" ssid="45">The approximation achieved can be seen in the differenttreatment of Example 1049 (see Section 3.5) in Ex periments 3 and 4.</S>
			<S sid="176" ssid="46">In Experiment 3, this example 3The inconsistent feature was not used by the decision tree as very few examples were covered by that feature.</S>
			<S sid="177" ssid="47">633 Table 1: Summary of Results for Experiments 1 to 6 Exp 1: Human 2: Shallow 3: Strict 4: Deep 5: Hybrid 6: Hybrid+Task Task acc cws acc cws acc cws acc cws acc cws acc cws CD 0.967 n/a 0.827 0.881 0.547 0.617 0.713 0.787 0.700 0.790 0.827 0.827 IE 0.975 n/a 0.508 0.503 0.542 0.622 0.533 0.616 0.542 0.639 0.542 0.627 MT 0.900 n/a 0.500 0.515 0.500 0.436 0.592 0.596 0.525 0.512 0.533 0.581 QA 0.961 n/a 0.531 0.557 0.461 0.422 0.515 0.419 0.569 0.520 0.577 0.531 RC 0.979 n/a 0.507 0.502 0.557 0.638 0.457 0.537 0.507 0.587 0.557 0.644 PP 0.920 n/a 0.480 0.467 0.540 0.581 0.520 0.616 0.560 0.667 0.580 0.619 IR 0.922 n/a 0.511 0.561 0.489 0.421 0.567 0.503 0.622 0.569 0.611 0.561 all 0.951 n/a 0.569 0.624 0.520 0.548 0.562 0.608 0.577 0.632 0.612 0.646 is wrongly classified as FALSE as no proof can be found; in Experiment 4, it is correctly classified asTRUE due to the small difference between domain and modelsizes for T and T+H. There is hardly any overall difference in accuracybetween the shallow and the deep classifier.</S>
			<S sid="178" ssid="48">How ever, it seems that the shallow classifier in its currentform has very little potential outside of the CD subset whereas the deep classifier shows a more promis ing performance for several subsets.</S>
			<S sid="179" ssid="49">Experiment 5: Hybrid classification As shallow and deep classifiers seem to perform differently on differently designed datasets, we hypothesized that a combination of these classifiers should bring furtherimprovement.</S>
			<S sid="180" ssid="50">Experiment 5 therefore used all shal low and deep features together.</S>
			<S sid="181" ssid="51">However, the overallperformance of this classifier (see Column 5 in Ta ble 1) is not significantly better than either of the separate classifiers.</S>
			<S sid="182" ssid="52">Closer inspection of the results reveals that, in comparison to the shallow classifier, the hybrid classifier performs better or equally on all subsets but CD.</S>
			<S sid="183" ssid="53">In comparison to the deep classifier in Column 4, the hybrid classifier performs equallywell or better on all subsets apart from MT. Overall, this means more robust performance of the hy brid classifier over differently designed datasets and therefore more independence from dataset design.</S>
			<S sid="184" ssid="54">Experiment 6: Dependency on dataset designAs Eperiment 5 shows, simple combination of methods, while maybe more robust, will not necessar ily raise overall performance if the system does notknow when to apply which method.</S>
			<S sid="185" ssid="55">To test this hy pothesis further we integrated the subset indicator as a feature with the values CD, IE, MT, RC, IR, PP, QA into our hybrid system.</S>
			<S sid="186" ssid="56">Indeed, the resulting overall accuracy (0.612) is significantly better thaneither shallow or deep system alone.</S>
			<S sid="187" ssid="57">Note that us ing both a combination of methodologies and thesubset indicator is necessary to improve on individ ual shallow and deep classifiers for this corpus.</S>
			<S sid="188" ssid="58">We integrated the subset indicator also into the shallowand deep classifier by themselves, yielding classi fiers Shallow+Task and Deep+Task, with no or only very small changes in accuracy (these figures are not included in Table 1).</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Related Work. " number="5">
			<S sid="189" ssid="1">Our shallow analysis is similar to the IDF models proposed by (Monz and de Rijke, 2003; Saggion etal., 2004).</S>
			<S sid="190" ssid="2">We have expanded their approach by us ing other shallow features regarding text length.The basic idea of our deep analysis, using a de tailed semantic analysis and first-order inference,goes back to (Blackburn and Bos, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="191" ssid="3">It is similar to some of the recent approaches that were pro posed in the context of the PASCAL RTE workshop, i.e. using the OTTER theorem prover (Akhmatova, 2005; Fowler et al, 2005), using EPILOG (Bayer et al., 2005), or abduction (Raina et al, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="192" ssid="4">None of these systems, however, incorporate model building as a central part of the inference mechanism.</S>
			<S sid="193" ssid="5">We have shown that solely relying on theorem proving is normally insufficient due to low recall, and that using model builders is a promising way to approximate entailment.Results of other approaches to determining tex tual entailment indicate that it is an extremely hard 634 task.</S>
			<S sid="194" ssid="6">The aforementioned RTE workshop revealed that participating systems reached accuracy figuresranging between 0.50 and 0.59 and cws scores between 0.50 and 0.69 (Dagan et al, 2005).</S>
			<S sid="195" ssid="7">Com paring this with our own results (accuracy 0.61 and cws 0.65) shows how well our systems performs onthe same data set.</S>
			<S sid="196" ssid="8">This is partly due to our hy brid approach which is more robust across different datasets.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions. " number="6">
			<S sid="197" ssid="1">Relying on theorem proving as a technique for de termining textual entailment yielded high precision but low recall due to a general lack of appropriate background knowledge.</S>
			<S sid="198" ssid="2">We used model building as an innovative technique to surmount this problem toa certain extent.</S>
			<S sid="199" ssid="3">Still, it will be unavoidable to incor porate automatic methods for knowledge acquisition to increase the performance of our approach.</S>
			<S sid="200" ssid="4">Future work will be directed to the acquisition of targeted paraphrases that can be converted into background knowledge in the form of axioms.</S>
			<S sid="201" ssid="5">Our hybrid approach combines shallow analysis with both theorem proving and model building and achieves high accuracy scores on the RTE dataset compared to other systems that we are aware of.</S>
			<S sid="202" ssid="6">The results for this approach also indicate that (a) the choice of entailment recognition methods might have to vary according to the dataset design and/or application and (b) that a method that wants to achieve robust performance across different datasetsmight need the integration of several different entail ment recognition methods as well as an indicator of design methodology or application.</S>
			<S sid="203" ssid="7">Thus, although test suites establish a controlledway of assessing textual entailment detection sys tems, the importance of being able to predict textual entailment in NLP might be better justified usingtask-based evaluation.</S>
			<S sid="204" ssid="8">This can be achieved by in corporating them in QA or summarisation systems.Acknowledgements We would like to thank Mirella Lapata and Malvina Nissim as well as three anonymous review ers for their comments on this paper.</S>
			<S sid="205" ssid="9">We are also grateful to Valentin Jijkoun and Bonnie Webber for discussion and Steve Clark and James Curran for help on using the CCG-parser.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
