<PAPER>
	<ABSTRACT>
		<S sid ="1" ssid = "1">Some Information Extraction (IE) systems are limited to extracting events expressed in a single sentence.</S>
		<S sid ="2" ssid = "2">It is not clear what ef­fect this has on the di.culty of the extrac­tion task.</S>
		<S sid ="3" ssid = "3">This paper addresses the prob­lem by comparing a corpus which has been annotated using two separate schemes: one which lists all events described in the text and another listing only those expressed within a single sentence.</S>
		<S sid ="4" ssid = "4">It was found that only 40.6% of the events in the .rst anno­tation scheme were fully contained in the second.</S>
	</ABSTRACT>
	<SECTION title="Introduction" number = "1">
			<S sid ="5" ssid = "5">Information Extraction (IE) is the process of identifying speci.c pieces of information in text, for example, the movements of company execu­tives or the victims of terrorist attacks.</S>
			<S sid ="6" ssid = "6">IE is a complex task and a the description of an event may be spread across several sentences or para­graphs of a text.</S>
			<S sid ="7" ssid = "7">For example, Figure 1 shows two sentences from a text describing manage­ment succession events (i.e. changes in corpo­rate executive management personnel).</S>
			<S sid ="8" ssid = "8">It can be seen that the fact that the executives are leaving and the name of the organisation are listed in the .rst sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="9" ssid = "9">However, the names of the executives and their posts are listed in the second sentence although it does not mention the fact that the executives are leaving these posts.</S>
			<S sid ="10" ssid = "10">The succession events can only be fully understood from a combination of the informa­tion contained in both sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="11" ssid = "11">Combining the required information across sentences is not a simple task since it is neces­sary to identify phrases which refer to the same entities, “two top executives” and “the execu­tives” in the above example.</S>
			<S sid ="12" ssid = "12">Additional di.­culties occur because the same entity may be referred to by a di.erent linguistic unit.</S>
			<S sid ="13" ssid = "13">For ex­ample, “International Business Machines Ltd.” may be referred to by an abbreviation (“IBM”), Pace American Group Inc. said it noti.ed two top executives it intends to dismiss them because an internal investigation found ev­idence of “self-dealing” and “undisclosed .­nancial relationships.” The executives are Don H. Pace, cofounder, president and chief executive o.cer; and Greg S. Kaplan, senior vice president and chief .nancial o.cer.</S>
			<S sid ="14" ssid = "14">Figure 1: Event descriptions spread across two sentences nickname (“Big Blue”) or anaphoric expression such as “it” or “the company”.</S>
			<S sid ="15" ssid = "15">These complica­tions make it di.cult to identify the correspon­dences between di.erent portions of the text de­scribing an event.</S>
			<S sid ="16" ssid = "16">Traditionally IE systems have consisted of several components with some being responsi­ble for carrying out the analysis of individual sentences and other modules which combine the events they discover.</S>
			<S sid ="17" ssid = "17">These systems were of­ten designed for a speci.c extraction task and could only be modi.ed by experts.</S>
			<S sid ="18" ssid = "18">In an ef­fort to overcome this brittleness machine learn­ing methods have been applied to port sys­tems to new domains and extraction tasks with minimal manual intervention.</S>
			<S sid ="19" ssid = "19">However, some IE systems using machine learning techniques only extract events which are described within a single sentence, examples include (Soderland, 1999; Chieu and Ng, 2002; Zelenko et al., 2003).</S>
			<S sid ="20" ssid = "20">Presumably an assumption behind these ap­proaches is that many of the events described in the text are expressed within a single sen­tence and there is little to be gained from the extra processing required to combine event de­scriptions.</S>
			<S sid ="21" ssid = "21">Systems which only attempt to extract events described within a single sentence only report results across those events.</S>
			<S sid ="22" ssid = "22">But the proportion of events described within a single sentence is not known and this has made it di.cult to com­pare the performance of those systems against ones which extract all events from text.</S>
			<S sid ="23" ssid = "23">This question is addressed here by comparing two versions of the same IE data set, the evaluation corpus used in the Sixth Message Understand­ing Conference (MUC6) (MUC, 1995).</S>
			<S sid ="24" ssid = "24">The corpus produced for this exercise was annotated with all events in the corpus, including those described across multiple sentences.</S>
			<S sid ="25" ssid = "25">An inde­pendent annotation of the same texts was car­ried out by Soderland (1999), although he only identi.ed events which were expressed within a single sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="26" ssid = "26">Directly comparing these data sets allows us to determine what proportion of all the events in the corpus are described within a single sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="27" ssid = "27">The remainder of this paper is organised as follows.</S>
			<S sid ="28" ssid = "28">Section 2 describes the formats for rep­resenting events used in the MUC and Soder­land data sets.</S>
			<S sid ="29" ssid = "29">Section 3 introduces a common representation scheme which allows events to be compared, a method for classifying types of event matches and a procedure for comparing the two data sets.</S>
			<S sid ="30" ssid = "30">The results and implications of this experiment are presented in Section 4.</S>
			<S sid ="31" ssid = "31">Some related work is discussed in Section 5.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Event Scope and Representation. " number = "2">
			<S sid ="32" ssid = "1">The topic of the sixth MUC (MUC6) was management succession events (Grishman and Sundheim, 1996).</S>
			<S sid ="33" ssid = "2">The MUC6 data has been commonly used to evaluate IE systems.</S>
			<S sid ="34" ssid = "3">The test corpus consists of 100 Wall Street Jour­nal documents from the period January 1993 to June 1994, 54 of which contained manage­ment succession events (Sundheim, 1995).</S>
			<S sid ="35" ssid = "4">The format used to represent events in the MUC6 corpus is now described.</S>
			<S sid ="36" ssid = "5">2.1 MUC Representation.</S>
			<S sid ="37" ssid = "6">Events in the MUC6 evaluation data are recorded in a nested template structure.</S>
			<S sid ="38" ssid = "7">This format is useful for representing complex events which have more than one participant, for ex­ample, when one executive leaves a post to be replaced by another.</S>
			<S sid ="39" ssid = "8">Figure 2 is a simpli.ed event from the the MUC6 evaluation similar to one described by Grishman and Sundheim (1996).</S>
			<S sid ="40" ssid = "9">This template describes an event in which “John J. Dooner Jr.” becomes chairman of the company “McCannErickson”.</S>
			<S sid ="41" ssid = "10">The MUC tem­plates are too complex to be described fully here but some relevant features can be discussed.</S>
			<S sid ="42" ssid = "11">Each SUCCESSION EVENT contains the name of &lt;SUCCESSION_EVENT9402240133-2&gt; := SUCCESSION_ORG: &lt;ORGANIZATION-9402240133-1&gt; POST: &quot;chairman&quot; IN_AND_OUT: &lt;IN_AND_OUT9402240133-4&gt; VACANCY_REASON: DEPART_WORKFORCE &lt;IN_AND_OUT9402240133-4&gt; := IO_PERSON: &lt;PERSON-9402240133-1&gt; NEW_STATUS: IN ON_THE_JOB: NO OTHER_ORG: &lt;ORGANIZATION-9402240133-1&gt; REL_OTHER_ORG: SAME_ORG &lt;ORGANIZATION-9402240133-1&gt; := ORG_NAME: &quot;McCannErickson&quot; ORG_ALIAS: &quot;McCann&quot; ORG_TYPE: COMPANY &lt;PERSON-9402240133-1&gt; := PER_NAME: &quot;John J. Dooner Jr.&quot; PER_ALIAS: &quot;John Dooner&quot; &quot;Dooner&quot; Figure 2: Example Succession event in MUC format the POST, organisation (SUCCESSION ORG) and references to at least one IN AND OUT sub-template, each of which records an event in which a person starts or leaves a job.</S>
			<S sid ="43" ssid = "12">The IN AND OUT sub-template contains details of the PERSON and the NEW STATUS .eld which records whether the person is starting a new job or leav­ing an old one.</S>
			<S sid ="44" ssid = "13">Several of the .elds, including POST, PERSON and ORGANIZATION, may contain aliases which are alternative descriptions of the .eld .ller and are listed when the relevant entity was de­scribed in di.erent was in the text.</S>
			<S sid ="45" ssid = "14">For ex­ample, the organisation in the above template has two descriptions: “McCannErickson” and “McCann”.</S>
			<S sid ="46" ssid = "15">It should be noted that the MUC template structure does not link the .eld .llers onto particular instances in the texts.</S>
			<S sid ="47" ssid = "16">Conse­quently if the same entity description is used more than once then there is no simple way of identifying which instance corresponds to the event description.</S>
			<S sid ="48" ssid = "17">The MUC templates were manually .lled by annotators who read the texts and identi.ed the management succession events they contained.</S>
			<S sid ="49" ssid = "18">The MUC organisers provided strict guidelines about what constituted a succession event and how the templates should be .lled which the an­notators sometimes found di.cult to interpret (Sundheim, 1995).</S>
			<S sid ="50" ssid = "19">Interannotator agreement was measured on 30 texts which were examined by two annotators.</S>
			<S sid ="51" ssid = "20">It was found to be 83% when one annotator’s templates were assumed to be correct and compared with the other.</S>
			<S sid ="52" ssid = "21">2.2 Soderland’s Representation.</S>
			<S sid ="53" ssid = "22">Soderland (1999) describes a supervised learn­ing system called WHISK which learned IE rules from text with associated templates.</S>
			<S sid ="54" ssid = "23">WHISK was evaluated on the same texts from the MUC6 data but the nested template struc­ture proved too complex for the system to learn.</S>
			<S sid ="55" ssid = "24">Consequently Soderland produced his own sim­pler structure to represent events which he de­scribed as “case frames”.</S>
			<S sid ="56" ssid = "25">This representation could only be used to annotate events described within a single sentence and this reduced the complexity of the IE rules which had to be learned.</S>
			<S sid ="57" ssid = "26">The succession event from the sentence “Daniel Glass was named president and chief executive o.cer of EMI Records Group, a unit of London’s Thorn EMI PLC.” would be represented as follows:1 @@TAGS Succession {PersonIn DANIEL GLASS} {Post PRESIDENT AND CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER} {Org EMI RECORDS GROUP} Events in this format consist of up to four components: PersonIn, PersonOut, Post and Org.</S>
			<S sid ="58" ssid = "27">An event may contain all four components although none are compulsory.</S>
			<S sid ="59" ssid = "28">The minimum possible set of components which can form an event are (1) PersonIn, (2) PersonOut or (3) both Post and Org.</S>
			<S sid ="60" ssid = "29">Therefore a sentence must contain a certain amount of information to be listed as an event in this data set: the name of an organisation and post participating in a management succession event or the name of a person changing position and the direction of that change.</S>
			<S sid ="61" ssid = "30">Soderland created this data from the MUC­6 evaluation texts without using any of the existing annotations.</S>
			<S sid ="62" ssid = "31">The texts were .rst pre-processing using the University of Mas­sachusetts BADGER syntactic analyser (Fisher et al., 1995) to identify syntactic clauses and the named entities relevant to the management suc­cession task: people, posts and organisations.</S>
			<S sid ="63" ssid = "32">Each sentence containing relevant entities was examined and succession events manually iden­ti.ed.</S>
			<S sid ="64" ssid = "33">1 The representation has been simpli.ed slightly for clarity..</S>
			<S sid ="65" ssid = "34">This format is more practical for machine learning research since the entities which par­ticipate in the event are marked directly in the text.</S>
			<S sid ="66" ssid = "35">The learning task is simpli.ed by the fact that the information which describes the event is contained within a single sentence and so the feature space used by a learning algorithm can be safely limited to items within that context.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Event Comparison. " number = "3">
			<S sid ="67" ssid = "1">3.1 Common Representation and Transformation.</S>
			<S sid ="68" ssid = "2">There are advantages and disadvantages to the event representation schemes used by MUC and Soderland.</S>
			<S sid ="69" ssid = "3">The MUC templates encode more information about the events than Soderland’s representation but the nested template struc­ture can make them di.cult to interpret man­ually.</S>
			<S sid ="70" ssid = "4">In order to allow comparison between events each data set was transformed into a com­mon format which contains the information stored in both representations.</S>
			<S sid ="71" ssid = "5">In this format each event is represented as a single database record with four .elds: type, person, post and organisation.</S>
			<S sid ="72" ssid = "6">The type .eld can take the values person in, person out or, when the di­rection of the succession event is not known, person move.</S>
			<S sid ="73" ssid = "7">The remaining .elds take the person, position and organisation names from the text.</S>
			<S sid ="74" ssid = "8">These .elds may contain alternative values which are separated by a vertical bar (“|”).</S>
			<S sid ="75" ssid = "9">MUC events can be translated into this format in a straightforward way since each IN AND OUT sub-template corresponds to a sin­gle event in the common representation.</S>
			<S sid ="76" ssid = "10">The MUC representation is more detailed than the one used by Soderland and so some in­formation is discarded from the MUC tem­plates.</S>
			<S sid ="77" ssid = "11">For example, the VACANCY REASON .led which lists the reason for the manage­ment succession event is not transfered to the common format.</S>
			<S sid ="78" ssid = "12">The event listed in Figure 2 would be represented as follows: type(person in) person(‘John J. Dooner Jr.’| ‘John Dooner’|‘Dooner’) org(‘McCannErickson’|‘McCann’) post(chairman) Alternative .llers for the person and org .elds are listed here and these correspond to the PER NAME, PER ALIAS, ORG NAME and ORG ALIAS .elds in the MUC template.</S>
			<S sid ="79" ssid = "13">The Soderland succession event shown in Section 2.2 would be represented as follows in the common format.</S>
			<S sid ="80" ssid = "14">type(person in) person(‘Daniel Glass’) post(‘president’) org(‘EMI Records Group’) type(person in) person(‘Daniel Glass’) post(‘chief executive officer’) org(‘EMI Records Group’) In order to carry out this transformation an event has to be generated for each PersonIn and PersonOut mentioned in the Soderland event.</S>
			<S sid ="81" ssid = "15">Soderland’s format also lists conjunctions of post names as a single slot .ller (“president and chief executive o.cer” in this example).</S>
			<S sid ="82" ssid = "16">These are treated as separate events in the MUC for­mat.</S>
			<S sid ="83" ssid = "17">Consequently they are split into the sepa­rate post names and an event generated for each in the common representation.</S>
			<S sid ="84" ssid = "18">It is possible for a Soderland event to consist of only a Post and Org slot (i.e. there is nei­ther a PersonIn or PersonOut slot).</S>
			<S sid ="85" ssid = "19">In these cases an underspeci.ed type, person move, is used and no person .eld listed.</S>
			<S sid ="86" ssid = "20">Unlike MUC templates Soderland’s format does not contain alternative names for .eld .llers and so these never occur when an event in Soderland’s for­mat is translated into the common format.</S>
			<S sid ="87" ssid = "21">3.2 Matching.</S>
			<S sid ="88" ssid = "22">The MUC and Soderland data sets can be com­pared to determine how many of the events in the former are also contained in the latter.</S>
			<S sid ="89" ssid = "23">This provides an indication of the proportion of events in the MUC6 domain which are express­ible within a single sentence.</S>
			<S sid ="90" ssid = "24">Matches between Soderland and MUC events can be classi.ed as full, partial or nomatch.</S>
			<S sid ="91" ssid = "25">Each of these possi­bilities may be described as follows: Full A pair of events can only be fully match­ing if they contain the same set of .elds.</S>
			<S sid ="92" ssid = "26">In addition there must be a common .ller for each .eld.</S>
			<S sid ="93" ssid = "27">The following pair of events are an example of two which fully match.</S>
			<S sid ="94" ssid = "28">type(person in) person(‘R. Wayne Diesel’|‘Diesel’) org(‘Mechanical Technology Inc.’| ‘Mechanical Technology’) post(‘chief executive officer’) type(person in) person(‘R. Wayne Diesel’) org(‘Mechanical Technology’) post(‘chief executive officer’) Partial A partial match occurs when one event contains a proper subset of the .elds of an­other event.</S>
			<S sid ="95" ssid = "29">Each .eld shared by the two events must also share at least one .ller.</S>
			<S sid ="96" ssid = "30">The following event would partially match either of the above events; the org .eld is absent therefore the matches would not be full.</S>
			<S sid ="97" ssid = "31">type(person in) person(‘R. Wayne Diesel’) post(‘chief executive officer’) Nomatch A pair of events do not match if the conditions for a full or partial match are not met.</S>
			<S sid ="98" ssid = "32">This can occur if corresponding .elds do not share a .ller or if the set of .elds in the two events are not equivalent or one the subset of the other.</S>
			<S sid ="99" ssid = "33">Matching between the two sets of events is carried out by going through each MUC event and comparing it with each Soderland event for the same document.</S>
			<S sid ="100" ssid = "34">The MUC event is .rst compared with each of the Soderland events to check whether there are any equal matches.</S>
			<S sid ="101" ssid = "35">If one is found a note is made and the matching process moves onto the next event in the MUC set.</S>
			<S sid ="102" ssid = "36">If an equal match is not found the MUC event is again compared with the same set of Soderland events to see whether there are any partial matches.</S>
			<S sid ="103" ssid = "37">We allow more than one Soder­land event to partially match a MUC event so when one is found the matching process con­tinues through the remainder of the Soderland events to check for further partial matches.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Results. " number = "4">
			<S sid ="104" ssid = "1">4.1 Event level analysis.</S>
			<S sid ="105" ssid = "2">After transforming each data set into the com­mon format it was found that there were 276 events listed in the MUC data and 248 in the Soderland set.</S>
			<S sid ="106" ssid = "3">Table 1 shows the number of matches for each data set following the match­ing process described in Section 3.2.</S>
			<S sid ="107" ssid = "4">The counts under the “MUC data” and “Soderland data” headings list the number of events which fall into each category for the MUC and Soderland data sets respectively along with corresponding percentages of that data set.</S>
			<S sid ="108" ssid = "5">It can be seen that 112 (40.6%) of the MUC events are fully cov­ered by the second data set, and 108 (39.1%) partially covered.</S>
			<S sid ="109" ssid = "6">Match MUC data Soderland data Type Count % Count % Full 112 40.6% 112 45.2% Partial 108 39.1% 118 47.6% Nomatch 56 20.3% 18 7.3% Total 276 248 Table 1: Counts of matches between MUC and Soderland data.</S>
			<S sid ="110" ssid = "7">Table 1 shows that there are 108 events in the MUC data set which partially match with the Soderland data but that 118 events in the Soderland data set record partial matches with the MUC data.</S>
			<S sid ="111" ssid = "8">This occurs because the match­ing process allows more than one Soderland event to be partially matched onto a single MUC event.</S>
			<S sid ="112" ssid = "9">Further analysis showed that the di.erence was caused by MUC events which were partially matched by two events in the Soderland data set.</S>
			<S sid ="113" ssid = "10">In each case one event contained details of the move type, person in­volved and post title and another contained the same information without the post title.</S>
			<S sid ="114" ssid = "11">This is caused by the style in which the newswire sto­ries which make up the MUC corpus are writ­ten where the same event may be mentioned in more than one sentence but without the same level of detail.</S>
			<S sid ="115" ssid = "12">For example, one text contains the sentence “Mr. Diller, 50 years old, succeeds Joseph M. Segel, who has been named to the post of chairman emeritus.” which is later fol­lowed by “At that time, it was announced that Diller was in talks with the company on becom­ing its chairman and chief executive upon Mr. Segel’s scheduled retirement this month.” Table 1 also shows that there are 56 events in the MUC data which fall into the nomatch cat­egory.</S>
			<S sid ="116" ssid = "13">Each of these corresponds to an event in one data set with no corresponding event in the other.</S>
			<S sid ="117" ssid = "14">The majority of the unmatched MUC events were expressed in such a way that there was no corresponding event listed in the Soder­land data.</S>
			<S sid ="118" ssid = "15">The events shown in Figure 1 are examples of this.</S>
			<S sid ="119" ssid = "16">As mentioned in Section 2.2, a sentence must contain a minimum amount of information to be marked as an event in Soder­land’s data set, either name of an organisation and post or the name of a person changing po­sition and whether they are entering or leaving.</S>
			<S sid ="120" ssid = "17">In Figure 1 the .rst sentence lists the organisa­tion and the fact that executives were leaving.</S>
			<S sid ="121" ssid = "18">The second sentence lists the names of the exec­utives and their positions.</S>
			<S sid ="122" ssid = "19">Neither of these sen­tences contains enough information to be listed as an event under Soderland’s representation, consequently the MUC events generated from these sentences fall into the nomatch category.</S>
			<S sid ="123" ssid = "20">It was found that there were eighteen events in the Soderland data set which were not in­cluded in the MUC version.</S>
			<S sid ="124" ssid = "21">This is unexpected since the events in the Soderland corpus should be a subset of those in the MUC corpus.</S>
			<S sid ="125" ssid = "22">Anal­ysis showed that half of these corresponded to spurious events in the Soderland set which could not be matched onto events in the text.</S>
			<S sid ="126" ssid = "23">Many of these were caused by problems with the BAD­GER syntactic analyser (Fisher et al., 1995) used to pre-process the texts before manual analysis stage in which the events were identi­.ed.</S>
			<S sid ="127" ssid = "24">Mistakes in this pre-processing sometimes caused the texts to read as though the sentence contained an event when it did not.</S>
			<S sid ="128" ssid = "25">We exam­ined the MUC texts themselves to determine whether there was an event rather than relying on the pre-processed output.</S>
			<S sid ="129" ssid = "26">Of the remaining nine events it was found that the majority (eight) of these corresponded to events in the text which were not listed in the MUC data set.</S>
			<S sid ="130" ssid = "27">These were not identi­.ed as events in the MUC data because of the the strict guidelines, for example that historical events and non-permanent management moves should not be annotated.</S>
			<S sid ="131" ssid = "28">Examples of these event types include “...</S>
			<S sid ="132" ssid = "29">Jan Carlzon, who left last year after his plan for a merger with three other European airlines failed.” and “Charles T. Young, chief .nancial o.cer, stepped down voluntarily on a ‘temporary basis pending con­clusion’ of the investigation.” The analysis also identi.ed one event in the Soderland data which appeared to correspond to an event in the text but was not listed in the MUC scenario tem­plate for that document.</S>
			<S sid ="133" ssid = "30">It could be argued that there nine events should be added to the set of MUC events and treated as fully matches.</S>
			<S sid ="134" ssid = "31">However, the MUC corpus is commonly used as a gold standard in IE evaluation and it was de­cided not to alter it.</S>
			<S sid ="135" ssid = "32">Analysis indicated that one of these nine events would have been a full match and eight partial matches.</S>
			<S sid ="136" ssid = "33">It is worth commenting that the analysis car­ried out here found errors in both data sets.</S>
			<S sid ="137" ssid = "34">There appeared to be more of these in the Soderland data but this may be because the event structures are much easier to interpret and so errors can be more readily identi.ed.</S>
			<S sid ="138" ssid = "35">It is also di.cult to interpret the MUC guidelines in some cases and it sometimes necessary to make a judgement over how they apply to a particular event.</S>
			<S sid ="139" ssid = "36">4.2 Event Field Analysis.</S>
			<S sid ="140" ssid = "37">A more detailed analysis can be carried out examining the matches between each of the four .elds in the event representation individu­ally.</S>
			<S sid ="141" ssid = "38">There are 1,094 .elds in the MUC data.</S>
			<S sid ="142" ssid = "39">Although there are 276 events in that data set seven of them do not mention a post and three omit the organisation name.</S>
			<S sid ="143" ssid = "40">(Organisa­tion names are omitted from the template when the text mentions an organisation description rather than its name.)</S>
			<S sid ="144" ssid = "41">Table 4.2 lists the number of matches for each of the four event .elds across the two data sets.</S>
			<S sid ="145" ssid = "42">Each of the pairs of numbers in the main body of the table refers to the number of matching in­stances of the relevant .eld and the total num­ber of instances in the MUC data.</S>
			<S sid ="146" ssid = "43">The column headed “Full match” lists the MUC events which were fully matched against the Soderland data and, as would be expected, all .elds are matched.</S>
			<S sid ="147" ssid = "44">The column marked “Partial match” lists the MUC events which are matched onto Soderland .elds via partially matching events.</S>
			<S sid ="148" ssid = "45">The column headed “No­match” lists the event .elds for the 56 MUC events which are not represented at all in the Soderland data.</S>
			<S sid ="149" ssid = "46">Of the total 1,094 event .elds in the MUC data 727, 66.5%, can be found in the Soderland data.</S>
			<S sid ="150" ssid = "47">The rightmost column lists the percent­ages of each .eld for which there was a match.</S>
			<S sid ="151" ssid = "48">The counts for the type and person .elds are the same since the type and person .elds are com­bined in Soderland’s event representation and hence can only occur together.</S>
			<S sid ="152" ssid = "49">These .gures also show that there is a wide variation between the proportion of matches for the di.erent .elds with 76.8% of the person and type .elds be­ing matched but only 43.2% of the organisation .eld.</S>
			<S sid ="153" ssid = "50">This di.erence between .elds can be ex­plained by looking at the style in which the texts forming the MUC evaluation corpus are writ­ten.</S>
			<S sid ="154" ssid = "51">It is very common for a text to introduce a management succession event near the start of the newswire story and this event almost in­variably contains all four event .elds.</S>
			<S sid ="155" ssid = "52">For ex­ample, one story starts with the following sen­tence: “Washington Post Co. said Katharine Graham stepped down after 20 years as chair­man, and will be succeeded by her son, Don­ald E. Graham, the company’s chief executive o.cer.” Later in the story further succession events may be mentioned but many of these use an anaphoric expression (e.g. “the company”) rather than explicitly mention the name of the organisation in the event.</S>
			<S sid ="156" ssid = "53">For example, this sen­tence appears later in the same story: “Alan G. Spoon, 42, will succeed Mr. Graham as presi­dent of the company.” Other stories again may only mention the name of the person in the suc­cession event.</S>
			<S sid ="157" ssid = "54">For example, “Mr. Jones is suc­ceeded by Mr. Green” and this explains why some of the organisation .elds are also absent from the partially matched events.</S>
			<S sid ="158" ssid = "55">4.3 Discussion.</S>
			<S sid ="159" ssid = "56">From some perspectives it is di.cult to see why there is such a di.erence between the amount of events which are listed when the entire text is viewed compared with considering single sen­tences.</S>
			<S sid ="160" ssid = "57">After all a text comprises of an ordered list of sentences and all of the information the text contains must be in these.</S>
			<S sid ="161" ssid = "58">Although, as we have seen, it is possible for individual sentences to contain information which is di.cult to con­nect with the rest of the event description when a sentence is considered in isolation.</S>
			<S sid ="162" ssid = "59">The results presented here are, to some ex­tent, dependent on the choices made when rep­resenting events in the two data sets.</S>
			<S sid ="163" ssid = "60">The events listed in Soderland’s data require a min­imal amount of information to be contained within a sentence for it to be marked as con­taining information about a management suc­cession event.</S>
			<S sid ="164" ssid = "61">Although it is di.cult to see how any less information could be viewed as repre­senting even part of a management succession event.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Related Work. " number = "5">
			<S sid ="165" ssid = "1">Huttunen et al.</S>
			<S sid ="166" ssid = "2">(2002) found that there is varia­tion between the complexity of IE tasks depend­ing upon how the event descriptions are spread through the text and the ways in which they are encoded linguistically.</S>
			<S sid ="167" ssid = "3">The analysis presented here is consistent with their .nding as it has Full match Partial match Nomatch TOTAL % Type 112 / 112 100 / 108 0 / 56 212 / 276 76.8% Person 112 / 112 100 / 108 0 / 56 212 / 276 76.8% Org 112 / 112 6 / 108 0 / 53 118 / 273 43.2% Post 111 / 111 74 / 108 0 / 50 185 / 269 68.8% Total 447 / 447 280 / 432 0 / 215 727 / 1094 66.5% Table 2: Matches between MUC and Soderland data at .eld level been observed that the MUC texts are often written in such as way that the name of the organisation in the event is in a di.erent part of the text to the rest of the organisation de­scription and the entire event can only be con­structed by resolving anaphoric expressions in the text.</S>
			<S sid ="168" ssid = "4">The choice over which information about events should be extracted could have an e.ect on the di.culty of the IE task.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Conclusions. " number = "6">
			<S sid ="169" ssid = "1">It seems that the majority of events are not fully described within a single sentence, at least for one of the most commonly used IE evaluation sets.</S>
			<S sid ="170" ssid = "2">Only around 40% of events in the original MUC data set were fully expressed within the Soderland data set.</S>
			<S sid ="171" ssid = "3">It was also found that there is a wide variation between di.erent event .elds and some information may be more di.cult to extract from text when the possibility of events being described across multiple sentences is not considered.</S>
			<S sid ="172" ssid = "4">This observation should be borne in mind when deciding which approach to use for a particular IE task and should be used to put the results reported for IE systems which extract from a single sentence into context.</S>
	</SECTION>
	<SECTION title="Acknowledgements">
			<S sid ="173" ssid = "5">I am grateful to Stephen Soderland for allowing access to his version of the MUC6 corpus and advice on its construction.</S>
			<S sid ="174" ssid = "6">Robert Gaizauskas and Beth Sundheim also provided advice on the data used in the MUC evaluation.</S>
			<S sid ="175" ssid = "7">Mark Hep­ple provided valuable comments on early drafts of this paper.</S>
			<S sid ="176" ssid = "8">I am also grateful to an anony­mous reviewer who provided several useful sug­gestions.</S>
	</SECTION>
</PAPER>
